<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outsiders Venting Their Inner Darkness</title>
    <meta content="22META" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ROCK REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1D6173AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outsiders Venting Their Inner Darkness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews performance of various rock musicians in Tattoo the Earth Tour at Giants Stadium; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tattoo the Earth Tour, which arrived at Giants Stadium on Thursday, was organized to illustrate a longstanding concept in rock: the steadfast commitment of serious devotees to life beyond the norm. Heavy rock is an outsider's pleasure, and tattoos are permanent emblems of the soul's insurrection. Seriously tattooed people, with ink on the neck or down both arms, can alienate employers, family and people in line at the supermarket. They incorporate confrontationalism into their very membranes.</p>
        <p>Tattoo the Earth is intended to honor this ultimate commitment to strangeness alongside the music that, to many ears, shares its stance. Elsewhere on the national tour's 18 stops, this idea is being realized by having famous tattoo artists practice their art on willing customers. But New Jersey officials decided to ban the tattoo artists, fearing they would not be properly regulated. So the bands had to promulgate outsiderness on their own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Tattoo the Earth Tour, which arrived at Giants Stadium on Thursday, was organized to illustrate a longstanding concept in rock: the steadfast commitment of serious devotees to life beyond the norm. Heavy rock is an outsider's pleasure, and tattoos are permanent emblems of the soul's insurrection. Seriously tattooed people, with ink on the neck or down both arms, can alienate employers, family and people in line at the supermarket. They incorporate confrontationalism into their very membranes.</p>
        <p>Tattoo the Earth is intended to honor this ultimate commitment to strangeness alongside the music that, to many ears, shares its stance. Elsewhere on the national tour's 18 stops, this idea is being realized by having famous tattoo artists practice their art on willing customers. But New Jersey officials decided to ban the tattoo artists, fearing they would not be properly regulated. So the bands had to promulgate outsiderness on their own.</p>
        <p>That wasn't a stretch, since estrangement is the wellspring for heavy rock. Its intense amplification, frantic speed and brutal repetition is purgative. It strips away politeness to reveal darker emotions: fear, craving, rage. Heavy rockers locate these feelings within disquieting scenarios: countless songs played Thursday were about death, war, crime or self-directed violence.</p>
        <p>''My spirit's so cold,'' sang Rey Oropeza of Downset, a socially conscious hardcore band that played the show's first half, which unfolded on a temporary stage outside the stadium. Whether expressing defiance of social authorities or focusing on inner turmoil, heavy rock draws listeners into that chilliness, that refusal of comfort and serenity, as a way of freeing the mind. Each band at Tattoo the Earth worked a variation on this approach. The artists that played the daytime outer stage, aside from the virtuous Downset, switched off between the blend of hip-hop and hardcore guitar bashing that has worked for Limp Bizkit and the more glam-inflected variation on that theme practiced by Korn.</p>
        <p>The hardcore screamers in Hatebreed got the biggest response from the crowd. But the melodiously gloomy Full Devil Jacket may have shown the biggest commercial potential. On the mainstage, heavy rock's nuanced alienation played out in more masterly hands. Metallica's claim on the headlining spot turned the night into friendly combat. The band that has defined monster metal since the 1980's is dealing with a serious image problem because of its battle with Napster, the online service that allows fans to connect and download music free. Lars Ulrich, Metallica's drummer, has alienated many Internet-loving fans with his vehement protest against what he (and many artists) considers Napster's abetment of piracy.</p>
        <p>Add to this trauma a back injury that forced the singer James Hetfield to sit out several dates of the group's Summer Sanitarium tour, and the death of a fan who fell from a balcony at a July 5 concert in Baltimore, and Metallica had to be feeling some pressure. The evening also put the band up against Slipknot, heavy rock's newest pretender to the throne, as well as old rivals Slayer and Sepultura and rising contenders Sevendust. Each artist raised the event's stakes a little higher. The Brazilian band Sepultura played old-fashioned thrash with unusually complex rhythms, courtesy of the fine drummer, Igor Cavelera. Next came Sevendust, an Atlanta-based outfit featuring the singer Lajon Witherspoon, who slipped a little James Brown into his gruff and sweet delivery.</p>
        <p>These bands suggested how black music is turning metal on its ear, and unlike many currently popular bands, their members were as multicultural as their styles. These good bands still had nothing on the mighty Slayers' purist thrash. These California-based veterans are idolized by heavy rock specialists, having wielded rapid-fire riffs and hellish visions for decades. ''How many people can I kill?'' howled Tom Araya, the band's singer of legendary manliness, in ''Holy War,'' and the band answered his question symbolically with an unrelentingly focused set. This was a pure and totally effective sonic attack.</p>
        <p>Slipknot took the exactly opposite approach, with a similar effect. The Iowa-based band is the flavor of choice among teenage rockers. Its highly theatrical set demonstrated why. In jump suits and hideous masks, banging on garbage-can style drums or manhandling their guitars, Slipknot's members were not just unfocused. They were anti-focused, making music closer to a Nintendo game than conventional rock. As his eight bandmates, including a D.J., pounded away, the vocalist Corey Taylor rapped, crooned, grunted and growled. The jumble was hard to trace, but it obviously engaged the fans, who followed it like a round on their Game Boys. Slipknot disregarded virtuosity, lyricism and narrative suspense. It simply hit from all sides; the fun came in trying to absorb the assault.</p>
        <p>If such disorganized multiplicity is the new paradigm, Metallica may really be in trouble, because its artfulness is based on total control. It shapes heavy rock's dry-ice soundscape into grand, well-ordered tableaus. When the quartet appeared onstage to the strains of a Western movie soundtrack, its cool was as palpable as Clint Eastwood's. And in a two-hour set, Metallica won the shootout. The triumph had its cost. Metallica focused on older material, apparently heeding the fans who protested its recent experiments with softer-edged music. Unadulterated versions of crowd favorites like ''Fade to Black'' and ''One'' made this an official proclamation of dominance. Kirk Hammett, the band's High Romantic guitarist, flashed his filigree, but Metallica wanted to present itself as a virile powerhouse, and it did, without flinching.</p>
        <p>On the other leg of its tour, Metallica has been jamming with the members of Kid Rock's band. Those loose sessions probably aren't as satisfying as the band's herculean triumph at Tattoo the Earth. But they might show more about Metallica's future, if it dares mess with its invincible formula again and offer a new design for beautiful alienation.</p>
        <p>ROCK REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
