<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wood Shows Progress With 2nd Victory in Row</title>
    <meta content="NL22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Milwaukee Brewers</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Milwaukee Brewers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6DE153AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wood Shows Progress With 2nd Victory in Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Cubs defeat Milwaukee Brewers, 4-2; other National League results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kerry Wood is making progress, even without a 100-mile-an-hour fastball. It's just taking longer than he'd like.</p>
        <p>Wood put together consecutive victories for the first time this season, pitching the host Chicago Cubs to a 4-2 victory yesterday over the Milwaukee Brewers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kerry Wood is making progress, even without a 100-mile-an-hour fastball. It's just taking longer than he'd like.</p>
        <p>Wood put together consecutive victories for the first time this season, pitching the host Chicago Cubs to a 4-2 victory yesterday over the Milwaukee Brewers.</p>
        <p>''He's going to get better,'' Cubs Manager Don Baylor said of Wood, who is coming back from elbow surgery. ''But we have to wait until next year. We're all anxious that he's going to go out and strike out 15. It might happen.''</p>
        <p>Mark Grace had a go-ahead R.B.I. single in the third inning to spark the Cubs, who won for the eighth time in 11 games.</p>
        <p>Wood (5-6), who beat Kansas City July 16 in his last start, gave up two runs on four hits and five walks over six innings. He struck out four. The right-hander has worked at least six innings in 10 of his 14 starts.</p>
        <p>Rick Aguilera pitched the ninth for his 20th save in 27 chances.</p>
        <p>EXPOS 7, MARLINS 3: Geoff Blum homered and had a career-high four runs batted in, and Mike Thurman, fresh off the disabled list, pitched six strong innings for visiting Montreal.</p>
        <p>Blum's two-run homer, off Florida's Vic Darensbourg in the fifth inning, increased Montreal's lead to 6-1. One batter later, shortstop Tomas De La Rosa hit a solo homer, his first major league hit.</p>
        <p>Thurman (2-1), disabled since May 25 because of right-elbow tendinitis, was activated just hours before allowing Florida one run and five hits. He struck out six, walked three and worked out of one-out, bases-loaded jams in the second and third innings.</p>
        <p>Julio Santana relieved Thurman to start the seventh and promptly walked the bases loaded before allowing Alex Gonzalez's two-out, two-run single that pulled Florida within 7-3.</p>
        <p>PIRATES 9, PHILLIES 2: The rookie Jimmy Anderson allowed three hits in eight innings, and Mike Benjamin drove in three runs for host Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>Anderson (3-5) walked three, hit a batter and struck out five in his second straight solid start since making an adjustment in his delivery. Anderson allowed three hits and one unearned run in six and one-third innings at Los Angeles on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Anderson, trying to solidify a spot in the rotation, has not completed a game in 18 major league starts. He was pulled after throwing 123 pitches.</p>
        <p>DIAMONDBACKS 5, REDS 4: Luis Gonzalez's eighth-inning double drove in the go-ahead run as Arizona beat host Cincinnati after the Reds captain Barry Larkin revealed a tentative deal that would send him to the Mets.</p>
        <p>Several pro-Larkin banners fluttered around the stadium, and he got a louder than usual round of applause in his first at-bat.</p>
        <p>After wasting leadoff triples in the sixth and seventh -- both set up by Dante Bichette's misplays in right field -- the Diamondbacks finally got a clutch hit and broke a 4-4 tie in the eighth.</p>
        <p>CARDINALS 12, ASTROS 1: Edgar Renteria drove in four runs and the rookie Rick Ankiel struck out 11 in seven innings as visiting St. Louis stopped a three-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Ankiel (7-5) allowed only three hits and tied his career strikeout high to win for the first time in five outings. He had two no-decisions and two losses and had not won since June 20. Ankiel also went</p>
        <p>2 for 3 and scored two runs.</p>
        <p>Houston's Scott Elarton (9-4) had a five-game winning streak snapped, losing for the first time since June 16. Elarton allowed five runs, three earned, on seven hits and three walks with no strikeouts in three and one-third innings.</p>
        <p>PADRES 5, ROCKIES 1: Adam Eaton won for the first time in nine starts and went 3 for 3, and Al Martin drove in two runs as San Diego beat slumping host Colorado, which lost for the 13th time in 15 games.</p>
        <p>Eaton (2-1), who won on May 30 against Milwaukee and had seven no-decisions since, fanned three, walked four and gave up a run and seven hits in seven and one-third innings, his longest stint of the year.</p>
        <p>The 22-year-old right hander also walked and became the first Padres pitcher in over five years to steal a base.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
