<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Agent in Tow, Cuban Defector Looks for His Next Sign From Baseball</title>
    <meta content="22MIAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morales, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D8143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Agent in Tow, Cuban Defector Looks for His Next Sign From Baseball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuban national baseball team third baseman Andy Morales defects to United States; Cuban authorities, thinking Morales would defect, would not permit him to travel overseas; Morales can participate in Major League Baseball amateur draft in 2001 or establish residency in another country and go to highest bidder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Morales gleefully trotted around the bases after his three-run home run helped the Cuban national team clinch a 12-6 victory over the host Baltimore Orioles last year, and he felt on top of the baseball world. As it turned it, he said today, that moment turned into a nightmare.</p>
        <p>''After 40 years of having no professional baseball, to come here and be the first Cuban player to hit a home run against a professional team was a tremendous feeling,'' Morales said at a news conference at a Little Havana restaurant to celebrate his defection this week. ''But instead of that being a triumph for me, it turned into a defeat.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andy Morales gleefully trotted around the bases after his three-run home run helped the Cuban national team clinch a 12-6 victory over the host Baltimore Orioles last year, and he felt on top of the baseball world. As it turned it, he said today, that moment turned into a nightmare.</p>
        <p>''After 40 years of having no professional baseball, to come here and be the first Cuban player to hit a home run against a professional team was a tremendous feeling,'' Morales said at a news conference at a Little Havana restaurant to celebrate his defection this week. ''But instead of that being a triumph for me, it turned into a defeat.''</p>
        <p>Arriving back in Cuba, the third baseman/right fielder said Cuban authorities began suggesting that he was going to attempt to defect.</p>
        <p>''They made my life impossible,'' he told reporters. ''They wouldn't let me travel overseas. So it turned out to be a negative situation.''</p>
        <p>Morales, 25, was removed from the national team for having been seen talking to the California-based agent Gus Dominguez in Baltimore. Today Dominguez was by his side and talking excitedly about Morales's  prospects of becoming a major leaguer.</p>
        <p>Dominguez called Major League Baseball today to inquire about the possibility of conducting a special lottery on Morales's behalf, as it did in 1991 after the first Cuban defector, Rene Arocha, arrived in America. All interested teams would participate in the drawing to gain negotiating rights with him.</p>
        <p>But Dominguez said he was told that there was an 80 percent chance against a lottery being approved.</p>
        <p>''They don't want to be seen as doing anything special for anybody,'' he said, adding that there has been interest shown from ''at least five teams,'' including three in the minutes shortly after it became clear Morales was going to be released in the custody of his father-in-law, Carlos Castillo.</p>
        <p>If Morales, 6 feet 1 inch, 205 pounds, remains in the United States, he will participate in an amateur draft in 2001.</p>
        <p>That means he could negotiate with only the team that drafts him. He could establish residency in another country -- most likely Nicaragua, Venezuela or Peru -- and go to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>''Baseball-wise and businesswise it makes a lot more sense to go out of the country,'' Dominguez said. ''But there's a lot more to this than baseball. There's a family and just a lot of things that go with staying here in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Morales's decision could be affected by his family situation. His wife, Daiyana, and their 6-month-old son, Yandy, have received the United States's approval to immigrate and are now awaiting Cuban approval to leave.</p>
        <p>Dominguez said it would most likely be a week or two before Morales determined his course of action. For now, the agent is planning to return to Los Angeles soon with Morales, who will begin training.</p>
        <p>''I'd say he needs a good 60 days to get in real playing shape,'' Dominguez said. ''He hasn't played in a month.''</p>
        <p>How good is he? Dominguez's Total Sports International issued revised statistics from what had been available earlier in the week.</p>
        <p>Playing for Havana, he was said to have hit .371 during the 1998-99 season, with 71 runs batted in and 17 home runs. The season before: .349 with 68 R.B.I. and 12 home runs.</p>
        <p>Yankees pitcher Orlando (El Duque) Hernandez, who called to congratulate Morales, told his friend and the Dominguez publicist Rene Guim that Morales was one of the premier all-around third basemen in Cuban history.</p>
        <p>''I expect to see him in the major leagues one day soon,'' Guim said Hernandez had told him.</p>
        <p>Morales tried to defect in early June, but was one of 31 Cubans repatriated after they were intercepted at sea. The United States' policy on Cubans is clear. Those found at sea are usually returned to Cuba; those who reach land are not.</p>
        <p>He found himself ostracized upon returning and felt he was virtually forced out of baseball before his next defection try.</p>
        <p>''I felt like nobody wanted me because I was bearing the cross of having been a defector,'' he said. ''It was not a good situation.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
