<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High-Rise Fires Stir Chaos And Doubts in Jersey City</title>
    <meta content="22FIRE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jersey City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strunsky, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFDF153AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High-Rise Fires Stir Chaos And Doubts in Jersey City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strunsky, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jersey City, NJ, officials say that simultaneous fires in two new high rises on city's booming waterfront and subsequent safety citations at one of buildings have prompted concern that counstruction could be outpacing city's capacity to ensure fire safety (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Simultaneous fires in two new high-rises on this city's booming waterfront and subsequent safety citations at one of the buildings have prompted concern that construction could be outpacing the city's capacity to ensure fire safety, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A power surge on Thursday night caused havoc in a rapidly developing section along the Hudson River opposite Lower Manhattan, setting off transformer fires in an office building and a nearby apartment tower where residents say alarms failed to function despite thick, black smoke on the lower floors that injured four people. The surge brought blaring sirens and widespread confusion  along Washington Boulevard, the main thoroughfare on the stretch of waterfront known as the New Jersey Gold Coast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Simultaneous fires in two new high-rises on this city's booming waterfront and subsequent safety citations at one of the buildings have prompted concern that construction could be outpacing the city's capacity to ensure fire safety, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A power surge on Thursday night caused havoc in a rapidly developing section along the Hudson River opposite Lower Manhattan, setting off transformer fires in an office building and a nearby apartment tower where residents say alarms failed to function despite thick, black smoke on the lower floors that injured four people. The surge brought blaring sirens and widespread confusion  along Washington Boulevard, the main thoroughfare on the stretch of waterfront known as the New Jersey Gold Coast.</p>
        <p>The skyline here has grown with apartments and office buildings in recent years as a thriving economy has generated thousands of jobs and attracted tenants to spaces less expensive than those in Manhattan. But the rapid growth has also created added fire safety concerns.</p>
        <p>''It's very tough to keep up with the construction going on in this city,'' said Steven J. McGill, assistant director of the Jersey City Fire Department.</p>
        <p>The department has started a new training program to prepare for emergencies in high-rises, Firefighter McGill said. ''The simultaneous fires we had last night shows us that we do need to be diligent in maintaining good training.''</p>
        <p>Just after 8:30 p.m., officials said, the power surge caused an electrical transformer to explode at 525 Washington Boulevard, a 14-story office building that opened this year. The resulting fire set off an automatic alarm, Firefighter McGill said, and firefighters responded.</p>
        <p>Minutes later, at 8:42 p.m., firefighters were called to Portofino, a 26-story apartment building at 1 Second Street, just off the boulevard about two blocks away. The surge also caused power failures at another apartment tower, at 20 Second Street, and at a nearby shopping plaza. A Public Service Electric &amp; Gas spokeswoman said the utility was investigating the power surge, which occurred in three underground cables.</p>
        <p>Firefighter McGill said the transformer fire at Portofino quickly died down, but the two lowest floors had already filled with smoke. Firefighters were unable to locate controls for the building's heating, ventilation and air-conditioning system, which carried smoke throughout the building, he said. Firefighters met several tenants in a stairwell who said an elevator had filled with smoke. They were led out, holding hands, through the smoky lobby.</p>
        <p>''It was pretty scary,'' said Meredith Battin, 21, an intern at American Express in Jersey City. ''The firemen were wearing gas masks when they opened the door, which wasn't very comforting.''</p>
        <p>Residents of the building, where 172 of the 282 apartments are occupied, were allowed back in at 11:05 p.m. ''I'm pretty unhappy about the fact that the alarm didn't go off, seriously,'' said Ken Parrett, 44, a computer project manager for Barclays Bank in Manhattan. ''I'm going to move out. You don't get two chances.''</p>
        <p>The apartment building, which is not 100 percent complete and is operating under a temporary certificate of occupancy, has an automatic alarm system, but it was not turned on, officials said. Under an agreement with the city, the alarm can remain off during the day, so that construction work does not set it off, but it must be turned on each night.</p>
        <p>After an inspection today, the building's owner was ordered to correct seven fire safety violations, although none appeared to have contributed to the transformer fire,  Firefighter McGill said. The building was ordered, for example, to submit a fire safety plan and evacuation procedure, make sure the alarm was on at all times, post adequate signs, and cover an exposed wire.</p>
        <p>Laverne McCall, president of Roseland Management Company, a subsidiary of Portofino's owner, Roseland Property Company of Millburn, N.J., insisted the building was safe. She said she did not know why the alarm was off. Ms. McCall also said there was no fire, only smoke.</p>
        <p>Firefighter McGill, however, said firefighters saw flames in the room with the transformer, which was singed.</p>
        <p>No fire safety violations were found at the office building, he said. But fire safety violations were found at the apartment building that experienced a power failure but no fire, he said. It was inspected as a precaution.</p>
        <p>The department's full complement of more than 100 firefighters was called out to fight the two fires, and George Geyer, president of the city firefighters' union, said the department's staffing of 595 had not kept up with the city's growth.</p>
        <p>Tom Gallagher, Mayor Bret Schundler's chief of staff, said the department had made efforts to put as many uniformed firefighters on the street as possible but said modern firefighting was as much a matter of training and technology as of simple manpower.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
