<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Two Rounds, Woods Eyes a Knockout</title>
    <meta content="22GOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EED9143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Two Rounds, Woods Eyes a Knockout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ST. ANDREWS, Scotland, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tiger Woods leads British Open after 2 rounds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods sensed a career Grand Slam. His opponents sensed the door slamming shut.</p>
        <p>Watching Woods work today was like watching a top surgeon performing a delicate operation. His most precarious moment occurred at the Road Hole, the par-4 No. 17 at the Old Course at St. Andrews, when his second shot rolled off the green and down a ledge onto a thin strip of grass near the road. But Woods showed his brilliance once again, hitting a deft chip over the ledge that ran eight feet past the cup before making the putt coming back to save par.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tiger Woods sensed a career Grand Slam. His opponents sensed the door slamming shut.</p>
        <p>Watching Woods work today was like watching a top surgeon performing a delicate operation. His most precarious moment occurred at the Road Hole, the par-4 No. 17 at the Old Course at St. Andrews, when his second shot rolled off the green and down a ledge onto a thin strip of grass near the road. But Woods showed his brilliance once again, hitting a deft chip over the ledge that ran eight feet past the cup before making the putt coming back to save par.</p>
        <p>For the second consecutive round at the British Open, Woods did not have a bogey. He has now played 62 consecutive bogey-free holes at major championships.</p>
        <p>Heading into Saturday's third round, Woods held a three-stroke lead and the path to history in his hands. At age 24, Woods can become the youngest player to complete the career Grand Slam, having already won the Masters (1997), the P.G.A. Championship (1999) and the United States Open, which he won last month.</p>
        <p>Will anyone beat Woods? Perhaps only if he falters, and after today's performance that did not seem likely. Shooting a six-under-par 66 after his opening-round 67 on Thursday, Woods was 11 under par (136) for the tournament, three strokes ahead of David Toms (eight under par, 69-67) and four strokes ahead of three players who were tied at seven under: Steve Flesch (67-70), Sergio Garcia (68-69) and Loren Roberts (69-68).</p>
        <p>Whether he is magical, or simply methodical, Woods is by far the world's No. 1 player. And with 36 holes remaining between Woods and history, he looked determined to let nothing stand in his way.</p>
        <p>''I am playing very similar to how I played at Pebble,'' Woods said, referring to the United States Open, which he won by 15 strokes, the largest margin in major championship history.</p>
        <p>Asked about his bogey-free streak, Woods smiled and said: ''Bogeys aren't good for a scorecard. If you go around and not make any bogeys for the entire week, I guarantee you're going to have a chance to win.''</p>
        <p>Five prominent players were tied at six under par -- Fred Couples, Ernie Els, Tom Lehman, Thomas Bjorn and Phil Mickelson. They will all try to catch Woods, but that can be like trying to catch a world-class sprinter who has a 10-yard head start.</p>
        <p>His competitors have seen it before. They do not want to see it again. But there may be nothing they can do.</p>
        <p>''He hasn't made a bogey, and anybody who plays that kind of golf is going to be tough to beat,'' Lehman said. ''All we can do, all I can do, is play my best.''</p>
        <p>But Woods has played the Old Course as if it's his home course, taking advantage of the benign conditions that have allowed players to attack. There are 112 bunkers on the course, and Woods has not been in one since the tournament started.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Els faded today with an even-par 72, quickly surrendering the one-stroke lead he held over Woods and Flesch through 18 holes. Playing in near-prefect conditions in the morning, Els missed several short putts on the front nine, lost confidence and squandered an opportunity to put more pressure on Woods before he teed off in the afternoon. ''I never got into a rhythm,'' Els said. ''Today was my bad round. I know I can play better over the weekend, and I'll do that.''</p>
        <p>While Els foundered, Toms, Flesch and Garcia played well in the morning and put themselves in the hunt. But Flesch has yet to win a professional tournament, and Toms has only one top 10 finish in a major championship. Garcia, however, took on Woods last year in a thrilling back-nine duel at the P.G.A. Championship, losing by one stroke but gaining great respect at age 19. Garcia turned 20 in January, and he is young enough not to be intimidated by the prospect of chasing Woods.</p>
        <p>''It would be something special,'' Garcia said about the prospect of another final-round battle with Woods. ''I feel I'm playing very solid, very well.''</p>
        <p>But no one is playing better than Woods, who displayed his versatility in front of a crowd estimated at 47,000, the largest in tournament history. Woods opened with a birdie at the par-4 opening hole, hitting a sand wedge approach shot to eight feet, then making the putt. He added a 12-foot putt for birdie at No. 4, then birdied the par-5, 568-yard No. 5, hitting his second shot just short of the green, then chipping to four feet and making the putt.</p>
        <p>Woods also made 12-foot birdie putts at Nos. 9 and 12, but his up-and-down at No. 17 to save par was the highlight of his day. Showing his touch and imagination, Woods stood on the thin grass bordering the famous road and hit a soft shot over a three-foot ledge onto the green, running the ball past the cup but intentionally using a slope behind the hole to slow down the ball. He also saved par at No. 18 by making a testy six-foot double-breaking putt.</p>
        <p>With the tournament at his midway point, the world's best player had a three-stroke lead. The weather could turn nasty this weekend, which would make the Old Course far more difficult. That could also work to Woods's advantage.</p>
        <p>''I personally think that to put some heat on Tiger Woods, we need to have some good weather,'' Roberts said. ''If it's bad weather, he's such a strong player, with his length, it would be tough to catch him.''</p>
        <p>Regardless of the weather, Woods planned to stay where he was. When asked how he would feel in his competitors' shoes, he offered no advice.</p>
        <p>''It's hard for me to answer that one, because I am not in their shoes,'' Woods said. ''It's hard for me to understand what their thought process is. I know what mine is. And that's all I need to know.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
