<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civil Auction Suits Face Possible Curb</title>
    <meta content="22AUCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5D6173AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civil Auction Suits Face Possible Curb</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prosecutors investigating allegations of collusion and price fixing by world's largest auction houses, Sotheby's and Christie's, go to Federal District Court, Manhattan, to prevent lawyers for hundreds of angry buyers and sellers from formally interviewing people who may figure in investigation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors investigating allegations of collusion and price fixing by the world's largest auction houses, Sotheby's and Christie's, have gone to Federal District Court in Manhattan to prevent  lawyers for hundreds of angry buyers and sellers from formally interviewing people who may figure in the investigation.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Judge Lewis A. Kaplan dated July 17, federal prosecutors asked permission to file a motion to forbid lawyers in the civil case against the two auction houses to take depositions from Christopher M. Davidge, Christie's former chief executive, who resigned last Dec. 24. Further, they will move to stop the lawyers from deposing anyone else who may be connected to their investigation until a criminal grand jury finishes its work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prosecutors investigating allegations of collusion and price fixing by the world's largest auction houses, Sotheby's and Christie's, have gone to Federal District Court in Manhattan to prevent  lawyers for hundreds of angry buyers and sellers from formally interviewing people who may figure in the investigation.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Judge Lewis A. Kaplan dated July 17, federal prosecutors asked permission to file a motion to forbid lawyers in the civil case against the two auction houses to take depositions from Christopher M. Davidge, Christie's former chief executive, who resigned last Dec. 24. Further, they will move to stop the lawyers from deposing anyone else who may be connected to their investigation until a criminal grand jury finishes its work.</p>
        <p>If the motion is approved, the prospect for a quick settlement in the multimillion-dollar civil cases will greatly diminish.</p>
        <p>''Such a stay is necessary to prevent prejudice to the ongoing investigation and any subsequent prosecution,'' the letter said.</p>
        <p>Neither John L. Greene, the government's chief antitrust prosecutor, nor Judge Kaplan returned repeated phone calls seeking comment about the letter.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the day after the letter was sent, documents that Christie's turned over to the government in December in exchange for government leniency were delivered to Boise, Schiller &amp; Flexner, the lead lawyers for the plaintiffs in the class-action lawsuit, and lawyers for A. Alfred Taubman, Sotheby's former chairman, and for Diana D. Brooks, Sotheby's former chief executive. Judge Kaplan had ordered the government to hand over the documents. Both Mr. Taubman and Ms. Brooks resigned on Feb. 21 as the investigation heated up. The documents, which are said to number 153 pages, were given to top Christie's officials by Mr. Davidge before his departure. They are said to support allegations of collusion and price-fixing by the two auction giants.</p>
        <p>The documents were given to the lawyers on condition that they remain confidential, and none of the lawyers would comment on them. They are said to include memos from Mr. Davidge to Sir Anthony Tennant, Christie's former chairman, regarding secret meetings he had with Mrs. Brooks to discuss setting commissions. The documents are also said to include notes from Sir Anthony to Mr. Davidge about meetings he had with Mr. Taubman and records of discussions about new forms of financing offered to sellers by the two companies starting in about 1993.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
