<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="TRA22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DE153AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Recalled RHP Kane Davis from Buffalo of the International League. Optioned RHP Jim Brower to Buffalo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Recalled RHP Kane Davis from Buffalo of the International League. Optioned RHP Jim Brower to Buffalo.</p>
        <p>National League  ATLANTA BRAVES--Optioned C Fernando Lunar to Greenville of the Southern League.  CHICAGO CUBS--Traded OF Glenallen Hill to the New York Yankees for RHP Ben Ford and LHP Ozwaldo Mairena, assigned Ford to Iowa of the PCL and Mairnea to West Tennessee of the Southern League. Called up IF Chad Meyers from Iowa.  FLORIDA MARLINS--Purchased the contract of C Ramon Castro from Calgary of the PCL. Announced C Paul Bako was claimed on waivers from the Atlanta Braves.  MONTREAL EXPOS--Activated RHP Mike Thurman from the 15-day DL. Placed RHP Yovanny Lara on the 15-day DL.  NEW YORK METS--Purchased the contract of INF Mike Kindade. Optioned RHP Jim Mann to Norfolk of the International League. Moved OF Darryl Hamilton from the 15-day to 60-day disabled list.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Placed C Mike Lieberthal on the 15-day disabled list. Activated 1B Rico Brogna from the 15-day disabled list.  PITTSBURGH PIRATES--Called up OF Emil Brown from Nashville of the PCL.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League  NFL--Cut the two-game suspension of Tennessee Titans CB Denard Walker to one game.  ARIZONA CARDINALS--Agreed to terms with RB Thomas Jones.  BUFFALO BILLS--Agreed to terms with S Travares Tillman to a four-year contract.  CAROLINA PANTHERS--Agreed to terms DE Reggie White.  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Signed K Neil Rackers to a three-year contract.  KANSAS CITY CHIEFS--Agreed to terms with CB William Bartee on a four-year contract.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Agreed to terms with C-F Jarrod Skalde.  DETROIT RED WINGS--Signed LW Brent Gilchrist to a one-year contract.  DEVILS--Signed LW Michael Rupp.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE  ALLENTOWN--Named Scott Coval athletic director.  BROCKPORT STATE--Named John Tuttle women's volleyball coach.  CALIFORNIA TECH--Named Brent Reger women's volleyball coach.  CAL POLY-SAN LUIS OBISPO--Named Hugh Bream women's tennis coach.  CAL STATE NORTHRIDGE--Agreed to terms with Bobby Braswell, men's basketball coach, on a four-year contract extension.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
