<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journeys Where the Means Are the Ends</title>
    <meta content="22SHEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHELF LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solnit, Rebecca</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wanderlust: A History of Walking (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Shelf Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0D6173AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journeys Where the Means Are the Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Rothstein reviews Rebecca Solnit book Wanderlust: A History of Walking; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WANDERLUST  A History of Walking  By Rebecca Solnit.  Viking. 326 pages. $24.95.</p>
        <p>There are as many walks as there are walkers. One explorer trekked 1,700 miles across the Australian outback accompanied by three camels. A woman known as Peace Pilgrim set out in 1953 on a pilgrimage for world peace, beginning at the Rose Bowl Parade in Pasadena, Calif., and logging perhaps 80,000 miles before, in 1981,  she was killed in a car that had offered her a lift. In another era, Charles Dickens desperately paced London's streets; ''if I couldn't walk fast and far,'' he said, ''I should explode and perish.'' Walkers abound. There are climbers seeking glory, urbanites seeking respite, believers seeking salvation, protesters seeking change, flaneurs seeking amusements, joggers seeking slimness.</p>
        <p>So what can possibly be made of all this strolling, hiking and pacing? Writing about walking, it turns out, is almost as plentiful as writing about writing, yet much of it, as Rebecca Solnit points out in ''Wanderlust: A History of Walking,'' is ''episodic,'' with ''no overarching plot.'' Ms. Solnit, who is herself an avid walker and elegant essayist, calls one such book ''a sort of trail mix made up of bite-size epiphanies, moral lessons, blisters, social encounters and recounted practical details.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WANDERLUST  A History of Walking  By Rebecca Solnit.  Viking. 326 pages. $24.95.</p>
        <p>There are as many walks as there are walkers. One explorer trekked 1,700 miles across the Australian outback accompanied by three camels. A woman known as Peace Pilgrim set out in 1953 on a pilgrimage for world peace, beginning at the Rose Bowl Parade in Pasadena, Calif., and logging perhaps 80,000 miles before, in 1981,  she was killed in a car that had offered her a lift. In another era, Charles Dickens desperately paced London's streets; ''if I couldn't walk fast and far,'' he said, ''I should explode and perish.'' Walkers abound. There are climbers seeking glory, urbanites seeking respite, believers seeking salvation, protesters seeking change, flaneurs seeking amusements, joggers seeking slimness.</p>
        <p>So what can possibly be made of all this strolling, hiking and pacing? Writing about walking, it turns out, is almost as plentiful as writing about writing, yet much of it, as Rebecca Solnit points out in ''Wanderlust: A History of Walking,'' is ''episodic,'' with ''no overarching plot.'' Ms. Solnit, who is herself an avid walker and elegant essayist, calls one such book ''a sort of trail mix made up of bite-size epiphanies, moral lessons, blisters, social encounters and recounted practical details.''</p>
        <p>This subtle and suggestive study, though, is something else. ''Wanderlust'' is, as Ms. Solnit admits, an ''amateur history,'' but amateur in the best sense. The trail mix is always ready at hand, providing unexpected nuggets (Hobbes, we are told, had a walking stick with a built-in inkwell) and piquant sensations (the desert, Ms. Solnit writes, is ''a place where loneliness has a luxurious flavor, like the blues'').</p>
        <p>Its real pleasures, however, resemble the pleasures of walking. It doesn't systematically press on toward a goal, but savors detail and varied perspectives, stopping to consider the nature of mountaineering, the life of the London streetwalker, the conflict between public right of way and private property in 19th-century England and 20th-century Las Vegas. Ms. Solnit joyfully trespasses across disciplines and genres, tracing a path through philosophy, paleontology, politics, religion and literary criticism.</p>
        <p>But a path, as Ms. Solnit points out, ''is a prior interpretation of the best way to traverse a landscape.''</p>
        <p>''To follow a route,'' she says, ''is to accept an interpretation.'' And while Ms. Solnit's path may seem rambling, it does indeed have a shape. ''Walking is usually about something else,'' Ms. Solnit proposes, and the something else is usually an attempt to explore ''the unpredictable and the incalculable.'' Walking dwells in a strange in-between state: half-public, half-private; half-here, half-there; half-active, half-passive. For Ms. Solnit, though, walking is endangered, ''under assault'' by the forces of the modern era: the phony colonnades of Las Vegas, the growth of suburbia, the sterility of the treadmill. Modernity is eclipsing nature.</p>
        <p>This is a familiar romance -- perhaps too familiar -- one that has been part of the Western heritage since Romanticism and is linked to the countercultural sensibility Ms. Solnit celebrates. But it is also unavoidable; walking does indeed seem to have its rise and fall. As Ms. Solnit points out, it has long been associated with the philosophic mind: Aristotle paced while lecturing; Kierkegaard rambled around Copenhagen while thinking. Some recent paleontological theories cited by Ms. Solnit argue that the development of walking is associated with the development of intelligence. But it was only with Romanticism that walking really came into its own.</p>
        <p>''I can only meditate when I am walking,'' Rousseau proclaimed. ''My mind only works with my legs.'' The vision of the solitary walker that Rousseau pioneered came to define a culture. William Wordsworth -- ''one of the first to employ his legs as an instrument of philosophy,'' Christopher Morley wrote -- composed poems aloud as he hiked through England's Lake District. Ms. Solnit suggests that Coleridge stopped writing blank verse when he ceased taking walks.</p>
        <p>Ms. Solnit has less sympathy for 19th-century prescriptions for health and happiness that developed around the culture of walking and is more skeptical still about how walking's philosophic ramble is harnessed to power and status in the cult of mountaineering. But she is fascinated with how urban life caused the walk to mutate into soliciting, cruising, shopping, rioting, skulking, loitering. Each city defines its walkers. With her casual San Fransciscan ways, Ms. Solnit explains, she feels like an alien whenever she is in New York, disrupting the fast pedestrian flow, ''as though I were a butterfly strayed into the beehive, a snag in the stream.''</p>
        <p>As a guide, though, Ms. Solnit knows the path well; she is tireless and sure-footed. The only time she seems to stumble is when she enthusiastically recalls the ''populist communion'' of the street protests against the 1991 gulf war; she suggests that because of government censorship ''most Americans weren't much better off'' than Israelis in Tel Aviv who had to seal themselves in rooms, wearing gas masks. Surely a veteran walker would have a larger perspective on where particular paths come from and where they might lead.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Solnit's greatest worry about contemporary life is what is happening to the art of walking itself. The treadmill is the emblematic villain. One writer noted, ''It is its monotonous steadiness and not its severity which constitutes its terror and frequently breaks down the obstinate spirit.'' But this was a writer in 1823, who was talking about the treadmill's use in English prisons. Now, Ms. Solnit proposes, the treadmill's severity makes it ''a corollary to the suburb'': ''a device with which to go nowhere in places where there is nowhere to go.''</p>
        <p>And so the walk uneasily comes to an end. Are perceptions of time and space distorted now that the body is not the instrument of motion but its recipient? Are the unpredictable and incalculable doomed to be displaced by false certainties and familiar comforts? Perhaps, but a mental stroll still has its compensations, and Ms. Solnit makes thinking seem a lot like walking.</p>
        <p>SHELF LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
