<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A SPECIAL COUNSEL FINDS GOVERNMENT FAULTLESS AT WACO</title>
    <meta content="22WACO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Waco (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Branch Davidians</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koresh, David (1959-93)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Danforth, John C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EED7143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1317" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A SPECIAL COUNSEL FINDS GOVERNMENT FAULTLESS AT WACO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John C Danforth, special counsel investigating 1993 tear-gas assault by federal agents on Branch Davidian compound in Waco, Tex, issues sweeping report clearing Atty Gen Janet Reno and government of any wrongdoing in deadly episode; declares agents did not shoot at Branch Davidians and did not start fire that destroyed compound, claiming lives of at least 80; says military was not used imporperly, and that government did not mean to engage in 'massive conspiracy and cover-up;' places blame and responsibility for deaths on members of religious sect, particularly group's leader, David Koresh; also rebukes government; says confidence in government had eroded because certain officials failed to speak candidly about aspects of case; his findings detailed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John C. Danforth, the special counsel investigating the 1993 tear-gas assault by federal agents on the Branch Davidian compound, today issued a sweeping report that cleared Attorney General Janet Reno and the government of any wrongdoing in the deadly episode.</p>
        <p>Reminding a crowded news conference of his initial pledge to answer the ''dark questions'' surrounding the case, Mr. Danforth, a former Republican senator from Missouri, did not mince words. He declared that agents did not shoot at the Branch Davidians and did not start the fire that destroyed the compound on April 19, 1993, claiming the lives of about 80 people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John C. Danforth, the special counsel investigating the 1993 tear-gas assault by federal agents on the Branch Davidian compound, today issued a sweeping report that cleared Attorney General Janet Reno and the government of any wrongdoing in the deadly episode.</p>
        <p>Reminding a crowded news conference of his initial pledge to answer the ''dark questions'' surrounding the case, Mr. Danforth, a former Republican senator from Missouri, did not mince words. He declared that agents did not shoot at the Branch Davidians and did not start the fire that destroyed the compound on April 19, 1993, claiming the lives of about 80 people.</p>
        <p>He said that the military was not used improperly and that the government ''did not engage in a massive conspiracy and cover-up.'' Mr. Danforth placed blame and responsibility for the deaths on members of the  religious sect, particularly the group's leader, David Koresh.</p>
        <p>''We are certain,'' he said, reading from a statement. ''And I give you these conclusions with 100 percent certainty.</p>
        <p>''The blame rests squarely on the shoulders of David Koresh.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Danforth exonerated the government, he also rebuked it. He spoke pointedly and passionately about how public confidence in government had eroded because certain officials failed to speak candidly about aspects of the case. His own appointment by Ms. Reno had come in September after disclosures that agents of Federal Bureau of Investigation, despite repeated denials, had fired pyrotechnic tear-gas canisters capable of starting a fire into the compound on the day it burned.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Danforth said that Ms. Reno and other high-ranking government officials had not known that agents fired such projectiles. But he blamed ''a few government lawyers and an F.B.I. agent'' for concealing the use of the projectiles. They were launched hours before the fire and did not contribute to it, he said.</p>
        <p>The report concluded that F.B.I. agents fired three pyrotechnic rounds at a construction pit about 75 yards from the living quarters of the Davidians. The rounds did not cause any damage, the report said.</p>
        <p>The Danforth report comes one week after an advisory jury hearing a federal wrongful death civil lawsuit ruled that the government was not liable for the deaths of the Branch Davidians. The jury's verdict is not binding and the ultimate decision will be made by the judge hearing the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Danforth said he waited to publish his report in order not to influence the jury's deliberations. He called his investigation ''95 percent complete,'' saying an additional three and a half months would be needed to determine whether ''further action'' was necessary against those involved in covering up the use of the projectiles.</p>
        <p>Speaking in a conference room at a downtown hotel, Mr. Danforth said:</p>
        <p>''All of us should be more skeptical of those who make sensational accusations of evil acts by government. At the same time, government personnel, especially government lawyers, owe the American people an openness and candor that was lacking in response to the tragedy at Waco.</p>
        <p>''Although the government did nothing evil on April 19, 1993, the failure of some of its employees to fully and openly disclose to the American people the use of pyrotechnic devices undermined public confidence in government and caused real damage to our country.''</p>
        <p>In Washington, Deputy Attorney General Eric H. Holder issued a statement praising Mr. Danforth's findings. ''Today's independent review sheds further light on the truth, and discredits many of the unsubstantiated allegations that have skewed the public's perception of the events of April 19, 1993,'' Mr. Holder said. ''We join Senator Danforth in wishing that this report begins the process of restoring the faith of people in their government.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holder said he was concerned about the findings that government lawyers had withheld the information about the pyrotechnic rounds but ''heartened'' that those rounds had not caused the fire. He also said the report underscored Ms. Reno's ''diligent efforts to learn the truth.''</p>
        <p>Louis J. Freeh, the bureau director, said: ''The simple truth, as the F.B.I. has maintained since April 19, 1993, has been unmistakenly confirmed again today. The F.B.I. fired no shots on that day and the Davidians started the fire that ultimately engulfed the compound.''</p>
        <p>Michael Caddell, the lead lawyer for the Branch Davidians in the wrongful death lawsuit, expressed disappointment with Mr. Danforth's findings and found particular fault with his conclusion that federal agents had not fired weapons. Next month, Mr. Caddell and government lawyers will litigate that issue as a separate, but related, part of the wrongful death lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caddell said Mr. Danforth disregarded flaws in a simulation conducted in March to help discern if weapons were fired. The simulation was intended to determine if flashes that appeared on an aerial, infrared videotape filmed the day of the fire were caused by gunfire. A British company hired by Mr. Danforth to conduct the simulation said the flashes were caused by reflections from water and metal, not gunfire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Caddell had initially sought the test, but he later argued that the simulation was imprecise. He said overlooking the flaws, such as what he termed mistakes by the British company in carrying out the simulation, ''is both irresponsible and a disservice to the American people.''</p>
        <p>Throughout today's news conference, Mr. Danforth emphasized that the scope of his probe was limited to ''whether government agents engaged in bad acts, not whether they exercised bad judgment.'' He said his parameters were confined to certain specific questions: Did federal agents start the fire? Did they shoot  at the Davidians on April 19? Did they use pyrotechnic devices? Was there any illegal use of the military? Was there a cover-up?</p>
        <p>An ordained Episcopal minister, Mr. Danforth was chosen, in part, because of his reputation in the Senate for integrity and rectitude. In conducting his inquiry, he had 16 lawyers and 38 investigators.</p>
        <p>The Branch Davidian episode began on Feb. 28, 1993, when a gunfight broke out as Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms agents attempted to serve a warrant on Mr. Koresh at the compound near Waco. Four A.T.F. agents were killed. The ensuing 51-day standoff ended on April 19 when F.B.I. agents sought to subdue the Branch Davidians by firing tear gas into the compound with tanks. The wooden structure erupted in flames and burned to the ground.</p>
        <p>The remainder of the investigation will address the actions of those who hid information about the use of pyrotechnic rounds, which have disappeared from evidence collected at the scene. In the report, Mr. Danforth criticized the bureau's failure, until September 1999, to release an audiotape of Richard Rogers, the head of the bureau's Hostage Rescue Team, authorizing the use of the explosive rounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Danforth said Ms. Reno and then-F.B.I. Director William Sessions had sought and gotten reassurances from field agents that pyrotechnic rounds had not been used on April 19. Both testified to this before Congress in 1993. The report stated that Mr. Rogers sat behind them silently and his failure to correct their statements was ''a significant omission that contributed to the public perception of a cover-up and that permitted a false impression to persist for several years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers said he was not paying attention to their comments during the testimony. Mr. Danforth said the remainder of his investigation would address questions surrounding why government lawyers and bureau officials hid the existence of the pyrotechnic rounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Danforth's office will not pursue any further investigation of Mr. Rogers or any other members of the Hostage Rescue Team, the report said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
