<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Can't Find Its Footing on the Clay in Spain</title>
    <meta content="22TENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5D7143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Can't Find Its Footing on the Clay in Spain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>SANTANDER, Spain, July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States falls behind Spain 0-2 in Davis Cup tennis competition; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was no positive spin to put on the day, only the monotonous reality of the penetrating topspin strokes that ground the United States' Davis Cup chances to near miracle odds, if not red clay dust.</p>
        <p>John McEnroe could not help Todd Martin or Jan-Michael Gambill today, and it is quite possible that Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi would not have saved McEnroe from the bad luck of the semifinal draw. Playing in Spain, on clay, in the heat of summer, was never going to be a day at the beach, even if the beach was only a long forehand away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was no positive spin to put on the day, only the monotonous reality of the penetrating topspin strokes that ground the United States' Davis Cup chances to near miracle odds, if not red clay dust.</p>
        <p>John McEnroe could not help Todd Martin or Jan-Michael Gambill today, and it is quite possible that Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi would not have saved McEnroe from the bad luck of the semifinal draw. Playing in Spain, on clay, in the heat of summer, was never going to be a day at the beach, even if the beach was only a long forehand away.</p>
        <p>''We're not playing chopped liver here,'' McEnroe said after his team dropped both singles matches and fell into an 0-2 hole, with Saturday's doubles looming as the Americans' last gasp. ''We're playing the real deal, and these guys want to win.''</p>
        <p>It was hot, as promised, but not oppressively humid. The temporary stadium erected above the coastline of the Peninsula de Magdelana was jammed with an estimated crowd of 13,000, but one not excessively raucous. Opportunities were abundant for Martin and Gambill, but consistency is the name of the game on clay. In the end, Albert Costa was the Road Runner who eluded Martin's grasp in a 6-4, 6-4, 6-4 victory before Alex Corretja played rope-a-dope and let the aggressive Gambill punch himself out, 1-6,  6-3, 6-4, 6-4.</p>
        <p>The Spaniards, who have never won the Davis Cup, need to win only one of the three remaining matches to reach their first world group final in 33 years. Should they finish the job they began so impressively, they will play host to Australia in December in Barcelona, meaning they will have played an entire Cup year without leaving home soil, red clay.</p>
        <p>''This is tailor-made for them,'' McEnroe said. ''If they can't win this, they'll be winning the Davis Cup in the year 3000.''</p>
        <p>If there was any encouraging news for the Americans, it was that Gambill, the 23-year-old with the two-fisted ground strokes on either side, showed enough fire and rained enough winners to suggest he might help them contend for their 32nd Cup title long before the next millennium. Gambill, a quarterfinal loser to Sampras at Wimbledon, was not supposed to have enough clay-court game for a specialist of Corretja's quality. Yet after Martin lost to Costa routinely, Gambill set upon Corretja like a cyclone, winning the first set in 31 minutes.</p>
        <p>''He was playing just unbelievable tennis, just wonderful,'' said Corretja, the world's seventh-ranked player. ''He was serving big, and his returns were every time in the corner. He didn't drop his level until maybe the middle of the second set. I can tell you that I don't know if Sampras or Agassi would play better than Gambill.''</p>
        <p>It was quite a compliment, but Gambill strikes the ball and speaks as if he intends to be ranked a lot higher than No. 37 soon. He firmly believed he could have won.</p>
        <p>''I'm ticked, at the world, at myself,'' he said after failing to take advantage of several openings, even after the first set.</p>
        <p>Most frustrating for Gambill was a chance to perhaps demoralize Corretja by getting back on serve after trailing by 1-5 in the second set. Gambill broke for 2-5, then saved two set points for 3-5.</p>
        <p>In the ninth game, Gambill had three break points to get back on serve but missed, in the following order: a running backhand down the line that was two inches long, a forehand into the net off a very ordinary second serve and a backhand wide off a second serve that kicked effectively wide of the ad court.</p>
        <p>As McEnroe said, ''The break points were there, but you give these guys an out and you're in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Gambill would earn more chances in the third set, but Corretja was controlling the play by then, running and sliding and whipping his forehands cross-court like a maestro conducting a symphony. By the fourth set, Gambill's backhand broke down and his unforced errors, numbering 51 to Corretja's 27, piled up.</p>
        <p>Still, his performance was enough to make McEnroe, given his team's dire straits, reconsider the doubles team he will send out Saturday against Corretja and Juan Balcells. Having originally tabbed Chris Woodruff and Vince Spadea, McEnroe said he would most likely switch to Gambill or Martin with Woodruff, though it seemed unlikely that Martin could play three days in a row.</p>
        <p>Despite fast starts in the first and second sets, Martin turned in a wooden performance against Costa, putting in only 53 percent of his first serves and committing 31 unforced errors to 13 for the Spaniard. Martin, having had limited match play this year because of a viral infection and a sprained ankle, looked 30 going on 50 as he vainly tried to apply pressure to Costa.</p>
        <p>He did his best, McEnroe said. Both players did. But the draw was what it was, and Sampras and Agassi stayed home, and, as Gambill said when asked if the Americans needed more practice on clay: ''We could have maybe been here a month and still had these results because these guys are so tough on this surface.''</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>JOHN McENROE again expressed his frustration at the way the Davis Cup year appears to be playing out but said he had no plans to quit. A United States Tennis Association official said earlier this week that McEnroe was working on a year-to-year basis, but McEnroe said Friday that he had a three-year contract. ''The one thing I'm not going to do is say, 'That's it, I quit if we lose,' what I would have done when I was younger,'' he said. ''You know, I signed a three-year deal and I'd like to think I could do something positive. I'm not sure it's bad luck or I haven't made a difference. It's hard to say right now.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
