<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Orders State to Help in Financing Magnet High School in Englewood</title>
    <meta content="22SCHO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Englewood (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hespe, David C (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0D9143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Orders State to Help in Financing Magnet High School in Englewood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>ENGLEWOOD, N.J., July 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NJ appeals court orders state's Education Comr David C Hespe to help secure financing for proposed university-affiliated magnet school in Englewood, NJ (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state appeals court has directed New Jersey's education commissioner to help secure financing for a proposed university-affiliated magnet school here, in the latest chapter of a 15-year dispute over desegregation of Englewood's high school.</p>
        <p>The ruling, issued Thursday, did not explicitly order Commissioner David C. Hespe to provide state money for the proposed school, which Englewood officials hope will attract white students from neighboring communities. But a spokesman for the State Education Department suggested today that some money might be available from an $8.6 billion school construction program the Legislature approved last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state appeals court has directed New Jersey's education commissioner to help secure financing for a proposed university-affiliated magnet school here, in the latest chapter of a 15-year dispute over desegregation of Englewood's high school.</p>
        <p>The ruling, issued Thursday, did not explicitly order Commissioner David C. Hespe to provide state money for the proposed school, which Englewood officials hope will attract white students from neighboring communities. But a spokesman for the State Education Department suggested today that some money might be available from an $8.6 billion school construction program the Legislature approved last week.</p>
        <p>''The department is very encouraged this will provide meaningful capital support for the Englewood district,'' said the spokesman, John Crosbie.</p>
        <p>Englewood's mayor, Paul T. Fader, said today he was pleased with the directive from the Appellate Division of Superior Court and expressed hope that it would end what he called the education commissioner's ''cavalier'' attitude about helping to finance the magnet school.</p>
        <p>In October 1998, the State Board of Education ordered Englewood to integrate its high school, Dwight Morrow High, after it rejected the city's appeal that it order two predominantly white neighboring communities, Englewood Cliffs and Tenafly, to create a new regional high school with Englewood. Dwight Morrow's enrollment of about 700 is now about 97 percent nonwhite.</p>
        <p>In response to that order, Englewood's school board created a plan for a new magnet school with three educational themes: international studies and business, science and technology, and communications and fine and performing arts. The cost of the proposed school is estimated at $18 million for construction of three  wings and labs at Dwight Morrow and $5 million to $7 million more for staff members and supplies, Englewood's superintendent, Joyce Baynes, said today.</p>
        <p>The state board's 1998 integration order provided no state financing for Englewood. It required the education commissioner to provide the school board with ''appropriate assistance'' in creating the new school, but did not define that term. Consequently, planning for the school bogged down months ago over lack of money.</p>
        <p>Thursday's court order to Commissioner Hespe said ''appropriate assistance'' must include helping Englewood to obtain financing.</p>
        <p>''The state of New Jersey is presently flush with money,'' Mayor Fader said today. ''We're looking for the state to do what it has been constitutionally mandated to do by the court. The problem we're facing is the department doesn't seem to care. We'll have to wait and see if he'll take the same cavalier attitude toward the court's directive.''</p>
        <p>Another section of Thursday's ruling upheld the state board's refusal in 1998 to order an integrated regional district. Englewood first filed suit for a state-mandated regional district in 1985. In the mid-1990's the Education Department threatened to create one if communities in eastern Bergen County failed to organize an integrated regional district on their own. Several municipalities agreed on a voluntary plan to integrate Dwight Morrow, but Englewood's school board rejected the plan because it did not contain specific desegregation timetables.</p>
        <p>About the same time, Leo F. Klagholz, who was then education commissioner, refused to create an integrated district after the state's threat to do so generated deep opposition in communities around Englewood.</p>
        <p>Mayor Fader said today that Englewood had no plans to drop its 15-year-old suit for a state-created district and would decide soon on whether to appeal Thursday's ruling to the State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Months ago, Bergen County  pledged $1 million for the school if the suit were dropped. The State Education Department had agreed earlier to match that grant. After the county withdrew its $1 million, the state's $1 million also disappeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crosbie, the department spokesman, said today the state would again offer the $1 million grant, with no conditions, and carefully consider any application from Englewood for money from the state's new school-construction fund.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Dr. Baynes, the Englewood superintendent, said a  version of the magnet school was to open at Dwight Morrow in September. It will offer a few courses in international studies for 30 sophomores, all from Dwight Morrow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
