<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y22BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DB143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CHILE: PINOCHET DECISION DELAYED  The Supreme Court delayed a decision on whether Gen. Augusto Pinochet will be tried for the military's execution of 72 jailed dissidents after the 1973 coup. The court set no date for a ruling after three days of hearings, but Chief Justice Hernan Alvarez said ''we hope everything will be decided by next week.'' The court was hearing General Pinochet's appeal of a lower tribunal ruling last month that stripped him of congressional immunity.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CHILE: PINOCHET DECISION DELAYED  The Supreme Court delayed a decision on whether Gen. Augusto Pinochet will be tried for the military's execution of 72 jailed dissidents after the 1973 coup. The court set no date for a ruling after three days of hearings, but Chief Justice Hernan Alvarez said ''we hope everything will be decided by next week.'' The court was hearing General Pinochet's appeal of a lower tribunal ruling last month that stripped him of congressional immunity.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: WAY CLEAR FOR AMAZON PROJECT  Ending a long-standing dispute with the government, Indian tribes signed a pact allowing construction to resume on a high-voltage line that cuts through the Amazon rain forest to link Venezuela and Brazil. The deal ends a conflict between 24,000 Indians and a government eager to fulfill contractual obligations to Brazil.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>SPAIN: BOMB FACTORY FOUND  The police raided an apartment in Spain's northern Basque region and discovered an arsenal of explosives, bomb-making equipment and an apparent hit list of politicians prepared by the armed Basque separatist group E.T.A. The group has been blamed for six attacks over the past nine days.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: SPEED TRAP  A car carrying Home Secretary Jack Straw, a champion of ''zero tolerance'' for speeders, was stopped by a highway patrol this month going 103 miles per hour, the police said. Under guidelines laid down by Mr. Straw's department, a motorist exceeding 100 miles per hour can be banned from driving and fined up to $1,200. The police say they have not decided whether to charge the detective driving the car. At the time, Mr. Straw was late for a Labor Party meeting with Prime Minister Tony Blair.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: NO-SHOWS AT THE FAIR  The Expo 2000 World Fair in Hanover opened a new advertising campaign to boost disappointing attendance. The ads feature the British actor Peter Ustinov and the German actress Verona Feldbusch with the slogan: ''This happens just once. It will never come again.'' Four million people have visited the fair since it opened eight weeks ago, less than a quarter the number expected.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: SOLDIERS KILLED IN CHECHNYA  Rebels struck in the heart of Chechnya's capital, Grozny, killing two Russian soldiers when their armored vehicle was hit by grenade launchers. The army said it feared an imminent offensive against major Chechen towns.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>CHINA: FALUN GONG ARRESTS  The police continued to arrest members of the outlawed Falun Gong spiritual movement in Beijing's Tiananmen Square, and officers were also posted at the city's railroad and bus stations to stop Falun Gong followers from entering the capital. State media said the movement has evolved from an ''anti-science, anti-humankind, anti-society cult organization into a political organization openly opposing the government and a tool of overseas anti-China forces.''</p>
        <p>Craig S. Smith (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: ANTIMISSILE DEFENSE DRIVE  Beijing is expected to take its campaign against Washington's proposed antimissile system to the Association of Southeast Asian Nations next week during a regional security meeting in Bangkok. Beijing opposes the proposed plan because it would neutralize China's limited nuclear arsenal. President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia joined China in condemning the plan while in Beijing this week, and China hopes for similar support from Asean.</p>
        <p>Craig S. Smith (NYT)</p>
        <p>SOUTH, NORTH KOREA: MINISTERS TO MEET  The foreign ministers of North and South Korea will hold their first meeting ever next week to discuss cooperation after last month's summit meeting, said Choi Young Jin, the South's deputy foreign minister. The talks will take place in Bangkok, coinciding with the regional meeting of Asean nations.</p>
        <p>Samuel Len (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: SUHARTO-LINKED PROPERTY SEIZED  As part of their investigation of former President Suharto, prosecutors seized an office building owned by charitable foundations he is accused of manipulating for financial gain. On Thursday, the prosecutors impounded a mansion belonging to the treasurer of one of the foundations.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: MORE HOSTAGES FREED  Muslim gunmen released two more Filipinos from among dozens of hostages they are holding in the southern Philippines. The two women were released by the Abu Sayyaf rebels to officials in southern Jolo island.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>KUWAIT: NO TO PARTIES  Foreign Minister Sheik Sabah al-Ahmed al-Sabah ruled out the setting up of political parties, saying a party system would damage the emirate's unity, the official news agency KUNA reported. Kuwait is the only Persian Gulf monarchy to have an elected Parliament, although women may not vote.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: ARMY, REBELS MEET  Military officers and Hutu rebel leaders have met for the first time in their seven-year civil war to discuss a cease-fire and the integration of guerrillas into the country's Tutsi-dominated army, a mediator said. Burundi's government is pressing for suspension of hostilities before signing a peace accord, while the rebels insist that talks for a cease-fire should begin only after the agreement is signed, possibly next month.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
