<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religion Journal; Rabbi Sees Opportunity in Fire at His Synagogue</title>
    <meta content="22RELI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kehilat Ya'ar Ramot (Jerusalem Synagogue)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bateman, David (Rabbi)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5D8143AF931A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religion Journal; Rabbi Sees Opportunity in Fire at His Synagogue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Religion Journal article discusses healing following arson fire at Kehilat Ya'ar Ramot, Conservative synagogue in Jerusalem; Rabbi David Bateman comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Rabbi David Bateman arrived in the United States from Israel for a visit this month, he came with a harrowing story -- and a determination to try to make good come from it.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Bateman, 46, is the American-born spiritual leader of Kehilat Ya'ar Ramot, a Conservative synagogue in Jerusalem, which became famous a month ago after it was attacked by arsonists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Rabbi David Bateman arrived in the United States from Israel for a visit this month, he came with a harrowing story -- and a determination to try to make good come from it.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Bateman, 46, is the American-born spiritual leader of Kehilat Ya'ar Ramot, a Conservative synagogue in Jerusalem, which became famous a month ago after it was attacked by arsonists.</p>
        <p>The blaze occurred just after the Sabbath, consuming prayer books and furniture. But it stopped short of the ark, leaving the synagogue's three Torah scrolls undamaged. Still, the crime was so traumatic within Israel that Prime Minister Ehud Barak declared that it ''causes every Jew to shudder.''</p>
        <p>In the fire's immediate aftermath, some voiced suspicion that the arsonists might be young men on an extreme fringe of a fervently Orthodox group -- this in a nation where considerable tension exists between Orthodox Jews, the dominant religious group in a largely secular society, and the Reform and Conservative movements, which are far smaller in Israel than in the United States.</p>
        <p>But when Rabbi Bateman has spoken at American synagogues about the incident, he said, he has made clear he does not want to cast blame.</p>
        <p>''I think it only contributes to the problem that set the fire, by pointing fingers at communities that indeed are not responsible'' for it, he said in an interview this week. Of the attack, he added, ''No truly religious person would perform that kind of act.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the rabbi regards the incident as an opportunity to create understanding across lines that divide Jews in Israel.</p>
        <p>Although the fire caused great shock, he said, ''within 48 hours, we had a public rally that drew hundreds.'' The gathering drew Israelis from groups that do not often rub shoulders: ''Orthodox representatives, including ultra-Orthodox, the secular community, Reform representatives,'' Rabbi Bateman said, recalling who showed up.</p>
        <p>The gesture of solidarity gave Rabbi Bateman and his congregation a vision of how things might be. It was, he said, ''a kind of peak moment, where the significant differences that divide us were put aside.''</p>
        <p>''We are committed as a community to try to capitalize on that peak moment,'' Rabbi Bateman added, ''and hope to build with our neighbors a communitywide program that will promote tolerance, coexistence, and hopefully will be a model that will be replicable in other communities.''</p>
        <p>Rabbi Bateman grew up in Portland, Ore., in what he described as a not-too-observant household. In his youth, he found his way to Orthodox Judaism, trained as a rabbi and served an Orthodox synagogue in Randolph, N.J., for more than a decade, until he moved to Israel two years ago. Last fall, he became rabbi at Khelit Ya'ar, with about 100 families affiliated with the Masorti movement, as Conservative Judaism is called in Israel.</p>
        <p>What he and his congregation would like to create, he said, is a long-term effort to bring people together, with a speakers' program for adults, an educational effort in schools, a summer camp for children from different backgrounds.</p>
        <p>He was asked what he made of the turn his life has taken: that after he immigrates to Israel, he finds himself articulating a vision of social peace and unity.</p>
        <p>''The Lord works in mysterious ways,'' Rabbi Bateman replied. ''For years, I've considered myself a principled pluralist, which is what enabled me to make the transition from a primarily Orthodox orientation to the Masorti community. I've been deeply concerned with the divisions among the Jewish community, and wanted to get involved in narrowing those rifts and bringing people together.''</p>
        <p>''Through circumstances not under my control,'' he said, ''I've been thrust into the middle of that undertaking.''</p>
        <p>Episcopalians Call For the Removal of Guns</p>
        <p>A week ago, when leaders of the Episcopal Church were wrapping up their General Convention, a policy-making gathering that meets every three years, news centered on how they handled a statement on human sexuality.</p>
        <p>But the Episcopalians also adopted several other resolutions, with far less fanfare, one of which calls on members of the 2.4-million-member church to remove guns from their homes, as a step toward protecting children from gun violence.</p>
        <p>The convention, says the resolution, ''calls upon all members of the church to work intentionally in their several communities, legislatures and institutions toward the removal of handguns and assault weapons from our homes, other residential communities and vehicles.''</p>
        <p>The resolution came from the church's Diocese of Chicago, which adopted a similar statement this year. ''I think people are just fed up with the amount of violence in our society and the ready availability of guns for people of any age,'' said Bishop William D. Persell of Chicago.</p>
        <p>''So often in the church, we call on the government or we call on someone else to do something,'' he said. ''For credibility, we should talk about our own lives first.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
