<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Samples From the Albertina, a Princely Collection</title>
    <meta content="05GLUE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DF1638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Samples From the Albertina, a Princely Collection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few art acquisitors of the 18th -- or any -- century had the drive, determination and buying power of Albert, Duke of Saxe-Teschen (1738-1822), for whom the Albertina in Vienna is named. Thanks in large part to his diligence, it is one of the world's greatest holdings of works on paper, housing some 65,000 drawings and watercolors and nearly a million prints from Gothic to contemporary.</p>
        <p>Albert, fourth son of Frederick Augustus II, Prince Elector of Saxony, inherited an interest in art from his paternal ancestors, who had spent lavishly to build a fabulous royal collection in Dresden. He grew up at the Saxon court there, became an army officer and presented himself to the Habsburg royals in Vienna. This underprivileged princeling, as a younger son not an heir to the royal fortune, was lucky enough to win the hand of the young Archduchess Marie Christine of Austria. It was a love match, to be sure, but a generous dowry came with it, assuring Albert of a lifetime art allowance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few art acquisitors of the 18th -- or any -- century had the drive, determination and buying power of Albert, Duke of Saxe-Teschen (1738-1822), for whom the Albertina in Vienna is named. Thanks in large part to his diligence, it is one of the world's greatest holdings of works on paper, housing some 65,000 drawings and watercolors and nearly a million prints from Gothic to contemporary.</p>
        <p>Albert, fourth son of Frederick Augustus II, Prince Elector of Saxony, inherited an interest in art from his paternal ancestors, who had spent lavishly to build a fabulous royal collection in Dresden. He grew up at the Saxon court there, became an army officer and presented himself to the Habsburg royals in Vienna. This underprivileged princeling, as a younger son not an heir to the royal fortune, was lucky enough to win the hand of the young Archduchess Marie Christine of Austria. It was a love match, to be sure, but a generous dowry came with it, assuring Albert of a lifetime art allowance.</p>
        <p>Not only that: his mother-in-law Maria Theresa, Queen of Hungary and the Austrian Netherlands, fixed him up with well-paid, influential posts governing her territories. From a general interest in all forms of art, Albert, who loved to draw, zeroed in on drawings and prints, a pursuit he followed zealously for the rest of his life. He began to collect on a grand scale, at first prints and then drawings, ingesting whole collections at one fell swoop.</p>
        <p>After his death the collection -- at that time consisting of 14,000 drawings and 230,000 prints -- went to his nephew Archduke Charles of Austria; then to Charles's son, Archduke Albrecht. Both augmented it considerably. In 1920 the holdings, kept to this day in Albert's Viennese palace, were combined with those of the Imperial Court Library to form the Albertina. A living collection, it continues to acquire contemporary works as well as old masters, recently venturing into photography and focusing more on the work of Austrian artists.</p>
        <p>A small mixed sampling of holdings from the Albertina -- whose early 19th-century building is now undergoing restoration and expansion -- can be seen at the Frick Collection, in a show organized by the Art Gallery of Ontario and the Albertina in conjunction with the Frick. The 45 master drawings and watercolors, by artists ranging from Michelangelo to Jackson Pollock, include many that have never left Austria or are rarely seen even there.</p>
        <p>One of the extraordinary things about Albert's collection, apart from its depth and breadth, was its objective, writes Barbara Dossi, head of collections at the Albertina, in her recent book ''Albertina: The History of the Collection and its Masterpieces.'' Wanting ''primarily to impart knowledge of art and history of art,'' Albert arranged his holdings not by subject matter, as was the tradition, but by regions, schools and artists in chronological order, in accordance with more modern thought.</p>
        <p>His policy, Ms. Dossi writes, was to amass ''a complex whole, which was also to feature the work of the great masters when and if the rank of work on the art market and the asking price for it met his exacting standards.'' What he achieved, she says, was one of the most important collections in terms of quality and encyclopedic completeness, not only of his own time but of any period from which collections are known.</p>
        <p>One of the great ornaments of the Albertina is its collection of Durer drawings and watercolors. Four are in the show, among them the famous ''Head of an Old Man'' (1521), a study for a painting of St. Jerome. The Durers represent one of Albert's boldest collecting coups. Pushing to acquire them from the Imperial Court Library, he proposed an exchange of far less valuable copperplate engravings. Emperor Francis II, petitioned in Albert's behalf by officials of the library, magnanimously granted permission for the exchange in 1796. Later speculation has it that the emperor wanted to compensate Albert for setbacks in his life and career. Among them was the loss of part of his collection in a shipwreck when he was forced to flee the Netherlands in 1789 during a rebellion brought about by the emperor's radical reforms.</p>
        <p>Among other northern old masters represented here are Rubens, Rembrandt, Albrecht Altdorfer, Hendrick Goltzius and Peter Saenredam. (Unfortunately the Albertina has not provided dates for many objects in the show.) The Rubens drawing, ''Two Young Women, One Holding a Lap Dog'' is particularly fine, depicting the chubby subjects, limned with Rubens's usual over-the-top ebullience, in close girlish conversation as the tiny dog stares solemnly out at the viewer.</p>
        <p>Michelangelo heads the show's Italian old master contingent, with an anatomical study in red chalk, ''Seated Male Nude With Two Arms,'' a preparatory study for one of the figures in the ceiling frescoes of the Sistine Chapel at the Vatican. Raphael, Guercino, Federico Baroci and Giovanni Battista Tiepolo are other stars in this firmament. In Tiepolo's campily exaggerated chalk, pen and wash drawing, ''Saints Fidelis of Signaringen and Joseph of Leonessa Banish Heresy,'' one saint prays while the other gestures ''Out!'' as a fallen Heresy lies prostrate at his feet.</p>
        <p>Works by Nicholas Poussin, Claude Lorrain and Hubert Robert among others speak for the French school. A standout is Poussin's ''Tree Study,'' a pen-and-ink sketch of two brotherly trees, one broken in half and falling sadly to the ground as the other soldiers sturdily on beside it.</p>
        <p>Moving toward our own times, there are works by a number of Austrian artists, ranging from Joseph Danhauser (1805-1845), whose lovely pencil drawing ''Boy Playing the Violin'' evokes the very spirit of musical Vienna, through Gustave Klimt and Egon Schiele to the contemporary artist Franz West, whose ''Made By (Untitled)'' (1976-77) is a satirical candy-box fantasy of a grotesquely distorted nude on a gold ground sprinkled with small hearts. (It would have appalled Albert.)</p>
        <p>Marvelous works by 20th-century masters include Picasso's powerful Cubist ''Head of a Woman,'' presumably his mistress Fernande Olivier; Marc Chagall's ''Lute Player'' (1911), depicting a pixie musician seated on a bed, and the Czech painter Frantisek Kupka's gouache ''Circular Composition,'' which brilliantly balances geometric shapes on a neutral ground.</p>
        <p>Not everything in this show, which includes works by lesser lights as well as masters, is of star quality. Still, it's a teaser for the full Albertina experience and will do nicely until you get to Vienna.</p>
        <p>''Michelangelo to Picasso: Master Drawings from the Collection of the Albertina, Vienna,'' remains at the Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, through June 18.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
