<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Clinton Counsel Grilled on E-Mail Issue</title>
    <meta content="Y05EMA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Natta, Don Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruff, Charles F C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Cheryl D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Cheryl D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0D81638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Clinton Counsel Grilled on E-Mail Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON VAN NATTA Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Natta, Don Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former White House counsel, Charles F C Ruff, testifies before a Congressional panel today that it is 'flat-out wrong' for Republicans to accuse Clinton administration of deliberately concealing a large cache of White House e-mail messages subpoenaed by investigators in 1998; his photo with his former deputy, Cheryl D Mills (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former White House counsel, Charles F. C. Ruff, testified before a Congressional panel today that it was ''flat-out wrong'' for Republicans to accuse the Clinton administration of deliberately concealing a large cache of White House e-mail messages subpoenaed by investigators in 1998.</p>
        <p>''Never -- not once -- did anyone on my staff seek to conceal any document,'' Mr. Ruff told members of the House Government Reform Committee. ''We did our best to act professionally, ethically and responsibly.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former White House counsel, Charles F. C. Ruff, testified before a Congressional panel today that it was ''flat-out wrong'' for Republicans to accuse the Clinton administration of deliberately concealing a large cache of White House e-mail messages subpoenaed by investigators in 1998.</p>
        <p>''Never -- not once -- did anyone on my staff seek to conceal any document,'' Mr. Ruff told members of the House Government Reform Committee. ''We did our best to act professionally, ethically and responsibly.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ruff acknowledged that he might have failed to address the issue aggressively after learning in June 1998 that the White House computer system had not properly stored incoming electronic mail correspondence because of unintentional computer errors.</p>
        <p>''If we failed,'' Mr. Ruff said, ''it was due to our inadvertence and not by intention.''</p>
        <p>At the time, Congress, the Justice Department and the independent counsel's office were seeking White House e-mail messages dealing with a wide range of investigative matters, including campaign fund-raising and Monica S. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Nobody is sure what will be found in the misplaced e-mail messages sent to White House officials from 1996 to 1998. Technicians are methodically retrieving the correspondence from a computer database. White House officials said today that the messages would be turned over to the panel over the next six months.</p>
        <p>Under questioning by the panel's chairman, Representative Dan Burton of Indiana, Mr. Ruff testified that he could not recall whom he had asked to conduct a limited test of the White House's e-mail archive system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruff, who left the White House last summer, said he recalled only that a member of his staff was conducting the search for e-mail messages sent to Ms. Lewinsky, which had been subpoenaed by the independent counsel, Kenneth W. Starr.</p>
        <p>''If I knew who it was, I'd tell you who it was but I do not recall,'' Mr. Ruff told the panel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton's jaw dropped. ''Mr. Ruff, you are one of the brightest lawyers in this town,'' the chairman said. ''Where does the buck stop?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruff replied, ''I took responsibility then, and I take responsibility now.'' A moment later, he added, ''I am willing to suffer the embarrassment if I failed to adequately pursue the matter.''</p>
        <p>Republicans on the panel could barely contain their fury at the White House lawyers for not disclosing the computer glitch after they learned about it nearly two years ago. Congressional Republicans first learned about the missing e-mail messages in an article published in The Washington Times in February.</p>
        <p>''The White House knew about it for almost two years, but they didn't inform the Justice Department until we started looking into it,'' Mr. Burton said. ''And the Justice Department didn't start an investigation until they realized that we were looking into it.''</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman of California, the committee's ranking Democrat, said the loss of the e-mail messages was the product of ''an unfortunate mistake,'' but he added, ''It's not criminal conduct, and it doesn't amount to a scandal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruff's former deputy, Cheryl D. Mills, told the panel she could not remember much about the e-mail episode. But she said she recalled that electronic mail sent to Ms. Lewinsky had been retrieved from the computer system in 1998 and was reviewed by a White House lawyer, who determined that the e-mail messages had already been turned over to Mr. Starr's office.</p>
        <p>At that point, Mr. Ruff said he assumed the e-mail problem had been resolved. Although a second computer glitch affecting the e-mail problem was found in April 1999, Mr. Ruff said he could not recall whether he had been informed about that problem.</p>
        <p>He admitted he had failed to recognize that the computer problem had hampered other White House document productions on a variety of investigative matters, including Whitewater and campaign finance.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, it was my judgment -- or my misjudgment -- that led me to conclude the problem did not have an adverse effect on our prior'' document productions, Mr. Ruff said. ''I candidly put it aside and went on to more pressing matters.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department's campaign finance task force has begun a criminal investigation into whether White House officials had deliberately suppressed the e-mail messages. The task force is also looking into the accusation that White House officials had threatened employees of a nongovernment contractor, Northrop Grumman, if they disclosed that the messages were missing.</p>
        <p>In her opening statement, Ms. Mills accused Republicans on the committee of wasting time and taxpayer dollars on the e-mail issue. She challenged committee members to focus on more important social questions.</p>
        <p>''Nothing you discover here today will feed one person, give shelter to someone who is homeless, educate one child, provide health care for one family or offer justice to one African-American or Hispanic juvenile,'' Ms. Mills said. ''You could do so much to transform our country, but instead you are compelled to use your great authority and resources to address e-mails.''</p>
        <p>In response, Representative Christopher Shays, Republican of Connecticut, said: ''Ms. Mills, you're not the only one disillusioned by this process. I have been pushed from disappointment to anger by the pervasive ethical and moral minimalism of this White House.''</p>
        <p>The deputy White House counsel, Bruce Lindsey, sat in the hearing room's first row behind the witness table. During recesses, Mr. Lindsey leaned close to Ms. Mills and Mr. Ruff to whisper in their ears.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
