<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons Learned Not by the Boy but the Father</title>
    <meta content="05TVWK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE1638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons Learned Not by the Boy but the Father</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With all the times we've seen or read ''Pinocchio,'' the story of a lovable little wooden marionette who yearns to become a real boy, have we ever given a thought to poor Geppetto? There he is, a lonely old toy maker in a tiny Italian village, wishing on a star for the joys of fatherhood, and what does he get? A puppet who comes to life, keeps him up all night asking silly questions, gets into fights at school, gives people splinters when he shakes hands, lies chronically, runs away, falls prey to kidnappers, ends up at a strange amusement park where he turns into a donkey and gets himself (and his father) swallowed by a whale. Not to mention that he doesn't even want to follow in Dad's footsteps as a toy maker. The nerve!</p>
        <p>Well, disappointment, imperfection and abject terror are what being a parent is all about, Mister. And so we are reminded in ''Geppetto,'' a two-hour musical that has its premiere on ''The Wonderful World of Disney'' on Sunday. But what is this message doing in a film made for children?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With all the times we've seen or read ''Pinocchio,'' the story of a lovable little wooden marionette who yearns to become a real boy, have we ever given a thought to poor Geppetto? There he is, a lonely old toy maker in a tiny Italian village, wishing on a star for the joys of fatherhood, and what does he get? A puppet who comes to life, keeps him up all night asking silly questions, gets into fights at school, gives people splinters when he shakes hands, lies chronically, runs away, falls prey to kidnappers, ends up at a strange amusement park where he turns into a donkey and gets himself (and his father) swallowed by a whale. Not to mention that he doesn't even want to follow in Dad's footsteps as a toy maker. The nerve!</p>
        <p>Well, disappointment, imperfection and abject terror are what being a parent is all about, Mister. And so we are reminded in ''Geppetto,'' a two-hour musical that has its premiere on ''The Wonderful World of Disney'' on Sunday. But what is this message doing in a film made for children?</p>
        <p>Once, ''Pinocchio'' was a fable about a child learning valuable lessons: the dangers of lying, of disobeying and of seeking freedom and immediate gratification at the cost of personal identity and safety (on Pleasure Island, as one boy explains, there are ''no rules, no parents and all the candy you can eat''). Pinocchio's becoming a real boy was a metaphor for children's evolution into responsible, caring human beings.</p>
        <p>Now the story is a reproach to mothers and fathers for expecting their children to behave. It's a good point to make to adults -- that no one's children are ever going to be perfect and that they are individuals, not just reflections of us -- but viewers under 12 are going to take this to the bank as further proof that discipline and expectations of responsibility are just cramping their style.</p>
        <p>Children are almost sure to enjoy ''Geppetto'' for other reasons. It consists of almost nonstop singing and dancing. Its special effects, on the night Pinocchio achieves consciousness and speech, are inspired by ''Close Encounters of the Third Kind.'' The film specializes in the ridiculous, like the completely inept magician (Wayne Brady) whom Geppetto happens upon and the town where an eccentric professor (Rene Auberjonois) has a child-making machine that turns out perfect but bland sons and daughters faster than a cup of cappuccino. The film is colorful and often likable, if grossly misguided.</p>
        <p>Drew Carey, surprisingly, pulls off the title role gracefully, making us forget his sitcom and stand-up comic personas for the most part. Julia Louis-Dreyfus has less success as the Blue Fairy, levitating and speaking in a too-refined-to-be-American voice clearly inspired by Glinda the Good Witch in ''The Wizard of Oz.'' Seth Adkins is fine as Pinocchio, but the makeup artist might have worked a little harder on the wood grain of his face. Brent Spiner is effectively evil (and pretty much unrecognizable) as Stromboli, who wants Pinocchio for his traveling puppet show. Usher Raymond has some nice musical moments as the ringleader who carries boys off to Pleasure Island.</p>
        <p>The songs aren't particularly memorable. Some are playful, like the village children's group number ''I Love Toys, Especially When They're Mine.'' (Opening day at Geppetto's toy shop is pictured as the equivalent of the week before Christmas at F.A.O. Schwarz.) Some are sentimental. Geppetto's lyrics tend to be about his ''empty heart'' at the beginning and having given his heart away toward the end.</p>
        <p>Some are instructive. Ms. Louis-Dreyfus's best number is ''Just Because It's Magic Doesn't Mean It's Easy.'' But again the instruction is directed toward the parent, not the child. It doesn't take long for Geppetto to acknowledge that he has ''messed things up'' as a parent and to announce, ''You'd think I was the one with the wooden head.''</p>
        <p>Maybe so, Geppetto, but that's something you can share with Pinocchio when he's 30. Not now.</p>
        <p>THE WONDERFUL WORLD OF DISNEY  Geppetto  ABC, Sunday night at 7</p>
        <p>Teleplay and television story by David I. Stern; based on a story by C. Collodi.; Peter Green, co-executive producer; Ronald E. Frazier, supervising producer; Ted Zachary, producer; Tom Moore, director; music and lyrics by Stephen Schwartz; Stephen M. Katz, director of photography. Produced by James Pentecost Productions, Karz Entertainment Inc. and Walt Disney Television. Drew Carey, Mike Karz and James Pentecost, executive producers.</p>
        <p>WITH: Drew Carey (Geppetto), Julia Louis-Dreyfus (Blue Fairy), Brent Spiner (Stromboli), Rene Auberjonois (Buonragazzo), Seth Adkins (Pinocchio), Usher Raymond (Ringleader), Ana Gasteyer (Signora Giovanni) and Wayne Brady (Magician).</p>
        <p>CUPID AND CATE</p>
        <p>CBS, Sunday night at 9</p>
        <p>Mary-Louise Parker and the writers of the Hallmark Hall of Fame movie she stars in this weekend should sue whoever insisted on the title. This is not, as ''Cupid and Cate'' might suggest, an insipid sitcom about a single woman with a wacky love life and colorfully obnoxious friends. Of course, the film isn't a masterpiece either. It begins as a romantic comedy about a lively young woman (Ms. Parker in half the title role) engaged to a dull man, and it changes halfway through into a somewhat obvious drama about the intrusions of real tragedy into what should be the happiest of times.</p>
        <p>But the story isn't entirely predictable and the casting -- obviously handled by theatergoers -- is great: Bebe Neuwirth as Cate's sister the doctor, Rebecca Luker as the well-accessorized Greenwich sister, Joanna Going as the fashion-model sister and Philip Bosco as their widowed father, who can't seem to utter a sentence without throwing in a criticism of Cate at the end. Peter Gallagher is cast against type as the fun-loving single lawyer who comes into Cate's life at an inconvenient moment. Or is it just in time?</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
