<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shadow on Africa</title>
    <meta content="05ASSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E6D61638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shadow on Africa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <dateline>KINSHASA, Congo, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those hoping for peace in this vast, broken country in the heart of Africa, the news could not have come at a worse time.</p>
        <p>Just before a United Nations Security Council delegation arrived here to weigh the possibility of sending 5,500 peacekeepers to Congo, violence erupted in another corner of Africa. Despite the United Nations' aversion to getting involved in peacekeeping missions in Africa, it had deployed about 8,000 soldiers throughout Sierra Leone in recent months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For those hoping for peace in this vast, broken country in the heart of Africa, the news could not have come at a worse time.</p>
        <p>Just before a United Nations Security Council delegation arrived here to weigh the possibility of sending 5,500 peacekeepers to Congo, violence erupted in another corner of Africa. Despite the United Nations' aversion to getting involved in peacekeeping missions in Africa, it had deployed about 8,000 soldiers throughout Sierra Leone in recent months.</p>
        <p>Now, after what appeared to be coordinated incidents this week at three different spots in that West African nation, four peacekeepers from Kenya are missing and presumed dead. And at least 92 United Nations officials are still being held hostage by a group that the United Nations says is behind the killings and kidnappings: the Revolutionary United Front and its leader, Foday Sankoh, who signed a peace accord last July.</p>
        <p>The events immediately raised doubts about peacekeeping in Congo, in particular, and Africa, in general.</p>
        <p>''Already we know what happened after the tragedy in Somalia,'' Secretary General Kofi Annan said on Wednesday in Paris. In 1993, 24 Pakistanis were killed in Somalia in the worst single attack on United Nations peacekeepers, and 18 American soldiers were also killed there, leading the Clinton administration to oppose future peacekeeping missions in Africa. ''We know that the international community and the Western countries were not ready to go to Rwanda,'' Mr. Annan said. ''And after Sierra Leone, I think there's going to be very little encouragement for any of them to get involved in operations in Africa.''</p>
        <p>At a ceremony today in which the Congolese government agreed on conditions for deploying the force, Richard C. Holbrooke, the United States ambassador to the United Nations, who was leading the delegation, said the events in Sierra Leone should not influence the peace effort here. But he said that Sierra Leone would cast a ''potential shadow'' on United Nations operations and acknowledged that it would now be harder to persuade Congress to finance peacekeeping operations here.</p>
        <p>If the fate of United Nations peacekeeping in Congo is inextricably linked to the crisis in Sierra Leone, it is because of the history of disastrous missions in Africa in the past decade, particularly in Somalia and Rwanda. The contrast between the two nations will also hurt efforts in Congo.</p>
        <p>Sierra Leone's conflict, though unusually cruel, was simple -- essentially a fight over power between a government and a rebellion. Congo, by contrast, is caught up in a bewilderingly complex war involving six nations, three rebel groups and several militias, each fighting for different reasons in a country the size of Western Europe. The United Nations peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone is expected to reach 11,000; a force in Congo, to be effective, would have to number in the tens of thousands, rather than the 5,500 the United Nations is preparing to send.</p>
        <p>The current trouble in Sierra Leone seemed to have resulted in large part because the rebels were never really interested in peace. Mr. Sankoh's organization erected innumerable obstacles, and the majority of the rebels refused to disarm. They have stopped United Nations peacekeepers from deploying in the diamond mining areas, even as they have continued their illegal mining.</p>
        <p>And so it is a fair question to ask whether the warring parties in Congo are really interested in peace.</p>
        <p>Here in Kinshasa, the capital, the signs have not been encouraging. The government of Congo's president, Laurent Kabila, has continually blocked about 100 United Nations monitors in Congo from visiting several areas. About a month ago, the government infuriated the peace mediator, Sir Ketumile Masire, a former president of Botswana, by denying him clearance to fly outside the capital; Mr. Masire abruptly left the country.</p>
        <p>Just before today's signing ceremony, Abdoulaye Yerodia, Mr. Kabila's foreign minister, was asked by reporters whether United Nations officials would now be free to travel everywhere in the country, including to such strategic points as Mbuji-Mayi, the diamond mining center.</p>
        <p>''I can't give an answer to a question I consider a silly question,'' Mr. Yerodia said, after denying that his government had refused United Nations officials access to certain areas.</p>
        <p>As for the other countries fighting in Congo, there is pressure on them, particularly Zimbabwe, to stop their war efforts. But none have achieved the military and security goals that drew them into this conflict in August 1998; all are busy profiting from the Congo's vast mineral resources.</p>
        <p>And so few here believe that they are genuinely interested in peace.</p>
        <p>''Since the start of this war, the country's diamonds have been looted,'' said Kadiata Nzemba Mukamba, who oversaw Congo's diamond mining industry under the late Mobutu Sese Seko and was imprisoned for several months by the Kabila government. ''Rwanda and Uganda, or the government's allies, Zimbabwe and Angola -- all of them have been enriching themselves on our diamonds. So it is not in their interest to stop the war.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kabila's government has also remained deeply reluctant to permit any real political openness here. Under the peace effort, a dialogue is supposed to take place involving the government, rebels and the political opposition, among other organizations. But Mr. Kabila's government has insisted that the dialogue occur in Kinshasa, an unacceptable location to the rebels.</p>
        <p>''All Kabila does is buy time,'' said Jean-Jacques Kawende, a senior official at the Congolese National Movement of Lumumba, a party headed by Francois Lumumba. Mr. Lumumba, the son of Congo's first prime minister, Patrice Lumumba, was recently jailed for several days by the government, which routinely detains political opponents.</p>
        <p>''He creates obstacles or makes impossible demands that buy him time, so that he can continue this war,'' Mr. Kawende said of Mr. Kabila. ''Pressure from the international community is the only way that Kabila and the others in this war will be pushed toward peace.''</p>
        <p>What makes it even more difficult for the United Nations to push the players in this war toward peace, compared with Sierra Leone's, is the deep distrust that some countries, especially Rwanda, hold for the United Nations. The Tutsi-led government of Rwanda views the United Nations as having done little to stop the 1994 genocide in which Rwanda's Hutus killed at least half a million Tutsis.</p>
        <p>Stung by criticism that the West was willing to support expensive operations in Kosovo and East Timor, but not Africa, the United States backed the missions in Sierra Leone and Congo last year. And so no matter the difficulties in Sierra Leone, they will amount to a test case for Congo and Africa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
