<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loews Cineplex plans interactive displays of commercial video clips in theater lobbies.</title>
    <meta content="Y05ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DB1638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loews Cineplex plans interactive displays of commercial video clips in theater lobbies.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliot</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE next time you step inside the Megacinema Plethoraplex, or whatever your local movie palace is called, you will most likely notice the myriad ways that Hollywood embraces Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>There will probably be advertising on the popcorn bags, on the racks of postcards near the ticket counter, on the signs festooning the lobby and on the slides appearing on screen before the show. There will also probably be some commercials that run before the film starts, not to mention trailers, which are of course ads for other movies. And during the film, you may glimpse products whose makers paid to place them there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE next time you step inside the Megacinema Plethoraplex, or whatever your local movie palace is called, you will most likely notice the myriad ways that Hollywood embraces Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>There will probably be advertising on the popcorn bags, on the racks of postcards near the ticket counter, on the signs festooning the lobby and on the slides appearing on screen before the show. There will also probably be some commercials that run before the film starts, not to mention trailers, which are of course ads for other movies. And during the film, you may glimpse products whose makers paid to place them there.</p>
        <p>So what might you think about plans by a giant film exhibitor and a company that distributes sponsored postcards at the movies to bring to theater lobbies interactive wall-mounted displays that show commercial video clips at the touch of a button? Maybe it would be, to cite the title of a 1971 film with Peter Fonda and Dennis Hopper, ''The Last Movie'' you would go to see.</p>
        <p>That obviously is not the intent of the theater chain, Loews Cineplex Entertainment, nor of the postcard marketer, Max Racks Inc. Their goal for the wall display, named Bluscreen, is to provide another advertising medium for marketers attracted to the appealing demographic profiles of moviegoers without alienating those consumers.</p>
        <p>''It's all about choice,'' said Sylvie Anapol, president at Max Racks in New York.</p>
        <p>''People get involved in our advertising only if they choose to,'' she added. ''They can walk by or can stop and interact with it. They're not captives of it or hostages to it in any way.''</p>
        <p>That perspective is shared by executives at Loews Cineplex, which operates 3,000 screens at 400 locations around the world.</p>
        <p>''The customer makes the decision to go up to the display and choose an advertisement'' to watch, said Marc Pascucci, senior vice president for marketing at Loews Cineplex in New York.</p>
        <p>''The real estate in our theaters is very valuable,'' he added, ''and we've tried kiosks before, but they've never been able to withstand usage. This seems to be working.''</p>
        <p>Bluscreen, the most recent entry in the booming market for what is known as place-based advertising, is being tested in 11 Loews Cineplex theaters in Boston, Chicago, Los Angeles, New York (two Manhattan locations), San Francisco and Seattle. The video clips in the test are for advertisers that sponsor Max Racks postcard ads; they are not being charged for the test.</p>
        <p>''A lot of our postcard advertisers are doing great creative on TV,'' said Ms. Anapol, who heads Max Racks with Michael Gitter, vice president. ''My partner and I thought kiosk-type advertising seemed like a natural.''</p>
        <p>The test video clips have included trailers for films like ''Mission to Mars'' and ''The Road to El Dorado.'' There have also been spots for Web sites like Kozmo.com and Motorola.com; retailers like Sephora; and products like American Express cards and Todd Oldham jeans.</p>
        <p>''Instead of yelling out at the customer, it's self-activating,'' said Ross Klein, senior vice president for marketing at the Sun Apparel division of Jones New York, which makes the Oldham jeans line. ''I liked that.''</p>
        <p>Gail Wasserman, a vice president at the American Express Company in New York, which is advertising its new Blue charge card on Bluscreen -- natch -- had this to say: ''We're looking at a lot of different ways to use alternative media, from popcorn bags to the backs of Metrocards to water bottles in health clubs. We want to reach people where they work and play.''</p>
        <p>Another crucial place to reach consumers in a buying mood is where they shop. That is the idea behind a campaign for eDiets.com, which operates a Web site providing diet and fitness information. In addition to radio, print and online ads, dieters will see place-based promotions for eDiets.com on supermarket floors, shopping carts and even fruit stickers.</p>
        <p>''Media is the new creative department,'' said Mark DiMassimo, president and executive creative director at the eDiets.com agency, DiMassimo Brand Advertising in New York.</p>
        <p>''If we can show up in places where the message is relevant, then the ads make sense,'' he added. ''If we were just shilling, we'd be adding to the clutter.''</p>
        <p>Back in the theaters, Max Racks plans to install 100 Bluscreen wall displays in the third quarter, then expand to 480 displays, or about a pair for every Loews Cineplex theater in the United States.</p>
        <p>''We're in the process of selling it right now,'' Ms. Anapol said, ''and determining the cost structure.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
