<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residential Real Estate; Harlem to Add 8 Rental Buildings in City Program</title>
    <meta content="05REAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DF1738F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residential Real Estate; Harlem to Add 8 Rental Buildings in City Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight vacant or partly occupied city-owned lots in Harlem are to be filled over the next two and half years with 726 mixed-income rental apartments under a new city program.</p>
        <p>The studio to three-bedroom units will be in 4- to 11-story buildings at cross streets along Frederick Douglass Boulevard, Fifth, First and Bradhurst Avenues. Spread among the buildings will also be 104,000 square feet of space for professional offices, stores and community uses, including an annex for a charter school. While the plans for these buildings still must undergo review and could be modified, construction is expected to start in the summer of 2001, city housing officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eight vacant or partly occupied city-owned lots in Harlem are to be filled over the next two and half years with 726 mixed-income rental apartments under a new city program.</p>
        <p>The studio to three-bedroom units will be in 4- to 11-story buildings at cross streets along Frederick Douglass Boulevard, Fifth, First and Bradhurst Avenues. Spread among the buildings will also be 104,000 square feet of space for professional offices, stores and community uses, including an annex for a charter school. While the plans for these buildings still must undergo review and could be modified, construction is expected to start in the summer of 2001, city housing officials said.</p>
        <p>Most of the apartments are to be rented with income limits to tenants who may make up to $140,500 a year, depending on family size. Some units are to be leased at market rents.</p>
        <p>The projects are part of the Cornerstone Program, started by New York City's Department of Housing Preservation and Development last October to spur mixed-income housing in areas where the city has made substantial investments and private market forces have taken hold. Initially, the program will focus on Harlem, ''where the strength of the private market is most evident,'' said Richard T. Roberts, the commissioner of the housing department.</p>
        <p>''The program is intended to send a clear signal that we want to focus on housing that relies more on private financing and less on public subsidies,'' he said. Of the $145 million being invested in the initial projects, $11.7 million is in direct public subsidy, he said.</p>
        <p>The city is selling the first eight sites for $1 each to developers, whose proposals were selected last month from 44 others. In turn, the developers ''dictated what was viable to develop on the sites'' and chose from several existing public financing sources, Mr. Roberts said.</p>
        <p>While many civic and political leaders in Harlem have welcomed the new housing, there are concerns. One is the lack of opportunities for home ownership; another is that few Harlem-based development groups were selected to build the projects.</p>
        <p>The developers were chosen on the strength of their proposals, development records and access to ''the equity to successfully develop the projects,'' Mr. Roberts said.</p>
        <p>Five of the initial eight projects are to receive financing from the New York City Housing Development Corporation's New Housing Opportunities Program. It provides developers with bond financing as well as a subsidy in the form of a second loan at an interest rate of 1 percent for up to $40,000 per unit.</p>
        <p>Depending on family size, the tenant's annual income may not exceed seven or eight times the monthly rents, or 250 percent of the median city income, or $140,500, whichever is less. Tenants are expected typically to earn $40,000 to $90,000 a year. Maximum monthly rents are to range from $850 for a studio to $1,750 for a three-bedroom unit.</p>
        <p>Among the projects is a 64-unit, 6-story apartment building at the southwest corner of Frederick Douglass Boulevard and West 117th Street. The $15 million project will include a 31,500-square-foot annex for the John A. Reisenbach Charter School as well as 5,300 square feet of stores. It will be developed using $1.9 million in bond financing from the city's Housing Development Corporation and $1 million from the borough president's office. The developer is a joint venture of TNS Development Group of Mount Vernon and Lemle &amp; Wolff of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''Harlem is an active market where rents are rising,'' said Steven M. Judelson, vice president of TNS. ''But today, the rental income is still not enough to cover the cost of developing and owning the project.''</p>
        <p>He said the partners would invest $2.2 million of their own money into the project and secure the rest from private sources. Rents for the one- to three-bedroom apartments are expected to be $850 to $1,250 a month.</p>
        <p>The partners, using $1.2 million in private financing, will also redevelop a smaller site, about 200 feet east of their corner site, into three four-story three-family homes.</p>
        <p>The other middle-income projects are a 145-apartment building on the west side of Fifth Avenue between 138th and 139th Streets; a 144-unit structure on the west side of First Avenue between 102nd and 103rd Streets; a 98-unit building on the northeast corner of Douglass Boulevard and West 117th Street; and a 41-unit on the south side of 117th Street between Douglass Boulevard and St. Nicholas Avenue.</p>
        <p>The final two developments, both on Bradhurst Avenue, are proposed as so-called 80-20 projects. With such projects, the state or the city issues tax-exempt bonds to provide financing to builders, who in return keep 20 percent of the rentals affordable to low-income tenants. The remaining units are leased at market rents.</p>
        <p>Those projects -- one with 153 apartments in an 11-story, $35 million building, the other with 60 units in a 5-story $16 million structure -- are to rise on the northeast corner and southwest corner respectively of Bradhurst Avenue and West 145th Street. The developer is a partnership between the Richman Group, based in Elmsford, N.Y., and the Gotham Organization of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Plans call for each of the buildings to have one- to three-bedroom apartments, with 608 to 1,200 square feet. The affordable units will be for tenants with annual incomes of up to $32,600, depending on family size. Monthly rents for the market-rate apartments are expected to be $1,200 to $2,700 a month, said Pam King, assistant vice president of the Richman Group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
