<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sri Lanka Lists Tough New Controls on Speech and Property</title>
    <meta content="05LANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tamils (Ethnic Group)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sri Lanka</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Sri Lanka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D71638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sri Lanka Lists Tough New Controls on Speech and Property</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka, May 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sri Lanka government, after series of humbling military defeats at hands of Tamil rebels, goes on 'war footing;' announces that authorities will now be able to confiscate private property, shut newspapers and prohibit public meetings, strikes and criticisms of president, if doing so is deemed necessary to national security (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a series of humbling military defeats at the hands of Tamil rebels, the government of Sri Lanka, a democracy, has gone on a ''war footing.'' It announced today that authorities would now be able to confiscate private property, shut newspapers and prohibit public meetings, strikes and criticism of the president, if doing so is deemed necessary to the national security.</p>
        <p>Up to now, the government had routinely censored Sri Lankan news reports about its war with the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, a guerrilla group that has been battling for a separate homeland for the Tamil minority since 1983. And a state of emergency already allowed security forces to conduct searches without court orders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a series of humbling military defeats at the hands of Tamil rebels, the government of Sri Lanka, a democracy, has gone on a ''war footing.'' It announced today that authorities would now be able to confiscate private property, shut newspapers and prohibit public meetings, strikes and criticism of the president, if doing so is deemed necessary to the national security.</p>
        <p>Up to now, the government had routinely censored Sri Lankan news reports about its war with the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, a guerrilla group that has been battling for a separate homeland for the Tamil minority since 1983. And a state of emergency already allowed security forces to conduct searches without court orders.</p>
        <p>But the 37 pages of new regulations, promulgated under the Public Security Ordinance, go further. Newspapers that print reports without submitting them first to the government for censorship face the seizure of printing presses and closing. Foreign as well as Sri Lankan journalists will be required to turn over their articles before publication for scrutiny.</p>
        <p>Meetings and marches may be banned if they are likely to cause a disturbance or ''promote disaffection,'' the regulations say. And authorities may requisition houses, cars and even people to work as directed. Resisters face a trial and the forfeiture of all property to the government.</p>
        <p>President Chandrika Kumaratunga and her administration have been defensive over the war since April 22, when 10,000 troops were forced by a smaller number of rebels to abandon their crucial military base at Elephant Pass. The base rested on a thin strip that connects the mainland to the Jaffna Peninsula in the north of this island country just below the southern tip of India.</p>
        <p>The Tigers have since seized control of another base and are threatening to take the city of Jaffna, the cultural heart of the Tamil-dominated north.</p>
        <p>The opposition United National Party accused the government today of using the new regulations to squelch dissent in the name of security. ''These measures are taken only to keep the truth from the people of this country and hide the debacles caused due to the poor strategy adopted by the government,'' the party said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Some experts said the tough line might also be part of a strategy to control right-wing Sinhalese militants who are calling for an all-out war on the rebels and oppose the efforts to begin peace talks with the Tigers.</p>
        <p>In parliamentary elections this year, Ms. Kumaratunga's party will undoubtedly face tough opposition from candidates who contend that it was the government's incompetence that let the rebels gain the upper hand in the north -- five years after the government had recovered the same territory from the rebels and held on to it at great human cost.</p>
        <p>There are also fears that if the rebels take Jaffna, the hard-liners among the majority Sinhalese could fan the flames of rage against Tamils in the south, leading to the widespread violence against Tamils that has scarred the country before.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how long the new regulations will be in place or how they will affect the elections, especially in light of the restrictions on criticizing the president. The current term of Parliament is scheduled to run out in mid-August. The press had already been chafing under the old censorship rules. As the new ones begin to be enforced, they will undoubtedly stir greater discontent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
