<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Posters For Profit</title>
    <meta content="05FLIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6D91F39F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Posters For Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the resident expert on film-related autographs and posters on the popular PBS series ''Antiques Roadshow,'' Rudy Franchi travels the country evaluating precious (and not-so-precious) scraps of paper brought to him by hopeful owners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franchi, a native New Yorker, is also the owner of the Nostalgia Factory (www.nostalgia.com), a Boston-based Internet business that is one of the leading sources of new and old film memorabilia. Recently he was appointed the poster consultant for Christie's East, where he is supervising an auction of 300 rare pieces to be held on May 24 at 2 p.m. in Manhattan. Viewing begins on May 20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the resident expert on film-related autographs and posters on the popular PBS series ''Antiques Roadshow,'' Rudy Franchi travels the country evaluating precious (and not-so-precious) scraps of paper brought to him by hopeful owners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franchi, a native New Yorker, is also the owner of the Nostalgia Factory (www.nostalgia.com), a Boston-based Internet business that is one of the leading sources of new and old film memorabilia. Recently he was appointed the poster consultant for Christie's East, where he is supervising an auction of 300 rare pieces to be held on May 24 at 2 p.m. in Manhattan. Viewing begins on May 20.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Franchi's own shelves are bare. ''I had a nice Orson Welles collection,'' he said, ''but I sold it recently. There's a collector in upstate New York who is building a new headquarters for his garbage-collecting company, and it's going to be a shrine to Welles. Every room has Welles posters and Welles memorabilia. I'm in the process of putting together a complete set of lobby cards for 'Citizen Kane' for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franchi may no longer keep his trophies, but he clearly still enjoys the thrill of the hunt. ''Every auction needs a calling card, and what really drove me on this one was the 'Casablanca' poster, which is the last lot. I'd known where it was hidden for a long time, and I could never get the guy to bring it out. Finally when I got Christie's, I called him up and said, 'I'm the poster consultant for Christie's, and I'd like your ''Casablanca,'' and he said, 'You just said the magic word.' '' The poster, known as a ''six-sheet'' because of its size, measures 81 by 81 inches and is listed with an estimate of $115,000 to $125,000.</p>
        <p>''Then I discovered the 'Grand Hotel' one-sheet, which is the only known poster for the original release, and 'The Rounders,' the earliest known Chaplin poster,'' Mr. Franchi said. ''It's from 1914, and it's in beautiful condition, with almost no restoration. This couple down in Florida, a pair of retired schoolteachers, had them.</p>
        <p>''Their uncle had run a movie theater in the Midwest, and he just kept things. At one point he put them in a trunk and shipped them to them. He said, 'I don't have an inheritance to give you, but maybe someday these will be worth something.' '' Mr. Franchi estimates ''Grand Hotel'' will sell for $12,000 to $15,000, and ''The Rounders'' for $8,000 to $10,000.</p>
        <p>He is already lining up material for his next auction, set for the fall. ''I've taken in two spectacular pieces. One is a major 'King Kong' three-sheet from a Hollywood director who has a huge collection, and the other is the only known half-sheet for 'The Jazz Singer.' It's the one with Jolson in blackface, and it is a fantastic graphic.''</p>
        <p>Pushing the Limit</p>
        <p>In Mexico the director Alfonso Cuaron is completing a film that promises to be radically different from his two American studio projects, ''The Little Princess'' and ''Great Expectations.''</p>
        <p>''Y Tu Mama Tambien'' is the story of two hormonally supercharged teenage boys who take an unhappily married 28-year-old woman on a beach vacation. The script suggests that this will not be a movie for family outings. It is about as explicit as explicit can be.</p>
        <p>''Y Tu Mama Tambien'' -- it translates as ''So's Your Mother'' but the English title has not yet been chosen -- is being produced by a New York company, Good Machine, as the first in a series of films titled ''Uncensored Cinema.''</p>
        <p>James Schamus, a screenwriter (''The Ice Storm'') and producer (''Happiness,'' the controversial 1998 comedy by Tod Solondz) who is one of the founding partners of Good Machine, explained the idea behind the series:</p>
        <p>''In terms of what's cutting-edge in independent cinema these days, we are seeing more and more people moving to the margins of what has been in the past the outer limits of representation of sexual relationships. I think that the art-house audiences are responding instinctively to the recent wave of transgressions and are expecting real artists to go further. What we're finding is that a lot of people we think of as cinema artists are beginning to take an interest in images and representations that have to date been taboo for more mainstream media.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''The old distinctions between pornography on the one hand and erotica on the other are of little or no interest. It used to be in the good old, or bad old, days that one could go just so far and say: 'You see, I'm not doing pornography, I'm doing erotica.' The filmmakers we have been talking to have very little interest in that distinction. What they're interested in is pushing the boundaries of representation and coming up with new ways to think through representing the human condition and in particular the aspects of that condition that pertain to the sexual side of things.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Schamus is reluctant to release the names of filmmakers with whom his company is still in negotiations, talks have been held with well-known directors from Britain, France and the United States. ''We're saying two things to filmmakers as we begin this process,'' he said. ''One is, we're interested in creating a production context which allows for the absolute maximum in creativity and freedom for the filmmakers and that requires budgets that are reasonable, and finally we fully expect and in fact require that people be willing to go the NC-17 route.''</p>
        <p>When Good Machine's ''Happiness,'' which dealt with sexual desperation in the suburbs of New Jersey, was slapped with an NC-17 rating, its distributor, October Films, then a subsidiary of Universal, dropped it from its release schedule. ''That let us know what the boundaries are when corporate censorship takes over,'' Mr. Schamus said. ''So in this round, that's why I think we'll be rather unflappable.''</p>
        <p>Au Revoir</p>
        <p>Olivier Barrot, the French television journalist who was the heir apparent to the directorship of the Cannes Film Festival, abruptly left his interim post as the festival's artistic consultant on April 18, the day the list of films selected for this year's festival was released to the press. ''My functions were put to an end, brutally and unilaterally,'' Mr. Barrot told Le Monde, without expanding on the reasons for the separation, though in an article published in the Paris daily Liberation on April 28 he described the festival's selection process as uneven and rebuked the festival for not working more seriously with Hollywood. He could not be reached for comment this week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrot's departure was confirmed by Gilles Jacob, the festival's director for the last 22 years. Mr. Jacob's office declined further comment.</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
