<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stanton and Nelson Enjoy Status as Setup Men for Rivera</title>
    <meta content="05YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFD71638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stanton and Nelson Enjoy Status as Setup Men for Rivera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre reaches to take the baseball from them, but they don't want to share. At that moment on the mound, when the competitive part of their personalities are most evident, Mike Stanton and Jeff Nelson often appear to be barely suppressing fury, the way a frustrated kid does just before flipping a Monopoly board.</p>
        <p>But Stanton and Nelson dutifully turn over the ball to the Yankees' manager, knowing Torre is probably  relaying it to the closer, Mariano Rivera. Their satisfaction comes later, when they loiter in the aftermath of another victory and feel they played their part as supporting actors. This is the fourth season Stanton and Nelson have served as setup men and Rivera has finished games for the Yankees, the kind of collective tenure that has been virtually nonexistent since the advent of free agency a quarter century ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre reaches to take the baseball from them, but they don't want to share. At that moment on the mound, when the competitive part of their personalities are most evident, Mike Stanton and Jeff Nelson often appear to be barely suppressing fury, the way a frustrated kid does just before flipping a Monopoly board.</p>
        <p>But Stanton and Nelson dutifully turn over the ball to the Yankees' manager, knowing Torre is probably  relaying it to the closer, Mariano Rivera. Their satisfaction comes later, when they loiter in the aftermath of another victory and feel they played their part as supporting actors. This is the fourth season Stanton and Nelson have served as setup men and Rivera has finished games for the Yankees, the kind of collective tenure that has been virtually nonexistent since the advent of free agency a quarter century ago.</p>
        <p>Teams usually cannot hold together their bullpens to this extent. Most setup men aspire to be closers, for the esteem and the extra pay that comes with being a closer, and many setup men graduate into the role of closers, as Rivera did. There are injuries, slumps and there are the financial considerations.</p>
        <p>Few teams can afford to pay top dollars for a closer and two setup men, the way the Yankees have. Sparky Lyle could not coexist with Goose Gossage in the late 1970's, the team of Gossage and Ron Davis broke apart in the early 1980's, and the dynamic Cincinnati Reds trio of Randy Myers, Rob Dibble and Norm Charlton -- the Nasty Boys -- fractured after one incredible season in 1990.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees' trio is in its fourth year, to great effect: the bullpen is 8-0 and has an earned run average of 1.20 over its last 12 games. Early in their bid for a third consecutive title, the Yankees are 18-8, in spite of a struggling offense and erratic starting pitching and defense. The bullpen has been consistent in its excellence throughout, with Stanton, Nelson and Rivera at the core. The Yankees begin a three-game series with the Baltimore Orioles at Yankee Stadium tonight.</p>
        <p>''The bullpen has been terrific,'' Torre said, ''and as long as you don't overuse them and abuse them, they figure to do that for us. They've been huge.''</p>
        <p>They could not work as a unit if they didn't embrace their roles. Stanton was the closer for the Atlanta Braves at one time, saving 27 games in 1993, but he has twice signed lucrative three-year deals with the Yankees -- most recently after last season. Nelson signed a three-year, $5.3 million deal before the 1998 season, and he has said flatly that he would  like to negotiate another contract with the Yankees before he becomes eligible for free agency in the fall.</p>
        <p>They both know Rivera is the closer and will be for the future. ''For both of us, I don't think it's in our mind we're going to close games,'' Nelson said. ''You might get your one occasional save a year. But otherwise you accept your role and you know what you have to do. Mariano is the best closer in the game, and everybody accepts that. We just have to be his support staff.</p>
        <p>''I like what I do, coming into games in the seventh and eighth inning. Sometimes it's a tougher job in a way, but it's just a role that I'm satisfied with. I like being the setup guy.''</p>
        <p>Nelson believes he would probably  succeed as a closer elsewhere. ''But that might mean that I would have to go to a team that doesn't win,'' he said. ''I enjoy winning and I enjoy going to the postseason.''</p>
        <p>''The only time you ever really get any recognition as a setup man is when you give up the game,'' Nelson continued, stating a general truth. ''But I get enough recognition from my teammates. I know what kind of job I have to do, and nowadays you know what a big part the bullpen plays.''</p>
        <p>Stanton said: ''I want to win. What else is there?''</p>
        <p>Mel Stottlemyre, the Yankees' pitching coach, said the relievers in the Yankees' bullpen have shaped personal goals into ''the team concept.''</p>
        <p>''We really have that, probably much more than any team I've been associated with, because they take a lot of pride in their roles,'' Stottlemyre said.</p>
        <p>Nelson, who is particularly effective against right-handed batters, is 4-0 with a 1.65 E.R.A. and 21 strikeouts in 16 1/3 innings. Rivera has 10 saves and 2 victories in 12 appearances. Stanton, the left-hander, has 2 walks and 12 strikeouts in 11 2/3 innings, with a 2.31 E.R.A., and he leads in appearances with 15.</p>
        <p>Rivera is quiet and gracious, not given to flaunting his status. He does not ask for special treatment, Stottlemyre said, such as pitching only the ninth inning. He follows orders, getting three outs or four or whatever is asked of him, and does nothing to create tension with Nelson or Stanton. A situation ripe for personality conflict is defused. He acknowledges how important Stanton and Nelson are to him, in absorbing innings he might otherwise have to pitch, and creating situations for him. ''They are the heart of the bullpen,'' Rivera said.</p>
        <p>If Rivera had a ''really arrogant attitude, it would be different down there,'' Nelson said. ''If he was like, 'I'm the closer, I'm the guy,' or 'I'm not coming out until I think I should,' it would be really tough for everybody down there.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, when Nelson or Stanton is pitching and Torre decides to make a change, their faces will tighten and redden and they will march off the mound, head down, preferring to pitch to the next hitter, and maybe the hitters that follow as well.</p>
        <p>''You get mad because you're competitive and you're frustrated and you want to get that guy out,'' Nelson said. ''But you realize the situation; that's just the role.''</p>
        <p>Stanton might be coming in, or Rivera. It's a combination that has been working over four seasons, and counting.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CHUCK KNOBLAUCH had a bone scan and arthrogram on his left wrist at Beth Israel North Hospital yesterday, and doctors again reached the conclusion that Knoblauch has a mild sprain. General Manager BRIAN CASHMAN said that the Yankees have no intention of putting him on the disabled list now and that he will be evaluated daily. . . . SCOTT ERICKSON, back from elbow surgery, will make his first start of the season for the Baltimore Orioles today, against the Yankees' ORLANDO HERNANDEZ, in the first of three games between the first- and second-place teams in the American League East. Baltimore's PAT RAPP faces ROGER CLEMENS tomorrow, and SIDNEY PONSON throws against RAMIRO MENDOZA Sunday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
