<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Rising Steadily, Productivity Slows in First Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y05ECON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1D81638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Rising Steadily, Productivity Slows in First Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After rising spectacularly for six months, the productivity of American workers climbed more slowly in the first quarter, the Bureau of Labor Statistics reported yesterday. Once again, most of the improvement came in the manufacture of computers, machinery, autos, appliances and other durable goods -- particularly computers and the chips that go into them.</p>
        <p>Labor productivity rose at a 2.4 percent annual rate. That was less than half the improvement in the two previous quarters and, indeed, one of the poorer quarterly performances in the last two years. But over the last four quarters, productivity is still rising at a very strong 3.7 percent, unchanged from December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After rising spectacularly for six months, the productivity of American workers climbed more slowly in the first quarter, the Bureau of Labor Statistics reported yesterday. Once again, most of the improvement came in the manufacture of computers, machinery, autos, appliances and other durable goods -- particularly computers and the chips that go into them.</p>
        <p>Labor productivity rose at a 2.4 percent annual rate. That was less than half the improvement in the two previous quarters and, indeed, one of the poorer quarterly performances in the last two years. But over the last four quarters, productivity is still rising at a very strong 3.7 percent, unchanged from December.</p>
        <p>''Underlying productivity is still very strong,'' said James Glassman, senior domestic economist at Chase Manhattan Bank.</p>
        <p>The labor productivity growth rate published by the bureau is the chief measure of the efficiency of the average American worker. When the growth rate rises at a 2.4 percent annual rate, that means in effect that a steelworker, for example, has improved his efficiency sufficiently to produce $102.40 worth of steel each hour, up from $100. Or an auto mechanic, given better tools, or simply working faster, has increased the garage's revenue from repairing cars by a similar amount.</p>
        <p>Higher productivity means that companies collect more revenue without employing more labor. The additional money can then go into raising profits or raising wages, or both, without having to raise prices. ''There is not a lot of inflation pressure coming from labor costs yet,'' said Ken Matheny, senior economist at Macroeconomic Advisers in St. Louis, ''but that situation could quickly reverse.''</p>
        <p>Unit labor costs, the outlay in wages and benefits to labor for making a fixed amount of steel or repairing a car, did rise at a 1.8 percent annual rate in the first quarter, after having fallen in the two previous quarters. But over the last 12 months, from April 1999 through March of this year, unit labor costs were up only 0.7 percent.</p>
        <p>The strong productivity growth -- averaging 2.8 percent annually since the end of 1995, up from 1.8 percent in the first half of the decade and even slower rates in most of the 1980's and 1970's -- helps to explain why inflation has remained mild.</p>
        <p>Another measure of labor costs, however, is not as promising. Hourly compensation -- covering every outlay for labor, including bonuses and stock options, when they are cashed in -- rose at a 4.2 percent annual rate in the first quarter, up from 3.8 percent in the fourth, the bureau reported yesterday. Although 4.2 percent represents one of the smallest quarterly increases in the last two years, many economists on Wall Street nevertheless expressed the worry that inflationary pressures were developing.</p>
        <p>They note that the rise in compensation is now clearly outstripping the rise in productivity, a trend not as clear in the third and fourth quarters of 1999, when productivity grew at annual rates of 5 percent and 6.9 percent, respectively.</p>
        <p>If productivity growth is slowing, and it may be, Mr. Matheny said, that would create inflationary wage pressures.</p>
        <p>For many economists, the most interesting issue is whether the surge in productivity since 1995 reflects rising productivity throughout the economy or is narrowly focused. And the answer appears to be narrowly focused, on durable manufactured goods: machinery, steel, appliances, vehicles, computers, semiconductors, communications equipment and the like.</p>
        <p>Those goods account for 12 percent of the nation's nonfarm business output, and if they are subtracted, then the productivity growth rate for the remaining 88 percent is only 1.8 percent, said Robert Gordon, a Northwestern University economist.</p>
        <p>Other experts gave similar credit to the efficiencies achieved in manufacturing durable goods, particularly computers, semiconductors and communications equipment. Part of the strong productivity growth in computers represents improvement in quality. Workers, in effect, get credit for manufacturing ever more powerful and more valuable computers.</p>
        <p>A drag on productivity in the first quarter came in the service sector, in such things as legal and educational services and auto repair. The number of hours worked rose more quickly in the first quarter than output, contributing to the slower productivity growth rate.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department also contributed -- by making payments in the fourth quarter for goods and services produced in the first. The payments were added to fourth-quarter output, but the hours worked to produce the prepaid goods and services were registered in the first.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
