<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Harrelson Now Pitching His Own Team</title>
    <meta content="05VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3D71638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Harrelson Now Pitching His Own Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is called minor league, but the manager quotes Casey Stengel from memory. It is called minor league but the manager behaves like Gil Hodges from memory.</p>
        <p>It is called minor league, but most of the seats are sculptured, and there are gift shops and luxury boxes, for goodness' sake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is called minor league, but the manager quotes Casey Stengel from memory. It is called minor league but the manager behaves like Gil Hodges from memory.</p>
        <p>It is called minor league, but most of the seats are sculptured, and there are gift shops and luxury boxes, for goodness' sake.</p>
        <p>In truth, Bud Harrelson has more in common with Joan Payson than his early managers. The rather jolly first owner of the Mets never put on a uniform and tried to manage, but here is Bud Harrelson, a major investor in a new team called the Long Island Ducks, hitting fungoes and coaching third base and recruiting players, and even giving calm Hodges-like counsel to an umpire.</p>
        <p>Harrelson has put up his own money to be part of either a fad or a resurgence of minor league baseball. He is not only wearing his old No. 3 but he is also the president of the independent Atlantic League, with eight teams including the Ducks, who are based in Central Islip, N.Y. -- ''exactly 4.2 miles from my house,'' notes Harrelson, who considers himself a homebody.</p>
        <p>He doesn't see himself riding the bus from Aberdeen, Md., to Lehigh Valley, Pa., to Newark and Somerset and Atlantic City in New Jersey to Bridgeport, Conn., to Nashua, N.H., for long.</p>
        <p>But for now, Bud Harrelson is the most visible big-league icon in this young league. He played in two World Series, grappled in the dust with Pete Rose, waved runners around third on that manic Mookie night in 1986, went slightly mad managing the Mets, but now is a patient 56-year-old builder of ball teams.</p>
        <p>''What else do I know?'' Harrelson said the other night. ''I wanted something I could get involved in. I didn't care for restaurants, things like that. I know this.''</p>
        <p>This venture goes beyond building malls or multiplexes or theme restaurants, although it surely aims for those same discretionary dollars. Minor league baseball does not exist in a vacuum but rather for its mystical links to the major leagues.</p>
        <p>That 35-year-old playing first base for the Ducks, Doug Jennings, got a hit in the 1990 World Series for Oakland. That chap sitting by the Newark dugout, the very hands-on owner of the Bears, Rick Cerone, once told off his owner, a chap named Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>That youngster smacking the ball for the Bears, Bobby Hill, an all-American out of the University of Miami, is only waiting for the major league draft in June. Catch him now for single-digit dollars, right in downtown Newark, where the old Newark Bears once produced future Yankees.</p>
        <p>The purpose of this league is to make money, draw fans, win games, propel players toward the majors, teach the game, entertain, all at the same time. Harrelson regards baseball as something worth passing on, the way others passed it on to him.</p>
        <p>There was Charles Dillon Stengel, waiting impatiently for the youth of America. One early spring the hapless Mets brought in a scrawny shortstop and suggested he try switch-hitting. (''Why wouldn't ya wanna. . . .?'' as the Old Man used to say in Socratic fashion.)</p>
        <p>''I was out in the back cage one morning all by myself, just taking my cuts,'' Harrelson recalled the other night. ''Suddenly I heard this voice. 'Hey!' He put me in the starting lineup that day. Led off against Bob Gibson, batting lefty. I bunted one down the third-base line for a hit.''</p>
        <p>Casey turned him over to Solomon Hemus, a savvy coach, and Roy McMillan, a grizzled shortstop, until the kid was ready.</p>
        <p>Now Harrelson aims for the same instincts Casey had. The other night in Newark he sent his 35-year-old player-coach, Bert Heffernan, a catcher who went 1 for 11 for Seattle in 1992, out to play left field to get some swings. Heffernan, who had sought out the Ducks so he could stay home on Long Island, had two hits and drove in two runs. Harrelson was almost as thrilled as Heffernan.</p>
        <p>Then there was a touch of Hodges, one of the greatest players, managers and human beings not yet in the Baseball Hall of Fame. The other night, a pitch hit a Ducks batter on the foot, and ricocheted to the catcher. Just about everybody saw it that way but the umpire.</p>
        <p>Harrelson strolled out methodically, the way Hodges had done in the 1969 World Series when he produced the ball -- a ball -- with a smudge that looked like shoe polish, insisting that very ball had hit Cleon Jones on the shoe.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'It hit the batter first,' '' Harrelson said the other night. ''The umpire said, 'Oh, I didn't see it.' ''  Rather amazingly, the ump waved the batter to first. Did it help that Harrelson is also president of the league? Who knows. Tom O'Malley, the Bears' manager, who had a career in North America and Japan, knew he was whipped, just as Earl Weaver had known back in 1969.</p>
        <p>''Gil never argued,'' Harrelson said later. ''He just talked.''</p>
        <p>The hip fans know they are watching a glorious history. The youngsters know they can get close to ball players who sign autographs, and can play a little.</p>
        <p>''Our prices are cheaper, too,'' said the manager, who has a piece of the action.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
