<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="05VIDB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME VIDEO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D61F39F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Straight Story</p>
        <p>Denied a driver's license because of poor eyesight, the elderly Alvin Straight (Richard Farnsworth, left) decides to drive his lawn mower to see his estranged brother (Harry Dean Stanton). Alvin lives in Iowa and his brother in Wisconsin, so the trip, at several miles an hour along the road shoulder, takes weeks and gives Alvin ample opportunity to revisit notable periods of a long and difficult life. And that, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, provides David Lynch a chance to do what he set out to do: ''make a folksy-looking, profoundly spiritual film that can hold an audience in absolute thrall.''</p>
        <p>1999. Disney. $104.16. 111 minutes. Closed captioned. G. Release date: May 9.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Straight Story</p>
        <p>Denied a driver's license because of poor eyesight, the elderly Alvin Straight (Richard Farnsworth, left) decides to drive his lawn mower to see his estranged brother (Harry Dean Stanton). Alvin lives in Iowa and his brother in Wisconsin, so the trip, at several miles an hour along the road shoulder, takes weeks and gives Alvin ample opportunity to revisit notable periods of a long and difficult life. And that, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, provides David Lynch a chance to do what he set out to do: ''make a folksy-looking, profoundly spiritual film that can hold an audience in absolute thrall.''</p>
        <p>1999. Disney. $104.16. 111 minutes. Closed captioned. G. Release date: May 9.</p>
        <p>Dogma</p>
        <p>In an attempt to get back into heaven, two banished angels, Bartleby (Ben Affleck) and Loki (Matt Damon) plan to crash the rededication of a church in Red Bank, N.J., where the populist Cardinal Glick (George Carlin) plans to invigorate Catholicism by introducing the repositioned ''buddy Christ.'' If Bartleby and Loki do get past the holy portal and make it back upstairs, God will be proved fallible, negating all existence. Since all of this springs from the mind of the director, Kevin Smith, understanding the holy happenings ''is not essential to finding the movie extremely funny'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1999. Columbia Tri-Star. $107.37; DVD, $24.95. 125 minutes. Closed captioned. Release date: May 9.</p>
        <p>Mystery, Alaska</p>
        <p>In the far reaches of the nation's largest state, they play their hockey not in auditoriums but on outdoor ponds where the wind-chill factor is as big a worry as the final score. In Mystery, the sheriff (Russell Crowe) anchors the team until he is relegated to the bench by a pair of fresh legs half his age (Ryan Northcott). But then a slick native son turned television producer (Hank Azaria) returns to set up a match with the New York Rangers. That could lead to some schmaltz but doesn't in a film in which ''a dozen sharply drawn characters interact in ways that are fairly predictable without seeming too smugly formulaic'' (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. Hollywood. $104.16; DVD, $32.99. 118 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: May 9.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>THE DINNER GAME. In France, Francis Veber's comedy was the second most popular film of 1998, after ''Titanic.'' A smug, wealthy publisher named Brochant (Thierry Lhermitte) joins a group of his bored aging yuppie friends to see who can bring the biggest fool to dinner. But his choice, a supposed clown who builds architectural models out of match sticks, lingers after the meal to help make a shambles of Brochant's life. Universal. $98.99; DVD, $24.98. 82 minutes. French with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
        <p>BLACK TIGHTS, NEW ORLEANS, CARNEGIE HALL. Three old films salute the arts in a couple of their cradles. Terence Young's ''Black Tights'' (1960, 125 minutes) mounts versions of ''Cyrano de Bergerac'' and ''Carmen'' and two other musicals staged by Roland Petit's Ballet de Paris. Louis Armstrong and Woody Herman contribute some hot licks and Billie Holiday sings ''Farewell to Storyville'' and other numbers in ''New Orleans,'' Arthur Lubin's fiction feature about the birth of jazz (1947, 90 minutes). Lily Pons, Rise Stevens and Artur Rubinstein are among the artists in Edgar G. Ulmer's ''Carnegie Hall'' (1947, 136 minutes). Kino. $24.95 each; ''Black Tights'' and ''New Orleans'' are available on DVD, $29.95 each. Information: (800) 562-3330.</p>
        <p>STACY'S KNIGHTS. It's not the greatest movie, but it has a diverting take on casino gambling and it also has Kevin Costner in his first leading role. 1983. Rhino. $9.95; DVD, $19.95. 95 minutes. PG.</p>
        <p>HOME VIDEO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
