<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After He Gives Up Too Many Walks, Hampton Walks Alone</title>
    <meta content="05HAMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D71638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After He Gives Up Too Many Walks, Hampton Walks Alone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a 25-minute walk from Pacific Bell Park to the Westin St. Francis hotel, and Mike Hampton walked every step of it alone Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Hampton left the park immediately after the Mets lost to the San Francisco Giants in 11 innings. He had left the game in the sixth, after walking six and allowing five runs in five and one-third innings. It was Hampton's fifth poor outing in seven starts this season, and he did not feel like riding the team bus or talking to the news media.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a 25-minute walk from Pacific Bell Park to the Westin St. Francis hotel, and Mike Hampton walked every step of it alone Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Hampton left the park immediately after the Mets lost to the San Francisco Giants in 11 innings. He had left the game in the sixth, after walking six and allowing five runs in five and one-third innings. It was Hampton's fifth poor outing in seven starts this season, and he did not feel like riding the team bus or talking to the news media.</p>
        <p>''Rather than say something stupid or something I would later regret, I just decided not to say anything,'' Hampton said.</p>
        <p>He was talking again this morning -- though not about the umpires, who have not been giving him close calls lately -- and he is still at a loss to explain what is wrong. In his seventh start last season, he threw a shutout in which he issued no walks, and his record was 4-1, with a 2.83 earned-run average. Now, he is 2-4, with a 6.52 E.R.A., and his 36 walks are 10 more than any other pitcher in the majors.</p>
        <p>''It just feels like everything that can go wrong is going wrong,'' Hampton said. ''I'm not really catching a break, and it seems like everything's going against me. I'm pretty close to bottom, but hopefully I can start swimming to the top and I can help this team. I feel like I was brought here for a reason -- to help this team win a championship. So far, I'm not living up to my part of the bargain.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Steve Phillips said Hampton might be struggling both mentally and mechanically, but Hampton insisted he is doing nothing wrong mechanically. He does not start again until Tuesday in Pittsburgh, and he will be restless during the layoff.</p>
        <p>''I want to go out there and do it again,'' Hampton said. ''I want another shot. I hate the way things are going.''</p>
        <p>Henderson and Valentine Meet</p>
        <p>Left fielder Rickey Henderson said he was let down when he learned he was not in the lineup on Wednesday, and he met with Manager Bobby Valentine to discuss the strategy. Henderson said he would like to know in advance when he will not be starting.</p>
        <p>''I ain't a kid in this game,'' Henderson said he told Valentine. ''I know probably just as much as you know about the game, and I want to know your strategy. We shouldn't have a problem.''</p>
        <p>Valentine told Henderson he wanted to start Jon Nunnally now and then against right-handed pitchers, and Henderson said he accepted that. Henderson, who had three walks today but no hits and is now batting .208 with no homers and only two stolen bases, said he was having problems tracking the ball from the pitcher's hand to the zone in which he looks for the pitch.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to panic,'' Henderson said.</p>
        <p>Henderson, 41 years old, is looking forward to temperatures rising as the season goes on. ''Warm weather always helps the old boy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bell Gets a Look in Center</p>
        <p>With Darryl Hamilton about to have toe surgery that could sideline him from three to eight weeks, the Mets need to know who can play center field. Derek Bell, who came up as a center fielder, told Valentine he enjoyed playing there, and he made his first appearance in center for the Mets today.</p>
        <p>Valentine gave a day off to second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo, who has made several diving stops lately and has a bruised upper thigh.</p>
        <p>''In talking with him, he felt he played too much last year,'' Valentine said of Alfonzo, who had played every game before today.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
