<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Baseball; Johnson and Martinez Very Much Alike in Their Mastery</title>
    <meta content="05BASE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1D81638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Baseball; Johnson and Martinez Very Much Alike in Their Mastery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The plans and hopes of other teams aside, this baseball year could end in no better manner than to have the Arizona Diamondbacks and the Boston Red Sox win their respective league pennants so that Randy Johnson and Pedro Martinez can pitch against each other in Games 1, 4 and 7 of the World Series. What more fitting climax could the season have than to put the premier pitcher in each league on the mound in the sport's ultimate set of games.</p>
        <p>Although that's the only way Johnson and Martinez could pitch in the same meaningful games, they have been mirroring each other this season, making four starts on the same day and another start on consecutive days. In their latest turns in their teams' rotations, Johnson is scheduled to pitch against San Diego tonight and Martinez against Tampa Bay tomorrow afternoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The plans and hopes of other teams aside, this baseball year could end in no better manner than to have the Arizona Diamondbacks and the Boston Red Sox win their respective league pennants so that Randy Johnson and Pedro Martinez can pitch against each other in Games 1, 4 and 7 of the World Series. What more fitting climax could the season have than to put the premier pitcher in each league on the mound in the sport's ultimate set of games.</p>
        <p>Although that's the only way Johnson and Martinez could pitch in the same meaningful games, they have been mirroring each other this season, making four starts on the same day and another start on consecutive days. In their latest turns in their teams' rotations, Johnson is scheduled to pitch against San Diego tonight and Martinez against Tampa Bay tomorrow afternoon.</p>
        <p>Johnson, the left-hander, will take a 6-0 record and a 0.91 earned run average into the game in Phoenix; Martinez, the right-hander, will take a 5-0 record and a 1.27 E.R.A. into his game in Boston. Martinez has made one fewer start than Johnson because the Red Sox were rained out for four consecutive days last month. Both pitchers have been no less than terrific. They clearly have become the most dominating, most intimidating pitchers in their respective leagues.</p>
        <p>''The similarities are they are both intimidating,'' Mike Hargrove, the Baltimore Orioles' manager, said by telephone yesterday. ''The differences are how they go about it.''</p>
        <p>Hargrove was asked to compare the two pitchers because as a long-time American League manager, he has had to deal with both, during the regular season and in playoff games.</p>
        <p>''Randy is physically intimidating,'' Hargrove said. ''Here's a guy 6 foot 12 or whatever he is, 6-10, and when he lets the ball go, it looks like he lets it go halfway to the plate. That's intimidating, especially to left-hand hitters. Pedro goes about his business quietly on the mound, but there's no doubt in your mind that Pedro feels he owns the entire plate and if you try to take any of it away from him, he'll come and get you.''</p>
        <p>That's what Martinez did last Sunday in Cleveland with Einar Diaz. His brushback pitch led to an exchange of hit batters and a five-game suspension for Martinez. If his appeal is unsuccessful, he presumably will fall another start behind Johnson, though not necessarily in stature and success.</p>
        <p>Johnson, 36 years old, leads the National League in victories, E.R.A., strikeouts (64), strikeouts per nine innings (11.7), batting average against (.156), complete games (3) and shutouts (2). Martinez, 28, is tied for the A.L. lead in victories and leads the league in E.R.A., strikeouts (50), strikeouts per nine innings (12.7) and opponents' batting average (.173).</p>
        <p>Neither has lost a regular-season game since last August, though the Mets beat Johnson in a playoff game last October. Since he lost last Aug. 31, Johnson has started 11 games and been the winning pitcher nine times. Martinez has not incurred a loss since last Aug. 19, winning 11 of 12 starts and adding one victory each as a starter and a reliever in last year's playoffs. Johnson (17-9, 2.48) and Martinez (23-4, 2.07) were the 1999 Cy Young award winners.</p>
        <p>Jim Beattie, general manager of the Montreal Expos, knows both pitchers intimately. He was in the Seattle front office when Johnson pitched for the Mariners, and he was the Expos' general manager who traded Martinez to the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>''They both have a lot of confidence,'' Beattie said. ''They don't let anything bother them. Randy is more emotional out there, but it doesn't affect how he throws his next pitch. It's the same with Pedro. They've gotten past those things. That's the mark of a good pitcher.''</p>
        <p>Beattie, a former pitcher himself, said neither Johnson nor Martinez was born on the pitching pinnacle; they worked hard to get there.</p>
        <p>''It was probably 1994, '95 when Randy started to step it up and concentrate,'' Beattie said. ''He worked hard in the off-season. He started applying himself and got stronger. The same with Pedro. He worked hard. Conditioning for both these guys is outstanding.''</p>
        <p>People who don't know the pitchers, Beattie suggested, might look at both pitchers and think Johnson was just this tall, skinny guy and Martinez was a small, skinny guy. Both, however, are very strong, he said.</p>
        <p>''You saw the maturing of both into the pitchers they have become,'' the Expos' executive said. ''Both had questions about them early in their career, but they developed mental toughness and concentration. It's something they learned as they got more experienced.''</p>
        <p>Early in his career, after the Los Angeles Dodgers decided he was too small to become a good major league pitcher and traded him to the Expos, Martinez was accused of being a headhunter. He hit batters with pitches liberally, and the batters went after him.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he was a headhunter,'' Beattie said. ''I think his ball just ran so much that he ended up hitting a lot of guys. He has refined the way he approaches the game. So has Randy.''</p>
        <p>Russ Davis, a San Francisco infielder, played with Johnson in Seattle and has played against him as a member of the Yankees and the Giants.</p>
        <p>''He's gotten so good right now,'' said Davis, who doesn't have a hit in 11 at-bats against Johnson. ''I don't ever remember him throwing a sinking fastball, a two-seamer that just runs away from right-handers now. I thought that was pretty incredible when he came here and I saw that. Other than that pitch, everything's real hard, a hard slider -- it's hard to detect if it's a fastball or a slider. And he pitches. He's not just throwing 95 every time. It's like he's getting better with age, with time.''</p>
        <p>Hargrove hasn't had to deal with Johnson since he left the American League during the 1998 season. Sight unseen, though, the Baltimore manager said Johnson is the best pitcher in the National League. But he added, ''Without a doubt I think Pedro's the best in both leagues. He's kind of a combination of Maddux and Johnson. He has Johnson's fastball, but Maddux's composure and control.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
