<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y05BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDC1638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: ACEH ACCORD -- Indonesia and pro-independence rebels in Aceh province said they would sign a three-month cease-fire, raising hopes of an end to a decades-long conflict that has killed thousands of civilians. But the Free Aceh Movement said the deal to be signed by mid-month did not mean they were giving up their struggle to end Jakarta's rule over the province. The government and the rebels are scheduled to sign a memorandum of understanding in Geneva on May 12.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: ACEH ACCORD -- Indonesia and pro-independence rebels in Aceh province said they would sign a three-month cease-fire, raising hopes of an end to a decades-long conflict that has killed thousands of civilians. But the Free Aceh Movement said the deal to be signed by mid-month did not mean they were giving up their struggle to end Jakarta's rule over the province. The government and the rebels are scheduled to sign a memorandum of understanding in Geneva on May 12.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>INDIA: KASHMIR REBEL FREED -- India freed the jailed chairman of the Jammu and Kashmir Liberation front, Yasin Malik, but he said he did not favor any talks between Kashmiri separatists and the government. Mr. Malik was arrested six months ago under a public security law after he asked voters to boycott parliamentary elections.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>MALAYSIA: ANWAR TRIAL ON HOLD -- The sex trial of Anwar Ibrahim was postponed indefinitely to allow the former deputy prime minister to appeal a ruling preventing the defense from calling Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad as a witness. High Court officials said a date would be fixed for the trial to reconvene after the appeals court's ruling.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: AIDS MEETING -- President Thabo Mbeki will convene a meeting of 33 international AIDS researchers in Pretoria to advise the government on the cause of AIDS and its treatment. The panel, which will meet on Saturday and consult regularly over the next two months, is almost evenly split between those who believe that H.I.V. causes AIDS and those who do not. Mr. Mbeki's decision to seek advice from those who argue that H.I.V. does not cause AIDS has raised fears that South Africa's already soaring infection rate will continue to climb.</p>
        <p>Rachel L. Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>MOZAMBIQUE: FLOOD RELIEF -- President Joaquim Chissano's call for money to help with flood relief was answered with an international donation of $452.9 million, the United Nations Development Program said. The amount, about $3 million more than Mr. Chissano requested, was announced at the end of a two-day donor conference in Rome.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ALGERIA: LOOKING FOR THE MISSING -- An Amnesty International team visiting Algeria said it was trying to compile full lists of thousands of people reported missing in eight years of political violence. Algerian rights activists say more than 22,000 people have been reported missing by their relatives, many believed ''kidnapped'' by government security and paramilitary forces waging a campaign to quell an Islamist rebellion.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS</p>
        <p>NEW RIGHTS MEMBERS -- Cuba, Saudi Arabia, Libya and Syria, all of which have been criticized for their human rights records, were among 24 countries elected to the United Nations Human Rights Commission. Members of the Geneva-based panel, the main United Nations body concerned with rights, are elected to three-year terms. Cuba has itself been the target of resolutions adopted by the 53-member commission.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: WHITE HOUSE SHOTS -- Unidentified assailants fired off seven shots from a 9-millimeter weapon directly outside Los Pinos, the Mexican White House. A spokesman said no one was hurt and the shots, which were apparently fired from a car on an avenue 50 yards from the entrance to the presidential residence, did no damage.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>GAZA: PLANES INTERCEPTED -- Israel intercepted a Palestinian plane flying from Gaza International Airport to Jordan, the third incident this week in which Israel said an airplane was using the wrong flight path. Israel's military said that earlier in the week, an Egyptian plane and a Moroccan plane landing at the Palestinian-controlled airport had also used unauthorized flight paths and endangered Israeli fighter jets.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: MAZE TO CLOSE -- The top-security Maze prison outside Belfast that was a scene of conflict and protest in the past 30 years of sectarian troubles in the British province is to close this summer, officials said. The prison, which started life as the Long Kesh internment camp, will be vacated by August with the departure of the remaining 80 inmates of the estimated 450 Catholic and Protestant paramilitary prisoners who have qualified for early release.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>NORWAY: STRIKE GROWS -- The national strike that has idled 85,000 workers, set off widespread hoarding and crippled a broad range of consumer businesses, tourism services and public utilities will be expanded to include 10,000 more people and affect new areas like forestry, the union confederation said. But, in a move seen as an effort to forestall government intervention, labor leaders said they would not extend the wage dispute to the oil or air transport sectors.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: AMBUSH REPORTED -- The Russian military said its special forces ambushed and killed at least 18 Chechen rebels southeast of Grozny. The report could not be confirmed, but if true it could signal a shift in Russian tactics. Russians have relied on armor and air power to press their assault; ambushes have been the rebels' most successful tactic.</p>
        <p>Michael Wines (NYT)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: NAPOLEON MYSTERY -- Did Napoleon die of cancer or was he poisoned? Tests showing traces of arsenic in a few strands of his hair were not definitive. Now some leading French pathologists, encouraged by DNA tests that ended an historical mystery by proving that 10-year-old Louis XVII died in jail, want to exhume Napoleon's body.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
