<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="05CLAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1D81F39F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="6842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LA BOHEME,'' Metropolitan Opera. Yet again, all Paris descends on the Latin Quarter in Act II of Puccini's opera, and viewers will get their fill. Listeners are another matter. In Franco Zeffirelli's extravaganza of a production, from 1981, it is hard for any singer of less than Pavarottian amplitude in both voice and physique even to register, let alone make a vivid impression. Certainly, the singers in the lead roles on opening night did not exactly shine. Perhaps Nuccia Focile and Alfredo Portilla will fare better here. But Placido Domingo, to judge from this listener's experience of his work in the pit, may be hard put to match that of the original conductor, Marco Armiliato. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out, but returns may be available; also standing room tickets at $12 and $16 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LA BOHEME,'' Metropolitan Opera. Yet again, all Paris descends on the Latin Quarter in Act II of Puccini's opera, and viewers will get their fill. Listeners are another matter. In Franco Zeffirelli's extravaganza of a production, from 1981, it is hard for any singer of less than Pavarottian amplitude in both voice and physique even to register, let alone make a vivid impression. Certainly, the singers in the lead roles on opening night did not exactly shine. Perhaps Nuccia Focile and Alfredo Portilla will fare better here. But Placido Domingo, to judge from this listener's experience of his work in the pit, may be hard put to match that of the original conductor, Marco Armiliato. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out, but returns may be available; also standing room tickets at $12 and $16 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>EOS ORCHESTRA. This quick-paced evening offers a well-nigh irresistible way for anyone shoulder-deep in the Met's ''Ring'' cycle this week to spend a rare night off. Eos's clever and delightful staging of six 10-minute operas last season seemed worthy of revival sooner rather than later. But Jonathan Sheffer, ever enterprising as artistic director, goes a step further if not necessarily better in ''Six 10-Minute Operas II,'' with a new array of works, by Monteverdi, Salieri, Ernst Toch, Darius Milhaud, Karl Amadeus Hartmann and, in an Eos commission, Jake Heggie. Perhaps some lost 10-minute Wagner opera will turn up for the next installment. Tonight at 8, Society for Ethical Culture, Central Park West at 64th Street, (212) 691-6415. Tickets: $25 and $40; half-price for students and the elderly (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''GIULIO CESARE.'' A parade of gorgeous voices. Jennifer Larmore, bright, eager and very much in command, is the smiling world conqueror. Stephanie Blythe, in a majestic performance, is poignant and stately as Cornelia, while Hei-Kyung Hong portrays Cleopatra as a brilliant performer, agile and dazzling. David Daniels, exquisitely sweet yet fresh, is the young hero, Sextus, and Brian Asawa the swaggering Ptolemy. John Nelson conducts. Tomorrow at noon, Metropolitan Opera. Remaining tickets: $170 and $225; standing-room tickets, $12 and 16; (212) 362-6000 (Paul Griffiths).</p>
        <p>''GOTTERDAMMERUNG.'' Jane Eaglen's soprano voice is not flawless. Her low range is weak, and her top notes can be a bit thin-toned. But for the most part her voice is plush, poignant and enormous in sound without being forced. She is the dramatic soprano Wagner fans have been waiting for. And in the Metropolitan Opera's current presentations of the ''Ring'' cycle, the conductor James Levine is inspiring Ms. Eaglen, who can be a stolid singer, into some of her most musically and dramatically incisive work. She sings Brunnhilde tomorrow evening in ''Gotterdammerung.'' The Danish tenor Stig Andersen, fresh from his successful Met debut, sings Siegfried. The bass John Macurdy isthe tormented Hagen. Tomorrow night at 6:30, Metropolitan Opera House. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available; standing-room tickets, $25 and $35; (212) 362-2000 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''LA GRISELDA.'' Teatro Instabile, a new opera company with homes in both New York and Bologna, introduces itself with a production of this rarely heard 1735 Vivaldi opera about a peasant woman who is put through a series of cruel ordeals to prove her worthiness to marry a king. The company is presenting the work with a female cast that includes Shira Lissek, Sally Wilson, Nita Baxani, Anna Tonna, Lucy Tucker Yates and Stephanie Jensen-Moulton. Sunday at 3 p.m., Riverside Church, Riverside Drive at 120th Street. Tickets: $20; (212) 870-6784 (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''MADAMA BUTTERFLY.'' The homespun but attractive qualities of the Amato Opera's productions and the intimacy of its shoe-box theater offer a useful change of perspective for operagoers used to the big houses uptown. The casts here vary. At the very least, the singers are eager and enthusiastic; sometimes the singing shows great promise. And Anthony Amato, the company's founder, conducts the performances with an evident love of the music. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly'' is on the boards. Amato Opera Theater, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village. Tickets: $25; $20 for the elderly and children; (212) 228-8200 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''DON PASQUALE.'' For more than 30 years the independent, community-based Bronx Opera Company has been presenting standard repertory operatic works (and now and then unusual fare like Nielsen's ''Maskarade'') as well as giving performance opportunities to young singers and introducing audiences to opera. The company's current offering is Donizetti's popular ''Don Pasquale,'' performed in English. Michael Spierman will conduct, and Nathaniel Merchant directs. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 2 p.m., Lovinger Theater at Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West, the Bronx. Tickets: $20 and $15; $18 and $13 for students and the elderly; (212) 201-1490 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. There are few better places in the city to hear chamber music than this barge floating on the East River, with its live, intimate acoustics and its spectacular view of lower Manhattan. Good weather will only enhance the experience, and the performances are often as fine as the setting. Mark Peskanov, a violinist, has assembled the programs for this weekend: tonight, a concert of Bach, Brahms, Rachmaninoff and Shostakovich; and tomorrow and Sunday, a Vivaldi concert, inevitably including ''The Four Seasons.'' Today and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m., Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing under the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-4061. Tickets: $23; $20 for the elderly; $15 for students (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>BEAUX-ARTS TRIO. For all the changes of personnel around him -- now with Young Uck Kim as violinist and Antonio Meneses as cellist -- Menahem Pressler, the pianist, has kept a firm hand on this group's rudder. Not that any ensemble can claim Beethoven as its special preserve, but the Beaux-Arts has always held that master's trios as the center of its activity, and it is now finishing yet another complete cycle, with the Trios Nos. 3, 6 (the justly famous ''Archduke'') and 9. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 570-3949. Tickets: $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>YEFIM BRONFMAN. A superlative pianist and a superlative musician offers an intriguing combination of Beethoven and Berg, the bookends of Romanticism. The Beethoven works are the G minor Fantasy and the ''Spring'' Sonata (with Cho-Liang Lin on violin). Berg's contributions are the Four Pieces for Piano and Clarinet (David Shifrin) and the glorious rhapsodic-dramatic Chamber Concerto, in which Mr. Bronfman and Mr. Lin are accompanied by front-rank wind players with Joseph Silverstein conducting. Today at 8 p.m., Sunday at 5 p.m., Alice Tully Hall. Tickets: $35; (212) 721-6500 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>CANTICUM NOVUM SINGERS. Harold Rosenbaum's estimable and adventurous band of singers offers Britten, Isaac, Weelkes, Victoria, Berlioz and Jonathan Harvey in a program called ''Heaven Is Here: Music of Angels, Saints and Spirits.'' Tomorrow night at 8, St. Ignatius Episcopal Church, 87th Street and West End Avenue, Manhattan. Tickets, $20, $10 for students and the elderly; (914) 763-3453 (Bernard Holland).</p>
        <p>RENEE FLEMING. The celebrated American soprano joins Andre Previn at the piano in a program heavy on Americana. Mr. Previn is one of the composers, and others include Aaron Jay Kernis, Ricky Ian Gordon and Craig Harris. Sunday at 2 p.m., Alice Tully Hall. Tickets, $45; the performance is sold out but returns may be available; (212) 721-6500 (Holland).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK COLLEGIUM. Here is a logical sequel to the group's last choral program, ''Bach's Spiritual Heritage,'' which ranged from the work of such forebears as Matthias Weckmann and Johann Kuhnau to small-scale cantatas by Bach himself. Here, in ''Bach in the Thomaskirche,'' Andrew Parrott conducts longer if not necessarily larger works: the Cantata No. 21, ''Ich Hatte Viel Bekummernis,'' and the ''Easter Oratorio.'' Mr. Parrott's support of Joshua Rifkin's theory that Bach's ''choral'' works were originally sung one voice per part is outlined in Mr. Parrott's new book, ''The Essential Bach Choir,'' and presumably exemplified here. Tomorrow at 8, Church of St. Vincent Ferrer, Lexington Avenue at 66th Street, (212) 717-9246. Tickets: $20 and $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Stephen Sondheim considers himself a composer for the musical theater and has no aspiration to be an opera composer. But many devotees of his musical ''Sweeney Todd'' consider it to be more ingenious and musically rich than countless contemporary works called operas. So a great deal of anticipation attends this weekend's performances of ''Sweeney Todd'' by the New York Philharmonic. Additional interest had been generated by the announcement that a major opera singer, the bass-baritone Bryn Terfel, was going to sing the title role, while the role of Mrs. Lovett would be sung be a diva of Broadway, Patti LuPone. Mr. Terfel has withdrawn because of a back injury. In his place will be George Hearn, who sang the role memorably during the original Broadway run. The rest of the cast includes illustrious singers from both the musical theater and opera worlds, including Audra McDonald, Heidi Grant Murphy and Paul Plishka. And it should be interesting to hear the score played by the Philharmonic, conducted by Andrew Litton. Friday and Saturday nights at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall. Tickets: $75 to $250 at CenterCharge, (212) 721-6500 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>ORPHEUS. As part of a celebration of the 100th anniversary of Yaddo -- the artists' colony in Saratoga Springs where composers, authors, poets and artists go for a few weeks of work without the distractions of daily life -- Orpheus is offering a three-concert series devoted to works by composers who have worked at Yaddo. The opening concert includes music by Aaron Copland, David Diamond and David Del Tredici as well as the world premiere of a work composed for the occasion by Daron Hagen. Sunday at 8 p.m., the Ethical Culture Society, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $15, $10 for students and the elderly; (212) 592-4156 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>PEOPLES' SYMPHONY. Since 1900 the Peoples' Symphony Concerts have been presenting performances by first-rate soloists and chamber ensembles at bargain prices. Several of these musicians -- among them, the Juilliard, Tokyo and Guarneri String Quartets, the Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson Trio, Musicians From Marlboro, the Ethos Percussion Ensemble and the clarinetist Richard Stoltzman, accompanied by his son, Peter Stoltzman -- are joining forces to celebrate the organization's centenary. The program includes works by Beethoven, Janacek, Webern, Gyorgy Kurtag and Gershwin. And the ticket prices, true to form, are modest. Tonight at 7:30, Carnegie Hall. Tickets: $5 to $25; (212) 247-7800 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>SANFORD SYLVAN. The American baritone Sanford Sylvan could probably have a much more extensive career in opera that he has. But thankfully for lovers of song, Mr. Sylvan has been passionately involved with song literature as well. The major work on his program tonight is a 60-minute song cycle from 1994 by the composer Jorge Martin, ''The Glass Hammer: Scenes From Childhood Kept Against Forgetting,'' on poems by Andrew Hudgins. He will also sing songs by Debussy and Ravel. His pianist is his longtime recital partner David Breitman. Tonight at 8, Weill Recital Hall. Tickets, $31. The recital is sold out, but returns may be available before the concert; (212) 247-7800 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''THEODORA.'' One of Handel's more rarely performed oratorios, on a story of faith and fortitude in the early Christian era, is the subject of William Christie's latest Baroque adventure, with his ensemble Les Arts Florissants. The piece should benefit from Mr. Christie's blend of scholarship and fun, sophistication and exuberance. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene. Tickets: $20 to $55; $7.50 rush tickets for students and the elderly available two hours before the performance; (718) 636-4100 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>ARIANE ANTHONY &amp; COMPANY. Ariane Anthony, a sparklingly true original, cites the writers Wallace Stevens and Samuel Beckett as the inspirations for her new ''Why Imagine Golden Birds?,'' drawn from Stevens's ''Thirteen Ways of Looking at a Blackbird,'' and ''Seeing I,'' a male trio drawn from Beckett's final prose poem, ''Stirrings Still.'' Tomorrow, Monday and Tuesday (and May 13-15) at 8 p.m.; Sunday (and May 16) at 6 p.m., Construction Company, 10 East 18th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $12; $10 for students and the elderly; T.D.F. vouchers accepted; (212) 924-7882 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>ABUABUA BAND AND MUSICAL TEAM ''LOVE.'' From Japan, a group of retarded and autistic dancers who have been creating dance and musicals for two decades. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street; (212) 346-8510. Free. (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TRISHA BROWN DANCE COMPANY. Trisha Brown's premiere, ''Five Part Weather Invention,'' is set to original jazz scores by Dave Douglas and has witty interplays of improvisation and rigorous structure. For the company's 30th anniversary, the repertory also includes a generous selection of older works. Today at 8 p.m., Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $35; TDF vouchers accepted;  (212) 242-0800 (Jack Anderson).</p>
        <p>BUGLISI-FOREMAN DANCE. This first-class company of pedigreed dancers, directed by Jacqulyn Buglisi, Donlin Foreman, Terese Capucilli and Christine Dakin, will perform to live music in works that include Ms. Buglisi's new ''Suspended Women,'' set to music by Daniel Roumain and inspired by the writings of the 17th-century poet Sor Juana Ines de la Cruz, and Mr. Foreman's new ''Gilgamesh Project,'' a dance about man's mortality that is set to scores by Andy Monroe, Josh Haden and an improvisation by Crispin Campbell on music by Miles Davis. Today and tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., John Jay College Theater, 899 10th Avenue, at 59th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $15 and $20; $10 for students and the elderly; (212) 279-4200 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NAI-NI CHEN DANCE COMPANY. Nai-Ni Chen's dances were inspired by carousels, a Korean lake and river, and conversations with Bei Dao, exiled from China for his activism in the 1970's. Joan LaBarbara and Harry Wook-Suk Lee's Hanulsori Korean Percussion Ensemble are the guest musicians. Today and tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., Clark Studio Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $15; $10 for students and the elderly; (800) 650-0246 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>SEAN CURRAN COMPANY. Sean Curran offers choreographic meditations on love, longing and loss. His ''Approaching a City'' examines the differences between loneliness and solitude. ''Seven Laments'' suggests how loss can simultaneously break hearts and startle people awake. ''That Place, Those People'' concerns the ways in which memories influence our present relationships. Tonight, tomorrow night and Sunday night at 8:30, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village. Tickets: $15; (212) 674-8194 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>DANCE AT THE 92ND STREET Y HARKNESS DANCE CENTER. This week's ''Fridays @ Noon,'' the free dance showcase, features work by Randy James, Valerie Green and Katie Stevenson. Today at noon. The ''Sundays @ Three'' series of works-in-progress features dances by Yanira Castro, Tiffany Mills and Pam Tanowitz. Sunday at 3 p.m. 92nd Street Y, Lexington Avenue at 92nd Street. Tickets: $10; (212) 415-5552 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>ANDREA DEL CONTE DANZA ESPANA. Flamenco choreographed by La Cintia, Raquel Heredia and members of this 10-member ensemble of dancers, singers and musicians. The program also includes Aurora Reyes and Andrea Del Conte's restaging of work by Valeriano Mayorga. Tonight through Sunday at 8 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $20; $18 for students and the elderly; T.D.F. vouchers accepted; (212) 924-0077 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FOXHOLE. This phantasmagoric dance-drama created by Tanya Gagne and Karen Sherman is a portrait of an all-female rough-and-tumble street gang, and its women go into battle with sharp tongues, dagger eyes and a steely self-confidence. Tonight, tomorrow night and Sunday night at 8:30, Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village. Tickets: $12 (212) 477-5288 (Jack Anderson).</p>
        <p>TERRY HOLLIS. This workshop production of Terry Hollis's theater and dance piece ''NewSex'' -- hope springs eternal -- is set to music by Sean Meehan and performed by a cast that includes Tamieca McCloud, formerly of Pilobolus Dance Theater. Sunday (and May 14 and 21) at 3 p.m., Dixon Place at Vineyard 26, 309 East 26th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $12; $8 for students and the elderly; T.D.F. vouchers accepted; (212) 532-1546 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>''JOYCE SOHO PRESENTS.'' This series by 12 choreographers begins this weekend with work by Hope Clark, Barbara Mahler, Satoshi Haga and Gina Jacobs. Tonight and tomorrow night (and May 11-13 and 18-20) at 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street. Tickets: $10; T.D.F. vouchers accepted; (212) 334-7479 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JENNIFER LACEY. One of these days Jennifer Lacey may burst through her status as a wittily imaginative underground star and take New York dance by storm. Her new ''$Shot,'' which explores the relationship between acquisitive and contemplative sexual gazes, may be the piece that does it. Performed with Erin Cornell to music by Zeena Parkins, with visuals by Nadia Lauro. Today at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $15; (212) 255-5793 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>MARTHA @ MOTHER. Mikhail Baryshnikov and Yvonne Rainer will frolic with the Martha @ Mother crew in a guest cast that also includes the elegant tap stylist Herbin Van Cayseele, Daniel Ezralow, Bebe Miller and Ida Nevasayneva of the all-male Ballets Trockadero de Monte Carlo. Presiding over it all will be Richard Move in the guise of Martha Graham, though he looks far more like the former Graham lead dancer Peggy Lyman. Tonight at 8, Martha @ Mother, 875 Washington Street, at 14th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $35; $15 for standing room; reservations required; (212) 924-0077 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>MOVING ON. A performance and reception tomorrow night begins two weekends of dances by 15 choreographers, including Wally Cardona and Nicholas Leichter, to raise money for the Dance Space Center and its classes. Tomorrow (and May 13) at 8 p.m.; Sunday (and May 14) at 5 and 8 p.m., Evolving Arts Theater, Dance Space Center, 451 Broadway, near Grand Street, SoHo. Tickets: tomorrow, $65 minimum donation, which includes a reception; $20 minimum donation all other performances; (212) 625-8369 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>LEE NAGRIN. Lee Nagrin's new performance-art piece, ''The Valley of Iao,'' takes the viewer along with her on a mystical remembered journey through the dying of a loved one in Hawaii. Today and tomorrow and Thursdays through May 13) at 8 p.m.; Sunday (and May 14) at 3:30 and 8 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village; Tickets: $20 (Fridays and Saturdays); $15 (Sundays); T.D.F. vouchers accepted. (212) 475-7710 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY BALLET. Jerome Robbins will be saluted tonight with performances of ''In the Night'' (also tomorrow afternoon), ''West Side Story Suite'' (tonight and tomorrow night) and his delicately pretty ''Glass Pieces'' (tonight only). Today at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $25 to $72; $10 for student rush tickets; (212) 870-5570 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NICHOLASLEICHTER DANCE. Sleek high-energy dance with an undercurrent of humor. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Miller Theater, Columbia University, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights. Tickets: $15; $7.50 for students; $5 for Columbia students;  (212) 854-7799 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>CAROL NOLTE AND DIANE FAY. A mixed meal of modern dance by Carol Nolte and Dance Collective and ballet by the Diane Fay Dance Theater. Ms. Fay, in her New York debut, presents a one-act piece about a dancer's reflections on her career. Ms. Nolte presents dances set to music by Terence Blanchard, William Brooks and Maryasque Fendley and Brandt Passalaqua. Sunday at 8 p.m.; Monday at 9 p.m., Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, West Village. Tickets: $15; $10 for students and seniors (212) 924-0077 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>KAMAL SINCLAIR: ''THE BEAT.'' Kamal Sinclair explores the power of music as a force for social unity and spiritual transcendence, with help from the performance artist Robbie McCauley, the poet Mustafa Shakir and the tap dancer Baakari Wilder. Tonight and tomorrow night (and Thursdays through Saturdays through May 20) at 8; Context, 28 Avenue A, at Third Street, East Village. Tickets: $25; $15 for students; (212) 802-9350 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>STONER BLOSSOM PINHASI. It would be hard to beat these three pros -- Jeanette Stoner, Beverly Blossom and Amos Pinhasi -- for resonance and quirky individuality. Now they have banded together in an evening of new dance theater. Tonight through Sunday night at 8, Fifth Floor Theater, 83 Leonard Street, Lower Manhattan. Tickets: $12; (212) 226-1576 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>WORLD MUSIC INSTITUTE: MUSIC AND DANCE OF HUNGARY. The Hungarian folk troupe Muzsikas, starring the singer Marta Sebestyen, the violinist Alexander Balanescu and the dancers Zoltan Fakas and Ildiko Toth. Tonight at 8, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street. Tickets: $26; $21 for members of Symphony Space and World Music Institute; (212) 864-5400 or (212) 545-7536 (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
