<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spring Fireworks for an Old Hub</title>
    <meta content="05SMIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DD1638F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spring Fireworks for an Old Hub</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE credit should go to the reviving art market, the arrival of spring or some kind of harmonic convergence, but Madison Avenue from 69th to 79th Street is rife with art. It's hard to recall a time in the last 20 years when so many galleries on or just off the avenue offered such a diverse range of high-quality viewing opportunities. One resident art dealer cheerfully described the neighborhood as ''the Chelsea you can get to.''</p>
        <p>In the 1960's and 70's Madison Avenue was a major art world hub. Leo Castelli had his gallery on East 77th Street. Sotheby Parke-Bernet, as it was then called, occupied much of the office building at 980 Madison. But by the late 1970's Castelli and other dealers refocused their energies in SoHo, and Sotheby's moved to York Avenue, leaving 980 with a ghost town feeling that it still hasn't shaken. Galleries never completely left the area, but the center of action shifted decisively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE credit should go to the reviving art market, the arrival of spring or some kind of harmonic convergence, but Madison Avenue from 69th to 79th Street is rife with art. It's hard to recall a time in the last 20 years when so many galleries on or just off the avenue offered such a diverse range of high-quality viewing opportunities. One resident art dealer cheerfully described the neighborhood as ''the Chelsea you can get to.''</p>
        <p>In the 1960's and 70's Madison Avenue was a major art world hub. Leo Castelli had his gallery on East 77th Street. Sotheby Parke-Bernet, as it was then called, occupied much of the office building at 980 Madison. But by the late 1970's Castelli and other dealers refocused their energies in SoHo, and Sotheby's moved to York Avenue, leaving 980 with a ghost town feeling that it still hasn't shaken. Galleries never completely left the area, but the center of action shifted decisively.</p>
        <p>It would be an exaggeration to say it has shifted back, but some reconcentration is definitely going on. Over the last few seasons several new galleries have opened, and even more have moved here from sites around Manhattan or beyond. There has been a flurry of renovation as town house spaces and whole town houses have been readied for showing art.</p>
        <p>Even Castelli's old gallery has been spiffed up and occupied by Michael Werner, the German art dealer who has relocated his New York headquarters from East 67th Street and reopened with a spectacular late Picabia show. Given that the new owners of the Fuller Building, one of the main anchors of the 57th Street gallery neighborhood, plan to make it a residential condominium, this trend will probably continue.</p>
        <p>But pure serendipity may also be a big factor. At the moment there are outstanding shows in galleries that don't have regular public exhibitions, like the imposing display of Lucian Freud's new paintings at Acquavella. There are shows that are special occasions, like the engaging survey of the 19th-century American painter Frederic Edwin Church at Berry-Hill, and shows that observe them, like Knoedler's ''Collector as Patron in the 20th Century,'' intended to mark the end of the century. And there are new signs of activity in galleries that have been unusually quiet lately, like ''Willem de Kooning: Mostly Women'' at Gagosian and the mesmerizing selection of Andy Warhol's paintings of Marilyn, Liz and Jackie at C&amp;M.</p>
        <p>If many of the shows are historical, much of the information feels fresh. And while blue-chip painting and big names dominate, shows of photographic works by relatively young artists contribute to the fray. And even when a theme sounds traditional -- the confluence of shows with images of women, for example -- the evidence on the walls is otherwise.</p>
        <p>PICABIA:  If anything can evoke Madison Avenue's glory days, it's a visit to the second floor of 4 East 77th Street, where Leo Castelli showed his historic roster of artists for more than 30 years. Castelli's simple bronze plaque is still in place to the left of the entrance; Mr. Werner's equally simple new one has been installed respectfully below it. The heavy oak doors are still knobless and still open with a vigorous push; the hallway walls are still dark red, as are the thickly carpeted stairs, which still guarantee a suitably hushed, reverential ascent. The gallery space, discreetly reconfigured by the architect Annabelle Selldorf, looks wonderful, and the Picabia show, full of images of women, gets the main theme of these shows off to a dazzling start.</p>
        <p>Francis Picabia (1879-1953), the hyperactive bad boy of French modernism, liked fast cars and glamorous women and changed artistic styles the way most people change socks. He was anointed a postmodernist precursor in the 1980's, when his stylistic profligacy and the layered images of his transparency paintings were hailed as a precedent for artists like Sigmar Polke and David Salle.</p>
        <p>This show of more than 40 paintings and gouaches from the early 1920's to the late 40's reiterates Picabia's prescience but emphasizes physical experimentation over polymorphous naughtiness, and a free-ranging curiosity over ironic posturing. It takes passion to maintain such constant motion.</p>
        <p>In this show Picabia moves from abstraction to semiabstraction, from single to layered representations. He conjures commercial graphics, thrift-shop painting, Renaissance Madonnas or tourist art, as in the textured starfish in ''Etoile.'' Sometimes, in ''Visages,'' for example, fashion illustration teams up with abstraction, mostly through a love of line, with results that seem simultaneously sweet, seductive and rigorous. And with so many different, often ersatz images of women in play, the effect is often richly ambiguous.</p>
        <p>The tangled imagery of ''Ridens,'' one of the best transparencies here, may be suavely random, but it also suggests a portrait of Eve: the overlapping outlines of two Botticelli faces are combined with suggestions of a garden, a serpent, a ram's head, an animalistic face and, at the canvas's left edge, a long double helix that suggests a DNA strand.</p>
        <p>De Kooning</p>
        <p>While Picabia's habit of using existing images of women ties him to Warhol, it also brings him closer to de Kooning than you might expect. The show at Gagosian has a marvelously intimate, overheated feeling, like a visit to de Kooning's East Hampton studio on an August afternoon. The paintings and drawings on view come from one source, the well-known collector John Powers, who died last year, and his wife, Kimiko; the works often bear affectionate inscriptions by the artist.</p>
        <p>Dating mostly from the mid-1960's, they are closely related. Adding to the vivid sense of work in progress, they are executed on a remarkable whatever's-handy range of materials: newspaper, kraft paper, paper towels, Masonite and, in one case, a hollow-core door.</p>
        <p>If Picabia's images of women can have a surprising sincerity and intensity, de Kooning's manifest an impassioned ribaldry. His paintings seem emotionally and perceptually specific, as if they were painted in direct response to seeing a certain woman in a certain situation and light.</p>
        <p>But as Robert Rosenblum reiterates in his catalog essay, they also tap into existing sources, from the ferocious power of prehistoric idols and the monumentality of Rubens's nudes to the luxe sensuality of American movie goddesses like Marilyn Monroe. Her red lips and blue eyes are frequently glimpsed among the slathered pink tones of de Kooning's famously wobbly, blurry, frowzy, implicitly carnal brushwork, and sometimes the famous white sundress, caught in the updraft, seems to be there, too.</p>
        <p>Warhol</p>
        <p>Unlike Picabia and certainly de Kooning, Warhol's paintings of Monroe, Elizabeth Taylor and Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis have nothing to do with the flesh. They are images first and last, through and through, disembodied ghosts, really, redolent of newspapers, publicity photographs and film.</p>
        <p>Warhol's means centered on a simple silk-screen enlargement of the photograph, a flat, thin black-and-white image animated by a modicum of color. (In his catalog essay, Robert Pincus-Witten notes Warhol's childhood attachment to coloring books.)</p>
        <p>Most of the images of Monroe and Ms. Taylor involve blobs and patches of off-register pinks, reds, blues and yellows signaling flesh, lipstick and eyeshadow. The images of Ms. Taylor as Cleopatra and all the paintings of Onassis, which show her during the week of President John F. Kennedy's assassination and funeral, are basically monochromes, printed on canvas painted with a single tone of blue or brown.</p>
        <p>To look at these works is, on one level, to appreciate the economy and obviousness of Warhol's magic: variations, both deliberate and accidental, enhance the effect, including imperfections in printing, shifts in color tone and the occasional reversal of negatives.</p>
        <p>Yet Warhol also had history on his side. For weight, he relied on the connection between his paintings and actual events, counting on the ways his subjects already existed in the public imagination and assuming, correctly, that his own work would embed them even more deeply. Few artists have got more out of less.</p>
        <p>Cindy Sherman</p>
        <p>In Cindy Sherman's ''Fairy Tale'' pictures at Skarstedt, a woman takes the depiction of women into her own hands, and it's not a pretty sight. In these very large color photographs from 1985, Ms. Sherman broached the grotesque for the first time. She began adding prosthetic body parts -- from false noses and masks to breasts and buttocks -- to her disguises. The resulting images suggest cautionary fairy tales intended to induce proper behavior, but in adults rather than children.</p>
        <p>These dark, gritty, claustrophobic close-ups show women, or hybrid femalelike creatures, in extreme states, as outcasts or aliens. Sometimes they lie stunned on the ground like victims after a battle or attack; sometimes they are harridans bent on revenge. In one image the addition of little more than a large red tongue creates a devouring giant, while a scattering of tiny toy figures looks very much like her lunch.</p>
        <p>These images have lost little of their harsh, enigmatic force. It is especially telling to see so many of them in proximity to the Warhols, with which they share a similar economy of means and obvious yet effective magic.</p>
        <p>Vik Muniz</p>
        <p>At Ubu, Vik Muniz, the peripatetic photographic trickster, unveils two amusing bodies of new work, one in which he shows his hand (like Warhol and Ms. Sherman) and another in which he hides it. The artist's '' 'Photographs' '' (the quotation marks are part of the title) are facsimiles of snapshots, or so they appear from a distance. Up close they are visibly hand-made: crude, worried-over approximations of the most instantaneous and haphazard of all photographic images.</p>
        <p>The rest of the gallery is devoted to Mr. Muniz's ''Personal Articles'' series, a large group of individually framed clippings from, it would appear, familiar newspapers from the United States and Britain. ''Disney Corporation Buys Venice,'' reads one headline, while others announce ''Advertising on Cows and Sheep Forbidden in U.K.'' and ''Oil Spill Shaped Like Virgin.''</p>
        <p>Not a bit of it is true, at least not yet. Everything that meets the eye -- the headlines, typefaces, layout, texts and newspaper nameplates -- has been created by Mr. Muniz working with a small newspaper printing company in Lower Manhattan. And yet it is more by reading than by looking that the visual lie is apprehended. The frustrations of this experience, undoubtedly intended, are eased by reading the articles, some of which make you laugh out loud.</p>
        <p>Thomas Ruff</p>
        <p>A more traditional approach to photography is evident in a small survey of mostly large works by the 42-year-old German photographer Thomas Ruff at Zwirner &amp; Wirth, one of the neighborhood's recent arrivals. The gallery, which opened in February, is the joint effort of David Zwirner, who has a seven-year-old gallery in SoHo, and Iwan Wirth, a partner in Hauser &amp; Wirth, a longtime gallery in Zurich. (The new space, the ground floor of a town house, is another Annabelle Selldorf design and might almost be in Zurich, it feels so trim and understated.)</p>
        <p>The exhibition, meanwhile, confirms that Mr. Ruff, like other younger photographers, is determined to explore his medium from as many angles as possible. It includes small color close-ups of the living spaces in homes of the artist's German relatives that are rich anthropological documents from the early 1980's;  two recent examples of the colossal portrait photographs for which he is perhaps best known; an eerily green image of a house made using the infrared night-vision technology used by the military during the Persian Gulf war; and two enormous black-and-white images of dark, star-studded skies that are big enough to feel engulfing and that were made from negatives bought from the European Southern Observatory.</p>
        <p>Also on view are examples of Mr. Ruff's latest work, large photographs based on pornographic images taken from the Internet and digitally manipulated. The blurry results are beautiful, mysterious and reminiscent of Gerhard Richter's early paintings. Additional works from this series form a show at Mr. Zwirner's gallery in SoHo.</p>
        <p>'Collector as Patron'</p>
        <p>''The Collector as Patron in the 20th Century'' is a two-tiered celebration of Knoedler's long involvement with the cultural life of the United States through its dealings with clients who have given works to museums or, in the case of J. P. Morgan and Henry Frick, founded their own. Upstairs are 22 postwar American works, owned by several contemporary collectors, organized by the art historian and critic Irving Sandler; it includes especially impressive works by Romare Bearden, David Park, de Kooning (an exceptional drawing of two women from 1949) and Roy Lichtenstein.</p>
        <p>Lining the downstairs gallery, and more unusual, is an archival section that profiles 28 collectors, beginning with Catharine Lorillard Wolfe and including the Havemeyers, the Lewisohns, the Potter Palmers, Albert C. Barnes and Lillie P. Bliss, as well as Frick and Morgan.</p>
        <p>Organized by DeCourcy E. McIntosh, executive director of the Frick Art and History Center in Pittsburgh, this display draws heavily but not entirely on the Knoedler archive. It includes short biographies, correspondence, photographs and color reproductions of artworks as well as a few Knoedler ledgers, including one noting Frick's purchase of Vermeer's ''Soldier and Laughing Girl'' in 1911. The show would make a good book, and Mr. McIntosh, who has already written one on art patronage in Pittsburgh at the turn of the century, may be just the person to do it.</p>
        <p>Church, Among Others</p>
        <p>The Berry-Hill survey of the art of Frederic Edwin Church, accompanied by a detailed catalog by Gerald L. Carr, is a museum-quality show peppered with loans from institutions both famous and obscure. Yet its 50 works on canvas and paper gain immeasurably from an intimate gallery setting.</p>
        <p>Ranging from early paintings from the late 1840's and 50's up to the mid-1880's and including a hefty selection of oil sketches, the show creates a vivid picture of Church's innate talent and his dazzling maturation; his affinity for the American landscape; and the interest in exotic vistas and historic sites that took him nearly around the world.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece is the grandiose ''Cotopaxi'' of 1862, from the Detroit Institute of Art, replete with plunging waterfall, shimmering lake, flaming sunset and active volcano, which some consider Church's greatest work. Perhaps one won't be considered chauvinistic for preferring work that originates closer to home, including restrained and meticulous early paintings like ''View of Pittsford, Vt.'' (1848) and views of the Hudson Valley from Church's beloved home Olana, especially one blanketed in snow, from the Heckscher Museum of Art in Huntington.</p>
        <p>Nearby, the Gerald Peters Gallery is having a retrospective survey of the painter Max Weber (1881-1961), whose estate it now represents. Weber is remembered primarily as the first American Cubist and an artist who went into a long decline after 1920. This show makes a convincing case for Weber as a restless stylistic vagabond, who (not unlike Picabia) was largely indifferent to the idea of chronology and circled through different ideas for most of his career.</p>
        <p>Other shows are worth visiting on one side or the other of those reviewed here. Between Madison Avenue and the Warhols at C&amp;M, Winston Wachter Mayer is showing American paintings from the 1980's.</p>
        <p>In the same building as the Sherman show at Skarstedt, one can also visit the Leon Kossoff works at Mitchell-Inness &amp; Nash and a show of Sam Francis's elegantly spare ''Edge'' paintings from the mid-1960's at Richard Gray.</p>
        <p>Across the street from 980 Madison, at the Carlyle Hotel, Ursus Rare Books has organized a show of 40 illustrated books by Picasso, supplemented by a dozen or so etchings from the Vollard Suite.</p>
        <p>And among the shows with openings this week are a survey of Louisa Matthiasdottir's paintings at Salander-O'Reilly (now on view) and a new installation of works by Fred Sandback (opening tomorrow) that will inaugurate the Lawrence Markey Gallery, newly arrived from SoHo.</p>
        <p>Where They Are</p>
        <p>Here are details about visiting the exhibitions mentioned by Roberta Smith. Admission is free.</p>
        <p>''ART OF THE 80'S,'' Winston Wachter Mayer Fine Art, 39 East 78th Street, (212) 327-2526. Through May 20. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''FREDERIC EDWIN CHURCH: IN SEARCH OF THE PROMISED LAND,'' Berry-Hill, 11 East 70th Street, (212) 744-2300. Through July 15. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>''THE COLLECTOR AS PATRON IN THE 20TH CENTURY,'' Knoedler &amp; Company, 19 East 70th Street, (212) 794-0550. Through July 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''WILLEM DE KOONING: MOSTLY WOMEN,'' Gagosian Gallery, 980 Madison Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 744-2313. Drawings and paintings from the John and Kimiko Powers Collection. Through June 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''SAM FRANCIS: THE EDGE,'' Richard Gray, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street, (212) 472-8787. Through June. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''LUCIAN FREUD: RECENT WORK,'' Acquavella, 18 East 79th Street, (212) 734-6300. Through May 19. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>''ILLUSTRATED BOOKS BY PICASSO,'' Ursus Rare Books, 981 Madison Avenue, near 76th Street, (212) 772-8787. Through June 3. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>''LEON KOSSOFF: RECENT PAINTINGS AND DRAWINGS,'' Mitchell-Inness &amp; Nash, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street, (212 744-7400. Through May 20. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>LOUISA MATTHIASDOTTIR, Salander-O'Reilly, 20 East 79th Street, (212) 879-6606. Through May 27. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''VIK MUNIZ: 'PHOTOGRAPHS' AND PERSONAL ARTICLES,'' Ubu Gallery, 16 East 78th Street, (212) 794-4444. Through June 10. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''FRANCIS PICABIA: LATE WORKS,'' Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623. Through June 9. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''THOMAS RUFF: SELECTED PHOTOGRAPHS,'' Zwirner &amp; Wirth, 32 East 69th Street, (212) 517-8677. Through June 24. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''FRED SANDBACK: RECENT WORK,'' Lawrence Markey Gallery , 42 East 76th Street, (212) 517-9892. Tomorrow through June 17. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>''CINDY SHERMAN: FAIRY TALES, 1985,'' Skarstedt Fine Art, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street, (212) 737-2060. Through July 1. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>''MAX WEBER,'' Gerald Peters, 24 East 78th Street, (212) 628-9760. Through June 10. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>''WOMEN OF WARHOL: MARILYN, LIZ AND JACKIE,'' C&amp;M Arts, 45 East 78th Street, (212) 861-0020. Through June 3. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
