<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Time Warner to Give Refund And Free Channel in the City</title>
    <meta content="05REBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DC1738F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Time Warner to Give Refund And Free Channel in the City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after the staff of the Federal Communications Commission accused Time Warner Cable of violating regulations by cutting ABC television stations off in New York and other cities, Time Warner officials announced a rebate and a free month of a premium channel's programming for all New York City customers.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the City Council speaker, Peter F. Vallone, the president of Time Warner Cable of New York City, Barry Rosenblum, wrote that the company planned to refund ''two full days of basic service charges to our customers.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after the staff of the Federal Communications Commission accused Time Warner Cable of violating regulations by cutting ABC television stations off in New York and other cities, Time Warner officials announced a rebate and a free month of a premium channel's programming for all New York City customers.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the City Council speaker, Peter F. Vallone, the president of Time Warner Cable of New York City, Barry Rosenblum, wrote that the company planned to refund ''two full days of basic service charges to our customers.''</p>
        <p>He added that, to make up for any inconvenience, ''we will provide customers with their choice of any premium channel they currently don't have for 30 days.''</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Vallone said that Time Warner's offer was ''a pretty good response,'' but added that ''it leaves a lot to be desired.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone called it ''a short-term remedy to a long-term problem,'' and said he still planned to hold hearings on the matter and on cable competition today.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Cable Bureau of the F.C.C. issued an opinion faulting Time Warner for the ABC blackout and saying that the cable company might face fines for taking the programming off during ''sweeps week,'' a ratings period of special importance to broadcasters and advertisers.</p>
        <p>F.C.C. officials said that Time Warner was likely to face fines of up to $7,500 per violation per day in the areas that were blacked out. Because seven areas lost access to ABC stations, Time Warner could be liable for seven violations for each of the two days.</p>
        <p>Also on Wednesday, Mr. Vallone met with Mr. Rosenblum and contended that Time Warner had also violated its franchise agreement with the city, and that the company had an obligation to reimburse customers for part of their cable bill this month.</p>
        <p>After the meeting, company officials said that they were not prepared to announce a refund, but that the company intended to go further than a simple rebate.</p>
        <p>Time Warner dropped ABC's signal at 12:01 a.m. Monday after months of fruitless negotiations with ABC's parent corporation, the Walt Disney Company, over retransmission fees, which cable providers pay to broadcast stations for their programming. But, on Tuesday afternoon, Time Warner agreed to allow ABC back on its cable systems until at least July 15, and said it would continue negotiating. The signal was restored at 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>Time Warner's response came after pressure from local politicians and an extensive public relations campaign by Disney. On Tuesday, the second day of the blackout, Disney officials lobbied at City Hall.</p>
        <p>Hours later, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani assailed Time Warner as an ''out-of-touch monopoly'' and added that, ''for the life of me, I don't understand why the Justice Department has spent so much time on Microsoft, but not looked at the cable industry.''</p>
        <p>Gerry Warren-Merrick, a spokeswoman for Time Warner in New York, said that the rebate had nothing to do with public relations, but that it was ''credit for the two days that they did not have programming.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Warren-Merrick added that the offer of the free premium channel was ''to thank our customers for being deeply patient, and just to recognize that we deeply regret the frustration that they felt when ABC was off the air.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
