<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Regents Vote for Ratings Of All Schools Based on Test Scores</title>
    <meta content="05REGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDD1738F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Regents Vote for Ratings Of All Schools Based on Test Scores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pushing further in its drive for accountability and tougher standards, the New York State Board of Regents voted yesterday to publicly grade every school in the state based on scores on the new statewide tests, rewarding or punishing schools according to where they rank.</p>
        <p>In another significant departure, the grades would tease out the scores of black, Hispanic, non-English speaking and special education students in each school, to distinguish gaps between their performance and that of white students. By doing so, the grades will potentially expose weaknesses in better-off districts where the average grades have sometimes masked low achievement by students from those groups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pushing further in its drive for accountability and tougher standards, the New York State Board of Regents voted yesterday to publicly grade every school in the state based on scores on the new statewide tests, rewarding or punishing schools according to where they rank.</p>
        <p>In another significant departure, the grades would tease out the scores of black, Hispanic, non-English speaking and special education students in each school, to distinguish gaps between their performance and that of white students. By doing so, the grades will potentially expose weaknesses in better-off districts where the average grades have sometimes masked low achievement by students from those groups.</p>
        <p>With the Regents' vote, New York joins Texas and California in considering racial data in the rankings and 26 other states that have imposed some form of grading on their schools. In large part, the grades are a way of publicly shaming schools into improvement, or enticing them, as Kentucky and South Carolina do, with cash rewards.</p>
        <p>Although the state has previously branded the worst schools, the new system, to begin with next year's test scores, will be the state's first to rank schools that do not fail. The message, officials say, is that simply passing is no longer the only goal and that serving only middle-class white students well is no longer good enough.</p>
        <p>''When you get beyond the averages and see how minority students and non-English-language learners and other students are performing, you get to the heart of the matter,'' said Richard P. Mills, the state's education commissioner. ''To be called a good school, a school needs to work for all students.''</p>
        <p>Schools will initially be graded on three levels: meeting standards, below standards and farthest from standards. The last category will essentially be the same as the only grade now used: schools under registration review, or SURR. The new system will also recognize ''rapidly improving'' schools that make strong gains over several years of the tests. Within the next year, the state expects to add at least one higher category for schools that exceed standards.</p>
        <p>But the grades have also been used for more drastic measures. Florida legislators voted to give private-school vouchers to students at schools that receive F's for two years out of four. the state is appealing a court decision that ruled the vouchers, but not the grading, unconstitutional. In a speech outlining his presidential campaign pledges on education, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas proposed grading all schools and stripping some federal financing from those that received low grades for three years.</p>
        <p>New York schools superintendents worry that the scores will be used by real estate brokers and parents to measure the merits of one community over another.</p>
        <p>Advocates for minority children applauded the Regents' decision to disaggregate data, or separate the scores of blacks, Hispanics and other groups that have traditionally scored low on tests. Districts where those groups are a minority, especially suburban districts, have tended to score well even though minority students may score at the lowest levels. Separating the data will expose the so-called achievement gap, in which black and Hispanic students score far worse than white students whose parents have the same education level and income.</p>
        <p>''The problem with data based on averages is that it masks the gaps, it allows schools that are not serving kids of color well to skate by on the achievement of affluent kids and white kids,'' said Amy Wilkins, a policy analyst with the Education Trust, a group in Washington that advocates higher standards in schools with poor and minority children.</p>
        <p>For elementary and middle school students, the state will phase in the rankings based on the scores from the mathematics and English tests for fourth and eighth graders in the 2000-2001 school year. The Regents will assign a grade to each school depending on what percentage of students reach Level 2 or Level 3 on each test. (Tests are scored from Level 1 to Level 4, the highest.)</p>
        <p>But the board has yet to determine the percentage of students who have to be in each level for a school to earn a certain ranking.</p>
        <p>Each year, the commissioner will set goals for each ranking, so schools will have to continue to improve to consistently earn high rankings.</p>
        <p>''We are adopting this new accountability system in order to encourage improvement and recognize achievement,'' Carl T. Hayden, the Regents chancellor, said.</p>
        <p>High schools will earn their grades based on the percentage of students graduating, that is, having achieved all course credits and passed the five required Regents exams. While those requirements are being phased in, high schools will be graded on the statewide English and math exams.</p>
        <p>After the grades are assigned, Mr. Mills said, the Regents will consider what rewards or penalties to assign to each level. Rewards will most likely mean waiving some regulations for high-performing schools. Punishments will most likely mean schools that are not making progress will have to come up with improvement plans to be approved by the State Department of Education.</p>
        <p>Some suburban superintendents worried that any form of grading might heighten anxieties in their communities. Michael McGill, superintendent of Scarsdale public schools, asked: ''What happens if you're a parent in a middle-class family and you go to a school which is serving a real diverse group of kids, and where you have some kids performing quite well, but because you're serving a wide range of kids, other kids don't perform well? Your entire district ends up being branded as a poor school.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
