<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Killer Apologizes At Sentencing</title>
    <meta content="05GOLD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DE1738F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Killer Apologizes At Sentencing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew Goldstein, the schizophrenic man convicted of pushing a young woman to her death in front of a speeding subway train, stood in a Manhattan courtroom yesterday, blamed a ''psychotic incident'' for the attack and apologized to the victim's parents for the ''nightmare'' he created. He was then sentenced to 25 years to life in prison for the murder, the maximum possible sentence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein made his brief, disjointed statement to the family of the victim, Kendra Webdale, shortly after her mother, Patricia Webdale, said in a tearful speech that Mr. Goldstein had learned over the years that because he was mentally ill, he was never held accountable for 13 past assaults on doctors, medical staff and strangers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andrew Goldstein, the schizophrenic man convicted of pushing a young woman to her death in front of a speeding subway train, stood in a Manhattan courtroom yesterday, blamed a ''psychotic incident'' for the attack and apologized to the victim's parents for the ''nightmare'' he created. He was then sentenced to 25 years to life in prison for the murder, the maximum possible sentence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein made his brief, disjointed statement to the family of the victim, Kendra Webdale, shortly after her mother, Patricia Webdale, said in a tearful speech that Mr. Goldstein had learned over the years that because he was mentally ill, he was never held accountable for 13 past assaults on doctors, medical staff and strangers.</p>
        <p>''It is my contention,'' Mrs. Webdale, speaking before Justice Carol Berkman of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, said,  ''that if Andrew Goldstein had been held responsible many incidents ago, there would not have been 13 assaults and one homicide committed by him. His ongoing aggression was tolerated and deemed acceptable.''</p>
        <p>During the sentencing hearing, Justice Berkman and the prosecutor joined Mrs. Webdale in saying that the attack stemmed from the state mental health system's failure to punish Mr. Goldstein for past assaults.</p>
        <p>That view stood in sharp contrast to the long-running contention of defense lawyers and mental health advocates that Mr. Goldstein's attack on Ms. Webdale in January 1999 happened because Mr. Goldstein had received shoddy care from the state's underfinanced mental health system. Mr. Goldstein's attack on Ms. Webdale focused intense scrutiny on the state mental health system, which had repeatedly sent him back to the streets despite his history of violence and mental illness and his requests for hospital treatment or other care.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein admitted pushing Ms. Webdale to her death on Jan. 3, 1999, but blamed  his schizophrenia for his actions and pleaded not guilty by reason of insanity. After his first trial ended in a hung jury last November, a Manhattan jury convicted him of second-degree murder on March 22 after little more than an hour of deliberations.</p>
        <p>In his statement to the court yesterday, Mr. Goldstein seemingly dismissed the symbolism and political debate surrounding his case. He said that it did not matter to him whether he served his sentence in a mental institution or state prison, which is where he will be sent because of his guilty conviction. ''Granted, you kill somebody, you deserve punishment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But moments later, Mr. Goldstein, 30, seemed to attribute the killing to his failure to take his anti-psychotic medication. If he had taken it the morning he killed Ms. Webdale, ''this thing would have never happened,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers and advocates for the mentally ill have said that Mr. Goldstein's failure to take his medication contributed to the attack. The killing, they contend, illustrates the need to expand state mental health facilities that could have housed Mr. Goldstein and to create new ways to compel the mentally ill to take their medication.</p>
        <p>In response to the murder, the State Legislature passed a measure last year known as Kendra's Law that makes it easier to commit mentally ill people who resist treatment.</p>
        <p>In a biting attack, the prosecutor in the case, William Greenbaum, argued that the meaning of the case had been twisted by defense lawyers.</p>
        <p>''What a slur on the mentally ill to have this individual made a poster child for mental illness,'' Mr. Greenbaum, an assistant district attorney, said. He added that it was ''a gross unfairness to so many people who have struggled every day with mental illness.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenbaum repeated his argument that Mr. Goldstein was a manipulative, high-functioning schizophrenic who used his mental illness as a crutch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein's lawyer, Kevin Canfield, scoffed at that account. He said Mr. Goldstein was clinically insane and asked Justice Berkman to sentence him to the minimum sentence of 15 years to life in prison. ''He's not a monster, judge, he never was,'' Mr. Canfield said. ''He is the shell of a man that he used to be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Canfield produced two letters written by Mr. Goldstein's parents, who did not appear at his trials and refused to testify in his defense. The letters, which included photos of Mr. Goldstein as a child and teenager before schizophrenia set in, said that ''as a boy he had friends, played ball, played tennis, rode a bike, and belonged to school clubs.''</p>
        <p>''Throughout school he ranked at the top of his class, achieving the dean's list in his college freshman year,'' wrote Mr. Goldstein's father, Edward Goldstein, a doctor in Milford, Del. ''Then his life began eroding into a delusional world.''</p>
        <p>In her comments, Justice Berkman called mental illness a curse but added that Mr. Goldstein was dangerous. She said turning Mr. Goldstein into a poster child for any cause was wrong and faulted the system for failing to punish him earlier.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't understand punishment because we've taught him these bad lessons,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Webdale's parents, three of her sisters, her brother, her aunt and uncle, the driver of the subway that hit her, a witness on the platform that day and the officer who arrested Mr. Goldstein all attended yesterday's sentencing. In a tearful statement to the judge, Ms. Webdale's oldest sister, Kim, said she lived near where her sister did, and is still haunted each day when she goes to work and stands on the same subway platform her sister was hurled from.</p>
        <p>And Ms. Webdale's youngest sister, Krista, tried to bring to life an exuberant young women the city only came to know in death. ''Her eyes spoke to you,'' she said, sobbing uncontrollably. ''She could say, 'I am so proud of you, I understand, you're so funny, I love you,' all with the tilt of her head and flash of her gentle, honest eyes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
