<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lindros Is Injured Again in Workout</title>
    <meta content="05PENS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DE1738F936A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lindros Is Injured Again in Workout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even while the Philadelphia Flyers tried to even their second-round playoff series tonight, the focus of the franchise was divided. As the Flyers played the Penguins in Game 4 in the Mellon Arena, much of the conversation around the rink concerned Eric Lindros, Philadelphia's former captain, who has missed the playoffs with concussion symptoms.</p>
        <p>Working out with the team's taxi squad near Philadelphia this morning and hoping to return to the lineup if the Flyers are involved in the next round, Lindros accidentally collided with defenseman Francis Lessard  and needed to go to a hospital for treatment of a cut upper lip, a bruised lower lip and headaches, the Flyers said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even while the Philadelphia Flyers tried to even their second-round playoff series tonight, the focus of the franchise was divided. As the Flyers played the Penguins in Game 4 in the Mellon Arena, much of the conversation around the rink concerned Eric Lindros, Philadelphia's former captain, who has missed the playoffs with concussion symptoms.</p>
        <p>Working out with the team's taxi squad near Philadelphia this morning and hoping to return to the lineup if the Flyers are involved in the next round, Lindros accidentally collided with defenseman Francis Lessard  and needed to go to a hospital for treatment of a cut upper lip, a bruised lower lip and headaches, the Flyers said.</p>
        <p>After taking 20 stitches to close the wound, Lindros was given medication for pain relief and sent home, according to the team.</p>
        <p>Lindros lost his rank as Philadelphia's captain after he criticized the team's medical staff for failing to diagnose the fourth concussion of his career. Lindros worked out this morning in Voorhees, N.J., before a scheduled trip to Chicago, where he was to be examined by James Kelly, a concussion specialist who was to decide whether or not Lindros was fit for full practice.</p>
        <p>The trip was postponed. Although Lindros has not been cleared for scrimmaging with contact, today's workout was what the team called a controlled scrimmage, with no contact expected. The workout was authorized by the club, according to Zack Hill, a team spokesman.</p>
        <p>The team said Lindros was alert and clear when examined by Gary Dorshimer, a team physician. He was said to be experiencing headaches.</p>
        <p>The Flyers' chairman, Ed Snider, said Lindros's continuing medical problems were ''almost unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>''We're very sorry that it happened,'' he said. ''Whether or not it's serious remains to be seen. His intentions were good.''</p>
        <p>Dorshimer added that Lindros had total recollection and had no visual symptoms and ''didn't feel unsteady on the ice.'' But the doctor also said he told Lindros, ''We'll have to re-evaluate you tomorrow to see what your symptoms are.''</p>
        <p>The recent strife involving Lindros and his injuries has caused a serious rift within the Flyers organization. Snider and General Manager Bob Clarke are known to be unhappy with the player once thought to be the cornerstone of the franchise.</p>
        <p>Lindros remains close to Roger Neilson, the head coach, who missed the last quarter of the season while being treated for cancer.</p>
        <p>Neilson has rejoined the team and said he wanted to coach in this round. But the request was declined by upper management, which cited concern for Neilson's health.</p>
        <p>In a radio interview in Toronto last week, Neilson said management did not want the team coached by a cancer patient who is close to Lindros.</p>
        <p>When his words created another wave of controversy, Neilson at first said he was kidding and later apologized. He is with the team as a special assistant to Craig Ramsay, who is listed as the head coach and directs the team from behind the bench.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh played on Thursday night without defenseman JIRI SLEGR, who missed many shifts in Game 3 after a collision with Philadelphia's JOHN LECLAIR. Slegr fell to the ice, appearing to injure either his head or a leg, or both.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
