<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRICE OF GASOLINE EMERGES AS ISSUE IN BUSH-GORE RACE</title>
    <meta content="22GAS.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harkin, Tom (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DD1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRICE OF GASOLINE EMERGES AS ISSUE IN BUSH-GORE RACE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>NASHVILLE, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore's presidential campaign, worried that voters will blame Gore and Clinton administration for gasoline price surge, seeks to paint Gov George W Bush, former oil company executive, as tool of oil interests it says are gouging consumers; Sen Tom Harkin, speaking for Gore campaign, charges Bush gets 'all his money' from oil companies; says he wants oil executives to testify before Congress; Bush and Congressional Republicans blame price rise on Clinton administration; Bush, who had been reluctant to discuss issue publicly, joins Gore in endorsing Federal Trade Commission probe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Worried that voters will blame the Clinton administration -- and Vice President Al Gore -- for the recent surge in gasoline prices, the Gore campaign has begun an effort to paint Gov. George W. Bush, a onetime oil company executive, as a tool of the oil interests it says are relentlessly gouging consumers.</p>
        <p>Speaking today for the Gore campaign, Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa, said Mr. Bush was ''getting all his money'' from the oil companies, a reference to the industry's substantial financial contributions to Mr. Bush's presidential campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Worried that voters will blame the Clinton administration -- and Vice President Al Gore -- for the recent surge in gasoline prices, the Gore campaign has begun an effort to paint Gov. George W. Bush, a onetime oil company executive, as a tool of the oil interests it says are relentlessly gouging consumers.</p>
        <p>Speaking today for the Gore campaign, Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa, said Mr. Bush was ''getting all his money'' from the oil companies, a reference to the industry's substantial financial contributions to Mr. Bush's presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harkin said he wanted oil executives to testify under oath on Capitol Hill about the price increases.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Bush and Republicans on Capitol Hill blame the gas-price increase on the Clinton administration, saying the administration has had no coherent domestic energy policy and, in imposing regulations to meet clean air standards, had allowed prices to drift as high as $2.39 a gallon in the Midwest. Mr. Bush also said the administration had failed to persuade the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries to ''open the spigots'' to increase the supply.</p>
        <p>The group did decide today to increase production by more than most experts had expected, but the increase remained too small to bring down gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who has been reluctant to discuss the issue publicly, broke his silence today and joined Mr. Gore in endorsing the investigation by the Federal Trade Commission that was announced on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I do think it's fair to have the F.T.C. investigate,'' he told reporters in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's comment could undercut Mr. Gore's efforts to portray the governor as part of the problem. In any case, the issue has jumped to the top of the agenda in presidential politics as Americans begin their summer vacations and both sides are trying to exploit it.</p>
        <p>The prices have hit hardest in the Midwest, the very states where the two campaigns are competing most fiercely for votes.</p>
        <p>Gas prices in Illinois, Michigan and Wisconsin are substantially higher than in other parts of the country for several reasons, but chief among them, Republicans say, is the special kind of reformulated gas the area must use under Environmental Protection Agency regulations. Those regulations went into effect on June 1, which is when prices began to rise considerably. The Midwest is the first region, under the rules, to begin using this ethanol-laced reformulated gas to prevent pollution.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials said that new polling shows that voters believe the price of gasoline is far and away the No. 1 problem in the country. The officials also say that voters blame American oil companies most, then the OPEC oil cartel.</p>
        <p>Gore officials see the emergence of this issue as an opportunity to link Mr. Bush directly in the public mind with the oil companies and portray Mr. Gore as on the side of working families. This has been a longtime goal of the Gore campaign, but it has not succeeded so far.</p>
        <p>Mark Fabiani, a spokesman for Mr. Gore, said: ''It all comes down to who people think is on their side. People believe, and rightly so, that the oil companies are in large part responsible for the price of gasoline. They don't believe the government is responsible for the price of gas. So what average people are deciding is, 'Who do I want in the government when gas prices skyrocket?' We think the answer is clear: Vice President Gore is on their side, Governor Bush isn't.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore himself has ratcheted up his language on the price increases, last week saying in selective interviews with Midwest television stations that he wanted an investigation into possible collusion. Today, he said at the opening of a Social Security speech in Iowa, one of the states most affected, that he was concerned about the ''conduct of the oil companies'' and that they may have been price gouging.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore noted that OPEC had indicated today that it would increase oil production, a move that would presumably put downward pressure on gasoline prices in the United States. But he said the issue deserved thorough investigation by the Federal Trade Commission.</p>
        <p>''I hope that it will be thorough and hard-hitting,'' Mr. Gore said of the investigation. ''If there's evidence of what I suspect there's evidence of, it ought to be dealt with quickly and harshly. I think it's time to put our feet on the brakes of what may well be big oil's price gouging.''</p>
        <p>Senator Harkin, speaking on behalf of the Gore campaign on a conference call with reporters, accused the oil companies of ''outright thievery.'' He went on to castigate Mr. Bush for his ''silence'' on the matter, saying, ''What can you expect of someone who once claimed, and I quote, 'There's no such thing as being too closely aligned to the oil business in West Texas'?''</p>
        <p>The quotation from Mr. Bush was made in a 1978 Congressional campaign. Acknowledging that the quotation was more than 20 years old, Mr. Harkin said: ''The point is, the test of character and leadership is when you're willing to take on your friends when it's in the nation's best interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush signed an emergency tax bill in 1999 that gave state tax breaks to oil and gas companies. The Dallas Morning News reported that the bill saved Richard Rainwater, a former Bush business partner, $1 million. At least 14 of Mr. Bush's ''Pioneers,'' his largest financial contributors, have ties to the oil industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's campaign has received $1.5 million from energy interests as of April 30, while Mr. Gore had received less than $125,000 as of the same date.</p>
        <p>But the Gore strategy of opening up fire on the oil front carries some dangers for the Gore campaign. For one thing, rising prices -- and being reminded of them -- could undermine consumer confidence in the economy at a time when Mr. Gore is boasting about the economy on his ''progress and prosperity tour.''</p>
        <p>Representative Dick Armey, the majority leader and a Texan, told reporters in Washington today: ''The vice president has a growing political problem because his administration has been asleep at the wheel when it comes to dealing with OPEC. Instead of acknowledging that his administration has no energy policy, which leaves our nation overly dependent on foreign oil, the vice president is looking for a scapegoat.''</p>
        <p>Republicans also said that Mr. Gore has obsessively lobbied for so-called ''clean-air fuel,'' the kind that is now at the center of the Midwestern price increases, without worrying about the consequences. ''He is the one who pushed this whole idea of a different type of gasoline,'' said Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois.</p>
        <p>But Gore officials say the environmental standards leading to the reformulation of gasoline have added only four to eight cents a gallon to the cost of fuel and would not account for such a drastic price increase.</p>
        <p>In his 1992 environmental treatise, ''Earth in the Balance,'' Mr. Gore himself proposed the idea of higher fuel taxes on oil companies to help reduce pollution; as part of that, he suggested a corresponding cut in corporate income and payroll taxes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
