<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Gunfire, but No Peace, at Lebanon-Israel Border</title>
    <meta content="Y22ISR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD61131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Gunfire, but No Peace, at Lebanon-Israel Border</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenberg, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>METULLA, Israel, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel's border with Lebanon remains free of gunfire but unsettled nearly a month after Israel withdrew troops from southern Lebanon; United Nations teams continue to check withdrawal line, leaving Hezbollah guerrillas, not Lebanese or UN soldiers, facing Israelis along frontier; UN Sec Gen Kofi Annan meets in Israel with Prime Min Ehud Barak to iron out reported violations of withdrawal line; notes Hezbollah restraint and says UN peacekeepers will be posted at border; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Armed with a slingshot, a walkie-talkie and a pistol tucked into his pants, a Hezbollah guerrilla across the fence in Lebanon let another stone fly today toward a mesh-covered Israeli Army post on the outskirts of this northern border community.</p>
        <p>What had once been a frontier lookout point for Israeli visitors was closed off with coils of barbed wire. The ground was strewn with rubble heaved in recent weeks from the Lebanese side, where burned-out buildings and barriers in an abandoned Israeli base were covered with anti-Israeli graffiti and posters for Hezbollah, or the Party of God.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Armed with a slingshot, a walkie-talkie and a pistol tucked into his pants, a Hezbollah guerrilla across the fence in Lebanon let another stone fly today toward a mesh-covered Israeli Army post on the outskirts of this northern border community.</p>
        <p>What had once been a frontier lookout point for Israeli visitors was closed off with coils of barbed wire. The ground was strewn with rubble heaved in recent weeks from the Lebanese side, where burned-out buildings and barriers in an abandoned Israeli base were covered with anti-Israeli graffiti and posters for Hezbollah, or the Party of God.</p>
        <p>Rocks regularly sail over the fence these days at Israeli farmers from Metulla who work in apple orchards along the border. Vehicles have been hit and irrigation systems smashed, disrupting work in recent weeks, although no one has been hurt.</p>
        <p>Israeli soldiers at the border are under strict orders not to fire unless they are fired upon, and it has been only stones, not bullets, that have crossed the fence.</p>
        <p>Nearly a month after Israel withdrew its troops from southern Lebanon, the frontier between the countries remains free of gunfire but unsettled. The line of Israeli withdrawal, certified by the United Nations but disputed in some points by Lebanon, is still being checked by United Nations teams. In the meantime, Hezbollah guerrillas -- not Lebanese or United Nations soldiers -- face the Israelis along the frontier.</p>
        <p>''If all our land is not liberated we will continue fighting, and we want our prisoners released,'' one warned near the border fence today, echoing the pledge of his movement's leader, Sheik Hassan Nasrallah.</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan, who is visiting the Middle East, was in Israel today to try to iron out the reported violations of the withdrawal line. Prime Minister Ehud Barak said after he met with Mr. Annan that he expected that the matter would be settled within a day or two.</p>
        <p>Mr. Annan, who met Sheik Nasrallah in Lebanon on Tuesday, noted the ''restraint, responsibility and discipline'' of Hezbollah, which has not fired across the border since the Israeli withdrawal, and he asserted that United Nations peacekeepers would be posted on the frontier.</p>
        <p>''We will move the troops to the border,'' he said, adding that Lebanese officials had indicated to him that they too would soon send their troops to southern Lebanon.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, life in Metulla is ''anything but routine,'' said Herzl Boker, the local council's security officer. Farmers take roundabout routes to their orchards and work in the early morning to avoid the stone throwing, but are often are forced to leave, he said. Recently, he added, the army discovered an attempted entry through the fence, but the intruders fled back to Lebanon.</p>
        <p>''There's no one to talk to right now on the other side,'' Mr. Boker said. ''The minute the Lebanese Army and the United Nations arrive and take control, it will be possible to stop the vandalism.''</p>
        <p>Avi Rauner, who has apple and pear orchards near the border fence, said he had cut back his work there to avoid the daily shower of stones. Yet compared with  the warfare that used to rage across the border between Hezbollah and the Israeli Army, ''the situation is quiet,'' he added.</p>
        <p>''We expected that when the army left Lebanon, Hezbollah would take over and that mobs would loot what was left behind,'' he said. ''But in a few weeks U.N. and Lebanese forces will come. This situation is only temporary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
