<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tighter Rules for 527 Groups</title>
    <meta content="22THU1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFD81131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tighter Rules for 527 Groups</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial urges House to end secrecy surrounding campaign fund-raising and advertising spending by shadowy political slush funds created under tax code Section 527; scores spreading abuses by such groups</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an earlier setback, the drive to end the secrecy surrounding a pernicious form of campaign fund-raising is gaining in the House. Today a House subcommittee is to begin drafting a bill that could stop shadowy political slush funds from raising and spending undisclosed sums for campaign ads. A disclosure requirement for these groups, which have been created under Section 527 of the tax code, passed the Senate two weeks ago. It fell short in the House the next day because of promises that supporters of disclosure would get a chance to vote on an alternative later. The moment to cast such a vote has now arrived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After an earlier setback, the drive to end the secrecy surrounding a pernicious form of campaign fund-raising is gaining in the House. Today a House subcommittee is to begin drafting a bill that could stop shadowy political slush funds from raising and spending undisclosed sums for campaign ads. A disclosure requirement for these groups, which have been created under Section 527 of the tax code, passed the Senate two weeks ago. It fell short in the House the next day because of promises that supporters of disclosure would get a chance to vote on an alternative later. The moment to cast such a vote has now arrived.</p>
        <p>The abuses of the Section 527 groups have spread this year, blowing another hole in campaign fund-raising laws. Those laws were largely obviated when the Justice Department allowed elected officials and party organizations to use ''soft money'' to circumvent longstanding limits on donations. But at least the parties disclosed the donors. This year Representative Tom DeLay and others have set up what they say are independent units that run ads attacking candidates but do not have to make their donors known. The most notorious example occurred in March, when secret donors who later turned out to be supporters of Gov. George W. Bush ran attack ads against Senator John McCain.</p>
        <p>Joining with Senators Russell Feingold of Wisconsin and Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut, Mr. McCain got the disclosure requirement for Section 527 groups passed in the Senate. Foes of reform struck back, proposing an alternative bill that would require disclosure of donors for a wide array of public affairs and charitable groups. Their approach was actually tailored to repel lawmakers by making it overly broad and punitive toward unions.</p>
        <p>In the House, Christopher Shays of Connecticut and Michael Castle of Delaware, both Republicans, are joining a Democrat, Martin Meehan of Massachusetts, to push a bill to broaden the disclosure requirements beyond the 527 groups without making it so inclusive that it violates the constitutional right to privacy of advocacy organizations. Their measure would impose disclosure requirements only on groups that spend $10,000 or more per year on ads that mention a candidate 90 days before a general election or 60 days before a primary. Organizations that sponsor campaign advertising would have the option of setting up separate accounts for that purpose. Donors for these accounts would have to be disclosed, a requirement not applying to donors supporting other activities.</p>
        <p>This approach has emerged as the best opportunity for reform in the House. Other lawmakers are pushing for even broader disclosure requirements. But they should take care not to undermine  the bill's bipartisan backing by doing anything one-sided or destructive of the constitutional rights of organizations involved in political activities. After so many disappointments, if Congress cannot even stop the clandestine fund-raising infecting the process this year, it will be consigning the election system to the dark pre-Watergate days of corruption and backdoor financial dealings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
