<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Dropping Managed Care For Its Jails After Disputes</title>
    <meta content="22JAIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Barnabas Hospital (Bronx)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rikers Island Prison Complex (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Detention Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DE1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Dropping Managed Care For Its Jails After Disputes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three years after New York City brought managed care to its jails and gave St Barnabas Hospital in Bronx set fee to care for roughly 17,000 inmates at Rikers Island jail complex and Manhattan Detention Center, initiative has been quietly abandoned; problems besetting project discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years after the city brought managed care to its jails and gave one hospital a set fee to care for the roughly 17,000 inmates at the Rikers Island jail complex and the Manhattan Detention Center, the initiative has been quietly abandoned and the city appears set to return to the system it once derided as too costly and inefficient.</p>
        <p>The city's effort to contain costs and improve care at the jails, which was built around a three-year, $342 million deal with St. Barnabas Hospital in the Bronx, had been plagued by disputes over the city's role in monitoring the care provided as well as a continuing criminal investigation into possible negligence by the hospital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years after the city brought managed care to its jails and gave one hospital a set fee to care for the roughly 17,000 inmates at the Rikers Island jail complex and the Manhattan Detention Center, the initiative has been quietly abandoned and the city appears set to return to the system it once derided as too costly and inefficient.</p>
        <p>The city's effort to contain costs and improve care at the jails, which was built around a three-year, $342 million deal with St. Barnabas Hospital in the Bronx, had been plagued by disputes over the city's role in monitoring the care provided as well as a continuing criminal investigation into possible negligence by the hospital.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, St. Barnabas announced that it would not seek to renew its contract when it expires next February.</p>
        <p>In April, though, the city began to solicit proposals for a new contract, and the payment system it proposes is strikingly similar to the fee-for-service plan it had sought to overhaul.</p>
        <p>Under the old system, the city reimbursed the medical provider for each inmate's care, and also paid for each inmate's hospital visits without limit, a system that it said led to excessive hospital visits, related security risks and rising costs. Inmates made almost 10,700 hospital visits a year when Montefiore Medical Center held the contract, often for minor ailments that could have been treated at the jails, city officials said.</p>
        <p>Four medical providers, including St. Vincent's Hospital in Manhattan, are presenting bids this week for a new contract, which is likely to be the largest jail-care contract in the country. Two other providers are bidding for a smaller part of the contract.</p>
        <p>Ernesto Marrero, the executive director of Correctional Health Services, the city unit that oversees jail care and developed the new contract, said that the new contract would incorporate the best of both models.</p>
        <p>St. Barnabas's on-site treatment centers, and the designated triage doctors who send only the sickest inmates to the hospital, will remain, he said. But because the city will reimburse its new provider only for care that it gives, it will be better able to monitor how money is spent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marrero added that a plan in which payments were capped, or capitated, served a purpose by giving St. Barnabas an incentive to improve care in the jails by expanding preventive care and creating specialty clinics on site. With that goal met, he said, ''it was time to moderate the approach.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marrero acknowledged that since the current contract allowed St. Barnabas to submit projected, and not actual, spending and staffing levels, it was hard for the city to know exactly how much profit the hospital was making or how much care it was providing. ''I like as much control as possible,'' he said, ''and a capitated plan doesn't give me as much control as I would like.''</p>
        <p>But conflicts over the contract with St. Barnabas continue. On Tuesday, St. Barnabas filed a lawsuit against the Health and Hospitals Corporation, the parent of Correctional Health Services, asserting its right to remove key pieces of medical equipment from the Rikers Island jail complex, along with ''intellectual property'' like software systems. The managed-care contract did not specifically compensate St. Barnabas for these items, which it now owns as a result, the lawsuit states. Mr. Marrero said that in any multimillion-dollar contract, litigation was always brewing.</p>
        <p>Inmate advocates are delighted with the new plan and say they hope it will restore the humanity in jail care and the ideal of Rikers as a  laboratory in which to treat medical and social ills. ''That whole ethic has been ripped to shreds and stomped on the floor by St. Barnabas,'' said John Boston, director of the prisoners' rights project for the Legal Aid Society. ''The central concept of giving the provider a bag of money and saying, 'You can keep what you don't spend,' has certainly been abandoned.''</p>
        <p>When the managed-care contract began in January 1998, with St. Barnabas as the provider, city officials hailed the new venture as a remedy for the problem of open-ended costs.  Luis R. Marcos, director of the Health and Hospitals Corporation, said it would provide an incentive not to send patients to the hospital unnecessarily.</p>
        <p>But within six months, two inmates had died after delayed hospitalization and the Manhattan district attorney opened an investigation into criminal negligence in the deaths. Emergency room doctors said that many inmates sent to the city hospitals showed serious signs of neglect.</p>
        <p>An internal report done by the city showed that in its first year, St. Barnabas was on a path to make $14 million in profit, in part by spending far less on each inmate than it proposed to the city it would.</p>
        <p>As the city tried to defend St. Barnabas's performance, several officials at Correctional Health Services quit their jobs, saying that medical neglect was going unchecked.</p>
        <p>However, St. Barnabas, which has formed a for-profit entity that is seeking national jail-care contracts and recently began a promotional Web site, has defended its performance, saying that it reversed a jail-care system in decline.</p>
        <p>''The critics notwithstanding, St. Barnabas Hospital has done an exceptional job at Rikers Island, as evidenced by new services, reduced inmate mortality and the fact that its employees and systems are being sought for the next vendor,'' said Gerald McKelvey, a hospital spokesman. He added that the city's oversight was archaic and ''obsolete from its inception,'' and called the quality of health care that St. Barnabas inherited deplorable.</p>
        <p>With the contract in its final months, the city and St. Barnabas agree on almost nothing. For example, Correctional Health Services recently found that in the last quarter of 1999, St. Barnabas failed to meet 12 of 30 performance benchmarks outlined in the contract, including providing required levels of asthma care and H.I.V. testing. The agency fined St. Barnabas $60,000, but the hospital is refusing to pay, asserting that the city has refused to divulge how it came up with those findings.</p>
        <p>Next month, the city will select its new jail-care provider and has emphasized in its request for proposals that ''complete cooperation'' with its monitoring efforts ''is essential.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
