<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sydney Olympics Turns to DNA Ink to Mark Official Souvenirs</title>
    <meta content="22DNA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scanning Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ink</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DNA Technologies Inc</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DF1131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sydney Olympics Turns to DNA Ink to Mark Official Souvenirs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL SORID</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sydney Olympics organizing committee, in effort to combat sale of counterfeit items at this summer's games, is using ink containing DNA to mark official merchanidse; DNA Technologies, Los Angeles, developed ink, which contains DNA strands from an Australian athlete who has not been identified as well as chemical that can be easily identified with an optical scanner (m)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIGH technology is nothing new for the Olympics. From finish-line computers to drug tests, the Olympic committee has often been an early adopter. This summer, technology will come into play where it really matters: the sale of souvenirs.</p>
        <p>To combat the sale of counterfeit items at the Olympics, the Sydney Olympics organizing committee is using ink containing DNA to mark official merchandise. DNA Technologies of Los Angeles developed the ink, which contains copies of DNA strands from an Australian athlete who has not been identified as well as a chemical that can be easily identified with an optical scanner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIGH technology is nothing new for the Olympics. From finish-line computers to drug tests, the Olympic committee has often been an early adopter. This summer, technology will come into play where it really matters: the sale of souvenirs.</p>
        <p>To combat the sale of counterfeit items at the Olympics, the Sydney Olympics organizing committee is using ink containing DNA to mark official merchandise. DNA Technologies of Los Angeles developed the ink, which contains copies of DNA strands from an Australian athlete who has not been identified as well as a chemical that can be easily identified with an optical scanner.</p>
        <p>DNA Technologies has developed inks, invisible or colored, for about a dozen companies; in some cases, the DNA strands used have come from  celebrities.</p>
        <p>For the Olympic souvenirs, the special ink is placed either directly on the goods or on a tag attached to them. If an Olympic official suspects that a product is not authentic, the product can be scanned on the spot as a preliminary check. To check the DNA, the product can be sent to the company for an analysis.</p>
        <p>Unlike holograms, which can be copied, DNA ink is virtually counterfeit-proof, said Chris Outwater, chief executive of DNA Technologies, because DNA, which contains a person's genetic code, is so complex.</p>
        <p>Making the DNA tags is straightforward. According to Mr. Outwater, a DNA sample is taken with either a blood sample or a swab of the mouth, and that DNA is copied many times. Some DNA is kept as an identifier, and some is mixed into the ink to be placed on the merchandise.</p>
        <p>''We just need a small fragment,''  Mr. Outwater said, ''to give us enough complexity to stop any counterfeiter or bad person from trying to copy it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Outwater said there was one chance in a trillion that a counterfeiter would be able to duplicate a tag because each DNA string used is made up of at least 20 ''beads''; each bead can be one of four molecules. Even if counterfeiters knew that the pieces of DNA in the ink were from a particular person's DNA, they would still have to figure out what part of the DNA had been used as a tag. Mr. Outwater gave this analogy: ''You're standing out in front of the New York Public Library, and you say to the counterfeiter, 'I'm using one sentence out of one book in that library. You figure it out.' ''</p>
        <p>Or counterfeiters could presumably clone the DNA in the tags to make their own version of the real ink. But Dr. Rick Tullis, a consultant to the company, said that would not be feasible because the DNA can be treated to make it hard to copy and other pieces of DNA can be included in the solution to foil counterfeiters.</p>
        <p>Why go to so much effort? The sale of official merchandise at the Sydney Olympics is expected to reach $36 million, according to the Sydney Olympics organizing committee.</p>
        <p>In one example of the severity of the problem with counterfeit products, the Customs Service points out that counterfeit products cost the United States economy around $200 billion a year, more than the annual gross domestic product of Greece.</p>
        <p>The technique used by Mr. Outwater's company, which received a contract with the Sydney Olympics organizers in 1998, is not perfected. While the company is making enough DNA tags to mark about 10 million souvenir items for the Olympics, it does not have a handheld device that can verify beyond a doubt that a product is authentic. Authorities doing spot checks of vending areas cannot test for the DNA itself, Mr. Outwater said. To do that, the inspector must send the item to DNA Technologies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Outwater says the instant checks have been adequate for the company's customers in the last two years -- no customer has actually sent an item to DNA Technologies for a DNA analysis.</p>
        <p>DNA Technologies has made DNA tags for more than just the Olympics. It used DNA tags to mark Mark McGwire's 70th-home-run ball and to protect movie props at Warner Brothers that ''tend to walk off the lot,'' Mr. Outwater said. Warner Brothers hopes that the tags will help the company identify stolen items that are offered for sale.</p>
        <p>As more companies turn to the Internet to sell consumer merchandise, there will be a greater push for anti-counterfeit measures like DNA tagging, Mr. Outwater said.</p>
        <p>''It's a little more scary to be on the Internet in some virtual store and not know exactly what you're buying,'' he said. With DNA tags, he contended, ''you're going to know that this is an authentic product.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
