<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summit Glow Fades as Koreans Face Obstacles to Unity</title>
    <meta content="22KORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">South Korea-International Relations-North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sims, Calvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EEDF1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summit Glow Fades as Koreans Face Obstacles to Unity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sims, Calvin</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Euphoria that followed summit meeting fades as North and South Korean leaders face reality of trying to reunite nations with common ancestry and language but drastically different ideologies and fortunes; Kim Jong Il releases number of provocative statements urging North Koreans not to stray from Communist principles; South Korea's main political opposition levies barrage of criticism against North Korea and peace plan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The euphoria that followed the summit meeting between North and South Korea last week has started to fade as their leaders face the reality of trying to reunite two countries with a common ancestry and language but drastically different ideologies and fortunes.</p>
        <p>Although foreign diplomats and political experts say the prospects of peace and reconciliation on the Korean Peninsula remain promising, antagonistic statements in both countries in recent days underscore the inevitable difficulties that North and South face in trying to overcome five decades as ideological enemies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The euphoria that followed the summit meeting between North and South Korea last week has started to fade as their leaders face the reality of trying to reunite two countries with a common ancestry and language but drastically different ideologies and fortunes.</p>
        <p>Although foreign diplomats and political experts say the prospects of peace and reconciliation on the Korean Peninsula remain promising, antagonistic statements in both countries in recent days underscore the inevitable difficulties that North and South face in trying to overcome five decades as ideological enemies.</p>
        <p>This week, the official North Korean news agency released numerous provocative declarations, some old and some new, by the country's leader, Kim Jong Il, admonishing North Koreans not to stray from the principles of the Communist revolution.</p>
        <p>''We must create a self-sufficient and strong nation and not yield to economic reforms and market openings that would certainly lead to our destruction,'' Mr. Kim said in a rebroadcast of a 1999 speech on Tuesday, a day after the United States had removed sanctions on nonmilitary trade with North Korea.</p>
        <p>In a broadcast today, the North Korean Foreign Ministry demanded that all sanctions be lifted and that the United States stop being ''hostile.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, North Korea said the United States, which has 37,000 troops in South Korea, had increased the likelihood of war on the peninsula.</p>
        <p>The diatribe, which political experts said was intended to appease North Korean hard-liners and  project an image of strength, was a sharp contrast to the conciliatory gestures that Kim Jong Il and President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea traded at their talks in Pyongyang.</p>
        <p>The two leaders signed an accord that called for closer ties, economic cooperation and eventual reunification.</p>
        <p>But the North's shift in tone has been no more caustic than a barrage of criticism that South Korea's main political opposition has levied against the Communist country and the agreement forged there.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging the significance of the summit meeting, leaders of the opposition Grand National Party said that North Korea remained a dangerous state and that the talks had failed to address important issues like the North's nuclear and missile programs and the costs of reunification.</p>
        <p>''Kim Jong Il is very good at putting on a show,'' Chung Hyung Keun, a legislator of the opposition Grand National Party, said. ''But he is an old-line Communist leader who believes that he can make the South his own at any time, and that is very dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Foreign and Korean experts said the verbal jabs had provided a much-needed reality check to the mass euphoria after the summit sessions and pointed to some of the difficulties ahead.</p>
        <p>''I think that both sides are working hard to achieve peace, but we can't expect them to abandon their political systems and party-line rhetoric overnight,'' said a European ambassador.</p>
        <p>Indeed, no one expects reunification of the peninsula soon. The stark economic differences between the two Koreas and astronomical costs of merging them make reunification a distant prospect.</p>
        <p>Fueled by foreign investment, open markets, advanced technology and entrepreneurial spirit, South Korea has become one of the world's most economically successful democracies.</p>
        <p>But North Korea, by all accounts, is in dire straits. Inefficient agriculture and devastating floods have created severe food shortages. Most of its factories are dormant.</p>
        <p>In most regions, there are virtually no paved roads, telephones or public transportation. Economists have estimated that it could cost hundreds of billions of dollars to integrate the two.</p>
        <p>How fast the two countries unify would largely depend on what political changes occur in North Korea. Because North Korea remains closed to the outside world, little is known about what effects the summit meeting has had there.</p>
        <p>South Korean envoys who attended the sessions said it was widely reported in newspapers and on radio and television in Pyongyang.</p>
        <p>But political experts said because Kim Jong Il's government so tightly controlled what North Koreans see and think and the country has been isolated so long, the meetings were highly unlikely to have significant political effects soon.</p>
        <p>''Kim Jong Il's power has never been stronger, despite his people's dismal economic situation,'' said Jo Dong Ho, an economist for the Korean Development Institute, a private think tank in Seoul. ''For change to take place, North Koreans have to become aware that their difficulties arise from bad governance. But most of them still believe that Kim Jong Il is great and all people on this planet worship him.''</p>
        <p>But the meeting may have had some repercussions in the North.</p>
        <p>''We support the notion that Kim Dae Jung's visit created a lot of excitement in North Korea and that the recent broadcasts reasserting revolutionary principles were designed to calm the excitement there that reunification was near,'' said Yoon Young Joong, who monitors North Korean broadcasts for the Unification Ministry in South Korea.</p>
        <p>North Korea's propagandistic broadcasts are also being put forward by South Korea's political opposition as evidence that Kim Jong Il has not changed his ways.</p>
        <p>The opposition has criticized Kim Dae Jung for not using the meetings to focus on the hundreds of thousands of North Koreans who international aid workers estimate have died because of famine and floods and the government's failure to adopt agricultural and market reforms.</p>
        <p>Opposition politicians also accused South Korean media of presenting an unrealistically positive view of the summit meetings.</p>
        <p>''Just recently,'' Mr. Chung said, ''the South Korean media were filled with images of starving North Korean children eating worms from the ground just outside Pyongyang and elsewhere around the country. But now the media have stopped showing these atrocities, and the only thing they show are pretty images of Pyongyang.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
