<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Expansion Effort, Fidelity Revises Management and Units</title>
    <meta content="Y22FUN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fidelity Investments</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fmr Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curvey, James C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Robert L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pozen, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D61131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Expansion Effort, Fidelity Revises Management and Units</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fidelity Investments, privately controlled financial giant that manages nearly $1 trillion, shuffles its top executives and reorganizes its businesses as part of its effort to move beyond managing mutual funds; James C Curey, president and chief operating officer, says he will leave both posts but remain at company; Robert L Reynolds will succeed Curvey as chief operating officer, effective July 3, and will also be vice chairman; Robert C Pozen, president of FMR Co, unit that includes Fidelity's vast mutual fund management operations, is also promoted to vice chairman; Fidelity will take more traditional corporate structure and create three operating units overseen by vice chairmen (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fidelity Investments, the privately controlled financial giant in Boston that manages nearly $1 trillion, shuffled its top executives and reorganized its businesses yesterday as part of its effort to move beyond managing mutual funds.</p>
        <p>James C. Curvey, 65, president and chief operating officer, said he would leave both posts, but remain at the company. Mr. Curvey has served for three years as the top executive under Edward C. Johnson III, the chairman and chief executive of Fidelity and son of the company's founder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fidelity Investments, the privately controlled financial giant in Boston that manages nearly $1 trillion, shuffled its top executives and reorganized its businesses yesterday as part of its effort to move beyond managing mutual funds.</p>
        <p>James C. Curvey, 65, president and chief operating officer, said he would leave both posts, but remain at the company. Mr. Curvey has served for three years as the top executive under Edward C. Johnson III, the chairman and chief executive of Fidelity and son of the company's founder.</p>
        <p>Robert L. Reynolds, 48, will succeed Mr. Curvey as chief operating officer, effective July 3, and will also be a vice chairman. He currently runs Fidelity's institutional retirement plans. In his new role, he will oversee that operation, as well as the brokerage business.</p>
        <p>Robert C. Pozen, 53, president of the FMR Company, the unit that includes Fidelity's vast mutual fund management operations, was also promoted to vice chairman.</p>
        <p>During Mr. Curvey's tenure, Fidelity was transformed from the largest mutual fund manager into a full-service asset management company where investors could trade stocks online or from pagers and hand-held devices, invest in initial public offerings, manage their estates, set up charitable contributions and open retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>In an acknowledgment of the organization's growing complexity, Mr. Curvey said Fidelity would take a more traditional corporate structure and create three operating units overseen by vice chairmen.</p>
        <p>''I turned 65 a couple weeks ago,'' said Mr. Curvey, who is a vice chairman. ''It's time to move some younger people into key management spots. This is important for the company's long-term management planning.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Curvey will return to his previous job running Fidelity Capital and Ventures, which now includes Fidelity's venture capital investments and a host of other interests, including life insurance and telecommunications holdings, as well as the transportation company Boston Coach.</p>
        <p>One thing that the reorganization does not clarify is the question of who will one day succeed Mr. Johnson, who turns 70 this month. Mr. Reynolds and Mr. Pozen will report to Mr. Johnson. The title of president will not be filled.</p>
        <p>''They tipped the title to Reynolds, but not the power,'' said James H. Lowell III, a former employee of Fidelity and editor of a newsletter that tracks Fidelity. ''That's very Fidelity. It's all about competition. I think it's very healthy.''</p>
        <p>A third contender to succeed Mr. Johnson is his eldest daughter, Abigail P. Johnson, 38, a senior vice president who is the largest shareholder of the FMR Corporation, the holding company that owns Fidelity Investments. While some in the industry say she will one day run the company, Fidelity itself did not indicate that possibility yesterday.</p>
        <p>''She'll stay in the same role,'' Mr. Curvey said. ''This organization doesn't change that at all.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
