<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="22CAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DE1131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Green Skyscrapers  An American Space Gallery, 1305 Madison Avenue (near 92nd Street); (212) 426-2879.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of photographs of New York street and park trees from ''Great Trees of New York City: A Guide,'' by Benjamin Swett, opens today and continues through July 22. The trees featured were chosen because of their size, age and rarity, and for the stories that surround them. Open Tuesday through Saturday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. No charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Green Skyscrapers  An American Space Gallery, 1305 Madison Avenue (near 92nd Street); (212) 426-2879.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of photographs of New York street and park trees from ''Great Trees of New York City: A Guide,'' by Benjamin Swett, opens today and continues through July 22. The trees featured were chosen because of their size, age and rarity, and for the stories that surround them. Open Tuesday through Saturday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. No charge.</p>
        <p>Preserving Gardens  Garden Conservancy; (914) 265-2029.</p>
        <p>The Garden Conservancy will offer a tour of the sculpture gardens at PepsiCo in Purchase, N.Y., and a buffet dinner, on Saturday, from 5:30 to 8:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Tickets, to benefit the conservancy, are $135; members, $125. Reservations are required.</p>
        <p>Park Businesses  Arsenal Gallery in Central Park, Third Floor, Fifth Avenue at 64th Street; (212) 360-8163.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of more than 60 historical and contemporary photographs of concessions in New York parks will be shown along with plans, drawings, postcards and models, through Aug. 31. The concessions depicted include restaurants, hot dog stands, beach shops, golf courses,  carousels and oyster bars. Open Monday through Friday, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. No charge.</p>
        <p>Four Views of New York  Museum of the City of New York, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street; (212) 534-1672, ext. 257.</p>
        <p>A guided walking tour of the Wall Street area, on July 13, will be the first of four tours offered in conjunction with ''The New York Century: World Capital, Home Town,'' an exhibition running through Feb. 4.</p>
        <p>The exhibition features photographs, architectural models, political memorabilia, artworks and collected pieces of New York history like a yellow-cab meter, a section of the Times Square news zipper and a costume from the Coney Island Mermaid Parade.</p>
        <p>The walking tour series will focus on four New York neighborhoods that developed in successive 25-year periods since 1900. The Wall Street tour will examine the development of New York as a skyscraper city in the early part of the century. The second tour, on July 27, will be in Harlem, which grew into a center of black culture in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>The last two tours are downtown; a tour on Aug. 10 will look at Greenwich Village as a Bohemian neighborhood beginning in the early 1950's, and the development of SoHo and NoHo in the last 25 years will be the topic of a tour on Aug. 24.</p>
        <p>Reservations are required for each tour, which start at 6:30 p.m. The fee for the series is $55; members, students and those 62 and older, $45; single tours, $15, $12.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
