<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Social Security, That Risky Issue, Is on the Table</title>
    <meta content="Y22SOCI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DF1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Social Security, That Risky Issue, Is on the Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>DES MOINES, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debate over Social Security poses risks for presidential campaigns of Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush; both campaigns have largely avoided discussing any potentially painful measures to ensure system remains solvent as population ages; Bush has focused on rewards of private investment accounts within system, while Gore has called for new retirement benefits inside and outside Social Security; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore stopped here today to talk about Social Security, and used charts and statistics to lead a friendly audience to a predictable conclusion: that his approach to retirement security was more prudent and a better deal than the plan advocated by Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>What may be more surprising, given the issue's long history of political sensitivity, is that Social Security is being debated at all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore stopped here today to talk about Social Security, and used charts and statistics to lead a friendly audience to a predictable conclusion: that his approach to retirement security was more prudent and a better deal than the plan advocated by Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>What may be more surprising, given the issue's long history of political sensitivity, is that Social Security is being debated at all.</p>
        <p>There are risks for both parties. It is still not clear that Mr. Bush's decision to push for private investment accounts within Social Security, the biggest change in the retirement program since its inception, will not blow up in his face, as some Democrats have predicted.</p>
        <p>But it is not clear either that deriding Mr. Bush's plan will help Mr. Gore turn out older voters who could tip the scales in swing states, or that he can avoid seeming out of step with younger voters for whom stock investing is an opportunity rather than a ''risky scheme.''</p>
        <p>The rival presidential campaigns have largely avoided discussing any of the potentially painful measures that might have to be taken to ensure that Social Security remains solvent as the population ages. Mr. Bush has focused instead on the rewards of investing, while Mr. Gore has stressed that the fast-growing federal budget surplus makes it possible to add new retirement benefits inside and outside of Social Security.</p>
        <p>But Social Security is squarely on the agenda for the presidential race, even if the two campaigns have not fully determined the political calculus that surrounds it.</p>
        <p>More than anyone else, it was President Clinton who put the issue on the table by calling two years ago for a national debate on it. His effort did not find any bipartisan common ground, in part because Republicans feared that he was leading them into a trap where any proposals they made would be subject to demagoguery by Democrats. But the debate inspired by his involvement helped educate voters about some of the options, including individual investment accounts. Because of the stock market boom, voters proved more intrigued by the idea than some Democrats had expected.</p>
        <p>Indeed, part of the problem for the campaigns is that voters do not seem to have fully sorted out where they stand. A New York Times poll last month found that 47 percent of voters felt Mr. Gore would do a better job of dealing with Social Security, compared with 39 percent for Mr. Bush. But when asked about private investment accounts, the centerpiece of Mr. Bush's plan, 51 percent said it was a good idea and 45 percent said it was a bad idea.</p>
        <p>The differences of opinion are most marked across generational lines. Among 30-to-44-year-olds, Mr. Bush's personal accounts plan was favored by 66 percent and opposed by 30 percent. Among people 65 and over, 27 percent favored private accounts, and 67 percent thought they were a bad idea.</p>
        <p>Partly in recognition of the appeal of investing to younger people, Mr. Gore rolled out a proposal this week to create savings and investment accounts outside of the Social Security system. The plan calls for the government to match deposits on a sliding scale, with most of the government subsidies going to low- and middle-income people.</p>
        <p>In making the proposal, Mr. Gore sought to reframe the debate as being not over whether investing amounts to casino economics, which he had occasionally seemed to suggest, but over whether it has a place within Social Security, a program built on a guaranteed government benefit unaffected by the ups and downs of Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that Gore's scare-tactic approach played very well,'' said Robert L. Bixby, executive director of the Concord Coalition, a fiscal policy research organization. ''I'm being hopeful here, but maybe the climate has changed enough that you can have a substantive debate on the issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has seemed intent in the last two days on addressing the issue not so much along generational lines as along class lines.</p>
        <p>Republicans see Mr. Bush's Social Security proposal as a way to cement their party's appeal to what they view as an emerging investor class, made up of people across income levels who have grown comfortable making choices about how to handle their money. Mr. Gore, by contrast, is increasingly pitching his proposal at working people struggling to take advantage of the good economy, and is implicitly casting Mr. Bush's approach to Social Security and economic policy as one designed for the wealthy.</p>
        <p>''We have to put an end to the days when savings are a scramble, if not an unaffordable luxury,'' Mr. Gore said before leaving Des Moines for Minnesota and a meeting with Gov. Jesse Ventura, whose popularity with independent voters has led the Gore camp to cultivate him throughout the campaign. ''This is the choice in this election: Are you for working people?'' Mr. Gore asked the crowd of supporters at a carpenters union hall here.</p>
        <p>In another indication of how the wealth amassed by many people in the last decade is upsetting traditional political calculations, Mr. Gore also set out his own plan today for reducing the federal estate tax.</p>
        <p>Democrats had long opposed reductions in the estate tax as a giveaway to the rich. But 65 Democrats joined the Republican majority in the House to pass legislation earlier this month to repeal the tax, and the party has found itself on the defensive over the issue. Democrats, including Mr. Gore, have become increasingly sensitive to pressure from farmers and small-business owners, who say the tax endangers their ability to pass their holdings along to another generation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's plan, which his campaign said would cost $7 billion over 10 years, is similar to a plan backed by House Democratic leaders and would focus its benefits on family farms and small businesses. Rather than repealing the tax entirely, as would the House Republican bill, Mr. Gore's plan would increase the value of a farm or small business that would be exempt from estate taxation. With some minimal estate planning, a married couple running a farm or business could eventually exempt $5 million of their estate under Mr. Gore's plan; such planning currently allows the couple an exemption of $2.6 million.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
