<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; A tough S.E.C. faults money manager over disclosures.</title>
    <meta content="Y22PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Founders Asset Management</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mellon Financial Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borgen, Bjorn Erik</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1D71131F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; A tough S.E.C. faults money manager over disclosures.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Berenson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission suspends and fines Bjorn Erik Borgen, former owner of Founders Asset Management, which manages more than $8 billion, for failing to disclose that some of firm's clients paid excessive commissions on stock trades in early 1990's; Borgen agrees to 180-day suspension from invstment business to settle complaint; will also pay $590,000 fine, representing profits that Founders made on affected clients during that time; Mellon Financial Corp, which bought Founders from Borgen in April 1998, will pay additional $50,000, although SEC does not cite any problems at Founders since Mellon acquired company (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REGULATORS have suspended and fined the former owner of Founders Asset Management, which manages more than $8 billion, for failing to disclose that some of the firm's clients paid excessive commissions on stock trades in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>Bjorn Erik Borgen, the sole owner of Founders during the three-year period in question, agreed to a 180-day suspension from the investment business to settle the complaint by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REGULATORS have suspended and fined the former owner of Founders Asset Management, which manages more than $8 billion, for failing to disclose that some of the firm's clients paid excessive commissions on stock trades in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>Bjorn Erik Borgen, the sole owner of Founders during the three-year period in question, agreed to a 180-day suspension from the investment business to settle the complaint by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borgen will also pay a $590,000 fine, representing the profits that Founders made on the affected clients during that time. The Mellon Financial Corporation, which bought Founders from Mr. Borgen in April 1998, will pay an additional $50,000, although the S.E.C. did not cite any problems at Founders since Mellon acquired the company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borgen, who is now president of the Borgen Investment Group, did not admit or deny any wrongdoing under the settlement, reached last week. A lawyer for Mr. Borgen said he had no comment.</p>
        <p>The fine and suspension add to the recent spate of aggressive enforcement actions from the commission. In the last 10 days, the S.E.C. has taken action against former officers of Cendant, who it said participated in a fraud at what used to be CUC International for more than a dozen years; a nationwide series of microcap fraud rings; and several people who traded on insider information in a Bay Networks acquisition.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. said that Mr. Borgen caused some Founders clients, though not the company's mutual fund clients, to pay excessive brokerage commissions as a way to compensate a broker who had placed the clients with Founders. The clients did not know that they were being overcharged, according to the commission. In addition, the trades were made later than those for other Founders clients, and so were usually done at less favorable prices, the commission said.</p>
        <p>''The focus of this case is on disclosure, and the responsibility of investment advisers to fully disclose their commission policies and their execution policy,'' said Don Hoerl, associate regional director of the S.E.C. office in Denver, which brought the case.</p>
        <p>The commission charged that the excessive commissions were paid to brokerage companies affiliated with William O. Foster, a San Diego broker who persuaded more than 40 of his clients to invest $123 million with Founders. ''Founders did so at Borgen's direction in order to provide Foster with a prearranged amount of brokerage commissions in exchange for Foster referring clients,'' the S.E.C. asserted in its complaint. By failing to disclose the practice, Mr. Borgen violated securities law, the commission said.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Mr. Foster, who simultaneously agreed to a $25,000 fine and 30-day suspension from the industry in a similar S.E.C. case that did not name Founders, said Mr. Foster had no comment.</p>
        <p>A Founders spokeswoman said the company had changed its rules and now treats all its clients fairly. ''In 1995, when these practices came to light, Founders proactively addressed them,'' said the spokeswoman, Bridget Richards. ''This matter did not involve the operations of our mutual funds. It was strictly a small number of small private accounts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
