<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officials Focus on Subway Switch as Cause of Derailment</title>
    <meta content="22DERA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3DD1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officials Focus on Subway Switch as Cause of Derailment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NYC transit officials say that B train that derailed in downtown Brooklyn, injuring 95 passengers, was traveling along route it did not usually take and was crossing back to its own tracks when its third car jumped off rails; say that it could be several weeks before they can determine what caused accidents; state transportation safety investigators and National Transportation Safety Board are focusing on switch south of DeKalb Avenue station; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The B train that derailed Tuesday night in downtown Brooklyn, injuring 95 passengers, was traveling along a route it did not usually take and was crossing back to its own tracks when its third car jumped off the rails, transit officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Officials said it could be several weeks before they determined what caused the accident, which sent passengers flying into the walls of the cars and into each other. But state transportation safety investigators and the National Transportation Safety Board were focusing on a switch south of the DeKalb Avenue station that was supposed to redirect the B train onto a crossover that leads back to its own tracks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The B train that derailed Tuesday night in downtown Brooklyn, injuring 95 passengers, was traveling along a route it did not usually take and was crossing back to its own tracks when its third car jumped off the rails, transit officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Officials said it could be several weeks before they determined what caused the accident, which sent passengers flying into the walls of the cars and into each other. But state transportation safety investigators and the National Transportation Safety Board were focusing on a switch south of the DeKalb Avenue station that was supposed to redirect the B train onto a crossover that leads back to its own tracks.</p>
        <p>Into the early morning hours of Wednesday, transit workers were unsure whether they could -- even with a team of 200 -- hoist the cars back into place and repair the damaged rails in time for the morning rush. But by 5:40 a.m., less than eight hours after the accident, service was back to normal at the station.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that the main theory was that the switch had failed. ''Why that affected the third car on the train and not the first two, I don't know,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In terms of injuries, the derailment was the worst accident in the subway system since 1997, when a train rear-ended another waiting at a red light in a tunnel between two stations in Queens. In that crash, 87 passengers had minor injuries.</p>
        <p>Tuesday's derailment was the third near the same area in the DeKalb Avenue station. The other two, in 1985 and 1996, were caused by problems with tracks that were under construction. But Tuesday's accident appeared to have none of the elements that usually conspire to cause a derailment. The tracks were not being repaired. The eight stainless steel cars that make up the train are among the newest in the system, built from 1986 to 1988. The B train was apparently not going too fast; it was just leaving the station. And the switch that the train was passing over had been refurbished in the mid-1980's and inspected twice in the last four months, transit officials said.</p>
        <p>But when the third car of the train passed over the switch at 9:52 p.m., the front half of the undercarriage failed to turn onto the connection tracks, which curve to the left. The whole car was pulled off the tracks, and the front of the car hit a dividing wall in the tunnel near the tracks. The third car also wrenched the back half of the second car off the tracks.</p>
        <p>Officials said one reason they thought that the train was not traveling too fast was that the accident  caused little damage to the front of the third car, where it smashed into the wall. The force did not even shatter the front window of the car. But it was enough to throw passengers around like dolls, especially in the front cars.</p>
        <p>''The train jerked, and in about two seconds, it jerked again,'' said Ruth Swen, 19, who was heading home from her job as a saleswoman. ''We looked at each other, and then people started flying. I flew. When I opened my eyes, everything was dark.</p>
        <p>''The driver, he came on and said: 'I don't know what is going on. I'm hurt myself. I banged my head. I don't know what is going on.' ''</p>
        <p>Transit officials said only one passenger remained in the hospital yesterday, a man who had suffered a head injury. Tuesday night, two other passengers were admitted to hospitals and listed in serious condition, one with a head injury and another who had a heart ailment and had complained of chest pains. Most of the injuries were bruises and cuts. Other passengers complained of problems related to the intense heat in the tunnel and the station.</p>
        <p>Officials said they did not know how many passengers were aboard the train.</p>
        <p>As is normal after any subway accident, the motorman -- who has been on the job for 23 years -- and the conductor, a 15-year veteran, were required to take drug and alcohol tests. ''I have no reason to suspect we're going to find any indications of that,'' said Lawrence G. Reuter, the president of New York City Transit.</p>
        <p>The motorman and conductor were also interviewed by investigators. Transit officials did not release their names yesterday, and the officials would not comment on the results of the tests or on the interviews.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reuter said investigators began examining the switch and connecting tracks about 4:30 a.m. yesterday, after the 37-ton cars were hoisted back onto the tracks and driven to a Coney Island yard, where they will be dismantled and examined.</p>
        <p>''Right now, we're going through a process of elimination, like we do on every accident,'' Mr. Reuter said. ''We're checking signals. There's no indication there was a signal problem, but all signals are being checked in that location. Power systems are going to be checked. The cars are going to be checked.''</p>
        <p>Mark A. Yanche, the chief of operations for the division that handles track repair, said yesterday that the B train involved in the accident had been rerouted from the B line to the D line at some point before it reached the DeKalb Avenue station because a slow-moving work train was in front of it on the B tracks, moving from one maintenance yard to another.</p>
        <p>Normally, the B bypasses DeKalb Avenue and makes its first Brooklyn stop at Pacific Street. But because the B train involved in the accident was passing through the DeKalb station, it stopped so passengers could get on and off. When the train pulled out, it headed toward the switch to take it to its connection to return to its usual tracks.</p>
        <p>Robert Slovak, a spokesman for the transit agency, said the switch and connection were often used to reroute trains from the B and from the nearby N tracks onto the D tracks to avoid congestion or repairs.</p>
        <p>But transit officials were unable to say yesterday whether the B train that derailed was the first to pass over the switch that night, or whether other trains had successfully made the crossover.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, the switch and connecting tracks were back in use yesterday. ''The switch right now is not a problem,'' Mr. Reuter said. ''Whether it was a problem last night, we'll have to tell you.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
