<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="22MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6DD1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: LAZIO'S TAX RETURNS -- Calling reports of Representative Rick A. Lazio's stock profits ''deeply troubling,'' the chairwoman of the New York State Democratic Committee, Judith Hope, challenged the Republican Senate candidate yesterday to release his income tax returns. The New York Times reported on Friday that Mr. Lazio had made a 600 percent profit on stock he bought in 1997 in Quick &amp; Reilly, a brokerage controlled by some of his campaign contributors. A spokesman said Mr. Lazio would release his returns ''as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>Eric Lipton (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: GRAVANO ALLEGATION -- Salvatore Gravano, left, the Mafia turncoat who testified against John J. Gotti, plotted to kill Ronald L. Kuby, a lawyer who represents the survivors of some of Mr. Gravano's murder victims, according to court papers. Mr. Gravano, whose ferocity earned him the nickname Sammy the Bull and who left New York under the cloak of the federal witness protection program to start a new life, was arrested in Arizona in February on charges that he was running a multimillion-dollar drug ring.</p>
        <p>William K. Rashbaum (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: LAZIO'S TAX RETURNS -- Calling reports of Representative Rick A. Lazio's stock profits ''deeply troubling,'' the chairwoman of the New York State Democratic Committee, Judith Hope, challenged the Republican Senate candidate yesterday to release his income tax returns. The New York Times reported on Friday that Mr. Lazio had made a 600 percent profit on stock he bought in 1997 in Quick &amp; Reilly, a brokerage controlled by some of his campaign contributors. A spokesman said Mr. Lazio would release his returns ''as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>Eric Lipton (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: GRAVANO ALLEGATION -- Salvatore Gravano, left, the Mafia turncoat who testified against John J. Gotti, plotted to kill Ronald L. Kuby, a lawyer who represents the survivors of some of Mr. Gravano's murder victims, according to court papers. Mr. Gravano, whose ferocity earned him the nickname Sammy the Bull and who left New York under the cloak of the federal witness protection program to start a new life, was arrested in Arizona in February on charges that he was running a multimillion-dollar drug ring.</p>
        <p>William K. Rashbaum (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: STEALING FROM THE DEAD -- Two attendants from the city morgue were arrested yesterday on charges that they pilfered sunglasses, a small cassette player, a flashlight, a fanny pack and $3 from the Sheepshead Bay apartment of a dead man they were to transport, the police said. The two men tried to hide the items in the mortuary bag with the body. A police officer guarding the dead man's residence said he saw Edward Rodriguez, 40, and Ruben Barrios, 50, both of Brooklyn, steal the items.</p>
        <p>William K. Rashbaum (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ORGAN DONATIONS -- To expand the availability of organs for transplants, the New York State Department of Health and the Department of Motor Vehicles have begun a computer registry of state residents who wish to be donors after death. Under state law, if no such instruction has been left, family permission is required for a dead person's organs and tissues to be used. Often, family members refuse because they do not know their relative's wishes.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Steinhauer (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: MUSEUM STRIKE -- With the union representing its administrative workers still on strike after six weeks, the Museum of Modern Art yesterday put into effect its latest contract offer for employees who have returned to work. Nearly half of the 250 workers in the bargaining unit have crossed the picket line, and yesterday's move gives them an immediate 3 percent raise and more generous retirement-plan contributions. Museum officials said it was unfair for those who returned to work to be left without a raise since November 1998.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>AMITYVILLE: PARTNER BENEFITS -- Maxine S. Postal, a Suffolk county legislator, plans to introduce a resolution on Tuesday seeking health benefits for domestic partners of Suffolk county workers. Ms. Postal, a Democrat of Amityville, said that the resolution, although nonbinding, would indicate that the county executive and the county's unions could negotiate similar benefits during collective bargaining. Last week, such a bill was voted down.</p>
        <p>Stacy Albin (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: DAMAGED APPLE CROP -- Hudson Valley apple growers say they will need federal aid because hailstorms on May 18 and June 2 damaged an estimated two million bushels of apples. Apples are the fourth most valuable crop in the state, generating $138 million in 1999. Loss estimates for the mid-Hudson alone run as high as $10 million. On Monday, Agriculture Commissioner Nathan L. Rudgers toured apple orchards to view the damage and heard from growers, some of whom said their economic survival was at stake.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: WENDY'S KILLINGS -- Two men who the police say supplied the gun used in the killing of five Wendy's restaurant workers last month have been arrested, the United States attorney's office for the Eastern District of New York announced yesterday. The handgun was found in a belt pack on John B. Taylor, left, one of two men charged in the killings. Prosecutors said that Bernard Gardier, 23, of Cleveland, had stolen the legally purchased weapon from his girlfriend and that Jamal Gales, 27, of Berea, Ohio, arranged its sale for $250 to an unnamed person in Nassau County.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>CAMDEN: RABBI MURDER CASE -- A rabbi charged with hiring two men to kill his wife in 1994 must await his trial in jail. Judge Linda G. Rosenzweig of Superior Court revoked the bail of Rabbi Fred J. Neulander yesterday, ruling that because Mr. Neulander now faced the death penalty, he would be more likely to flee. A grand jury returned a capital murder indictment against Mr. Neulander on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: EMISSION TESTS IN DOUBT -- State officials said they might drop or delay part of the state automobile inspections scheduled to begin on July 1. One problem, they said, is that the so-called tank pressure test, which would discover leaks in a car's exhaust system not detected by tailpipe testing, could increase the waiting time for drivers. Waits of several hours because of problems with the new tailpipe emissions test angered motorists soon after the new system went into effect in December, resulting in the test's suspension.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>BRIDGEPORT: DRUG RING SENTENCES -- Three people convicted of being part of Russell Peeler Jr.'s drug ring were sentenced to federal prison on Tuesday, the same day that Mr. Peeler escaped the death penalty for a double murder. Angelina Keene, 24, of Bridgeport, who has three children with Mr. Peeler and was accused of running the drug operation when he was away, received a three-year sentence in United States District Court. Cory King, 22, and Shawn Kennedy, 24, each received 10 years. Mr. Peeler will be sentenced to life because jurors in his case could not reach a unanimous decision on the death penalty.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
