<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Side Gets to Strut In Chicago</title>
    <meta content="22BERK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDC1E31F931A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Side Gets to Strut In Chicago</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column discusses success of Chicago White Sox so far this season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DISPENSING with Western Union, Al Capone sent a message to Bugs Moran. It was delivered on Valentine's Day 1929, from Mr. Capone's South Side headquarters in Chicago to his chief gangland rival in the city, Mr. Moran, on the North Side. The word ''dispatch'' was obviously taken in a literal sense by the South Siders, who lined up seven of Mr. Moran's operatives in a garage on North Clark Street and then riddled them with 90 bullets from submachine guns, shotguns and revolvers.</p>
        <p>This comes to mind because the South Side of Chicago is again in the news, as the White Sox -- whose home base, Comiskey Park, is just a handful of fungo hits from Big Al's old headquarters -- are wiping out the opposition, though, in a bloodless manner. The White Sox are the hottest team in baseball, with the best record, and play host to the Yankees this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DISPENSING with Western Union, Al Capone sent a message to Bugs Moran. It was delivered on Valentine's Day 1929, from Mr. Capone's South Side headquarters in Chicago to his chief gangland rival in the city, Mr. Moran, on the North Side. The word ''dispatch'' was obviously taken in a literal sense by the South Siders, who lined up seven of Mr. Moran's operatives in a garage on North Clark Street and then riddled them with 90 bullets from submachine guns, shotguns and revolvers.</p>
        <p>This comes to mind because the South Side of Chicago is again in the news, as the White Sox -- whose home base, Comiskey Park, is just a handful of fungo hits from Big Al's old headquarters -- are wiping out the opposition, though, in a bloodless manner. The White Sox are the hottest team in baseball, with the best record, and play host to the Yankees this weekend.</p>
        <p>On the other side of town, meanwhile, the Cubs continue in their bewildered ways, finding that their struggle to reach .500 is as daunting as Hercules cleaning the Augean stables, or at least trying to find a public toilet in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Yet comparisons appear inevitable between the White Sox and their century-old rival, the North Side Cubs. Fandom in Chicago has traditionally been bitterly and passionately divided -- the way it was with Dodger and Giant fans in New York. I grew up on the West Side of Chicago, which might have been thought a middle ground, but this particular pocket of Lawndale was very much tendentiously Cub. Everyone there knew who the White Sox fan living in our midst was -- and Mr. Rosenfeld was rarely seen on the street after dark. In contrast: the sister of the fine Chicago sportswriter, Bill Gleason, from a South Side home, once accepted a free ticket to a Cubs game in Wrigley Field. The Gleasons' father told her: ''It's worse than if you left the church.''</p>
        <p>It has been said that the Cubs, on the leafy North Side, are quiche and white wine, while the Sox, in the often less swanky districts, are kielbasa and draft beer. Not completely. I am aware of Sox fans who own yachts in Belmont Harbor, and Cub fans who work outdoors for the Department of Streets and Sanitation.</p>
        <p>Even after last night's 8-6 loss to Cleveland, the Sox had won 14 of their last 17 games. Their record stood at 45-26, for a .634 winning percentage, and they were six-and-a-half games ahead of the Indians, the team they have been chasing for the last five seasons without success, as the Indians captured the American League Central Division each time.</p>
        <p>And before losing Tuesday night to Cleveland, 4-1, the Sox had won eight straight games -- in remarkable fashion. They went to Cleveland and swept three games, then moved on to Yankee Stadium where they embarrassed the defending champs in a four-game sweep. Back in Comiskey Park on Monday, they whipped Cleveland again.</p>
        <p>The spectacular, and unexpected, doesn't stop there. It is virtually axiomatic in baseball that the teams that spend a lot of money on players win the bulk of the games. The Yankees, for example, the team with the highest payroll -- $92.5 million this year -- won the World Series last season. Seven of the highest-payroll teams were among the eight in the playoffs last season.</p>
        <p>But the White Sox, with a payroll of $31 million, stand 26th out of the 30 teams in the major leagues in cash doled to their on-field laborers. The White Sox have some brilliant young players, made some trades that -- heavily criticized at first -- proved a boon, have a few veterans like Frank Thomas who have rediscovered themselves, and a bespectacled, level-headed manager, Jerry Manuel.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the first day of their current homestand, and playing Cleveland, the White Sox drew a near sellout crowd of 43,062. This from a team that had been averaging about 21,000 a game. It helped, obviously, that it was ''Family Half-Price Night,'' all tickets selling for 50 percent of face value. The next night, at full fare, 20,000 fans showed up for the Indians' game, leaving half the park empty. The Cubs are again playing to crowds of 33,000 a game, close to capacity, with few promotions. Fact is, the attraction is purely Wrigley Field, that ivy-dripping jewel nestled in a gentrified precinct. The Sox play in a charmless new stadium located in an industrial setting. They remain one of the poorest drawing teams in baseball. The belief here is, if players changed ballparks and beanies, attendance would remain the same.</p>
        <p>But now if fans in Chicago want something more thrilling than to just watch ivy grow, Capone's old 'hood has become the place to be.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
