<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Adviser Said to Favor Financial Monitor for Nassau</title>
    <meta content="09NASS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zarb, Frank G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1D91038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Adviser Said to Favor Financial Monitor for Nassau</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank G Zarb, special adviser asked by New York Governor George E Pataki to study Nassau County's budget woes, is expected to call for some sort of outside monitor to oversee county's finances when he announces his findings on May 9; Zarb's analysis reportedly found that county's 2000 budget would come up $178.4 million short and warns that without further cuts or revenues, county's deficit would balloon to $233 million next year and to about $321 million in 2003 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The special adviser asked by Gov. George E. Pataki to study Nassau County's budget woes is expected to call for some sort of outside monitor to oversee the county's finances when he announces his findings on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The report by the adviser, Frank G. Zarb, who is chairman of the group that runs the Nasdaq stock market, has been eagerly awaited here by feuding county officials, who have hoped that he would step in like a deus ex machina to help Nassau overcome its political squabbling and its fiscal crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The special adviser asked by Gov. George E. Pataki to study Nassau County's budget woes is expected to call for some sort of outside monitor to oversee the county's finances when he announces his findings on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The report by the adviser, Frank G. Zarb, who is chairman of the group that runs the Nasdaq stock market, has been eagerly awaited here by feuding county officials, who have hoped that he would step in like a deus ex machina to help Nassau overcome its political squabbling and its fiscal crisis.</p>
        <p>It was still unclear tonight just how much power would be given to any outside monitor. But one plan  considered by Mr. Zarb in recent days called for the creation of a financing authority that would sell bonds using the county's sales tax as collateral, two associates said. In exchange, they said, the financing authority would be given some power to monitor the county's finances.</p>
        <p>The details of Mr. Zarb's report were a closely guarded secret today. The governor's office announced only that Mr. Pataki would visit the county with Mr. Zarb on Tuesday, and that the two men would announce their plan at noon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zarb's analysis has found that Nassau County's 2000 budget would come up $178.4 million short, and warned that without further cuts or new revenues, the county's deficit would balloon to $233 million next year and to about $321 million in 2003.</p>
        <p>The problem has grown critical: the county's bond rating is hovering just above junk status, and credit rating agencies have given Nassau until June 30 to come up with a workable plan to reduce its deficit or to risk a downgrade to junk status.</p>
        <p>Last week the county postponed a $254 million bond sale, saying it would wait until after the Zarb report was released, in the hope that the findings would reassure investors.</p>
        <p>County Democrats have long favored some form of fiscal oversight. This year the Democratic-controlled State Assembly passed a bill calling for creation of an oversight board with the power to approve the county budgets, while still leaving a great deal of autonomy for local officials.</p>
        <p>Until last Friday, Republicans in the County Legislature and the Republican county executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, had resisted calls for fiscal oversight. In the fall, after the Democrats won control of the Legislature for the first time in decades, both Mr. Gulotta and Republicans in the Legislature ridiculed their calls for an oversight board.</p>
        <p>Then, on Friday, everything changed. The nine Republicans in the legislature sent Mr. Zarb a letter saying that ''outside oversight, with the teeth necessary to make substantial cuts in spending, must be imposed by New York State.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta sent his own letter to Mr. Zarb asking for ''state intervention that will ensure maximum local governance while providing the mechanism to ensure that the necessary measures will be enacted to eliminate the shortfall, protect our taxpayers, and restore the confidence of our residents in our county's fiscal integrity.''</p>
        <p>Democrats made fun of the reversals of position and accused the Republicans of finding religion late and waging a pre-emptive strike to lessen the sting of an oversight board. Republicans denied any knowledge of what was contained in the Zarb report and said that the time had simply come for them to act.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
