<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Fetal Tests Weigh Heavy on Prospective Parents</title>
    <meta content="09AMNI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amniocentesis</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rapp, Rayna (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Amniocentesis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amniocentesis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DA1338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Fetal Tests Weigh Heavy on Prospective Parents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edited transcripts of interviews conducted by Prof Rayna Rapp with pregnant women who have used amniocentesis over last 10 years to test fetus for birth defects; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 1960's, researchers began diagnosing hereditary disorders by examining the amniotic fluid surrounding the fetuses carried by pregnant women considered at high risk.</p>
        <p>By the 1970's, amniocentesis had become available to women of advanced maternal age. Now, amniocentesis is routine. In testing, about three tablespoons of amniotic fluid with discarded fetal cells are withdrawn from the uterus, cultured in the lab and inspected for abnormalities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the 1960's, researchers began diagnosing hereditary disorders by examining the amniotic fluid surrounding the fetuses carried by pregnant women considered at high risk.</p>
        <p>By the 1970's, amniocentesis had become available to women of advanced maternal age. Now, amniocentesis is routine. In testing, about three tablespoons of amniotic fluid with discarded fetal cells are withdrawn from the uterus, cultured in the lab and inspected for abnormalities.</p>
        <p>Most often amniocentesis gives assurance. About 97 percent of those having tests find their fetus does not carry any of the disabilities for which the test is done.</p>
        <p>In other cases, the tests have left prospective parents with difficult decisions that generations before never faced. Following are edited transcripts of interviews with women who used the test over the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>They were interviewed for ''Testing Women, Testing the Fetus: The Social Impact of Amniocentesis in America'' (Routledge, 1999), by Dr. Rayna Rapp, a professor of anthropology at the New School for Social Research.</p>
        <p>A PSYCHOLOGIST, 34 -- When I received that phone call, everything slowed down. I don't get hysterical, I get methodical under stress. I didn't flip out until I found myself in the car, going to pick up my husband, sobbing on the highway. We found out that our fetus had spina bifida [a neural tube defect caused by an opening in the spine with mild to severe effects]. It showed up in the amniotic fluid.</p>
        <p>I interviewed everyone I could find: parents, teachers, doctors and nurses who dealt with spina bifida kids. I wanted to know what life with a little spina bifida child was like. They were very upbeat. One nurse made it clear it would be a full-time job, not easy, but very rewarding, that this child would accomplish a lot. But the work those families were doing, well, it was overwhelming.</p>
        <p>Later, when we could see the hole in his spine, that did me in. That's when we chose to end the pregnancy. The consequences?  Well, we pulled apart, we had to work back together again.</p>
        <p>AN EDUCATIONAL ADMINISTRATOR, 43 -- We're always called to crossroads, they aren't things we seek, they're situations that befall us. When I found out my baby had Down syndrome, I had to rely on my daughter, on my mother and my sisters. They saw me through the abortion.</p>
        <p>Whatever befalls you, you go on. I'm grateful for the test. I'm still grieving, but it's better this way.</p>
        <p>A LEGAL SECRETARY, 37 -- I'm not sorry I had the amnio. I don't believe in abortion; I'm too religious for that. But the test helped me get my head wrapped around it, that I was having a baby with Down syndrome.  When my doctor told me the news, he wanted me to have an abortion. But I didn't want that.</p>
        <p>I did some research; I visited this group home for adult retarded people. It was nice.  They looked happy, they had jobs, they went bowling. It really made me think. Stevie's growing up real nice. Just being with a child like that makes people think. I believe Stevie was put on earth for some reason: it's not ours to know. I go along from day to day, marveling at what Stevie accomplishes.</p>
        <p>As long as he's home with me, I don't think he's slow. Now he's counting to 10, pretty soon, he's bound to be potty-trained. Then once in a while, I'll take him somewhere with other kids and I really get slapped in the face. It's different when you have a different kind of child.</p>
        <p>A LAWYER, 42 -- At my age I'd be foolish -- I think anyone would be foolish -- not to have an amnio. Some problems can be avoided, and I'm glad to know my baby is healthy.  Plus we now know it's a girl. I'm just thrilled!</p>
        <p>A WAITRESS, 31 -- Among my cousins, there's a lot of slow children. Some go to special schools. The family doesn't like to talk about it. So you can imagine, I was scared when I came up pregnant. But they told me about this needle test. I took it; it didn't hurt. I was just a little nervous waiting. And in the end, the news was so good.</p>
        <p>A GENETICS COUNSELOR, 36 -- So now we know it's a second girl. Oh, Frank and I are very pleased, but we aren't going to tell our parents: they can find out after the birth.  Now, all they need to know is that the baby is healthy.</p>
        <p>A HOUSE CLEANER, 41 -- When they told me what the baby would suffer [an inevitably fatal condition], I decided to abort. But it was Easter, so I couldn't do it, until after.</p>
        <p>A COLLEGE PROFESSOR, 37 -- They called it ''an error in cell division.'' It feels like the cells could have a car crash, and produce this wreckage, and that's the extra chromosome, that's Down syndrome. And we both knew exactly what we were going to do. I felt like a minor figure in a major tragedy.</p>
        <p>After my abortion, I understood adoption much better. Because it can't be predicted how your child will be from getting your genes. And you don't need your kids to be genetic copies; they might be unlike you anyway. For some, I know it's guilt. For me, it was astonishment. And overwhelming grief. I feel like I fell off the edge of this earth. I've been falling through space so long I don't remember which end is up. Who could possibly understand this?</p>
        <p>A WAITRESS, 19 -- My sister, she can't walk [because of spina bifida], she can't see. When I got pregnant the first time, I was very young, 15 -- 16 when I had my baby. I talked with my mother: she really wanted me to have the tests. I wanted it too; she had such a cross to bear. Oh, we love my sister, it's just that God made her special.</p>
        <p>I was only concerned if my own baby couldn't walk or talk. The test wasn't hard, I wasn't worried, I just didn't want my baby to be like my sister. We're against abortion, so maybe I would have carried that cross, like my mother did. But then again, it's a case where I think I would have had an abortion.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, my baby didn't have what my sister had, but they found something else, my son has an extra sex chromosome: they said he'd be sterile, he might be slow. There's no reason to abort for that. As it turns out, my son looks normal, he acts normal, he's learning real well in school.</p>
        <p>A NURSE'S AIDE, 47 -- My doctor was so angry with me: he couldn't believe I wouldn't take the test when he wanted me to. ''How could you let this happen?'' he yelled at me, when my baby was born with Down syndrome. ''You're 40!'' But I think something else: even though he's mentally retarded, he could be a good person. It's just like finding out you have a new job. You just do it, and you accept it, that's all there is to it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
