<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Handel Rarity in Energetic Hands</title>
    <meta content="09FLOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arts Florissants (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Handel, George Frederick (1685-1759)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christie, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2D91338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Handel Rarity in Energetic Hands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews performance by Les Arts Florissants of Handel's dramatic oratorio Theodora, led by William Christie (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For anyone with a passion for Baroque music played on period instruments -- and particularly for the era's stage works -- William Christie's appearances with Les Arts Florissants are highlights of the concert season. Naturally the performances awaited most eagerly are the sumptuously staged operas that Mr. Christie and company have presented in France, where the group is based. But the audience for Mr. Christie's work tends to value music making above scenery, so when he presents dramatic works in concert -- as he did on Saturday evening, when he brought Handel's ''Theodora'' to the Brooklyn Academy of Music -- there is never much cause for complaint.</p>
        <p>In the case of ''Theodora,'' the second to last of Handel's dramatic oratorios (''Jephtha'' was his last), staging is more a luxury than a requirement. Mr. Christie presumably has nothing against staging it; he conducted a production at Glyndebourne four years ago. But on Saturday evening, the presentation seemed refreshingly clean and uncluttered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For anyone with a passion for Baroque music played on period instruments -- and particularly for the era's stage works -- William Christie's appearances with Les Arts Florissants are highlights of the concert season. Naturally the performances awaited most eagerly are the sumptuously staged operas that Mr. Christie and company have presented in France, where the group is based. But the audience for Mr. Christie's work tends to value music making above scenery, so when he presents dramatic works in concert -- as he did on Saturday evening, when he brought Handel's ''Theodora'' to the Brooklyn Academy of Music -- there is never much cause for complaint.</p>
        <p>In the case of ''Theodora,'' the second to last of Handel's dramatic oratorios (''Jephtha'' was his last), staging is more a luxury than a requirement. Mr. Christie presumably has nothing against staging it; he conducted a production at Glyndebourne four years ago. But on Saturday evening, the presentation seemed refreshingly clean and uncluttered.</p>
        <p>A rarity in performance despite Handel's having called it his favorite oratorio, ''Theodora'' has a libretto by Thomas Morell, based on ''The Martyrdom of Theodora and Didymus,'' Robert Boyle's 1687 novel about the tensions between the Christians and Romans in third-century Antioch. Valens, the Roman governor, has declared a feast and sacrifices to Jove in honor of the Emperor Diocletian's birthday, and is unwilling to tolerate the Christians' refusal to take part.</p>
        <p>Theodora, a young woman known for her virtue, is seized and told that she is to become a prostitute for the Roman army. But Didymus, a Roman soldier who has become a Christian (and is in love with Theodora), saves her by giving her his uniform and setting her free.</p>
        <p>Didymus is to be executed for this, and when Theodora comes out of hiding in the hope of getting Didymus released, Valens sentences them both to death. This is hardly the cheeriest of endings, but Handel made the most of it: in an exquisite final duet, Theodora and Didymus look forward to the world to come, and Irene, the leader of the Christians, leads a sublime devotional chorus, ''Oh Love Divine.''</p>
        <p>Handel's characterizations are masterly: Theodora's religious fervor, for example, is painted not as zeal but as an inner serenity that comes to life in a beautifully flowing vocal line. Didymus's music is similar, but with more of an edge. He is, after all, a loyal Roman soldier whose worldly duties are in conflict with his beliefs. Septimius, Didymus's superior, is also painted in gentle vocal colors: Handel gives him stern but regretful music as he arrests Theodora, an act redeemed by his encouraging Didymus's rescue plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christie's cast was equal to the score's demands, both in terms of characterization and sheer technique. As Theodora, Sophie Daneman sang with a gorgeously velvety soprano and a vibrato that was expressive and fully controlled. She fully captured her character's inner glow. Daniel Taylor, the countertenor who sang Didymus, has a clear, powerful voice and at his best -- in the ''Streams of Pleasure Ever Flowing'' duet, for example -- he matched the smooth texture of Ms. Daneman's voice uncannily.</p>
        <p>The singers in the supporting roles were nearly as strong. Juliette Galstian's dark-hued soprano sounded right for Irene. Richard Croft, a tenor, was a warm, sympathetic Septimius. And Nathan Berg, a bass-baritone, brought a touch of malevolent animation to Valens, the one cardboard role in the work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christie led his forces with the energy, clarity of gesture and sense of dramatic shape that have become his trademark.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
