<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President Vladimir Putin</title>
    <meta content="09TUE1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorbachev, Mikhail S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DE1038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President Vladimir Putin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial, commenting on inauguration of Vladimir Putin as Russia's new president, says Russians can rejoice in freedoms they have developed since Mikhail Gorbachev loosened straitjacket of Communism and Boris Yeltsin set country on course toward democracy and free markets; says Putin has chance to consolidate democracy and that what he does will determine whether Russia is able to escape its grim history (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Presidential authority in Russia passed from Boris Yeltsin to Vladimir Putin last New Year's Eve when Mr. Yeltsin resigned, but the symbolism of Mr. Putin's inauguration on Sunday was still lustrous. It completed the first transfer of power from one freely elected leader to another in more than 1,000 years of Russian history. After the ceremony, the energetic new president and his aging predecessor stepped into the bright sunshine of Cathedral Square, the very place where generations of czars appeared after being crowned in the Cathedral of the Assumption. Little more than a decade ago, the idea of a democratically chosen president occupying that ground would have seemed unimaginable.</p>
        <p>As Russians wait for Mr. Putin to make his intentions clear, they should rejoice in the freedoms that have developed since Mikhail Gorbachev first loosened the straitjacket of Communism and Mr. Yeltsin set Russia on a course toward democracy and free markets. For all the severe economic and political dislocations of the last 15 years, Russians today enjoy liberties, including open presidential elections and a largely free press, that their ancestors never attained. Any accounting of the period since the end of the cold war must begin with the recognition of this singular transformation -- something that Americans should bear in mind in a campaign year when there is likely to be a boisterous debate about how to handle Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Presidential authority in Russia passed from Boris Yeltsin to Vladimir Putin last New Year's Eve when Mr. Yeltsin resigned, but the symbolism of Mr. Putin's inauguration on Sunday was still lustrous. It completed the first transfer of power from one freely elected leader to another in more than 1,000 years of Russian history. After the ceremony, the energetic new president and his aging predecessor stepped into the bright sunshine of Cathedral Square, the very place where generations of czars appeared after being crowned in the Cathedral of the Assumption. Little more than a decade ago, the idea of a democratically chosen president occupying that ground would have seemed unimaginable.</p>
        <p>As Russians wait for Mr. Putin to make his intentions clear, they should rejoice in the freedoms that have developed since Mikhail Gorbachev first loosened the straitjacket of Communism and Mr. Yeltsin set Russia on a course toward democracy and free markets. For all the severe economic and political dislocations of the last 15 years, Russians today enjoy liberties, including open presidential elections and a largely free press, that their ancestors never attained. Any accounting of the period since the end of the cold war must begin with the recognition of this singular transformation -- something that Americans should bear in mind in a campaign year when there is likely to be a boisterous debate about how to handle Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin now has the chance to consolidate democracy in his country. Working with the moderate Parliament that Russians elected in December, he has an opportunity to stabilize the economy, to reform a dysfunctional tax code, to crack down on crime and to build a steady relationship with the United States and other Western nations. After the stifling decades of Communism and the erratic years of Mr. Yeltsin's rule, Russians yearn for a period of sustained tranquillity and prosperity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin, who spent most of his career working for the K.G.B. and its successor security organization, may be tempted to exercise the near-dictatorial powers that come with the Russian presidency. Russia needs constant, effective leadership, not a modern variation of authoritarian command. Mr. Putin's promise to rebuild a strong central government should not become an excuse for drawing all power back into the hands of the state.</p>
        <p>His initial moves reveal little about his governing strategy. Mr. Putin's choice for prime minister, Mikhail Kasyanov, suggests a desire to press ahead with economic reform and to reduce the corruption that distorts Russian commerce. Mr. Kasyanov, 42, is a financial expert with reformist instincts, but most of his work has involved dealing with the West to reschedule Moscow's debts, not wrestling with the deformities of the Russian economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's regard for police and military power is troubling. His leap from political obscurity to the presidency was accomplished primarily by directing a brutish military offensive against Chechen guerrillas and civilians. If he applies the same approach to other restless nationalities or uses excessive force in combating crime, he will undermine democracy.</p>
        <p>As for foreign policy, Mr. Putin seems to want a wary friendship with Washington and its allies, in part to attract Western loans and investment. He has encouraged a new round of arms reductions talks with the United States and reactivated Moscow's relations with NATO, which were curtailed during the war in Kosovo. But Mr. Putin has made clear he will plot an independent course designed to maintain Russia's role as a great power. The Kremlin is now his to command. What he does will help determine whether Russia is able to escape its grim history.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
