<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and McCain to Talk And Audience Is Eager</title>
    <meta content="Y09MCC$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ARIZONA SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0D91038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and McCain to Talk And Audience Is Eager</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political observers and analysts eagerly anticipate May 8 fence-mending meeting between Gov George W Bush and Sen John McCain, first since Bush trounced McCain in primaries on March 7; expectation is that McCain will make endorsement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Will they embrace as friends or briskly shake hands as embittered adversaries? Will the cameras record smiles of warmth, or ice? Will the loser deliver a qualified pledge of support for the winner, offer more lavish words of praise or perhaps utter the e-word?</p>
        <p>If politics is often about appearances, the eagerly anticipated meeting here on Tuesday between Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Senator John McCain of Arizona is being scrutinized by political observers and reporters as closely as Egyptologists might pore over hieroglyphics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Will they embrace as friends or briskly shake hands as embittered adversaries? Will the cameras record smiles of warmth, or ice? Will the loser deliver a qualified pledge of support for the winner, offer more lavish words of praise or perhaps utter the e-word?</p>
        <p>If politics is often about appearances, the eagerly anticipated meeting here on Tuesday between Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Senator John McCain of Arizona is being scrutinized by political observers and reporters as closely as Egyptologists might pore over hieroglyphics.</p>
        <p>In their first meeting since Mr. Bush trounced Mr. McCain in the primaries on March 7, the governor and senator are getting together at Mr. Bush's invitation for private fence-mending, public picture-taking and the expectation in the Bush camp that Mr. McCain would eventually make some kind of endorsement.</p>
        <p>That announcement could come after the meeting, aides to Mr. McCain said today.</p>
        <p>''It may or may not happen,'' John Weaver, McCain's political director, said. ''No decision formally has been made; that's the point of the meeting.''</p>
        <p>So obsessed is the political world  with how the two men get along and so starved is the national press corps for substantive campaign news that the event has taken on the proportions of a miniature summit or, a ''monster unity meeting,'' as Sam Donaldson labeled it on the Sunday morning talk show of which he is a co-host.</p>
        <p>By a Bush campaign estimate, 120 journalists had inquired about attending the news conference. Analysts have talked like color commentators about watching Mr. McCain's body language.</p>
        <p>''It's a test of leadership for Bush,'' said Tom Hannon, who oversees coverage of politics for CNN. ''In that sense, it's a purely political story; it has much to do with Bush's facility for handling it and how he handles the whole nomination process.''</p>
        <p>It is also, of course, a reflection of Mr. McCain's durable stardom, of how his moods, inclinations and peeves still carry remarkable weight. (Just last month, NBC News and a bevy of heavy-duty political writers were off with him to Vietnam.)</p>
        <p>''Politics is about ideas and strategy and tactics, but it is also about personality,'' said Mark Halperin, the political director of ABC News. ''It's extraordinary for a vanquished primary candidate to have this much perceived influence.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. McCain showed up at Waldenbooks in a shopping mall in suburban Pittsburgh today, the reporters and camera crews were so thick that it felt as if he were back in Nashua or Concord in the days before the New Hampshire primary.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's performance at the signing of copies of his autobiography showed how much he still enjoyed the attention. At a news conference, the senator dropped hints that he might yet endorse Mr. Bush on Tuesday: when asked if that was a possibility, Mr. McCain said, ''Sure.''</p>
        <p>''Endorse'' is the word Mr. Bush dearly wants Mr. McCain to utter when they emerge from their morning meeting at the William Penn Hotel here.</p>
        <p>And as if to keep Mr. Bush in suspense, Mr. McCain was quoted in The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette this morning as ruling out an endorsement for the time being. He told the paper that he wanted a clearer understanding of the governor's claim to be ''a reformer with results.''</p>
        <p>''That's his slogan,'' Mr. McCain said. ''I'd like to know what those are and how I can be helpful in achieving a reform agenda.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of Mr. McCain said the senator would almost certainly endorse Mr. Bush, if not today, sometime soon.</p>
        <p>Representative Lindsey Graham, a South Carolina Republican and confidant of Mr. McCain, said the two staffs should be able to meet after Tuesday's meeting and ''hone a common reform agenda'' on issues the candidates agree on like the patient's bill of rights and tort reform.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. McCain's signature issue, campaign finance reform, ''that may be the one where we agree to disagree,'' Mr. Graham added.</p>
        <p>But first, hurt feelings must be purged. In fact, in discussing the mending of the wounded egos on both sides -- Mr. McCain is still smarting over the governor's attack ads and Mr. Bush is said to remain miffed at the senator's resistance to come in from the cold -- Mr. Graham sounded more like a radio psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>''Tuesday is vitally important for the human interaction,'' Mr. Graham said. ''Some time alone, away from spin doctors and political operatives, some time to sit down and look at each other and say the things that human beings can say will do more than anything else to heal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seemed to acknowledge the need for catharsis. Speaking to reporters at La Guardia Airport in New York before attending the funeral of Cardinal John J. O'Connor, the governor said that he was ''looking forward'' to talking to Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>''I think that whether we have an endorsement tomorrow or not is really not what's important,'' he said. ''What's important is to sit down and visit. He has said over and over that he will support me as the nominee of the Republican Party. I take him for his word.''</p>
        <p>Reporters also said they will be looking for subtle signals of how the two men, who early in the primary campaign went out of their way to praise each other and profess their strong friendship, comport themselves after their meeting.</p>
        <p>''Probably the most important thing will be body language and tone,'' said Mr. Halperin said. ''All eyes and camera lenses will be on the question of, does McCain act as if George Bush is his leader, or does he act like the independent maverick, unhappy with the way things have turned out?''</p>
        <p>It is far from customary for a vanquished contender for president to withhold formal support for this long. This year, for instance, former Senator Bill Bradley endorsed Vice President Al Gore within 48 hours of losing every state on March 7.</p>
        <p>The Democrats said they are getting a kick out of the hoops that Mr. Bush appeared to be going through to win over Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>''It's part of the Bob Jones University Redemption Tour,'' said Joe Andrew, chairman of the Democratic National Committee, referring to Mr. Bush's efforts to distance himself from the Christian conservatives he wooed during the primaries. Mr. Andrew will hold a news conference here on Tuesday with senior citizens from across Pennsylvania, to point up discrepancies in Mr. Bush's and Mr. McCain's proposals regarding Social Security.</p>
        <p>Of course, the question of whether an endorsement by a member of one's own party is meaningful to anyone but the candidate and the people paid to write and talk about it remains an open one. To Senator Arlen Specter, a Republican whose home state is host to the meeting, the issue may be settled a lot more easily than a lot of people think: ''It's for Governor Bush to say, ''I'd like to have your support.' ''</p>
        <p>After all, Mr. Specter said, he hasn't made an endorsement, either. ''When McCain and Bush were in it together, I thought it was the better part of valor to stay out of it,'' he explained. Since then, he added, ''Nobody's asked me.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ARIZONA SENATOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
