<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Decode Down Syndrome Chromosome</title>
    <meta content="09GENO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Down Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Institutes of Health</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wellcome Trust</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Down Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D81338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Decode Down Syndrome Chromosome</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team of mostly Japanese and German scientists has essentially completed DNA sequence of chromosome 21, shedding light on workings of Down syndrome; finds chromosome has extremely few genes; affected children are born with three copies of chromosome instead of usual two, event that would be lethal with other chromosomes; team is part of international consortium led by National Institutes of Health and Wellcome Trust that is decoding human genome (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reaching another milestone in the race to decode the human genome, a team of principally Japanese and German scientists has essentially completed the DNA sequence of chromosome 21, a result that sheds light on the workings of Down syndrome.</p>
        <p>The team is part of the international consortium of academic centers led by the National Institutes of Health and the Wellcome Trust of London. The consortium has now completed two chromosomes, numbers 21 and 22, which are the two shortest of the human complement of 23 pairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reaching another milestone in the race to decode the human genome, a team of principally Japanese and German scientists has essentially completed the DNA sequence of chromosome 21, a result that sheds light on the workings of Down syndrome.</p>
        <p>The team is part of the international consortium of academic centers led by the National Institutes of Health and the Wellcome Trust of London. The consortium has now completed two chromosomes, numbers 21 and 22, which are the two shortest of the human complement of 23 pairs.</p>
        <p>Chromosome 21 is best known in the context of Down syndrome. Affected children are born with three copies of the chromosome instead of the usual two. Usually a third chromosome is lethal because the extra doses of its genes derange the carefully balanced economy of the cell.</p>
        <p>The decoded DNA sequence of chromosome 21, being published in this week's Nature, explains why Down syndrome children escape the usual death sentence, although at a cost. The chromosome has extremely few genes -- a mere 225, according to the consortium team's count, in its 33,827,477 decodable units of DNA.</p>
        <p>Biologists who study Down syndrome do not know whether there is a general imbalance because of all the extra genes, or whether a handful of specific genes underlies the 80 or so specific disorders of the syndrome. The decoding of chromosome 21 at least establishes a catalog of all the relevant genes.</p>
        <p>''So defining the players and the playing field is a very major step that the Down syndrome community has been working toward for years,'' said Dr. Roger H. Reeves, a geneticist at Johns Hopkins University who studies the syndrome.</p>
        <p>Identifying the genes, and when and where they operate, could lay the basis for someday devising gene therapy for the syndrome, Dr. Reeves said.</p>
        <p>The consortium team estimates that if chromosomes 21 and 22 between them have an average number of genes, the total number of human genes would be a mere 40,000. Other estimates range from 70,000 to 140,000.</p>
        <p>It may seem extraordinary that with the human genome so close to completion, the estimates of its number of genes are all over the lot. But recognizing human genes in the DNA sequence is a rapidly developing art.</p>
        <p>A bioinformatics company called DoubleTwist, of Oakland, Calif., said Monday that it had downloaded the consortium's human genome data, which at present cover 80 percent of the genome, and that with its own software it had identified about 105,000 probable human genes.</p>
        <p>If the higher estimates of human genes are correct, the consortium teams that analyzed chromosomes 21 and 22 may seem to have been too conservative in its gene count.</p>
        <p>The Japanese-German team decoded all of chromosome 21 except for the centromere region, which cannot be tackled by present methods, and 10 small gaps of particularly resistant sequence, which are being left for analysis later.</p>
        <p>In decoding chromosome 21, the consortium now leads 2 to 0 in the genome race against its rival, the Celera Corporation of Rockville, Md.  But the score is misleading because Celera's strategy is to decode all the chromosomes in tandem, and company officials say they are only weeks away from the goal.</p>
        <p>DoubleTwist's ability to survey the genome is evidence of the impressive amounts of human DNA data the consortium has been putting into the public database. The directors of the five leading sequencing centers said today that they had decoded 16 million units of DNA in overlapping segments that together covered 85 percent of the human genome. Their project is now moving into the finishing phase, that of filling the remaining gaps.</p>
        <p>''From my point of view the race is over in that the vast majority of the human genome sequence is freely available on the web,'' said Dr. Eric S. Lander, director of the genome sequencing center at the Whitehead Institute in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
