<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons for the Sisterhood In Turntable Wizardry</title>
    <meta content="09DECK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0D81338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons for the Sisterhood In Turntable Wizardry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews program of women in underground music, including DJ's and rappers, at Lighthouse Frying Pan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summer's first festival arrived in league with the May swelter at Lighthouse Frying Pan on Saturday night. ''Take Back the Decks: An Evening of Women in Underground Music'' presented female D.J.'s and rappers to a female-dominated audience that recalled Lilith Fair. On one important level this evening did Lilith one better. Male backing musicians outnumbered the female stars at that much-admired festival. ''Take Back the Decks'' featured pure female artistry.</p>
        <p>Technology, that old reliable liberator, made the leap possible. Machine-generated hip-hop and dance music can be created by a D.J. or turntablist alone, or in league with a vocalist. Instead of casting around for a female drummer, bassist and guitarist, an aspiring rapper can simply partner with a female turntablist. Or that turntablist can create a show all by herself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summer's first festival arrived in league with the May swelter at Lighthouse Frying Pan on Saturday night. ''Take Back the Decks: An Evening of Women in Underground Music'' presented female D.J.'s and rappers to a female-dominated audience that recalled Lilith Fair. On one important level this evening did Lilith one better. Male backing musicians outnumbered the female stars at that much-admired festival. ''Take Back the Decks'' featured pure female artistry.</p>
        <p>Technology, that old reliable liberator, made the leap possible. Machine-generated hip-hop and dance music can be created by a D.J. or turntablist alone, or in league with a vocalist. Instead of casting around for a female drummer, bassist and guitarist, an aspiring rapper can simply partner with a female turntablist. Or that turntablist can create a show all by herself.</p>
        <p>What women need, besides courage, is knowledge about equipment. ''Take Back the Decks'' was organized to share that science. Presented by Mishpucha, a New York-based ''music activism'' group, and sponsored by the teenager-oriented Web site gURL.com, the event paired education with entertainment. In a D.J. clinic at sunset, the turntablists Kelli Hand, Kuttin' Kandi, Shortee, Rekha and Anna discussed their skills and invited a few lucky amateurs onstage for lessons.</p>
        <p>''Take notes!'' ordered the Brooklyn-based Kuttin' Kandi as the San Francisco native Anna showed an audience participant how to ''baby scratch,'' creating the record-ripping noises that define hip-hop. The artists went into minute detail about which needles to purchase, how to break them in and how to use faders and other machines. The veteran Chicago D.J. Kelli Hand explained independent record production, while Rekha, New York's star proponent of Indian bhangra, weighed the merits of vinyl and compact discs.</p>
        <p>After class, the audience was ready for recess. Sets took place inside the Frying Pan, an old boat, and on the pier nearby. A loop of ''Nobody Knows My Name,'' Rachel Raimist's plainspoken documentary about women in hip-hop, showed in the boat's hull until 9 p.m, when the D.J.'s took over.</p>
        <p>Inside, Rekha built a sinuous flow that made bellies wiggle, while Shortee, the first female turntablist to release a full-length album, demonstrated intense musicality and cutting skills on the pier. She was followed by the flashy Kuttin' Kandi, who later backed the Anomolies, a raw but engagingly fervent group of rappers and dancers.</p>
        <p>Inside, the dance floor got sweaty as the Chicago-based deep house tag team Superjane established a mesmerizing groove. By the time Kelli Hand took over, a sense of freedom was thick in the air. The Emma Goldman quote that has become a leftist cliche was reinvigorated: this crowd was ready for revolution, but only if it got to dance.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
