<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating Yaddo With Works It Helped Spawn</title>
    <meta content="09HOUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yaddo Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hough, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFD91338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating Yaddo With Works It Helped Spawn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews recital by pianist Stephen Hough, part of festival marking centenary of artists' community Yaddo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a hundred years visual artists, writers and composers have been enjoying short-term, pleasant and often productive residencies at Yaddo, the bucolic artists' community in Saratoga Springs, N.Y. To observe its centenary, a festival of concerts, readings, art exhibitions and films is being presented in New York and in the Saratoga Springs region over the next three months. One of the first events was at Alice Tully Hall on Thursday night, when Stephen Hough, an excellent 39-year-old British pianist, presented a recital called ''Celebrating Yaddo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hough appropriately decided to commemorate Yaddo (rhymes with shadow) by performing works that were written there, beginning with Copland's landmark Piano Variations from 1930. In this work Copland freely adapted the 12-tone method to devise a steely harmonic language distinctively his own. He took the angst-ridden, 12-tone aesthetic devised in Austria after World War I and turned it into something that exulted in dissonance and spoke with a clear-headed energy that was somehow American. Mr. Hough captured these qualities in his compelling performance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a hundred years visual artists, writers and composers have been enjoying short-term, pleasant and often productive residencies at Yaddo, the bucolic artists' community in Saratoga Springs, N.Y. To observe its centenary, a festival of concerts, readings, art exhibitions and films is being presented in New York and in the Saratoga Springs region over the next three months. One of the first events was at Alice Tully Hall on Thursday night, when Stephen Hough, an excellent 39-year-old British pianist, presented a recital called ''Celebrating Yaddo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hough appropriately decided to commemorate Yaddo (rhymes with shadow) by performing works that were written there, beginning with Copland's landmark Piano Variations from 1930. In this work Copland freely adapted the 12-tone method to devise a steely harmonic language distinctively his own. He took the angst-ridden, 12-tone aesthetic devised in Austria after World War I and turned it into something that exulted in dissonance and spoke with a clear-headed energy that was somehow American. Mr. Hough captured these qualities in his compelling performance.</p>
        <p>Two works composed recently at Yaddo had premieres. David Del Tredici's ''Wedding Song'' is a miniature, a tenderly lyrical gift piece for friends. Still, you hear Mr. Del Tredici's keen ear at work in the ''wrong'' notes that keep disrupting the beguiling tonal harmony. Lowell Liebermann's Three Impromptu's pay homage to those of Schubert. Each one essentially fixates on a rhythmic figure, though unexpected excursions and outbursts occur in each work. This is unabashedly Neo-Romantic music, but Mr. Hough's sensitive performance made the most of the hazy tonal harmonies and seductive piano colors.</p>
        <p>George Tsontakis's ''Ghost Variations,'' composed in 1991, which received its New York premiere, is a 30-minute work of Lisztian brilliance. It begins with a wildly free fantasy that leads into a long set of variations in which bits and pieces of Mozart's Piano Concerto in E flat (K. 482), always fractured and distorted, keep surfacing through the disorienting musical textures in a ghostly way. Mr. Tsontakis's sheer inventiveness and understanding of piano sonorities is undeniable, though on first hearing the work seems overextended. It was hard to resist in Mr. Hough's engrossing performance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hough ended with a work definitely not composed at Yaddo, Liszt's mighty Sonata in B minor. Other pianists have dispatched the flurry of repeated double octaves and volleys of arm-blurring chords with more ease than Mr. Hough does. But it was fascinating to hear this work played by a pianist with such extensive experience in 20th-century music. Mr. Hough's ear was vividly alert to the music's curious interplay of inner voices. The dizzying, slightly crazed passage work, played here with crisp rhythmic clarity, seemed to be pointing the way to the scurrying, every-which-way counterpoint of Elliott Carter's 1945 Piano Sonata.</p>
        <p>Another event in the Yaddo Festival is planned tomorrow, a program of American songs, with Ned Rorem as host, at the 92nd Street Y.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
