<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel Hurries Pullout Plans After Clashes Along Border</title>
    <meta content="Y09ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DF1038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel Hurries Pullout Plans After Clashes Along Border</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel speeds up preparations to withdraw forces from southern Lebanon following spate of border violence, in event Prime Min Ehud Barak decides to do so before self-imposed deadline of July 7; senior military officials expect to withdraw under fire; several indicate they may as well withdraw as soon as possible and cut losses they could sustain in next two months (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a spate of border violence late last week, Israel is speeding up its preparations to withdraw troops from southern Lebanon in case Prime Minister Ehud Barak decides to do so before his self-imposed deadline of July 7.</p>
        <p>Senior military officials expect to be pulling out under fire, and several have indicated that they may as well withdraw as soon as possible and cut the losses they could sustain in the next two months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a spate of border violence late last week, Israel is speeding up its preparations to withdraw troops from southern Lebanon in case Prime Minister Ehud Barak decides to do so before his self-imposed deadline of July 7.</p>
        <p>Senior military officials expect to be pulling out under fire, and several have indicated that they may as well withdraw as soon as possible and cut the losses they could sustain in the next two months.</p>
        <p>One Israeli soldier and two Lebanese civilians were killed in intensified fighting last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak and his advisers dropped hints today, not for the first time, that the withdrawal date could be advanced, perhaps doing so as a way to put pressure on Lebanon to help curb the violence or to negotiate a withdrawal arrangement. A precipitous withdrawal could plunge southern Lebanon into chaos.</p>
        <p>The hints could also be aimed at Syria -- to remind the Syrians, whose forces control Lebanon, that they are running out of time to resume peace talks before a withdrawal. Or they could be straightforward expressions of intention. But for the moment, Mr. Barak has indicated that he wants to conduct the withdrawal under the auspices of the United Nations, with full international support. And that would make it less likely that Israel could pull out before July, though still possible.</p>
        <p>United Nations officials already consider time very short to obtain Security Council approval for a plan, organize nations that would contribute peacekeeping forces and make practical arrangements by July 7.</p>
        <p>Israel has been grappling with United Nations requirements for the withdrawal that have provoked intense internal debate in the military and the government. The major issue is a United Nations demand that the Israel-backed South Lebanon Army be dismantled when the withdrawal takes place, and that its Khiam prison, assailed by international human rights groups, be shut down and its detainees released.</p>
        <p>Gen. Antoine Lahad, the commander of the South Lebanon Army, today asked the Lebanese government to grant blanket amnesty to his soliders, who are considered to be traitors and face harsh prison terms or death sentences. General Lahad has maintained that without pardons, his men will choose to stay and fight rather than to emigrate.</p>
        <p>An Israeli official said Israel might seek United Nations intervention on behalf of militia members,  suggesting that persuading Lebanon to revoke their sentences would make it easier to disarm them.</p>
        <p>The Israeli newspaper Maariv reported today that Israel was already scaling back its transfer of arms and ammunition to the South Lebanon Army and that it is considering collecting heavy armaments.</p>
        <p>While Israel expects that United Nations peacekeeping forces will help quell violence after the pullout, it is especially anxious for United Nations help during the withdrawal itself. The United Nations will be called on to certify that Israel has indeed withdrawn from Lebanese territory. That will be important for Israel, which is expected to assert, and seek international backing for its assertion, that the guerrillas can no longer legitimize violent attacks on its northern border.</p>
        <p>The certification will be conditioned on Israel's full withdrawal and its compliance with all demands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak showed his inclination to accede to international specifications when he quelled internal debate on two points. Military officials were pressing to keep some outposts directly over the border after the withdrawal, an idea that he, a former general, squelched. And he also quieted disgruntlement about letting an outside force delineate the border line to be used.</p>
        <p>Many Arab leaders are inclined to suspect that Israel will not comply fully. Egypt's foreign minister, Amr Moussa, expressed concerns today that the Israeli withdrawal would not be complete -- ''on land, sea and air.''</p>
        <p>To determine whether Israel fully withdraws, United Nations officials will use a 1923, internationally recognized line between Israel and Lebanon, with mutually agreed upon amendments. Terje Roed-Larsen, a United Nations peace envoy who is in the region to make preparations for the withdrawal, said he had encountered ''no fundamental disagreement'' over this line.</p>
        <p>But the Lebanese prime minister, Selim al-Hoss, did tell Mr. Larsen that it considered a piece of territory on the edge of the Golan Heights to be Lebanese as well. That demand could cause problems, because if the border is disputed, then the completion of the withdrawal will be, too.</p>
        <p>''It's too early to tell if this is worrisome,'' a United Nations official said. But the issue will have to be resolved in the next couple of weeks so that the plan can be approved.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
