<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Infield Confident It Can Do Better Job</title>
    <meta content="09METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2D81038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Infield Confident It Can Do Better Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses problems besetting New York Mets infield (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, the Mets' starting infield was celebrated as one of the best defensive units in major league history, if not the best. Now, one-fifth of the way through this season, the club's infield regulars are confronting the sober reality of trying to live up to that standard.</p>
        <p>Through 33 games, this year's starting infield of Robin Ventura, Rey Ordonez, Edgardo Alfonzo and Todd Zeile has made 17 errors. Last year, in 163 games, Ventura, Ordonez, Alfonzo and John Olerud combined for just 27. So, as the Mets traveled to Pittsburgh to begin a three-game series on Tuesday night and try to end a tailspin that has led to 9 losses in their last 12 games, the infield is on a pace to make three times as many errors as it did a year ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, the Mets' starting infield was celebrated as one of the best defensive units in major league history, if not the best. Now, one-fifth of the way through this season, the club's infield regulars are confronting the sober reality of trying to live up to that standard.</p>
        <p>Through 33 games, this year's starting infield of Robin Ventura, Rey Ordonez, Edgardo Alfonzo and Todd Zeile has made 17 errors. Last year, in 163 games, Ventura, Ordonez, Alfonzo and John Olerud combined for just 27. So, as the Mets traveled to Pittsburgh to begin a three-game series on Tuesday night and try to end a tailspin that has led to 9 losses in their last 12 games, the infield is on a pace to make three times as many errors as it did a year ago.</p>
        <p>''There have probably been more mistakes than all of last year,'' pitcher Rick Reed acknowledged when asked about the infielders. ''But I know this: Every time the ball's hit to one of them, I still feel they are going to make the play.''</p>
        <p>One infield component -- first base -- has changed from a year ago, with Olerud departing for Seattle and Zeile arriving from Texas. Olerud is solid defensively at first base; Zeile is a third basemen learning a new position on the job.</p>
        <p>Olerud made nine errors last year, three by this juncture in the season. Zeile has four, and has looked uncertain on other plays. Second baseman Alfonzo, with two errors, has one more than he had by this time last year, when he finished with five.</p>
        <p>The biggest difference is on the infield's left side. Shortstop Ordonez, who finished with just four errors last season and put together a 100-game errorless streak, has six. At this time a year ago, he had two. And third baseman Ventura, with five errors, is within four of his season's total for 1999. Last year, he had just one error at this point.</p>
        <p>Ordonez's .994 fielding percentage last season and Ventura's .980 are Mets' records for their positions. Curiously, all but one of Ordonez's errors this season and all of Ventura's have come on the road, where the Mets have lost 10 of 17 games.</p>
        <p>''So far,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said, ''they haven't played as well as they're capable.''</p>
        <p>Ventura, a six-time Gold Glove winner, would prefer not to probe too deeply into why his errors have increased.</p>
        <p>''I've had years where I made a lot of errors and years where I didn't make many,'' Ventura said. ''I don't know any way to explain it. I just think that people sometimes make too much out of numbers. The only errors that really make you mad are the ones that cost you runs.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, only 20 of the 711 runs scored against the Mets were unearned, a remarkably low total when you consider that the 15 other National League teams averaged 73 unearned runs. This year, 17 of the opposition's 182 runs have been tainted.</p>
        <p>Two of Ordonez's errors this season were freakish events, Valentine said. The first came in Japan, he said, when a ground ball hit a crack in the artificial turf. Another came when the ball skidded off the edge of a grass infield.</p>
        <p>''He had an unbelievable year last year,'' said Alfonzo, Ordonez's double-play partner. ''Some of the things that have happened this year, I've told him not to get down about it.''</p>
        <p>Most of all, Alfonzo wants one thing understood.</p>
        <p>''We're human,'' he said. ''What we did last year -- it's hard to expect it to be like that every year. So many different things can happen. We don't go out and try to make errors, but sometimes it's going to be like that. I don't worry too much about numbers, anyway. I just come here and focus on my job.''</p>
        <p>And then there's Zeile.</p>
        <p>''I'm still learning the position, but I feel a lot more comfortable now,'' he said. ''It's never been my intention to just try to get by. I want to be an asset there, not just a guy you're trying to hide to get him in the lineup.''</p>
        <p>The Mets acquired Zeile primarily for his run-producing ability. Before that move, the Mets considered giving the job to Jorge Toca, a Cuban defector and minor leaguer, who is far more advanced as a defensive first baseman.</p>
        <p>''He's ready to be a big leaguer, and he's a top-rate fielder,'' Omar Minaya, the Mets' assistant general manager, said. ''But we didn't think the New York market would accept replacing John Olerud with someone they weren't familiar with.''</p>
        <p>So it's a work-in-progress Zeile with three teammates who are finding it difficult to provide an encore to 1999.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
