<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Household Names</title>
    <meta content="Y09OLD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Young &amp; Rubicam Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wpp Group Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDE1038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Household Names</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Agreement by Young &amp; Rubicam in New York to be acquired by WPP Group ends independent life of one of most influential, best-known mainstream advertising agencies; some of agency's advertising campaigns recalled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The agreement by Young &amp; Rubicam in New York to be acquired by the WPP Group in London ends the independent life of one of the most influential, best-known mainstream agencies.</p>
        <p>In fact, Y.&amp; R. is one of the few agencies actually on Madison Avenue, at 285 Madison between 40th and 41st Streets. That building has been its home since 1928.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The agreement by Young &amp; Rubicam in New York to be acquired by the WPP Group in London ends the independent life of one of the most influential, best-known mainstream agencies.</p>
        <p>In fact, Y.&amp; R. is one of the few agencies actually on Madison Avenue, at 285 Madison between 40th and 41st Streets. That building has been its home since 1928.</p>
        <p>It was Y.&amp; R. along with rivals like J. Walter Thompson; Batten, Barton, Durstine &amp; Osborn; Lord &amp; Thomas; and McCann-Erickson that helped create an image of Madison Avenue in the minds of Americans as the home of slick specialists in a newfangled industry who tried everything from slick slogans to earnest demonstrations to catchy jingles to sell products with emotional as well as rational appeals.</p>
        <p>Y.&amp; R. persuaded consumers to sing as they spelled out the letters ''J-E-L-L-O''; tickled funny bones with an unconventional campaign for Piels beer featuring animated pitchmen named Bert and Harry; convinced donors on behalf of the United Negro College Fund that ''a mind is a terrible thing to waste''; presented headaches by the numbers -- the tax audit, No.  1040, natch -- for Excedrin pain reliever; rocked the New York City of the late 1960's by urging citizens to ''give a damn'' and help the Urban Coalition; and exhorted the thirsty to ''be a Pepper'' for Dr Pepper soda.</p>
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam was a pioneer in the media of radio and television in the days when agencies created programs for their clients and then produced them for the networks. The comedian Jack Benny became identified with Jell-O when Y.&amp; R. brought him together with General Foods; not long after its debut in October 1934, ''The Jack Benny Program'' became a top-rated radio show -- and Jell-O the best-selling gelatin dessert, a standing it has maintained to this day.</p>
        <p>Other performers who went into homes with Young &amp; Rubicam clients as sponsors included Arthur Godfrey, Kate Smith, George Burns and Gracie Allen, Ronald Reagan (for ''G.E. Theater'') and Fanny Brice. Series developed under the aegis of Y.&amp; R. included ''The Aldrich Family,'' ''The Goldbergs,'' ''Schlitz Playhouse of Stars,'' ''American Bandstand'' and ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents.''</p>
        <p>General Foods, now part of the Kraft Foods unit of Philip Morris , was one of the first important clients for Y.&amp; R., which was founded in Philadelphia in 1923 by two former employees of N. W. Ayer, Raymond Rubicam and John Orr Young.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubicam and Mr. Young, both copywriters, began their agency with a $5,000 investment and one client -- a company that published leaflets with instructions for making shoelaces at home -- according to the trade publication Advertising Age. The Postum Company, a General Foods predecessor, hired the shop in its first year of business; in 1926, Y.&amp; R. relocated to New York when Postum agreed to award it the Jell-O dessert account on condition that it move.</p>
        <p>As Y.&amp; R. flourished with the explosive growth of radio, then television, top management plowed profits into expansion. It formed the first ad agency research department. It opened offices in Chicago, Hollywood, Montreal and Toronto and expanded into Europe as early as 1943 with an office in London.</p>
        <p>Other firsts achieved by Y.&amp; R., according to Advertising Age, included the first color television commercial in 1951, for Jell-O pudding and pie filling, and the first demonstration commercial in 1954, showing a Remington razor shaving a peach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
