<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Muscling Into the Hall To Submit to The 'Ring'</title>
    <meta content="09NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wagner, Richard (1813-83)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ring Des Nibelungen (Opera Cycle)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2D91338F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Muscling Into the Hall To Submit to The 'Ring'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland Critic's Notebook column discusses compromises involved in any production of Wagner's Ring des Niebelungen in light of Metropolitan Opera's production (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No ''Ring'' cycle guarantees customer satisfaction. Wagner's four-evening, weeklong operatic monster, known officially as ''Der Ring des Niebelungen,'' has too many spiritual and physical moving parts to inspire consensus. Barter and negotiation occupy the minds and hearts of every audience member: what must I surrender to gain what I most value? The trades are not easily made.</p>
        <p>Magnificent Wagnerian voices are, more often than not, housed in outsize and virtually immobile bodies. Those who look the parts too often cannot sing them, at least not for the hour-after-hour, day-after-day work schedules that these events demand. Good voices of less muscularity can manage Wagner in smaller opera houses (the tenor Siegfried Jerusalem comes to mind). But at the Metropolitan Opera, where the last of three ''Ring'' cycles ran its course last week, size and presence equal to a 3,800-seat house are demanded. Next to the Met's presentations, those in Vienna or London seem like chamber music (not necessarily a bad thing).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No ''Ring'' cycle guarantees customer satisfaction. Wagner's four-evening, weeklong operatic monster, known officially as ''Der Ring des Niebelungen,'' has too many spiritual and physical moving parts to inspire consensus. Barter and negotiation occupy the minds and hearts of every audience member: what must I surrender to gain what I most value? The trades are not easily made.</p>
        <p>Magnificent Wagnerian voices are, more often than not, housed in outsize and virtually immobile bodies. Those who look the parts too often cannot sing them, at least not for the hour-after-hour, day-after-day work schedules that these events demand. Good voices of less muscularity can manage Wagner in smaller opera houses (the tenor Siegfried Jerusalem comes to mind). But at the Metropolitan Opera, where the last of three ''Ring'' cycles ran its course last week, size and presence equal to a 3,800-seat house are demanded. Next to the Met's presentations, those in Vienna or London seem like chamber music (not necessarily a bad thing).</p>
        <p>Next, what is it we want to see? Wagner's gods and demigods have been parsed by every psychiatric, social, religious and political faction one can think of. Those unsatisfied by the face value of high and ancient people committing low deeds have had many metaphors to turn to. George Bernard Shaw reimagined the ''Ring'' as class struggle, and the evils of capitalism have run amok through ''Ring'' productions ever since. Surreal collisions of modern and ancient dress and props continue to create the images that ambitious directors hope will make Wagner relevant for us right now.</p>
        <p>The Met's 13-year-old production takes another tack. Otto Schenk and Gunther Schneider-Siemssen peer through Wagner's eyes, as midway through the 19th century he assembled in his mind the spears, swords, helmets, rocks and trees through which his dubious characters would move. The era's creaky stage machinery would be updated, however, with crafty backlighted projections, psychologically calculated color-codings and all the magic tricks a well-equipped new opera house can muster.</p>
        <p>Wagnerites have been alternately dismayed and relieved. Conservative German listeners, ignoring snide critical comments in their own newspapers, flock to the United States -- to Seattle, Chicago, San Francisco or New York -- hoping to escape the drastic interpretations their countrymen present them with. I have stayed at hotels during American ''Ring'' cycles and heard barely a word of English. Hip Americans appalled by a literalism they call listless and archaic flock to Bayreuth or Vienna, eager to be brought up to date by the latest vision of Wagner.</p>
        <p>There seemed to be fewer foreigners at the Met last week, perhaps because tickets were in such demand among the house's regular patrons. The Met's press department, usually happy to provide free entry for visiting journalists and critics, found its cache of tickets drastically curtailed. The three ''Ring'' cycles this spring stood outside regular subscription series, and top seats brought prices (ticket plus mandatory donation) close to $300. No one seemed to mind. People at the house do not deny that had its players, singers, stage hands, ushers and financiers possessed the lasting power, the Met could probably have sold out the cycle several more times.</p>
        <p>The principle trade-off last week involved eyes for ears. Musically, there was orchestra playing under James Levine breathtaking for its clarity and sophistication. Visually, suspension of disbelief was stretched to its breaking point but rescued by consistent singing quality. Jane Eaglen as Brunnhilde was a trumpet of triumphant proportions. Ms. Eaglen's physical size cannot be put aside out of politeness. Virtually immobile and nearly dwarfing last week's Siegfied, Stig Andersen, her contributions to theater during the early stages of this cycle consisted of a raised arm or two and none too convincing plays of joy and sorrow across the face.</p>
        <p>Confronted with such paradox, the eye rises up and says this will not do, but then there is the sound of that voice, which by its physical presence alone occupies the role. And then there were Brunnhilde's final sequences in ''Gotterdammerung,'' in which all disbelief melted away, allowing both eye and ear to be equally moved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andersen, who is from Denmark, handled one of opera's truly punishing roles with admirable reliability. His tenor is in good health, he moves well and there are blessedly few retreats into barking semi-speech.</p>
        <p>The size of Mr. Andersen's voice would fill a smaller hall, say Covent Garden or the Vienna Staatsoper, more fully. One had a hard time hearing him in early acts, but gratitude for what he was and forgiveness for what he was not in this impossible part gradually formed a truce.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, James Morris soldiered satisfyingly on. He is our Wotan for the generation, and may have a few good ''Ring'' cycles still in him. Deborah Voigt and Placido Domingo as Sieglinde and Siegmund knew that their duties were relatively brief,  and brilliantly held nothing back. Mr. Levine's Wagner remains very slow, but I for one do not mind. One values the breathing space that frames every detail. Nothing crude or careless could escape notice at these tempos, and one hears neither quality.</p>
        <p>The final barter: the production. I find some of the scenes insipid, like the 19th-century aquatints that chronically overstock bad antique shops (Act I of ''Siegfried,'' for example, or the start of Act III in ''Gotterdammerung''). Also, a Mark Morris or some choreographer like him should be brought in to do something about the Rhine Maidens and the Valkyries, whose gyrations are embarrassing. The great virtue of the Met's ''Ring,'' on the other hand, is that it does not get in the way. There are no metaphors of modern life to puzzle out. Wagner's characters are carried, as the old advertising slogan goes, ''factory to you'' with no directorial middlemen to intervene.</p>
        <p>I have always been fascinated by the many serious musical people who ardently champion the original intents and historical integrities of 18th-century performance style and at the same time dismiss the Met's ''Ring'' as hopelessly old-fashioned. Just as I love Stokowski conducting Bach, I wouldn't mind seeing Wotan as Homer Simpson or Norns as the Supremes. But, if you want Wagner faithful to his time, New York may be the place to be.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
