<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="09PUBL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000511T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ellis Island (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Holland</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duff, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuby, Ronald L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perelman, Ronald O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Vagina Monologues, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDD1038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Allen R. Myerson and David Rohde</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R; Barron, James; Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; actress Holland Taylor to replace Donna Hanover in The Vagina Monologues; Attorney General Janet Reno receives Ellis Island Medal of Honor at annual fund raiser organized by National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations; Ronald L Kuby joins Patricia Duff's legal team in her child custody battle with Ronald Perelman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 'Co-Star,' Not 'Replacement'</p>
        <p>DONNA HANOVER's replacement in ''The Vagina Monologues'' will be HOLLAND TAYLOR, who won an Emmy Award for playing a sexually charged judge on the television drama ''The Practice.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 'Co-Star,' Not 'Replacement'</p>
        <p>DONNA HANOVER's replacement in ''The Vagina Monologues'' will be HOLLAND TAYLOR, who won an Emmy Award for playing a sexually charged judge on the television drama ''The Practice.''</p>
        <p>''From my angle,'' Ms. Taylor said yesterday, ''this is about me coming in and doing it, not replacing anyone. I live in L.A., where you know nothing. I have no idea what's going on with the mayor's wife. Forgive my ignorance. I have a feeling it's bliss.''</p>
        <p>Here is what Ms. Taylor has missed: after Ms. Hanover's husband, MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI, announced that he had prostate cancer, Ms. Hanover dropped out of the production. Ms. Taylor and the other two actresses who were booked to appear with Ms. Hanover, KIRSTIE ALLEY and HAZELLE GOODMAN, will appear from May 30 to June 11.</p>
        <p>On June 13, they will be succeeded by CALISTA FLOCKHART of ''Ally McBeal,'' LISA GAY HAMILTON of ''The Practice,'' and the television news personality LINDA ELLERBEE. ''The David E. Kelley girls, plus one,'' Ms. Ellerbee said yesterday, referring to the prolific creator and producer of ''Ally McBeal'' and ''The Practice.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellerbee sounded relieved that actresses in ''The Vagina Monologues'' are allowed to read their lines from index cards. Her total acting experience consists of a fourth-grade play and an appearance as herself on the sitcom ''Murphy Brown.''</p>
        <p>''In one day, I learned the difference between playing yourself and being yourself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Hiding Out By Blending In</p>
        <p>Sometimes the best place to hide is out in the open. And so ATTORNEY GENERAL JANET RENO, seeking to avoid Cuban-Americans protesting the seizure of Elian Gonzalez, did not sneak onto Ellis Island Saturday night through a back door -- that is, through Liberty State Park in New Jersey -- on her way to receive an Ellis Island Medal of Honor at an annual fund-raiser organized by the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations. (Ms. Reno's father, HENRY RENO, was a Danish immigrant.)</p>
        <p>WILLIAM DENNIS FUGAZY, the coalition's chairman and owner of travel and limousine companies, had let it be known before the ceremony that some guests would be taking the Liberty State Park route. So that is where the protesters went. But Ms. Reno (and her police and Secret Service escorts) went to Battery Park and took the same ferry as the other guests.</p>
        <p>The only sign of the protesters was overhead. An airplane flew by with a banner saying, ''Reno is to freedom as Clinton is to honesty.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno, who was accompanied at the ceremony by REPRESENTATIVE CHARLES B. RANGEL, an old friend, made no direct mention of the protesters during her brief speech. But her critics were evidently on her mind. ''It is important that the people and the press start speaking on civil terms that honor this nation instead of tearing it down,'' she said. ''Instead of criticizing our leaders, go run for office and put your ideas into effect.''</p>
        <p>New Duff Lawyer</p>
        <p>PATRICIA DUFF called in another lawyer yesterday in her child-custody trial in State Supreme Court in Manhattan (she has had more than 20 in the long-running proceeding). This time, RONALD L. KUBY, the pony-tailed partner of the radical lawyer William M. Kunstler until Kunstler's death in 1995, said that Ms. Duff would take the Fifth Amendment.</p>
        <p>But JUSTICE EILEEN C. BRANSTEN said that in a civil trial, unlike a criminal trial, a judge could draw a negative inference when someone refused to testify.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuby's concern was a ruling by the judge, who found that Ms. Duff had ''contemptuously'' violated a 1997 court order by making more than 320 tapes.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Ms. Duff said that she had videotaped her 5-year-old daughter chatting on the telephone with the makeup mogul RONALD O. PERELMAN, who is Ms. Duff's former husband and the child's father. Ms. Duff also said that she had taped telephone calls to her own lawyers. ''It's simply a form of note-taking,'' she said.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Allen R. Myerson and David Rohde</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 11, 2000, Thursday  A report in the Public Lives column on Tuesday about the presentation of an Ellis Island Medal of Honor to Attorney General Janet Reno misspelled the middle name of the chairman of the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations. He is William Denis Fugazy, not Dennis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 11, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A report in the Public Lives column on Tuesday about the presentation of an Ellis Island Medal of Honor to Attorney General Janet Reno misspelled the middle name of the chairman of the National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations. He is William Denis Fugazy, not Dennis.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
