<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young &amp; Rubicam Agrees to $5.7 Billion Takeover by WPP</title>
    <meta content="Y09YOU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wpp Group Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Young &amp; Rubicam Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D81038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young &amp; Rubicam Agrees to $5.7 Billion Takeover by WPP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN with STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam ends 77 years of independence by agreeing to $5.7 billion takeover by WPP Group, rival based in London; it is largest deal in history of industry; takeover will make WPP largest advertising company in the world measured in billings and revenue; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam, a Madison Avenue icon that gave the world the Jell-O jingle and the numbered Excedrin headaches, ended 77 years of independence tonight by agreeing to a $5.7 billion takeover by the WPP Group, a rival based in London. It is the largest deal in the history of the industry.</p>
        <p>While the boards of the two companies have yet to vote formally on the agreement, executives close to the negotiations said the boards were expected to announce an accord as early as Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam, a Madison Avenue icon that gave the world the Jell-O jingle and the numbered Excedrin headaches, ended 77 years of independence tonight by agreeing to a $5.7 billion takeover by the WPP Group, a rival based in London. It is the largest deal in the history of the industry.</p>
        <p>While the boards of the two companies have yet to vote formally on the agreement, executives close to the negotiations said the boards were expected to announce an accord as early as Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The deal ends four months of off-again-on-again talks that included trans-Atlantic conference calls and hand-scrawled faxes with proposals and counterproposals, a second possible suitor and an 11th-hour breakdown in negotiations that rivaled the theatrics of some of the most creative commercials the companies produce.</p>
        <p>The takeover would make WPP the largest advertising company in the world measured in billings and revenue, leap-frogging the Omnicom Group and the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>The combined company would create advertising campaigns for household brands like Ford, I.B.M., American Express, AT&amp;T, Kraft Foods and Sony. The agreement brings under one roof famous ad agencies like Young &amp; Rubicam, J. Walter Thompson and Ogilvy &amp; Mather, while making siblings of well-known public relations agencies like Burson-Marsteller, Hill &amp; Knowlton and Cohn &amp; Wolfe. Each would retain its distinctive identity within WPP.</p>
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam had been one of the last big independent agency companies in an industry that has been consolidating relentlessly since the mid-1980's, as Madison Avenue sought to keep pace with the growth and international expansion of its clients seeking global reach.</p>
        <p>''The big are getting bigger,'' said Karen R. Ficker, managing director for advertising, publishing and new media at ING Barings. ''If you looked around out there, Y.&amp; R. was probably one of the best left for WPP.''</p>
        <p>Young &amp; Rubicam is losing its independence only 24 months after the agency, privately held since it was founded by the copywriters Raymond Rubicam and John Orr Young in 1923, decided to sell stock to the public.</p>
        <p>The shares had climbed until recently and then declined, which made Young &amp; Rubicam vulnerable to a takeover by larger advertising conglomerates like WPP.</p>
        <p>According to executives close to the talks, WPP has agreed to pay 0.835 American depository receipt for each share of Young &amp; Rubicam. That equates to WPP paying about $63 for each share of Y.&amp; R. based on Friday's closing price.</p>
        <p>Y.&amp; R.'s shares fell $4.3125, or 8 percent, to $49.8125 in Nasdaq trading today.</p>
        <p>In London, WPP dropped 65 pence, or 6.7 percent, to 910 pence ($13.95), after dropping as low as 890 pence. Its American depository receipts, each representing five ordinary shares, dropped 9 percent, to $66.875.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would give WPP control of 3 of the world's top 11  autonomous ad agency operations ranked by revenue: Thompson (No. 4), Ogilvy (No. 10) and Y.&amp; R. (No. 11). WPP's principal rivals -- Omnicom and Interpublic -- each also control three big agencies. Omnicom has BBDO (No. 3), DDB (No. 7) and TBWA (No. 15). Interpublic has McCann-Erickson (No. 2), Lowe Lintas &amp; Partners (No. 13) and Draft (No. 24).</p>
        <p>The goal of these huge new agency companies is to own or control as many of the large, multinational operations as possible to offer the most potential services to large, multinational clients. With each agency set up as an an autonomous unit, the intent is to minimize conflicts that would keep advertisers from hiring the agency company.</p>
        <p>For instance, agencies owned by Omnicom work for auto companies that compete against each other, but with the agencies operating separately, the automakers are ostensibly assured that no agency shares proprietary data with its siblings. So BBDO and Merkley Newman Harty work for DaimlerChrysler; DDB works for Volkswagen; TBWA works for Nissan; and Goodby, Silverstein &amp; Partners works for Isuzu.</p>
        <p>Some clients, however, disapprove of such arrangements and will not agree to use an agency with a sibling that works for a rival. That was an important issue in the talks between Young &amp; Rubicam and its second suitor, Publicis of France. Publicis said today that for now it was no longer interested.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard to say no when you have such an opportunity,'' Maurice Levy, chairman and chief executive at Publicis in Paris, said in a telephone interview. ''But there were some obstacles regarding the nature of the deal, organizational problems and client conflicts.''</p>
        <p>The primary stumbling block was Ford, which is a major Young &amp; Rubicam client and would probably have disapproved if Y.&amp; R. were bought by a company that also had subsidiaries working for rivals like BMW (Fallon McElligott in Minneapolis), General Motors (Publicis &amp; Hal Riney in San Francisco) and Renault (Publicis).</p>
        <p>''But if the WPP deal collapses,'' Mr. Levy said, ''we would be ready to look at Y.&amp; R. once again. The phone number is in the book.''</p>
        <p>The deal is more than twice the old record, set only in February when Havas Advertising agreed to acquire Snyder Communications for about $2.1 billion.</p>
        <p>The agreement struck between WPP and Young &amp; Rubicam came only after fits and starts in the negotiations as each side sought better position and leverage. The main sticking points, finally resolved over the weekend, were over price, Young &amp; Rubicam's ability to operate autonomously within WPP during the integration of the company over the first year as well as contractual and compensation provisions for the acquired company's senior executives.</p>
        <p>On price, Sir Martin Sorrell, WPP's chief executive, increased his exchange offer from 0.83 WPP depository receipt, to 0.835. The two companies also compromised on Young &amp; Rubicam's autonomy, creating a four-person board made up of two executives from WPP -- Sir Martin and Paul Richardson, chief financial officer -- and two executives from Young &amp; Rubicam --  Thomas D. Bell Jr., current chief executive, and Michael Dolan, chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>The companies also came to terms over provisions to retain Young &amp; Rubicam's top talent, with a clause that prevents its employees from working for competing clients at rival agencies for a year after leaving Y.&amp; R.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dolan is expected to become chief executive of Young &amp; Rubicam under WPP. Mr. Bell has been offered the position of chairman of WPP, but it remains unclear whether he will accept. Sir Martin was taking a Concorde flight from London to New York on Tuesday morning to meet with Mr. Bell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
