<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Board Member Hints He'll Again Support Levy</title>
    <meta content="09CHAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamer, Irving S Jr (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D61038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Board Member Hints He'll Again Support Levy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Board of Education member Irving S Hamer Jr, who threw search for new schools chancellor into chaos by declaring that he wanted to be considered, all but acknowledges that he is prepared to support interim chancellor Harold O Levy for permanent position (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Irving S. Hamer Jr., who threw the search for chancellor into chaos for the last five days by declaring that he wanted to be a contender, all but acknowledged yesterday that he was prepared to support Harold O. Levy, the interim chancellor, for the permanent job.</p>
        <p>Under heavy pressure from his patron, C. Virginia Fields, who is the Manhattan borough president and the person who appointed him to the Board of Education, Dr. Hamer said in an interview that with no groundswell of support by any of his colleagues or Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, there was no point in pursuing the chancellorship any further.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Irving S. Hamer Jr., who threw the search for chancellor into chaos for the last five days by declaring that he wanted to be a contender, all but acknowledged yesterday that he was prepared to support Harold O. Levy, the interim chancellor, for the permanent job.</p>
        <p>Under heavy pressure from his patron, C. Virginia Fields, who is the Manhattan borough president and the person who appointed him to the Board of Education, Dr. Hamer said in an interview that with no groundswell of support by any of his colleagues or Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, there was no point in pursuing the chancellorship any further.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer stopped short of promising to vote for Mr. Levy, however, saying that that would undermine the interview process that is to begin this week, as he and his colleagues consider Mr. Levy and five other candidates. But Dr. Hamer spoke highly of Mr. Levy and hinted that he would support Mr. Levy in the end.</p>
        <p>''I think Harold Levy is an extraordinarily excellent manager, a highly engaging personality, and I think he could probably stabilize the system for another year or two,'' Dr. Hamer said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, Ms. Fields announced that she supported Mr. Levy and urged Dr. Hamer to do likewise. Mr. Hamer said that he did not want to provoke a fight with Ms. Fields. ''It takes zero skin off my back to support the borough president if that is absolutely necessary to do before the process unfolds,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His remarks brought some closure to a roller-coaster series of events that began Wednesday, when, in a private conversation with the Board of Education president, William C. Thompson Jr., Dr. Hamer revealed that he was interested in becoming chancellor.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer said the idea of running for chancellor had been ''germinating in my belly'' for some time, but he took the plunge after a testy exchange with Mr. Levy over summer school at last Wednesday's board meeting. He said he thought Mr. Levy was focused too much on the administrative aspects of summer school, and not enough on the educational side.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer said he thought he could be a compromise candidate, garnering support from Mr. Giuliani, who has been cool to Mr. Levy, by offering both corporate and educational experience. A former teacher and book-publishing executive, Dr. Hamer is now vice chairman of testu.com, which sells educational services over the Internet. In contrast, Mr. Levy's background is primarily in the corporate world.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer was the only member of the Board of Education to oppose Mr. Giuliani's plan to end social promotion, promoting children to the next grade even if they are failing. But Dr. Hamer said he was not opposed to the concept, only the way it was being put into practice. The program, he said, was designed to be punitive, rather than to give children the help they needed before they failed, and the hardest hit would be poor, black and Hispanic students.</p>
        <p>''I have all the requisite stuff that everyone's been debating about,'' Dr. Hamer said. ''I am not doctrinaire; I am not dogmatic.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer said he was taken aback by the failure of his colleagues to support him. But he said he called Mr. Levy yesterday to assure him that his flirtation with seeking the chancellorship was nothing personal. ''It was a very cordial conversation,'' he said. ''We did not discuss whether I should be chancellor or he should be chancellor.''</p>
        <p>As a deputy state education commissioner in 1987, Dr. Hamer was at the forefront of a movement to recognize that black children have different learning styles from white ones. In a state handbook, he and his co-authors suggested that African-American students were more intuitive than others, that they were quick to recognize injustice and that they had ''a tendency to approximate space, number and time instead of aiming for complete accuracy.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hamer said yesterday that he was trying to provoke a discussion of how to encourage black students to stay in school, and that he did not regret the resulting controversy. ''In some ways that scenario was not unlike this one,'' he said. ''It was wonderful. I liked the action.''</p>
        <p>In the late 1960's, Dr. Hamer was a founder and leader of the Street Academy movement in Harlem, a group of storefront schools dedicated to educating dropouts, drug addicts and students who had trouble fitting in elsewhere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
