<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grading Schools Based on Performance by Race Poses Problems in Suburbia</title>
    <meta content="09REGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD1038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grading Schools Based on Performance by Race Poses Problems in Suburbia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article contends that while many suburban schools have been able to think of lagging achievement by minority students as city problem, one far away from their comfortable test scores and solid real-estate values, their worries about test scores will be altered because of New York State Board of Regents decision to grade schools based partly on how well their black and Hispanic students score, not just how students score overall; educators say that move will force suburbs to confront difficult issues about race as well as threat to their reputations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many suburban schools have been able to think of lagging achievement by minority students as a city problem, one far away from their comfortable test scores and solid real-estate values. Their worries about test scores usually seem to revolve around who  will be closest to the top -- whether the numbers might make, say, Chappaqua's schools look better than Scarsdale's.</p>
        <p>But when the New York State Board of Regents last week decided to grade schools based partly on how well their black and Hispanic students score, not just how students score over all, it moved the debate on standards to a far more controversial realm, one that will force suburbs to confront difficult issues about race as well as a threat to their reputations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many suburban schools have been able to think of lagging achievement by minority students as a city problem, one far away from their comfortable test scores and solid real-estate values. Their worries about test scores usually seem to revolve around who  will be closest to the top -- whether the numbers might make, say, Chappaqua's schools look better than Scarsdale's.</p>
        <p>But when the New York State Board of Regents last week decided to grade schools based partly on how well their black and Hispanic students score, not just how students score over all, it moved the debate on standards to a far more controversial realm, one that will force suburbs to confront difficult issues about race as well as a threat to their reputations.</p>
        <p>The challenge they face is now far thornier than simply raising overall test scores, educators say. They must close the stubborn gap that leaves black and Hispanic students -- even those with well-educated and more affluent parents -- trailing their white peers.</p>
        <p>''They're going to fail a lot of districts if they do this,'' said Paul Kelleher, superintendent of schools in Lawrence, which ranks high both on the list of Long Island's wealthiest communities and on the list of districts with the largest number of poor students. ''This achievement gap is in every school, it's true even in communities that have a middle-class African-American community.''</p>
        <p>Almost every suburb has at least a small population of black and Hispanic students, but they have been able to hide low scores in an average lifted by the good performance of affluent white and Asian students. Under the new rules, which for the first time will grade every school in the state as meeting, exceeding or falling below standards, the state could declare a school with high average test scores ''below standards'' if minority students at the school, even a handful, scored low.</p>
        <p>The new grades focus on what has become known as the achievement gap by making suburban parents stakeholders in solving it. Low achievement by minority students will no longer be a remote issue; it will affect the public perception of their schools and local property values.</p>
        <p>The Regents' move reflects a change in policy that has been occurring nationwide. Five other states evaluate schools based on how well their minority students score, and the United States Senate is debating a bill this week that would require all states to do the same. The experience of other states,  particularly Texas, suggests that tying school grades to achievement by race offers hope for lifting minority achievement.</p>
        <p>In New York, however, suburban superintendents say that the new grading policy is too onerous, that it will result in failures in many traditionally good school systems that could result in middle-class parents fleeing to private schools.</p>
        <p>In two years as superintendent, Mr. Kelleher of Lawrence has focused intensely on narrowing the achievement gap, increasing teacher mentoring for minority students and creating peer support networks to try to counter the notion prevalent among many black teenagers that doing well in school is ''acting white.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelleher and other superintendents applaud the state for highlighting the gap. They disagree, however, with grading schools on it.</p>
        <p>''The long-term data indicates very clearly there are not quick fixes,'' said Sherry King, superintendent of schools in Mamaroneck, in Westchester County. ''I'm not sure telling us that tomorrow there will be a new report card in the public view is going to change anything.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, superintendents say, punishing schools where minority students do not do well ends up making diversity look like a bad goal. ''When you have socioeconomically diverse communities, then you have these scores printed, it's sometimes hard to convince people that the mixes we're trying to seek are what we want,'' Ms. King said.</p>
        <p>More affluent white parents in a racially mixed school, she suggested, might think their children would be better off in another, less diverse district, or a private school.</p>
        <p>Many superintendents said that separating scores by race makes them uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>''It puts a negative spin on it,'' said Linda Kelly, the superintendent in New Rochelle, where 44.7 percent of the students are white, 30.2 percent are black and 21.2 percent are Hispanic. ''We're proud we're a gateway community. We have diversity, and we think it's the greatest kind of education.''</p>
        <p>Still, more and more educators and parents have begun focusing on the gap in the last year. In October, the College Board released an extensive report documenting the gap. Fifteen diverse middle-class communities nationwide, including Montclair, N.J., have begun sharing ideas on how to close the gap.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts and California recently decided to assess schools based on performance by race, as New York plans to do. In a presidential campaign event to mark National Teachers Day today, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas plans to discuss ways to close the gap.</p>
        <p>Texas, which for nine years has graded schools based on data broken out by race, offers the strongest evidence that the grading of schools tied to race might close the achievement gap.</p>
        <p>In schools that received poor grades, teachers began focusing more intensely on writing and math. Parents and students held pep rallies encouraging students to study hard and do well. Schools plastered the walls with sloganeering posters and reminders of tips that might come in handy on a math exam.</p>
        <p>The result: Texans ranked first among all black fourth graders in the nation on the federally administered National Assessment of Educational Progress and Hispanic Texans sixth. California's black fourth graders, by contrast, ranked 36th, and New York's Hispanic fourth graders ranked 30th.</p>
        <p>As with many tests, some critics contend that Texas teachers are merely ''teaching to the test,'' that they have become exclusively focused on test preparation. That, they say, is not the same as education.</p>
        <p>But Amy Wilkins, a policy analyst for the Education Trust, a Washington-based nonprofit group that focuses on minority and disadvantaged students, said such criticism minimized the improvements in teaching in Texas.</p>
        <p>''Some people claim this is 'drill and kill,' '' she said. ''But more, you see teachers just teaching at a higher level.</p>
        <p>''People say, 'They're so poor, you can't expect much of them,' But if the kids are going to get out of these communities, you have to push them. 'Pity the poor' is going to get these kids nowhere.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
