<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City's Rent Board Recommends Increases of 4% and 6%</title>
    <meta content="09RENT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3D61038F93AA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City's Rent Board Recommends Increases of 4% and 6%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Rent Guidelines Board gives landlords preliminary approval to raise one-year leases by 4 percent and two-year leases by 6 percent for one million apartments covered by rent stabilization; leaders of both landlord and tenant groups voice dissatisfaction with action and vow to press board to revise its numbers at its final vote on June 22; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clearing the way for the highest rent increases since 1996, the New York City Rent Guidelines Board gave landlords preliminary approval last night to raise one-year leases by 4 percent and two-year leases by 6 percent for the one million apartments covered by rent stabilization.</p>
        <p>Leaders of both landlord and tenant groups voiced dissatisfaction with the action and vowed to press the board to revise the numbers at its final vote on June 22. But historically, the board rarely makes major changes in its initial position. Once the increases are final, the new rates will apply to leases renewed between Oct. 1, 2000, and Sept. 30, 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clearing the way for the highest rent increases since 1996, the New York City Rent Guidelines Board gave landlords preliminary approval last night to raise one-year leases by 4 percent and two-year leases by 6 percent for the one million apartments covered by rent stabilization.</p>
        <p>Leaders of both landlord and tenant groups voiced dissatisfaction with the action and vowed to press the board to revise the numbers at its final vote on June 22. But historically, the board rarely makes major changes in its initial position. Once the increases are final, the new rates will apply to leases renewed between Oct. 1, 2000, and Sept. 30, 2001.</p>
        <p>For five of the last six years, the board had reflected the low-inflation era by adopting increases of 2 percent for one-year leases and 4 percent for two-year leases. The exceptions, after a spike in fuel oil prices four years ago, were increases of 5 percent for one-year leases and 7 percent for two-year leases.</p>
        <p>''It's much too high,'' said Michael McKee, associate director of the state's largest tenant group, the New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition. ''It's going to greatly overcompensate landlords more than they need, and it's going to increase their net income.''</p>
        <p>Tenant advocates argued that only a minimal increase was called for. Owners are making record profits, they said, because inflation is low, rent collections are up and the rent increases granted in recent years have been greater than needed.</p>
        <p>But the landlords, whose advocates had requested increases of 9 percent for one-year leases and 15 percent for two-year leases, said  they were still recouping from the lean years of the recession. They called for higher rents to offset rising operating costs.</p>
        <p>''The vote today is in the right direction, but a higher increase is justified,'' said Joseph Strasburgh, president of the Rent Stabilization Association, the biggest organization of owners of rent-stabilized buildings.</p>
        <p>Noting that the two tenant representatives on the board voted for the compromise, he said: ''I'm surprised, honestly surprised, because tenant members have never voted for increased rent guidelines before. They recognized that a higher rate was justified.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Strasburgh said his group would appeal to the board for higher increases, he conceded, ''I do not have high expectations'' of succeeding.</p>
        <p>The focal issue was a 54.8 percent rise in the last year in fuel oil costs for heat and hot water, which the landlords said justified their call for sharply higher rents. But tenant leaders said the rise in oil prices was temporary and should not be the basis for permanently higher rents.</p>
        <p>According to studies by the rent board's staff, general operating costs had undergone almost no increases for two years -- 0.13 percent in 1997 and 0.03 percent in 1998 -- but last year jumped by 7.8 percent, mainly because of oil prices. Another board study, however, also showed that net income, from which profits are drawn, had risen to its highest point in the 10 years that those statistics had been compiled.</p>
        <p>The impending rent increases would have been higher, Mr. McKee said, had it not been for organized tenant pressure that included numerous calls to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's office in recent days.</p>
        <p>''It's all a political process anyway,'' Mr. McKee said, ''and thank goodness he's been running for the Senate.'' He said the mayor was balancing his popularity among renters with the desires of his landlord campaign contributors.</p>
        <p>Putting their political views on display, a few dozen protesting tenants carried signs at the board meeting, in Lower Manhattan, with slogans like ''Rudy Giuliani, the Landlords' Candidate for Senate'' and ''Rudy, Don't Raise Our Rent.''</p>
        <p>Before its final vote, the board is to hold its annual public hearing on June 15 at Cooper Union, at Seventh Street and Third Avenue. Testimony on apartment rents will be from 1 to 5:30 p.m. and 8 to 9:30 p.m. Testimony on residential hotel rents will be from 10 a.m. to noon and 7 to 8:30 p.m.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
