<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Symposium's Vision Fades in Fight Over Martha Graham's Legacy</title>
    <meta content="17GRAH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royalties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frostburg State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Graham, Martha, Center for Contemporary Dance</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Martha (1894-1991)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Protas, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDF123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Symposium's Vision Fades in Fight Over Martha Graham's Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frostburg State University eliminates all of Martha Graham's dances from a three-week educational retreat after her legal heir, Ron Protas, demands dismissal of several teachers who were scheduled to participate; his lawyers also sought to ban readings from any of Graham's writings and any discussion of spiraling dispute that has pitted Protas against dancers from Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance, who have urged other dance companies not to license Graham's choreography from the trust that Protas controls (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hosts of a long-scheduled retreat at Frostburg State University that was to be focused on the work of Martha Graham had hoped their campus in the Allegheny Mountains of western Maryland could be the Camp David of modern dance. But instead of settling the bitter war over the Graham company and its legendary founder's contributions, the university itself was swept up last week in the turmoil.</p>
        <p>Frostburg University abruptly eliminated all of Graham's dances from a three-week educational retreat that began yesterday, after Graham's legal heir, Ron Protas, demanded the dismissal of several teachers who were scheduled to participate. His lawyer also sought a ban on readings from any of Graham's writings on the basis that Mr. Protas had inherited the rights to her works, including books and letters. They also sought a ban on the discussion of the spiraling dispute that has pitted Mr. Protas against dancers from the foundering Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance. The dancers are urging other dance companies not to license Graham's choreography from the trust that Mr. Protas controls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hosts of a long-scheduled retreat at Frostburg State University that was to be focused on the work of Martha Graham had hoped their campus in the Allegheny Mountains of western Maryland could be the Camp David of modern dance. But instead of settling the bitter war over the Graham company and its legendary founder's contributions, the university itself was swept up last week in the turmoil.</p>
        <p>Frostburg University abruptly eliminated all of Graham's dances from a three-week educational retreat that began yesterday, after Graham's legal heir, Ron Protas, demanded the dismissal of several teachers who were scheduled to participate. His lawyer also sought a ban on readings from any of Graham's writings on the basis that Mr. Protas had inherited the rights to her works, including books and letters. They also sought a ban on the discussion of the spiraling dispute that has pitted Mr. Protas against dancers from the foundering Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance. The dancers are urging other dance companies not to license Graham's choreography from the trust that Mr. Protas controls.</p>
        <p>The university refused Mr. Protas's conditions and instead stripped the retreat of Graham's name, replacing it with the muted title ''Dance Legends.'' Students will no longer perform Graham's 1934 ''Panorama,'' but a work donated last week by another modern dance pioneer, ''Harmonica Breakdown'' by Jane Dudley.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has got to put their egos on a shelf and figure what this is all about,'' said Barry Fischer, an associate professor of dance at the university who organized the retreat and offered to play the role of mediator.</p>
        <p>''This is about Graham's legacy,'' he said. ''This is about sharing what Graham has contributed to the 20th century. This is about healing and demonstrating her virtuosity. And this is a horrific global arts tragedy.''</p>
        <p>The university is caught up in the crossfire over Graham's more than 180 works, which constitute a cornerstone of modern dance. The rights to those works belong to Mr. Protas, who earlier this year was dismissed as artistic director of the company amid tensions with the board of the Graham Center, the company's parent organization. The board has temporarily suspended operations of its 500-student school, the company and the junior troupe because of its financial turmoil, blaming Mr. Protas for alienating donors.</p>
        <p>In turn, he complains that the board and company have turned him into a scapegoat for their own mistakes, arguing that much of the resentment toward him is based on petty envy over his rights to Graham's works.</p>
        <p>Last week dancers from the company started circulating a boycott letter, urging other companies not to license and perform Graham's dances until Mr. Protas and the board strike a new licensing agreement that would allow the Graham company to use her dances, something that Mr. Protas is prohibiting.</p>
        <p>It was that boycott letter, university officials said, that prompted Mr. Protas and his representatives to ask for the dismissals of three of the retreat's dance teachers who had signed the letter: Janet Eilber, Elizabeth Auclair and Christophe Jeannot. The trust was not aware at the time that each of the five visiting teachers had signed the letter, including the choreographer Pearl Lang.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, it's personal and antagonistic,'' Mr. Fischer said. ''They told us that we cannot do the repertoire for any performances unless these people are dismissed.''</p>
        <p>The 30 dancers enrolled in the retreat -- who range in age from 13 to 27 -- were initially promised that their lessons would culminate in a campus performance of Graham's ''Panorama.'' Mr. Fischer said the audience would have consisted largely of the family and friends of the dancers. In addition some of the retreat's teachers were scheduled to perform in two community events.</p>
        <p>Michael Quinn, the lawyer representing Mr. Protas, said that the Martha Graham Trust had offered to let the university use the licensed works without charge for teaching lessons. But he said the trust took issue with allowing supporters of the boycott letter to choreograph and perform Graham works.</p>
        <p>''Why would we give these individuals the opportunity to participate in any Martha Graham performance?'' Mr. Quinn asked. ''It's unfortunate they took this tack, and they have to realize they're responsible for these reactions. They are completely to blame for this fallout.''</p>
        <p>He added that he considered the dancers' call for a licensing boycott by other companies ''wrong, both legally and morally'' and said that the trust was exploring legal options. ''I'm not saying there will be a lawsuit,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Protas, who initially asked to lecture at the dance retreat, declined to comment, referring questions to his lawyer.</p>
        <p>Late last week the university sent a letter to Mr. Protas's lawyer, barring his client from attending the retreat, but as of Friday the trust was seeking permission to send a nonparticipating observer to monitor the classes to make sure there is no teaching of Graham. Mr. Fischer said Mr. Protas's lawyer had also asked the university for any videotapes of the dance classes and performances for later review, along with a pledge that the teachers would not read any of Graham's writings aloud to students.</p>
        <p>''I have all these dancers coming to teach, and they have fear and trepidation about Ron confronting them on campus,'' Mr. Fischer said. He added that he had tried to persuade the various factions to use the retreat to discuss reconciliation.</p>
        <p>''I had offered to be a mediator, hands across the water,'' said Mr. Fischer, who wrote his doctoral dissertation based on the early Graham work ''Steps in the Street.'' ''I thought they could come here to speak and start the healing. The Graham Center board was open to that, but I got very little response from the other side.''</p>
        <p>With the loss of Graham's repertory, Frostburg University scrambled to obtain the rights to other dances. Ms. Lang offered three of hers, and other choreographers also offered theirs, Mr. Fischer said. Then he contacted Ms. Dudley, who had danced with Graham beginning in the 1930's and was later dispatched by her to London to build the modern dance movement there. Ms. Dudley granted permission for ''Harmonica Breakdown.''</p>
        <p>At 88 Ms. Dudley is wheelchair bound, but Mr. Fischer said that she considered going to Frostburg with an attendant to watch the performance. But late last week she decided that she was not well enough to attend to show her support. So she added her name to the list of dancers signing the boycott letter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
