<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ebony Ends Publication in South Africa</title>
    <meta content="17EBON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebony (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johnson Publishing</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DE123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ebony Ends Publication in South Africa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>DURBAN, South Africa, July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Johnson Publishing shuts down South African edition of Ebony magazine, which has failed to find profits or many readers in the nearly five years since it began; prosperity has been slower than expected in reaching the country's black majority, and, as a result, the retail market had little interest in advertising to black consumers, and there was little room for a publication celebrating a level of success that few black people in South Africa can yet conceive, let alone achieve; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The South African edition of Ebony magazine, introduced nearly five years ago in the afterglow of the country's triumph over apartheid, has shut down after failing to find profits or many readers.</p>
        <p>On newsstands around the country, a few  left-over copies of last month's issue are all that remains of Ebony South Africa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The South African edition of Ebony magazine, introduced nearly five years ago in the afterglow of the country's triumph over apartheid, has shut down after failing to find profits or many readers.</p>
        <p>On newsstands around the country, a few  left-over copies of last month's issue are all that remains of Ebony South Africa.</p>
        <p>Leaping aboard the post-apartheid bandwagon, Ebony's American publisher, Johnson Publishing, had hoped to bring an institution of African-American culture to the coffee tables of South Africa, a country with enormous economic promise but still wrestling with the legacy of white domination and the struggle for black equality.</p>
        <p>But prosperity has been slower than expected in reaching the black majority. For Ebony South Africa, that meant a retail market with still too little interest in advertising to black consumers and a magazine industry with little room for a publication celebrating a level of success that few black people here can yet conceive, let alone achieve.</p>
        <p>In South Africa, blacks number about 34.6 million out of a total population of 44.7 million, according to the University of South Africa's  mid-year estimate. But millions of them are unemployed and the majority of them are poor, a problem that has worsened in recent years as job losses in government and industry have increased.</p>
        <p>Circulation peaked at 23,880 during the first half of 1999 before dropping to 22,477 during the second half of the year, according to the Audit Bureau of Circulations South Africa.</p>
        <p>Even at its highest circulation, the magazine never pulled in enough advertising, said Christopher D. Benson, a vice president of Johnson Publishing.</p>
        <p>''We didn't see that it was going to improve, and we just had to make the hard decision,'' Mr. Benson said in a telephone interview from Chicago. ''I think it's a function of the commitment that we had to the project that we held on as long as we did in the face of mounting losses.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, according to some industry observers here, the magazine never quite found the necessary balance of American and African content.</p>
        <p>''What they were turning out was more of an American Ebony with a touch of South Africa rather than a South African Ebony with a touch of America,'' said Fraser Mtshali, the editor in chief of Bona. Based in Durban, Bona is aimed at black readers and is the nation's best-selling lifestyle magazine. ''They were seeing South Africa through American eyes.''</p>
        <p>Ebony South Africa's final cover story, on the soccer star Lucas Radebe, was a revealing example, Mr. Mtshali said. Despite his popularity, Mr. Radebe is old news, Mr. Mtshali said. Without some tantalizing new tale about the athlete, there was little to attract the average South African reader, he said.</p>
        <p>Inside the last issue of Ebony South Africa were stories about the American singer Toni Braxton, the American jazz great Louis Armstrong and American athletes running into trouble with the law. There was also a feature on Nelson Mandela and his wife, short profiles of South African musical greats and a mix of health and romance items.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benson, the Johnson Publishing executive, said Ebony South Africa, which had a local staff directed by an American editor and took some of its articles from the American edition, tried to capture the interests and nuances of the South African audience. ''We were constantly evaluating it, through readership surveys, to find out what readers were looking for,'' he said. ''I think the magazine reflected that.''</p>
        <p>Bona, which is published in English as well as in three indigenous languages, is looking for the same successful, free-spending black people in their late 20's and early 30's that Ebony South Africa was aimed at. But Mr. Mtshali said his magazine also tried to embrace younger and older readers as well.</p>
        <p>The cover of the July issue of Bona advertises stories on ''Soccer's New Heroes,'' a ''Wake-up Call From God'' for a South African singer and a ''Baby That Took Five Years to Be Born.''</p>
        <p>''Our market is broader,'' Mr. Mtshali said. ''We're more family oriented.'' And yet, even Bona, which has been around for more than four decades, has watched its circulation fall to just under 178,000 during the second half of last year, compared with 271,230 four years earlier.</p>
        <p>With the economy growing only modestly here, the media sector is struggling to hold onto what share of the market it already has.</p>
        <p>Tribute, a glossy that aims for the same affluent audience that Ebony South Africa was going for, has seen its circulation drop from just over 16,000 in 1994 to slightly more than  10,000 during the second half of last year.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's been the kind of black aspirational success that had been hoped, and that has to have had an effect on publishing,'' said Kerry Swift, who in the late 1970's was an executive editor of Drum, a magazine that made its name as the literary conscience of the struggle against apartheid. Subsequently, Drum became a more conventional life style magazine that now has a weekly circulation of about 137,000 -- down several thousand from its heyday 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>''The market really hurts,'' said Mr. Swift, who is now a director for Core Media Holdings, a South African company that publishes the local editions of publications like PC, an American computer magazine owned by Ziff-Davis.  ''But I think there are much deeper cultural factors at work, too.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
