<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorenstam Has the Right Touch When It Counts</title>
    <meta content="17LPGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D7123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorenstam Has the Right Touch When It Counts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE, N.Y., July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Annika Sorenstam wins Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic golf tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam and Rosie Jones, playing in the final group of the day, were tied for the lead in the Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic this afternoon when they stepped to the 17th tee at Wykagyl Country Club.</p>
        <p>Things looked good for Jones when her tee shot found the fairway, because Sorenstam's shot had landed in the left rough, making a precise shot to the green difficult. A huge oak tree stood to the left, its branches hanging low, leaving Sorenstam only a narrow passage to the green.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam and Rosie Jones, playing in the final group of the day, were tied for the lead in the Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic this afternoon when they stepped to the 17th tee at Wykagyl Country Club.</p>
        <p>Things looked good for Jones when her tee shot found the fairway, because Sorenstam's shot had landed in the left rough, making a precise shot to the green difficult. A huge oak tree stood to the left, its branches hanging low, leaving Sorenstam only a narrow passage to the green.</p>
        <p>She took the only option she had: a low, knock-down shot under the tree. Her shot, with a 7-iron from 132 yards, ended up pin-high, 15 feet to the right of the hole. Sorenstam proceeded to make the putt for birdie that led to a one-shot victory over Jones in the $900,000 tournament, the lone stop in the New York metropolitan area for the Ladies Professional Golf Association Tour.</p>
        <p>''Don't ask me to hit that shot again,'' Sorenstam said about her second shot on the par-4, 396-yard 17th. ''To hit a low shot like that and get it pin-high, I had some luck there. I also knew that if I made that putt it would be the deciding putt.''</p>
        <p>It was and it gave Sorenstam her second victory in a row, third in the last four tournaments, and fifth of the season. She won for the second time in three years at Wykagyl. The first-prize check of $135,000 put Sorenstam, 29, on top of the L.P.G.A. Tour's money list.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam surpassed Karrie Webb, who ended at even-par 213, tied for 18th, today. It is the first time this season that Sorenstam leads the money list. She headed that list in 1997 and 1998, and finished fourth last season. Regaining the top spot has been Sorenstam's goal for almost two years.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam won the 54-hole tournament -- Saturday's third round was canceled because of heavy rain -- with a total of seven-under 206 from rounds of 69-65-72. The 6,161-yard Wykagyl course played much harder today because of Saturday's rain, with only 11 players in the field of 70 breaking par.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam and Jones shot 72 today, and Allison Finney, who finished alone in third after leading the first two rounds, shot 75 for a total of 208. It was the highest finish for Finney since a victory in 1989.</p>
        <p>''My goal was to make some birdies early, put some pressure and make people notice,'' Sorenstam said. ''But I made three bogeys on the front nine, and I was going the opposite direction. I felt like going home, that it wasn't my day. I felt like I had no energy. I tried to stay calm, but I was too calm. I couldn't get going. I was just hanging around.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam hung around long enough to be in contention, but she had plenty of help from Finney and Jones, her partners in the last threesome of the day. While Sorenstam had three bogeys to go with her two birdies on the day, Finney was worse. She made three consecutive bogeys starting on No. 9 and ended the day with six bogeys and two birdies.</p>
        <p>Jones, who started the day a shot behind Sorenstam, had the lead at the turn, but failed to stay on top with bogeys on No. 11 and No. 12 and no birdies the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>''Annika made a great shot on 17,'' said Jones, whose second-place finish was her best of the season. ''She can hit a shot like that and she is the type who can capitalize.''</p>
        <p>''I feel pretty confident for next week,'' Sorenstam said about the United States Open in Libertyville, Ill., which she captured in 1995 and 1996. ''A victory on this course is good because this course is like the U.S. Open.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>SHERRI STEINHAUER, last year's winner in a five-hole playoff with LORI KANE, shot a final-round 72 and finished at 217. . . . JULI INKSTER, who will defend her title in the United States Open this week, shot 72 for a total of 215. . . . BETSY KING, the winner of this tournament in its first two years, in 1990 and 1991, shot 71 and finished at 215. . . . ASHLI BUNCH, whose best finish for the year had been tied for 19th, in the first event of the season, was at six under at the turn, but she played the last five holes at four over par and finished in ninth place at 211.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
