<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gooden Answers The Call In Relief</title>
    <meta content="17PINS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gooden, Dwight</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED8123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gooden Answers The Call In Relief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of New York Yankees relief pitcher Dwight Gooden in victory over Philadelphia Phillies discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The advice from the other Yankees relievers for Dwight Gooden was simple. When warming up in the bullpen during a game, throw 10 fastballs, each harder than the one before, and then start mixing in breaking pitches.</p>
        <p>So Gooden followed their counsel yesterday, warmed up quickly in the third inning to relieve Andy Pettitte, and in his first relief appearance since joining the Yankees' bullpen, he allowed just one run in five and a third innings, on a homer by Philadelphia's Bobby Abreu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The advice from the other Yankees relievers for Dwight Gooden was simple. When warming up in the bullpen during a game, throw 10 fastballs, each harder than the one before, and then start mixing in breaking pitches.</p>
        <p>So Gooden followed their counsel yesterday, warmed up quickly in the third inning to relieve Andy Pettitte, and in his first relief appearance since joining the Yankees' bullpen, he allowed just one run in five and a third innings, on a homer by Philadelphia's Bobby Abreu.</p>
        <p>Gooden did not receive a decision, but he was responsible for holding down the Phillies before the Yankees rallied late in the game to win, 9-8, in 10 innings. ''I'll tell you who deserves credit: Dwight Gooden,'' said Chuck Knoblauch, the Yankees' second baseman.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said: ''I feel good for Doc. He kept us in there. That was big for us, five-plus innings. Somebody had to stop them.''</p>
        <p>Gooden started against the Mets on July 8 and won using his old mechanics, with his leg kick in the middle of his delivery. But he worked from the stretch yesterday, keeping his right foot anchored on the pitching rubber, something he decided to do once he was assigned to the bullpen. ''I felt good over all,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Cone Back on the Mound</p>
        <p>David Cone will pitch against the Phillies tonight. It will be his first start since Baltimore slammed four homers against him in five and two-thirds innings on July 4. ''To me, his start tomorrow is very important,'' Manager Joe Torre said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The manager has maintained all along that his intention is to keep Cone in the rotation. The Yankees have more depth and other options with experienced pitchers like Dwight Gooden and Ramiro Mendoza, and if Cone continues to struggle, Torre's hand may be forced. If Torre has any inclination to make a change, he will probably not even hint at those feelings until after he decided to switch and told Cone, out of respect for the veteran. The Yankees, who have won only 25 of their last 55 games, desperately need a lengthy winning streak, and it seems Torre does not have so much room for patience.</p>
        <p>Cone (1-7), who did not post a victory in May or June, was supposed to pitch July 9, in the last game before the All-Star Game break. He was replaced in that start when Torre elected to use Andy Pettitte on three days' rest instead. ''Emotionally, it had to feel like a couple of months to him,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Mendoza, coming back from arm stiffness, had a lengthy bullpen session yesterday and threw well. Assuming he does not have any setbacks, he could begin his minor league rehabilitation stint with Class AA Norwich in a couple of days.</p>
        <p>Posada Likely to Sit Out</p>
        <p>Jorge Posada, given a one-game suspension for his part in a fight with Tampa Bay on July 1, is expected to serve that penalty tonight, a matter of convenience for the Yankees. David Cone will pitch tonight's game, and he usually teams with Chris Turner these days.</p>
        <p>Posada was not going to play anyway, so he will use the day to serve the suspension. Posada was initially going to serve his suspension yesterday, but the Yankees' rotation was altered by Saturday's rainout, with Cone's start being moved from yesterday to today.</p>
        <p>The utilityman Clay Bellinger was promoted from Class AAA Columbus to the majors yesterday, with outfielder Luke Wilcox sent to Columbus to make room for Bellinger. For tonight's game, Bellinger will serve as the backup catcher.</p>
        <p>Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, declined to answer whether Posada would serve his penalty today. ''We'll see,'' he said. ''I've got no control over when a player serves his suspension.''</p>
        <p>Weather Worries</p>
        <p>There were rainless windows of weather on Saturday after the Yankees postponed their game with the Florida Marlins. But the contest was called off because of the field conditions, General Manager Brian Cashman said, and not the ominous forecast. ''If we played that game,'' he said, ''it would've been the worst conditions we've played with since I came to the team in 1987. It would've been a mistake. You'd hate to end Preston Wilson's season, or Bernie Williams's season, just because we wanted to get a game in.''</p>
        <p>The game will most likely not be rescheduled unless it has playoff implications for either team.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
