<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summing Up: Is Our House Divided by Race?</title>
    <meta content="LTR001644" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">President's Initiative for One America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1D7123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summing Up: Is Our House Divided by Race?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letter from Ben Johnson, assistant to Pres Clinton and director of President's Inititiatve for One America, comments on series on race relations; says Clinton recognized early on that race is a problem we cannot ignore, and has succeeded in getting American public to address racial issues in earnest</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your six-week series ''How Race Is Lived in America'' is truly eye-opening and a tremendous benefit to the American people. But I am baffled by the fact that President Clinton is being criticized by some, like a July 5 letter writer, who think that the president's race initiative died when his advisory board issued its report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your six-week series ''How Race Is Lived in America'' is truly eye-opening and a tremendous benefit to the American people. But I am baffled by the fact that President Clinton is being criticized by some, like a July 5 letter writer, who think that the president's race initiative died when his advisory board issued its report.</p>
        <p>In fact, John Hope Franklin, the chairman, and the board made several recommendations to the president, one of which encouraged him to establish a White House office to continue looking into the elimination of racial disparities among Americans. In February of last year,  he established the office known as the President's Initiative for One America.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton touches on race in almost all of his speeches. Furthermore, he has appointed more minority-group members and women to cabinet and White House positions than any other president in history. In addition, he continues to prod the major power sectors in the country  to seriously examine their roles in creating opportunities for people of all races. For example, as a result of the president's meeting with corporate chief executives in April, 25 leading high-tech companies pledged $250 million for science-based minority training to promote more diversity.</p>
        <p>More important, unlike any of his recent predecessors, President Clinton has succeeded in getting the American public to address racial problems in earnest. He recognized early on that race is a problem that we cannot ignore, especially if we want to continue to be the leading democracy in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>BEN JOHNSON  Washington, July 12, 2000</p>
        <p>The writer is assistant to the president and director of the President's Initiative for One America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
