<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Takes Tireless Chairmen To Make Those Tables Hum</title>
    <meta content="17CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brodsky, Art</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DF123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Takes Tireless Chairmen To Make Those Tables Hum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott column on a hand of bridge played by Art Brodsky, a tournament champion on Long Island, at annual party of Nassau-Suffolk Bridge Association; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the many thousands of volunteers who do significant work for the game, the hardest working are the tournament chairmen who arrange the details of sectional championships and other events. They have to plan schedules, make advance arrangements with hotels and directors, and see to countless matters during several days of play. Few players think of expressing thanks.</p>
        <p>The Greater New York Bridge Association was very lucky to have Bill Rosenbaum serve in that capacity for 15 years. He recently handed over the reins to Brady Richter. Other tournament chairmen in the New York metropolitan area are Thomas Simon in Westchester, Harris Schenker and Howard Halpern in New Jersey and Art Brodsky on Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the many thousands of volunteers who do significant work for the game, the hardest working are the tournament chairmen who arrange the details of sectional championships and other events. They have to plan schedules, make advance arrangements with hotels and directors, and see to countless matters during several days of play. Few players think of expressing thanks.</p>
        <p>The Greater New York Bridge Association was very lucky to have Bill Rosenbaum serve in that capacity for 15 years. He recently handed over the reins to Brady Richter. Other tournament chairmen in the New York metropolitan area are Thomas Simon in Westchester, Harris Schenker and Howard Halpern in New Jersey and Art Brodsky on Long Island.</p>
        <p>These chairmen would probably admit that their own playing improves when they are not being pursued by competitors complaining about the room temperature, a shortage of drinking water or other details. On the diagramed deal Brodsky was playing at the annual party of the Nassau-Suffolk Bridge Association in Smithtown, N.Y., in May; the atmosphere was relaxed, and nobody was pestering him.</p>
        <p>At the tables at which South doubled an opening bid of one diamond, North-South were in difficulty. They were likely to be in jeopardy if North responded one heart or one no-trump, and a penalty pass is not a normal action.</p>
        <p>Brodsky chose a one no-trump overcall, describing his hand accurately at the risk of missing a major-suit fit. This ended the bidding, and the club queen was led. East signaled with the eight, and the king won.</p>
        <p>There was no obvious way for South to proceed, and he chose to work on diamonds despite East's opening bid in the suit. He led the queen and was delighted to see the jack appear on his left. He played low from dummy, and East held up the king to prevent the declarer taking four tricks in the suit.</p>
        <p>Now Brodsky made a subtle play. If he had led the diamond 10, the king would have been held up again. Instead he led the diamond three to dummy's nine. If East had won with the king, a later overtake of the 10 with the ace would have produced three more diamond tricks.</p>
        <p>East chose to hold up again, and South had manufactured a useful entry to the dummy, which he used. He led a spade, and when the nine appeared, he finessed the 10 hopefully. When this won, he continued with the spade king and emerged with eight tricks. The defense collected only one spade trick and four clubs. East realized too late that he would have done better to take his diamond king at some point, giving the defense six tricks.</p>
        <p>''I've been waiting many years for that combination,'' Brodsky said later. His score of 120 was the top in two sections of play and helped him and his wife, Pat, to finish second overall in the event.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Championships will be played this week at the Smithtown Sheraton Hotel in Hauppauge, N.Y. This is the schedule of major events:</p>
        <p>Wednesday: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Limited Knockout Teams, 1 p.m. and continues</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Pairs and Stratified Newcomers Pairs, 1 and 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Thursday: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Newcomers Pairs and Stratiflighted Swiss Teams, 1 and 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Friday: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Newcomers Pairs and Stratiflighted Open Pairs, 1 and 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Saturday: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Newcomers Pairs, IMP Pairs and Stratified Open Pairs, 1 and 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Sunday: Stratiflighted Swiss Teams and Stratified Senior Teams, 11 a.m. (two sessions)</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
