<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Two Fouls, It Is Clear Sailing for Jones</title>
    <meta content="17OLYM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1215683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EED9123BF934A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Two Fouls, It Is Clear Sailing for Jones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marion Jones (long jump) and Regina Jacobs (1,500 meter run) qualify for US Olympic team at trials in Sacramento; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The warning signs for failure had been there all season. And when Marion Jones looked to see whether her second long jump today had been fair or foul, she saw the official raise a red flag. Foul. She had stepped beyond the takeoff board. One more foul, or a jump shorter than 20 feet 11 1/4 inches, and she would be out of the Olympic trials. Any hopes of winning five gold medals at the 2000 Summer Games would be gone.</p>
        <p>''For a blink of any eye, I said, 'O.K., I've got one more. If I don't get into it, this dream will be over,' '' Jones said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The warning signs for failure had been there all season. And when Marion Jones looked to see whether her second long jump today had been fair or foul, she saw the official raise a red flag. Foul. She had stepped beyond the takeoff board. One more foul, or a jump shorter than 20 feet 11 1/4 inches, and she would be out of the Olympic trials. Any hopes of winning five gold medals at the 2000 Summer Games would be gone.</p>
        <p>''For a blink of any eye, I said, 'O.K., I've got one more. If I don't get into it, this dream will be over,' '' Jones said.</p>
        <p>Then she looked into the stands and saw her coach, Trevor Graham, and her husband, C. J. Hunter, making encouraging gestures. No problem, she thought. If she got a legal jump, it would be far. She had to make the top eight to qualify for the final three jumps, and she comfortably sailed into fourth place with a leap of 22-1 3/4, puffing her cheeks and exhaling in relief afterward.</p>
        <p>But she was not finished. Before the competition was over, Jones had jumped 23- 1/2. It was the fourth-longest jump in the world this year and clear evidence that she could compete for a gold medal in the event in September at the Summer Olympics in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Dawn Burrell, who defeated Jones at the 1999 national championships, was second at 22-10 1/2, and Shana Williams was third at 22-6 1/2.</p>
        <p>The comeback of Jackie Joyner-Kersee, however, fell short. The greatest female athlete of her generation finished sixth at 21-10 3/4, never seeming comfortable on the runway, chopping her steps and never making a serious threat to qualify for her fifth Olympic team.</p>
        <p>However, Joyner-Kersee, 38, is a friend and idol to Jones, and she spoke some assuring words before Jones took her pressure-filled third jump. ''Just get a fair jump and you'll be easily into the finals,'' Joyner-Kersee said.</p>
        <p>''I was quite concerned,'' Jones, said. But if she was, she did not show that to her competitors.</p>
        <p>''Marion's a great competitor, but what I admire is that she knew exactly what to do,'' Joyner-Kersee said. ''If you're going to be the best in the world, you can't be worried about what's happening, only about what you have to do to execute. I didn't feel any concern in her voice.''</p>
        <p>Her winning jump was nearly a foot short of her career best of 23-11 3/4, but it was within a few inches of the year's best of 23-3 1/4 set by Fiona May of Italy. As significant as the distance of Jones's victory was her grace under pressure and fierce desire to prevail.</p>
        <p>She had won the 100 meters on Saturday in 10.88 seconds, the second-fastest time in the world this year, and she needed three jumps today to adjust her searing speed to the runway. She also needed time to acclimate herself to a strong tailwind that pushed her toward the takeoff board, forcing her to chop her steps on her first two jumps, both fouls.</p>
        <p>''I was aware of the wind,'' Jones said of her third jump. ''I stayed on the runway until I had a nice gust and it worked out perfectly.''</p>
        <p>This season, facing much criticism about her clumsy technique, Jones decided to simplify her style, dropping any pretense at technical expertise and relying on her speed to jump far. ''I tried to change too much, to turn her into a power jumper,'' Graham said. ''Last year, she tried to get a big hop on the takeoff board, but she didn't go anywhere. She went up and right back down. This year, we're forgetting all about that and we'll use her speed.''</p>
        <p>She began the season with a disappointing jump of 20-7 in May in Japan, then leaped 22-10 1/2 on June 24 at the Prefontaine Classic in Eugene, Ore., but her jumping remained erratic. She qualified only fifth on Friday night at the trials with a mediocre jump of 21-6 3/4, and seemed to wince in the pit after one awkward  landing. Several jumping experts, including the world record-holder Mike Powell, have offered to help Jones, but each time they have been rebuffed.</p>
        <p>''She might do something right,  and the world record could happen,'' Powell said. ''But it's better to know for sure 'I can do this,' as opposed to rolling the dice. She needs to know how to run the runway and jump instead of just sprinting.''</p>
        <p>Graham said that others were just seeking news media attention and Jones said she would never abandon the coach who had nurtured her career to such dominance in the sprints.</p>
        <p>She did, after all, win three national titles and a bronze medal at the 1999 world championships with Graham as her coach.</p>
        <p>''People are going to criticize, regardless,'' Jones said. ''We've decided we're going to focus on what Marion has to do. I knew I still had a long jump in me and I was able to carry through.''</p>
        <p>Joyner-Kersee, however, did not have a long jump in her, and she could only match a distance that she had jumped back in her college days at U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>She retired in 1998 and, in her comeback, did not show any of the form that won her an Olympic gold medal in the long jump in 1988 and bronzes in 1992 and 1996. She said she felt some discomfort in her left leg, passed on her fifth jump, then ran through the pit on her sixth.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't there,'' she said, adding that she had no regrets about trying a comeback.</p>
        <p>''I knew it was a long shot,'' Joyner-Kersee said.</p>
        <p>Jones said that this would in no way diminish the accomplishments of her idol.</p>
        <p>''This doesn't take anything away from Jackie,'' Jones said. ''In my opinion, she's the greatest ever. Nothing will take away from that.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: THE ROAD TO SYDNEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
