<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Can't Stand Rain of Heat 3-Pointers</title>
    <meta content="18KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFD7173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Can't Stand Rain of Heat 3-Pointers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Miami Heat defeats New York Knickerbockers, 87-81, to take 3-2 lead in Eastern Conference semifinal playoff series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was confusion creeping into the Knicks' scrambled minds as the Heat players began shuffling the ball from hand to hand, from man to man, like street hustlers in a game of three-card monte.</p>
        <p>The perplexed Knicks were crossed up. They could not decide who to follow. Dan Majerle? Bruce Bowen? Anthony Carter? Over the last 2 minutes 30 seconds of a pivotal Game 5, they picked wrong over and over again. Twice, they allowed the rickety Majerle to drift into open space on the perimeter for two 3-pointers that poured down the net over an 11-second span. Then, Majerle summoned a burst of speed out of his jalopy engine as he darted by Sprewell, plunged into the paint, pulled two Knicks with him, and caught Bowen out the corner of his eye.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was confusion creeping into the Knicks' scrambled minds as the Heat players began shuffling the ball from hand to hand, from man to man, like street hustlers in a game of three-card monte.</p>
        <p>The perplexed Knicks were crossed up. They could not decide who to follow. Dan Majerle? Bruce Bowen? Anthony Carter? Over the last 2 minutes 30 seconds of a pivotal Game 5, they picked wrong over and over again. Twice, they allowed the rickety Majerle to drift into open space on the perimeter for two 3-pointers that poured down the net over an 11-second span. Then, Majerle summoned a burst of speed out of his jalopy engine as he darted by Sprewell, plunged into the paint, pulled two Knicks with him, and caught Bowen out the corner of his eye.</p>
        <p>Bowen was standing in the corner of the court unnoticed when Majerle flicked the ball in his hands. With the menacing Alonzo Mourning sidelined and out of harm's way as a victim of fouls, the Knicks gave up a 3-pointer with 35.2 seconds left to a player who only shot twice all night.</p>
        <p>That was the crushing moment. There was a 6-point Heat lead and no time to recover as the Knicks went on to lose Game 5, 87-81, tonight.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' life span in this four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference semifinal may be fleeting as well. Down by three games to two, they are one game from elimination, with Game 6 set for Friday at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''You have to believe,'' said Allan Houston, who finished with 12 points. ''If you don't believe, you might as well go home.''</p>
        <p>If a team does have elasticity in its game, it's the resilient Knicks. But the odds are against them. In the history of seven-game series, the winner of Game 5 has gone on to advance 84 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>''We have to get the job done, or it's summer vacation,'' said Patrick Ewing, who finished with 16 points and 11 rebounds. ''I think we are going to win and come back here on Sunday and then win on Sunday.''</p>
        <p>It's in his proud nature to be optimistic. But there was a deflating feel to the end of yet another game when the Knicks continued their habit of losing their composure at the end of games. For most of the night, Latrell Sprewell tried in vain to sweep the rest of his team -- including his invisible co-star, Houston -- into his whirlwind of energy.</p>
        <p>But even Sprewell seemed to come undone in the end. After countering Jamal Mashburn (21 points) all night, Sprewell started running low on temperament. Perhaps trying to do too much to win the game, he scored 24 points and grabbed 5 steals, but he rushed shots, drove into too much traffic and hit just  1 of 6 shots in the fourth quarter. While he helped the Knicks pull even with the Heat at 68-68 with his lone field goal down the stretch, Sprewell was also part of an uninspiring finish by the defense.</p>
        <p>''We didn't lose our legs in the fourth quarter, we lost our will,'' Coach Jeff Van Gundy said. ''We certainly didn't have enough will to make the stops we needed. Right now, everyone wants to focus on individual performances but I want them to focus on the team performance.''</p>
        <p>As a team, the Knicks shot a series-high 47.3 percent, but were outrebounded by 42-32. They turned the ball over just 7 times, but went to the free-throw line just 12 times while the Heat took 27 attempts.</p>
        <p>''Hey, they're at home,'' Sprewell said. ''They are going to get the calls. We should have also been more aggressive. We can't hang our heads now.</p>
        <p>''We're going back home. And it's no secret that we have to win. To do so, we have to play better defense, especially down the stretch. We didn't do a good job rotating to the open man. They moved the ball well, and we were a little lost out there.''</p>
        <p>Once the last buzzer sounded, Sprewell slowly left the floor like a wind-up toy on it's last tick. He was out of energy and out of time. On the other end of the floor, the Heat players were raising their arms in victory. Two of the Heat players weren't on the court at the end but had everything to do with the victory. Mourning fouled out with 56 seconds left in the game, but had fought through double-teams for 18 points and rose up for 4 blocked shots.</p>
        <p>Tim Hardaway limped out of the building,  but not before he scored 10 third-quarter points as he blew by the Knicks' Game 4 hero, Charlie Ward, in a nice cameo that gave his team a 64-55 lead with 1:54 left in the third quarter. ''Tim is really playing with a lot of guts right now,'' Coach Pat Riley said. ''We needed him in the third quarter.''</p>
        <p>He gave the Heat a lead the Knicks couldn't overcome. They managed to tie up the game in the fourth, but never barged ahead. Meanwhile, the Heat leaned on the courage of Carter. He hit a key jumper in the panicked moments before the shot-clock expired. Off a turnover by Sprewell, Carter then led a fast break that ended up with Majerle scoring on a layup and drawing a foul with 5:16 left. Majerle converted the 3-point play to put the Heat up, 73-68. Majerle then answered Houston's first field goal of the second half with a 3-pointer with 2:27 on the clock to give his team a 77-70 lead.</p>
        <p>But the cool-headed Ward came right back with another three before Majerle trumped that with his own three. After a layup by Ewing, after Mourning picked his sixth foul, Houston went to the free-throw line. He hit both with 56.2 seconds on the clock. And the Knicks trailed, 80-77. But off the penetration of Majerle, Bowen ended up open for a 3-pointer with 35.2 seconds left -- a shot that put the Knicks away.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating,'' Houston said. ''But we have another opportunity to get a win in New York. We have to get to a Game 7. We still have that chance to do something special.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>MARCUS CAMBY had a miserable night. He missed his first five shots, was burned by CLARENCE WEATHERSPOON on a series of drives and fouled out after 23 minutes on the floor. He ended the game 1 for 6, with just four rebounds and no blocked shots. . . . ALLAN HOUSTON scored just one field goal in the second half.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
