<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="18TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D6173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Signed RHP Jason Davis.  DETROIT TIGERS--Released LHP Jim Poole. Purchased the contract of LHP Allen McDill from Toledo of the International League.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS--Optioned RHP Chad Durbin to Omaha of the Pacific Coast League. Purchased the contract of LHP Paul Spoljaric from Omaha.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Agreed to terms with OF Rickey Henderson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Signed RHP Jason Davis.  DETROIT TIGERS--Released LHP Jim Poole. Purchased the contract of LHP Allen McDill from Toledo of the International League.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS--Optioned RHP Chad Durbin to Omaha of the Pacific Coast League. Purchased the contract of LHP Paul Spoljaric from Omaha.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Agreed to terms with OF Rickey Henderson.</p>
        <p>National League  MILWAUKEE BREWERS--Placed RHP Curtis Leskanic on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 12. Recalled LHP Ray King from Indianapolis of the International League.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Placed RHP Joe Nathan on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to May 13. Recalled RHP Ben Weber from Fresno of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  JETS--Signed DT Richard Seals. Waived FS Pedro Cirino.  ATLANTA FALCONS--Agreed to terms with LB Mark Simoneau and CB Darrick Vaughn to three-year contracts.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Signed DE Rob Meier and RB Shyrone Stith.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS--Agreed to terms with Craig Hartsburg, coach, on a two-year contract extension.  MINNESOTA WILD--Signed F Kai Nurminen and F Brendan Walsh.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  MLS--Announced New England F Eduardo Hurtado has been transferred to an Ecuadorian first division club.  COLUMBUS CREW--Signed F Jeff Cunningham. Named Marcello Carrera part-time assistant coach.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>NCAA--Placed the men's cross country and track and field programs at Jackson State on five years probation for violations.  BALL STATE--Named Tim Buckley men's basketball coach.  DEPAUL--Announced junior basketball G Marlon London will transfer to the school from Kansas.  MISSISSIPPI--Announced the resignation of Pat Harrison, baseball coach, and Keith Kessinger, assistant baseball coach.  PACE--Named Henry Manning baseball coach.  SIENA--Named William Garrett and John Dunne men's assistant basketball coaches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
