<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Puck-ish Ramblings in Midsummer</title>
    <meta content="18EDER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drury, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hunts in Dreams (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DD163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Puck-ish Ramblings in Midsummer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews Hunts in Dreams by Tom Drury; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HUNTS IN DREAMS  By Tom Drury  200 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $22.</p>
        <p>How incompetent at reality the characters are in Tom Drury's beguiling novel -- beguiling and itself not 100 percent reality-competent. A common enough thing, this, in an age when reality can seem to float and a brightly attuned young writer may not feel authorized to assert it.</p>
        <p>In fact, the only truly competent character in the book is Micah, a little boy. But then in childhood, where the mind needs straying room to accommodate growth (an infant's skull bones drift for the same reason), it is essential sometimes to see things askew. In that respect, competence at reality lies in being incompetent at it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HUNTS IN DREAMS  By Tom Drury  200 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $22.</p>
        <p>How incompetent at reality the characters are in Tom Drury's beguiling novel -- beguiling and itself not 100 percent reality-competent. A common enough thing, this, in an age when reality can seem to float and a brightly attuned young writer may not feel authorized to assert it.</p>
        <p>In fact, the only truly competent character in the book is Micah, a little boy. But then in childhood, where the mind needs straying room to accommodate growth (an infant's skull bones drift for the same reason), it is essential sometimes to see things askew. In that respect, competence at reality lies in being incompetent at it.</p>
        <p>Micah is the youngest member of the Darling family, residents of a Midwestern farm town. Like Charles, his father; Joan, his mother; and his stepsister Lyris, he spends a long summer weekend wandering. Even in the most traditionally settled American heartland life is an unmoored thing, ''Hunts in Dreams'' suggests. The title sketches the theme.</p>
        <p>The four Darlings amble through something resembling separate fugue states; so do the other people in the book. Sunny, funny and lurching into disconcert, the fugues are musical as well as dismaying, their zigzags the best attempt the characters can make at straight lines.</p>
        <p>Charles, the local plumber, pursues a well-meaning principle of order without knowing how to go about it. He makes a series of far-fetched efforts to recover a fine old shotgun his stepfather once gave to the town minister. The minister's widow hung it over her fireplace and refused to sell it to Charles, who finds it demeaning that a thoroughbred weapon should be reduced to an ornament.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Joan, convinced that their marriage has gone dead, packs to attend an animal-rights convention in a nearby city, hoping to find romance and change her life. A vague suspicion prompts Charles to the antiromance precaution of emptying her makeup kit and substituting walnuts. Joan and the lover she acquires -- a smitten doctor neighbor who has followed her to the city -- nibble the walnuts to go with the vodka from her hotel room's minibar.</p>
        <p>Lyris, a teenager, has only joined the Darlings recently. An unmarried actress at the time of her daughter's birth, Joan had left her at an orphanage; later Lyris lived with four successive sets of foster parents. When explosives were found in the home of the last set (Lyris scorched her jeans while ironing them and the smoke alerted the authorities), Joan was traced.</p>
        <p>Though welcomed into her family, Lyris is insecure; on the same night that Joan goes off and Charles is breaking into the gun-widow's house (the widow smashes him in the nose with a heavy coat hanger and gives him a cold compress for the blood), she takes a ride with Follard, an unbalanced young man. When she nervously asks to go home, his answer is all the creepier for its fashionable blur of text and reality:</p>
        <p>''Well, I would take you, but the car's out of gas. Or it's thrown a rod, or the key's in the trunk, or there is no car. This is another story that I'm telling now, and this one is true. He wanted to take her home but could not, and therefore, with nothing better to do. . . . You see where I'm going.''</p>
        <p>As for Micah, deposited at his grandmother's so Charles can go burglarizing, he is unable to sleep. He ventures out in his pajamas and makes a dreamlike peregrination through the town's deserted streets.</p>
        <p>It is one of a number of lovely passages stretched between lyrical and cockeyed that give a Puck-like air to Drury's midsummer night's dream-hunt (even to its subliminal ''what fools these mortals be''). When Lyris manages to get away from Follard by jumping into the river and taking to the dark woods, she removes her wet socks under the gaze of an owl in a nearby tree. She resumes her flight: ''Soon the owl overtook her, flying low beneath the branches with one of her socks snagged in its talons. Its body hung like a weight from the yoke of its wings.''</p>
        <p>Misdirections abound, though most come out all right. Follard's later evil efforts, for instance, are frustrated by his pure incompetence. Drury is tender toward his characters (like many of his contemporaries, he uses an absurdist black light, but in his case the result is shade more than darkness). Meaning well, they occasionally manage to do well.</p>
        <p>There is a lovely sequence in which, with some difficulty, Charles gets Micah the pet goat he longs for.  An old farmer advises about the diet: separate buckets of oats, lamb feed and sunflower seed. To a child, suddenly, it is the newfound joy of the world's specifics: ''Many buckets, and one with black sunflower seeds . . .  The future was taking shape before Micah's eyes and it was good.''</p>
        <p>Joan's wandering is sensitively handled for a while. Her tryst with the doctor -- a figure of at least equal zaniness and misdirection -- is blissful and comically vague. When they stroll out together in the early morning, the walk seems more real to her than the love-making. ''Now what do we do?'' she wonders. ''We have no present.'' She continues her fugue alone; and here, in a series of incidents I would have to call toylike, Drury falls into some arch contrivance.</p>
        <p>Generally, he avoids it. ''Hunts in Dreams'' is just short of allegory, but the characters have a comic innocence that persuades us quite a way into even their more far-fetched ventures. The Darlings' struggles to find a balance in an unmoored world carry some real eloquence. ''Sometimes I feel like whatever I'm supposed to be is tacked to the back wall of the universe and moving away from me at the speed of light,'' Joan complains, uniting the contemporary states of physics and feelings.</p>
        <p>Carrying on with physics a moment to suggest the problem with this perceptive and captivating book: the characters are convincing in the postmodern wooziness with which they feel and think, most of all about their own lives. These float touchingly, but Drury cannot or does not choose to get them to tread hard enough for a reality that is more than conceptual. They do fine as wave; not so well as particle.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
