<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y18CAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3DB173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>BUCHANAN RESIGNATION SOUGHT  Reform Party leaders in Colorado and Georgia have called on Pat Buchanan, the leading contender for the Reform presidential nomination, to resign from the party on the grounds that he has been spreading hate and intolerance and ignoring the party procedures. At a meeting last Saturday, the executive committee of the party in Colorado passed a resolution saying that Mr. Buchanan was ''promoting discrimination, intolerance and hatred against various groups of law-abiding American citizens.'' In addition, it condemned remarks attributed to Mr. Buchanan in which homosexuality was called a disorder. ''We just don't have any room for intolerance,'' Victor Good, the party chairman, said. The Reform Party in Georgia called for Mr. Buchanan's resignation after he invited state residents to a May 21 state convention that party leaders said was scheduled illegally. Jim Mangia, secretary of the national Reform Party, predicted that more states would move against Mr. Buchanan. Bay Buchanan, Mr. Buchanan's sister and chief strategist, called the Colorado and Georgia moves ''much ado about nothing.''</p>
        <p>Irvin Molotsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>BUCHANAN RESIGNATION SOUGHT  Reform Party leaders in Colorado and Georgia have called on Pat Buchanan, the leading contender for the Reform presidential nomination, to resign from the party on the grounds that he has been spreading hate and intolerance and ignoring the party procedures. At a meeting last Saturday, the executive committee of the party in Colorado passed a resolution saying that Mr. Buchanan was ''promoting discrimination, intolerance and hatred against various groups of law-abiding American citizens.'' In addition, it condemned remarks attributed to Mr. Buchanan in which homosexuality was called a disorder. ''We just don't have any room for intolerance,'' Victor Good, the party chairman, said. The Reform Party in Georgia called for Mr. Buchanan's resignation after he invited state residents to a May 21 state convention that party leaders said was scheduled illegally. Jim Mangia, secretary of the national Reform Party, predicted that more states would move against Mr. Buchanan. Bay Buchanan, Mr. Buchanan's sister and chief strategist, called the Colorado and Georgia moves ''much ado about nothing.''</p>
        <p>Irvin Molotsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>BUSH ENDORSED AS REAGAN'S HEIR  Nancy Reagan endorsed Gov. George W. Bush of Texas for president yesterday, claiming him as an heir to the conservative political tradition of her husband, former President Ronald Reagan. ''His agenda of tax cuts, smaller government and a strong national defense will build pride in America just as it did when my husband was president,'' Mrs. Reagan said. ''This is a candidate Ronnie would be proud of.'' Mr. Reagan, 89, has Alzheimer's disease and no longer makes public appearances or statements. Mrs. Reagan has offered her endorsement of every Republican presidential candidate since her husband left office in 1988. Mr. Bush proudly embraced the Reagan mantle. ''I thank her for her endorsement and pledge an optimistic, positive campaign, in the Reagan tradition, to renew America's spirit and encourage a new era of personal responsibility and freedom,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>James Sterngold (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>THE VOTE IS IN THE MAIL  Unable to affect the presidential nominating contests at this late point, Oregon voters used Tuesday's vote-by-mail primary, the nation's first, to reject ballot proposals calling for a new gasoline tax and limits on damages in personal-injury lawsuits. Oregon residents have voted by mail in local elections and special statewide elections since the early 1980's, but they had never before voted entirely by mail in a regularly scheduled election. A footnote: Vice President Al Gore and Mr. Bush won going away, as expected, not that it made any difference in the nominating contests. And the turnout? The secretary of state's office put it at 47 percent, the highest since the 1992 primary, when turnout hit 49.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Evelyn Nieves (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE SENATE</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN FINANCING LOOPHOLE  A bipartisan group of senators introduced legislation yesterday to close a loophole in federal tax and election law that allows nonprofit groups to raise and spend unlimited amounts of money on political campaigns with virtually no disclosure. Organizations like the Sierra Club and the Republicans for Clean Air have taken advantage of the provision, Section 527 of the Internal Revenue Code, to raise and spend millions of dollars on behalf of candidates. They can run television advertisements and conduct telephone campaigns as long as they do not explicitly advocate the election or defeat of a candidate. The proposed legislation, similar to a bill already before the House, would require that such groups register with the Federal Election Commission and comply with federal election laws. It also would require that they disclose their existence to the Internal Revenue Service and that they reveal their large contributors and expenditures. One of the sponsors of the Senate bill, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, said that passage of the measure would ''remove 527s from the shadows and expose their activities to the light of public scrutiny.'' Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, another sponsor and longtime advocate of campaign finance reform, called the proliferation of 527 organizations ''a pernicious evil'' that has helped bring American politics to an all-time low.</p>
        <p>John M. Broder (NYT)</p>
        <p>LIBYAN INNUENDO  With an uphill battle to keep Senator Conrad Burns, Republican of Montana, from winning a third term, Brian Schweitzer, a Democratic challenger, has found another obstacle to overcome. Mr. Schweitzer said this week that the same phone bank company that made negative calls against Senator John McCain of Arizona before the Republican presidential primary in South Carolina was making calls to Montana on behalf of Mr. Burns. Mr. Schweitzer said a Houston firm, Voter Consumer Research, asked Montana voters if they had been aware that Mr. Schweitzer had once worked in Libya, ''a known terrorist state.'' Yes, he did once work in Libya, Mr. Schweitzer said, in 1980, as an importer of American-made farm equipment for farms being worked by Americans. And if there was something wrong with that, he went on, ''whoever is paying for this dirty trick push poll needs a civics lesson.'' Well, it was not the Burns campaign, said Tricia Pearson, the campaign coordinator. ''We're not doing it,'' she said. ''We don't know anything about it.''</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
