<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Pegasus' 3-5 Choice At Pimlico</title>
    <meta content="18RACI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DE173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Pegasus' 3-5 Choice At Pimlico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Post position draw held at Pimlico Race Course for Preakness Stakes (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus arrived at Pimlico Race Course with royal fanfare today after a flight from Louisville, where he won the Kentucky Derby a week and a half ago and put himself in position to become the 12th horse in racing history to win the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus, the star of the 3-year-old class, was made the 3-5 favorite to win the Preakness Stakes on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus arrived at Pimlico Race Course with royal fanfare today after a flight from Louisville, where he won the Kentucky Derby a week and a half ago and put himself in position to become the 12th horse in racing history to win the Triple Crown.</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus, the star of the 3-year-old class, was made the 3-5 favorite to win the Preakness Stakes on Saturday.</p>
        <p>The final test in the Triple Crown, the Belmont Stakes, is June 10. His chances were not particularly affected, for better or for worse, at the draw for post positions today. He received slot No. 7 in the field of eight starters.</p>
        <p>In fact, the draw gave none of the starters much cause for either joy or anxiety. Hugh Hefner, a long shot at 20-1, drew the rail.</p>
        <p>The speed horse Hal's Hope drew the outside and was also listed at 20-1. Red Bullet, who did not run in the Derby, drew the No. 4 gate and was made the second choice at 9-2.</p>
        <p>Captain Steve, eighth in the 19-horse Derby, drew the No. 6 slot and was made the co-third choice at 8-1. High Yield, 15th in the Derby but still carrying the flag for D. Wayne Lukas, will start from the fifth slot at 10-1.</p>
        <p>''This is very straightforward,'' said Neil Drysdale, the English trainer of Fusaichi Pegasus. ''It's a quarter of a mile to the first turn. Eight horses. I don't think the draw is that important.''</p>
        <p>Bob Baffert, who trains Captain Steve, quipped: ''I'd feel better if Fusaichi Pegasus were to break from behind the gate.''</p>
        <p>Lukas, who has won the Preakness five times, said he was still mystified by High Yield's flat performance in the Derby.</p>
        <p>The horse had won the Fountain of Youth Stakes and the Blue Grass Stakes.</p>
        <p>''When we went over for the Derby, I was convinced he was the best horse,'' Lukas said. ''I don't know what happened. But he's been training beautifully at Pimlico, he likes the track and we're expecting him to run a big race.''</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus was unloaded from his horse van by Drysdale, who bedded him down in Stall 20 of Barn 7 near the five-eighths pole.</p>
        <p>Drysdale elected to stable him across the track from the Preakness Barn, where the rest of the eight colts will be housed for the 125th running of the Preakness.</p>
        <p>The trainer decided that his star, who has a balky disposition, would find more privacy on the backstretch than at the Preakness Barn with its clamor of news media.</p>
        <p>''It was a very good flight,'' Drysdale said. ''He handled it very well. We expect to gallop him each morning up to the Preakness.''</p>
        <p>Fusaichi Pegasus led the midweek migration with a two-hour flight to Pimlico from Churchill Downs, and was promptly surrounded by the type of tumult that his trainer had been trying to avoid. He was met by about 80 people from the news media.</p>
        <p>He arrived on a flight of 14 horses, but only two others, Captain Steve and Snuck In, were headed for the Preakness.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Hugh Hefner arrived from the West Coast at 9 o'clock this morning after an overnight cargo flight from Los Angeles. He was greeted by an entourage of two: his owner, Ed Nahem, and his trainer, Marty Jones.</p>
        <p>''The cargo plane stopped in Dayton and had a layover for about an hour,'' Jones said, ''but that's pretty good when you hear stories of planes sitting on the ground for 10 hours. I'm tired, but he seems fine. Better the trainer is tired than the horse.''</p>
        <p>Red Bullet, who ran second to Fusaichi Pegasus in the Wood Memorial last month, took life easy today while awaiting his old nemesis. He galloped two miles, then drew praise from his trainer, Joe Orseno, who said he had handled the Pimlico track well.</p>
        <p>He won a reward of sorts by getting the first choice in the selection process, a two-tiered gimmick for adding suspense to the television program on which the draw was broadcast.</p>
        <p>Red Bullet will also gain the services of Jerry Bailey, the country's premier jockey, who replaced Alex Solis.</p>
        <p>As for post position, Orseno said: ''I'm not too concerned with only an eight-horse field and the long run to the first turn. It's different than when there was 12 in the Wood and a short run to the turn. He drew the 2-hole, and the horses outside were dropping down in there. Solis gunned him and he was up there dueling for the lead. That was the last thing I wanted to see, but he still ran a game race.''</p>
        <p>The eighth and last Preakness horse to arrive at Pimlico will be Impeachment, third in the Kentucky Derby and third in the Arkansas Derby.</p>
        <p>His trainer, Todd Pletcher, said the colt would board a van at Belmont Park at 4:30 in the morning and should join the Preakness parade about 9 o'clock. He will start the race from the No. 3 gate and will share third place in the betting with Captain Steve at 8-1.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
