<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Employers Found to Violate Law Requiring Parity for Mental Health Coverage</title>
    <meta content="Y18MEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7D8173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Employers Found to Violate Law Requiring Parity for Mental Health Coverage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Accounting Office says 1996 law has not increased workers' access to mental health services; say thousands of employers are violating federal law that requires level of insurance coverage for mental illness to be similar to that for physical illness; say even those in technical compliance with law find ways to skirt its intent; this is first authoritative data lawmakers have been given showing level of noncompliance (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congressional investigators say thousands of employers are violating a federal law that requires the level of insurance coverage for mental illness to be similar to that for physical illness.</p>
        <p>And even those that are in technical compliance with the law have in  most cases found ways to skirt its intent, the investigators said.</p>
        <p>As a result, they said, the 1996 law  does not appear to have increased access to mental health services as Congress intended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congressional investigators say thousands of employers are violating a federal law that requires the level of insurance coverage for mental illness to be similar to that for physical illness.</p>
        <p>And even those that are in technical compliance with the law have in  most cases found ways to skirt its intent, the investigators said.</p>
        <p>As a result, they said, the 1996 law  does not appear to have increased access to mental health services as Congress intended.</p>
        <p>The investigators, from the General Accounting Office, will present their findings on Thursday at a Senate hearing requested by lawmakers hoping to expand the law.</p>
        <p>Under the statute, the Mental Health Parity Act, group health plans may not set annual or lifetime dollar limits on a person's mental health care that are lower than the limits for general medical and surgical services.</p>
        <p>The General Accounting Office surveyed employers in 26 states and found that 14 percent were not complying with the federal standards. Most of those companies, by their own account, had lifetime limits on mental health benefits of $100,000 or less, but set higher ceilings for medical and surgical benefits.</p>
        <p>The G.A.O. estimated that 9,000 to 13,000 employers in the 26 states were violating the federal standards, but it did not identify them.</p>
        <p>Employees and their dependents in those states ''have often seen only minor changes in their health benefits, resulting in little or no increase in their access to mental health services,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The accounting office said it ''did not find significant differences in the rate of employer noncompliance based on characteristics such as employer size, industry or geographic region, or whether the plan was fully insured or self-funded.''</p>
        <p>The law does not apply to health plans sponsored by an employer with 50 or fewer employees. It does apply to employers that serve as their own insurers, paying claims from company assets, as well as to companies that buy health insurance.</p>
        <p>Until now, lawmakers have not had authoritative data showing the level of noncompliance. Their current focus, on broadening the law, is aimed at a related matter on which  they have amassed a great deal of anecdotal evidence: even employers that comply with the law find ways to restrict access to mental health care, by setting limits on the number of office visits or days of hospital care, as opposed to the dollar limits that the law governs.</p>
        <p>By such techniques, the report said, most health plans that comply with the law -- 87 percent -- ''restrict mental health benefits to a greater extent than medical and surgical benefits.''</p>
        <p>''Some employers seem to be living up to the letter of the law, but not its spirit,'' said Senator James M. Jeffords, Republican of Vermont. ''I believe these practices will have to be examined in more detail as we proceed with reauthorization of the Mental Health Parity Act.''</p>
        <p>The law expires on Sept. 30, 2001. The Senate hearing on Thursday is being held by the Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions, which Mr. Jeffords heads.</p>
        <p>The authors of the 1996 law, Senators Pete V. Domenici, Republican of New Mexico, and Paul Wellstone, Democrat of Minnesota, cited the findings to support their contention that Congress should broaden the law to prohibit all disparities in coverage for mental and physical ailments. Such a ban would be ''a major step toward ending the persistent discrimination against people who suffer from mental illness,'' Mr. Wellstone said.</p>
        <p>Tipper Gore, wife of the vice president, has advocated ''full parity'' in insurance coverage, and Mr. Gore sometimes promotes the idea in presidential campaign speeches.</p>
        <p>In testimony prepared for the hearing, Dr. Steven E. Hyman, director of the National Institute of Mental Health, says there is ''no reason based on biomedical or behavioral science why mental disorders should be treated differently from any other medical disorder.''</p>
        <p>There is, Dr. Hyman said, no scientific reason that a plan should cover Parkinson's disease but not schizophrenia, for both are ''chronic and not yet curable diseases that affect dopamine systems in the brain.''</p>
        <p>The General Accounting Office said the law had had ''a negligible effect'' on health insurance costs. A more comprehensive law requiring full parity could lead to ''cost increases of about 2 percent to 4 percent,'' it said.</p>
        <p>E. Neil Trautwein, director of employment policy at the National Association of Manufacturers, said, ''To the extent that an employer is not in compliance, it may be because of confusion over the application of the law or perhaps a continued struggle to hold health cost increases in check.''</p>
        <p>James A. Klein, president of the Association of Private Pension and Welfare Plans, a group composed mainly of Fortune 500 companies, said he was surprised to hear that some companies were not complying. ''I don't have any evidence to dispute that,'' Mr. Klein said, ''but our members tend to have very high compliance, because they track these requirements closely.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
