<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="18QNA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5DB163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving Wild Canada Columbine</p>
        <p>Q. Each day on the way to work I drive past a hillside that has many clumps of beautiful bright red and yellow flowers growing among the rocks. They look like little rocket ships on tall stems. What are they? Will they survive transplanting? I would like to put some by the edge of my front walk.  A. The wildflowers brightening your commute are Canada columbines, Aquilegia canadensis. This delicate-looking but tough species, ancestor of many garden hybrids, is widely distributed, growing in open woodlands and along roadsides from eastern Canada to Florida and New Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving Wild Canada Columbine</p>
        <p>Q. Each day on the way to work I drive past a hillside that has many clumps of beautiful bright red and yellow flowers growing among the rocks. They look like little rocket ships on tall stems. What are they? Will they survive transplanting? I would like to put some by the edge of my front walk.  A. The wildflowers brightening your commute are Canada columbines, Aquilegia canadensis. This delicate-looking but tough species, ancestor of many garden hybrids, is widely distributed, growing in open woodlands and along roadsides from eastern Canada to Florida and New Mexico.</p>
        <p>For the moment, at least, they are not endangered; but that doesn't mean it's all right to blithely start kidnapping them. Removal of plants is not only a threat to the parent colony, setting you on the path to sin, but also a bad idea from the point of view of pure survival. Plants dug up from the wild often suffer root damage, and even when roots are preserved intact, the transition to different soils and different light levels puts a lot of strain on the plants. Container-grown (or adapted) plants are expressly created to deal with moving and usually do better at it.</p>
        <p>From the columbine's point of view, it would be best if your front walk were in light shade, but the plants will tolerate full sun if it isn't baking hot, and they are adaptable to a wide range of soils as long as those soils are well drained.</p>
        <p>Canada columbine's flowers bloom only in spring, and the fernlike blue-green foliage is too delicate to attract the casual browser's eye, so this plant is seldom sold in garden centers. But it is widely available by mail order. Sources include Prairie Nursery, P.O. Box 306 Westfield, Wis. 53964, catalog free at (800) 476-9453  (there is also an extensive guide to and discussion of native plants at www.prairienursery.com.); and We-Du Nurseries, Route 5, Box 724, Marion, N.C. 28752, catalog, $2 at (828) 738-8300 or www.we-du.com.</p>
        <p>If You Want to Save a Yew</p>
        <p>Q. I have a yew about five feet wide next to the deck of my swimming pool. It is blocking part of the deck so  we cannot pass by. Can this be trimmed from the front? It looks as if all I will have is the inside branches left, a rather ugly sight.  But if I can do it, when is the best time?  A. It sounds as if you may secretly hope there is nothing to be done, so before we get to the pruning part, let me encourage you to be brave and get rid of the thing. Though it goes against a gardener's grain to kill a healthy shrub, why keep one where you can look forward to two or three years of bare spots followed by a lifelong commitment to time-consuming maintenance?</p>
        <p>If you are determined to keep it, there are two alternatives. The yew can be trimmed from the front, but it will be ugly, and not just while the inside branches are putting on new growth. No matter how green it gets, the shrub will always look like it has been sliced in half.</p>
        <p>A more attractive alternative is to reshape the whole plant. Cut back a little bit (6 to 9 inches) all around each year, pruning individual branches to slightly different lengths rather than shearing along the face. It will take longer to prune than to shear, but the result will be a tall, narrow, vaguely columnar shrub that won't look as though it belongs in a cemetery.</p>
        <p>No matter what shape you choose, the best time to start cutting is early spring, before the plant puts out new growth. This gives you maximum green to cover the exposed bare spots and gives the plant maximum time to harden up before winter. But it's not too late; get going right now and you will still have quite a bit of new yew this year.</p>
        <p>Address questions to Garden Q.&amp; A., The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York 10036, or by e-mail to gardening@nytimes .com. Those of general interest will be published. Unpublished questions cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
