<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan for Burn Near Los Alamos Called Wildfire Risk Moderate</title>
    <meta content="18ALAM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Alamos (Nm)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Park Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Babbitt, Bruce (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DB173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan for Burn Near Los Alamos Called Wildfire Risk Moderate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ALAMOS, N.M., May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Park Service plan for igniting what has become largest fire in New Mexico history called risk that prescribed blaze would escape beyond its bounds 'moderate'; at same time, plan warned that federal officials might be underestimating danger that such a fire might spill beyond its intended limits; copy of plan is made available by federal investigators tracing decisions that led to fire; Interior Sec Bruce Babbitt is scheduled to arrive in New Mexico on May 19 to discuss handling of event that has potential to reshape government's fire policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A National Park Service plan for igniting what has become the largest fire in New Mexico history called the risk that the prescribed blaze would escape beyond its bounds ''moderate.'' The plan said any damage would probably be confined to ''timber and private land values,'' not buildings.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, the plan warned that federal officials might be underestimating the danger that such a fire, set to reduce the possibility of unplanned fires, might spill beyond its intended limits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A National Park Service plan for igniting what has become the largest fire in New Mexico history called the risk that the prescribed blaze would escape beyond its bounds ''moderate.'' The plan said any damage would probably be confined to ''timber and private land values,'' not buildings.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, the plan warned that federal officials might be underestimating the danger that such a fire, set to reduce the possibility of unplanned fires, might spill beyond its intended limits.</p>
        <p>''You have not lost one in a long time and are starting to feel a little smug,'' said the 250-page plan, dated April 19 and filed to the National Park Service headquarters in Washington.</p>
        <p>It has been reported that before the fire was set, the National Weather Service told Park Service officials that winds would be brisk, humidity low and the chance of volatility high. Park Service officials have said that they knew that there was some danger of the fire spreading but that conditions for a successful controlled fire are typically similar to those for a dangerous wildfire.</p>
        <p>A copy of the plan was made available by federal investigators who are tracing the decisions that led to the fire, which has consumed more than 46,000 acres, destroyed more than 200 homes and shut down the nation's leading nuclear weapons laboratory.</p>
        <p>Preliminary results of the investigation are scheduled to be released in New Mexico on Thursday, when Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt arrives to discuss the handling of an event that has the potential to reshape the government's fire policy.</p>
        <p>Already, in the days since the Los Alamos blaze began to rage out of control, the government has imposed a 30-day ban in the West on the type of deliberate ignition that led to the conflagration. The fire was set by the Park Service at Bandelier National Monument on May 4 to diminish the chances of a catastrophic wildfire. The goal was to clear underbrush that had accumulated over years in which federal policy has emphasized suppressing fires, rather than allowing them to run their course.</p>
        <p>Today, fire officials said, firefighters had controlled about 45 percent of the blaze. The rest was burning in heavily forested areas north and east of Los Alamos, out of range of most human habitation.</p>
        <p>It was not clear who wrote the planning document for the fire, because all names were blacked out in the version released by the federal investigators. A spokeswoman for the task force would not identify the authors or recipients of the plan.</p>
        <p>Still, the document revealed deep apprehension among federal experts about risks inherent in setting fires, though the practice has become a routine part of forest management.</p>
        <p>The plan for the Los Alamos burn warned that escaping flames were ''somewhat likely'' and that ''political problems'' might result that could affect the use of such controlled fires in the future. The language seemed to refer to the potential for adverse publicity should the fire go awry and get close to the Los Alamos National Laboratory.</p>
        <p>The laboratory, the founding home of the nation's nuclear weapons program, remains closed, along with schools and most businesses in the area. Most residents in the town of Los Alamos have been allowed to return home, but at least 20 percent of the town remains off limits, with more than 400 structures burned.</p>
        <p>About 1 in 100 controlled fires ignited by federal workers typically escapes the expected bounds, Forest Service officials said today. In the case of Los Alamos, the report filed in April calculated the fire's expected range at 968 acres. Instead, driven by high winds and fueled by dry weather, it has consumed some 50 times that territory.</p>
        <p>The wind-driven fire quickly overran the burn area and roared into the town. Some lawmakers have called for a re-examination of the nation's controlled burn policies, which have been put on hold in 11 Western states until at least June 11.</p>
        <p>National Park Superintendent Roy Weaver, who took responsibility for igniting the blaze, has been placed on paid leave and declined requests to be interviewed.</p>
        <p>The plan for the fire in the Los Alamos area noted that ''smoke impacts to sensitive areas could produce political problems that may impact future prescribed fire operations.''</p>
        <p>The plan spelled out a number of conditions that should have been satisfied before any fire was ignited. It was unclear whether any of the conditions had been satisfied.</p>
        <p>The plan said dead wood in the burn area was to be tested for moisture content for at least three weeks before the fire was set and weather conditions were to be monitored hourly afterward. Smaller test fires were to be set before the big one.</p>
        <p>For the planned fire to take place, the plan said temperatures were to be between 40 and 90 degrees Fahrenheit, with relative humidity of 15 percent to 20 percent and wind speeds of no more than 8 miles per  hour.</p>
        <p>A National Weather Service report sent to the Park Service the day the fire began forecast temperatures of 68 to 72 degrees and a humidity of 14 percent to 18 percent.</p>
        <p>But that weather report also forecast winds of 5 to 10 m.p.h. at lower elevations and 10 m.p.h. at the ridge tops. Additionally, winds were projected to increase the next day to up to 15 m.p.h., with gusts reaching 20 m.p.h. at the ridge tops.</p>
        <p>The report also predicted humidity would fall overnight, creating dry and unstable air, making for conditions in which wildfires can easily rage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
