<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheers From the Pit Accompany a Coda; Leader Among Violins Leaves the Met</title>
    <meta content="18MAST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000525T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gniewek, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levine, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">gniewek, raymond (biographical sketch)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EEDB163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheers From the Pit Accompany a Coda; Leader Among Violins Leaves the Met</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Raymond Gniewek reflects on his 43 years at concertmaster of Metropolitan Opera Orchestra now that he is retiring; James Levine, artistic director, says the single luckiest thing to happen to him at the Met is to have Gniewek as concertmaster; Gniewek comments on changing role of concertmaster over the centuries and his multiple functions at the Met; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Raymond Gniewek was appointed concertmaster of the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra in 1957, he was a 25-year-old graduate of the Eastman School of Music with scant experience in vocal music, let alone opera. Though he was a brilliantly talented violinist, he immediately became the youngest member of the orchestra, its first American-born concertmaster, and he was expected to assume a leadership role among musicians far more knowledgeable than he about the European opera heritage.</p>
        <p>Things obviously turned out well. After 43 years as concertmaster -- a position little understood even by regular concertgoers -- Mr. Gniewek, 68, is retiring. During his tenure he has performed in 115 different operas under a roster of conductors ranging from some now-forgotten beat-keepers to giants like Dmitri Mitropoulos, Karl Bohm, Herbert von Karajan, Leonard Bernstein and, of course, James Levine. An opera neophyte when he arrived, he leaves with an incomparable understanding of operatic style and practice. In 1977 he even married a singer, the soprano Judith Blegen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Raymond Gniewek was appointed concertmaster of the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra in 1957, he was a 25-year-old graduate of the Eastman School of Music with scant experience in vocal music, let alone opera. Though he was a brilliantly talented violinist, he immediately became the youngest member of the orchestra, its first American-born concertmaster, and he was expected to assume a leadership role among musicians far more knowledgeable than he about the European opera heritage.</p>
        <p>Things obviously turned out well. After 43 years as concertmaster -- a position little understood even by regular concertgoers -- Mr. Gniewek, 68, is retiring. During his tenure he has performed in 115 different operas under a roster of conductors ranging from some now-forgotten beat-keepers to giants like Dmitri Mitropoulos, Karl Bohm, Herbert von Karajan, Leonard Bernstein and, of course, James Levine. An opera neophyte when he arrived, he leaves with an incomparable understanding of operatic style and practice. In 1977 he even married a singer, the soprano Judith Blegen.</p>
        <p>His final performances come this weekend with two concerts by the Met Orchestra conducted by Mr. Levine: tomorrow night at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center in Newark, and on Sunday afternoon at Carnegie Hall, an all-Bartok program offering the one-act opera ''Bluebeard's Castle'' and the Concerto for Orchestra. Count on Mr. Levine, who was a precocious 13-year-old piano student in Cincinnati when Mr. Gniewek got the Met job, to acknowledge him warmly at the end of the concert.</p>
        <p>During an interview the other day in his office, Mr. Levine grew emotional trying to explain how important Mr. Gniewek has been to the artistic growth of the orchestra. They share a musical heritage, since two of Mr. Levine's teachers, the conductors Jean Morel and Fausto Cleva, were important figures at the Met during Mr. Gniewek's early years. ''The single luckiest thing to happen to me since I have been at the Met,'' Mr. Levine said, ''is that Ray Gniewek was the concertmaster.''</p>
        <p>Many operagoers will have to accept Mr. Levine's tribute on faith, since there are such misconceptions about the role. What exactly does a concertmaster do?</p>
        <p>''It's hard to put into words,'' the silver-haired, fit and affable Mr. Gniewek said during a recent interview at the Met. In the 18th century, ''before conductors were even around,'' he said, ''the concertmaster essentially led the orchestra, for the simple reason that the violin was the highest voice in any ensemble.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''As music became more complicated, and more instruments were involved, communication between the musicians didn't work very well. So a director, a conductor, was put there, to keep things in order.''</p>
        <p>This outmoded historic conception of the concertmaster as a sort of second in command, ready to assume the podium if the conductor should be unable to continue, has persisted in the public imagination, Mr. Gniewek said. But all major orchestras have a number of assistant conductors on staff. The Met has a whole roster of them.</p>
        <p>Like most modern concertmasters, Mr. Gniewek has a different set of responsibilities. The public notices his work most when he plays solos in an opera. These can range in length and difficulty from the short, bittersweet melody that comforts Strauss's introspective Marschallin at the end of Act I in ''Der Rosenkavalier'' to the miniconcerto that functions as an orchestral interlude in Act III of Verdi's ''I Lombardi.''</p>
        <p>More important, he acts as a leader of the violin section, responsible for making sure that all phrasing, bowings and articulations are being done the same way by everyone. In a house with the heritage of the Met, such solutions have long been established and are written into the orchestra parts. But a conductor is free to change them. In that case the concertmaster must find a technical solution to the conductor's wishes and communicate it somehow to the other musicians.</p>
        <p>''Players tell me all the time, 'Don't worry, Ray, we're watching the tip of your bow,' '' Mr. Gniewek said. But many things have to be dealt with in detail, on the spot, in rehearsal:</p>
        <p>''For example, Jimmy will say, 'No, Ray, I want this phrase a little lighter, a little shorter.' So I'll play it. He'll say: 'No, that's too short. Just a little brushing sound, tat-tat-tat.' I'll play again. 'That's it!' he'll say. So I turn to the violins and demonstrate. It's my job to make technical translations of the desired sound. And you have to show, not tell, because the same words can mean different things to different people.''</p>
        <p>This intuitive way of working has been essential to Mr. Levine, whose goal has been to make the Met orchestra sound ''like a sensational, huge chamber group.'' This is critical in opera, where timing should be free and expressive, and where, ideally, the conductor and orchestra respond to the singers the way a pianist accompanies a voice recital.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, when a conductor is waiting on a singer's response, Mr. Gniewek said, ''there is a lag between them, between what is happening onstage and what is happening in the pit.'' If there is any uncertainty, the orchestra players ''feel a little surer if they can follow me,'' he said. ''I mean, I make a sound. The conductor's beat doesn't. So if they jump in when I start to play, they know they will be safe.''</p>
        <p>Some modern-day concertmasters have also been aspiring conductors, the most renowned example being Joseph Silverstein, who resigned as concertmaster of the Boston Symphony Orchestra in 1984 after 22 years to become the conductor of the Utah Symphony Orchestra. Mr. Gniewek ''never had the itch'' to conduct, he said. ''I'd rather play. I have strong feelings about sound, the actual act of playing of the instrument. It's what I do best.''</p>
        <p>He certainly must have done it impressively to win his post at such a young age, especially considering that his focus on a musical career came late. He was born in East Meadow, on Long Island, to a mother who loved music and sang in a church choir, and a Polish immigrant father who had played the violin at dances in Poland but wound up working as a barber in America.</p>
        <p>''The family joke was that my parents' first son was going to be a violinist,'' Mr. Gniewek said. Coming after two sisters, he was the first son. He became the violinist. ''I had no choice,'' he said wryly. ''I never really took to practicing too well. I loved math and science.''</p>
        <p>He intended to be a physics major and was accepted by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. But he was persuaded to attend the University of Rochester, where, somehow, he said, he wound up enrolling at the affiliated Eastman School of Music. Erich Leinsdorf, who had been conducting at the Met since 1938, was the director of the Rochester Philharmonic Orchestra at the time and invited Mr. Gniewek to be its concertmaster. But it was the conductor Max Rudolf, then an assistant manager at the Met, who worked with Mr. Gniewek in Rochester and told him of the opening at the Met.</p>
        <p>The concertmaster appointment came at a difficult time in Mr. Gniewek's life. His first marriage, which produced two daughters, was breaking up. ''I was 20 when we got married,'' he said. ''We were just too young.''</p>
        <p>The Met musicians might have been expected to be resentful of this young newcomer. But, Mr. Gniewek said, ''I sort of waded my way through things, wasn't too arrogant, and the musicians were very supportive.''</p>
        <p>Surely he earned that support through the quality of his musicianship. Today, after four decades of absorbing operatic style, his playing has a special vocal quality, Mr. Levine said: ''It shimmers, it's lyrical. You can imagine putting a text to it immediately.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gniewek joined the Met, the autocratic Rudolf Bing was in his seventh year as general manager. However Sir Rudolph's tenure is regarded today, he was ''a singer's man,'' Mr. Gniewek said. ''To him, we were just an accompanying orchestra.''</p>
        <p>He remembers Mr. Levine's 1971 debut as a turning point. ''When Jimmy came, it was the end of the season, just another 'Tosca' for us,'' Mr. Gniewek recalled. ''But he really lifted us up and carried us along. Afterward I did something I didn't do much. I found him backstage and said, 'That was the most phenomenal debut since Herbert von Karajan.' ''</p>
        <p>The morale in the orchestra, in that next-to-last year of the Bing era, was not high. Mr. Levine's positivism was just the tonic needed, Mr. Gniewek said. He sometimes chides jaded friends from the New York Philharmonic who are suspicious of Mr. Levine's enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>''They tell me, 'Ah, he's always smiling.'</p>
        <p>' 'What's wrong with that?' I say. 'You have to always make music scowling? Music always has to be done with suffering and intensity?' ''</p>
        <p>There have been times when Mr. Gniewek was so exhilarated after a Met performance -- many nights with Birgit Nilsson and Renata Tebaldi, he said, and Wagner's ''Ring'' with Mr. Levine -- that he would go home and stay up until 4 a.m. doing things like tiling the bathroom floor. He would have retired years ago, he said, but he wanted to be a part of two transforming additions to the orchestra's musical life introduced by Mr. Levine over the last 10 years: the Met Orchestra concert series and the founding of the Met Chamber Ensemble.</p>
        <p>During his tenure Mr. Gniewek has witnessed a turnover of orchestra personnel; only three players have been there longer than he. Naturally, he was very involved with the auditions for string players, though he said he was ''not 100 percent happy'' with the process. To prevent discrimination, the candidates play from behind a screen, and the musicians on the audition committee write down their comments without consultation.</p>
        <p>''I would like to have a little discussion,'' he said. ''Sometimes you don't completely trust what you are hearing.'' For example, was a violinist's playing exciting, or a bit aggressive? Different listeners may feel differently. Also, although he accepts the reasons for it, he has been frustrated by the use of the screen.</p>
        <p>''I like to see a person playing,'' he said. ''Playing an instrument is a very physical thing.'' If there are problems after the fact, the contract allows for a two-year probation period during which a newcomer can be removed.</p>
        <p>Only the concertmaster can be appointed directly by the artistic director, Mr. Levine. The Met orchestra has traditionally had two principal players of each instrument, but only one concertmaster, though there are several associates. Mr. Levine has been seeking to change that policy, and over the last season a second concertmaster, Nick Eanet, 28, whom everyone is excited about, was finally broken in. Mr. Gniewek is now taking part in the audition process to find another concertmaster to share the work with Mr. Eanet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gniewek knows that playing in an opera house orchestra involves a lot of hard, routine work, day after day. But he always had an answer for musicians who found themselves feeling uninspired.</p>
        <p>''I'd tell people: 'You are going to be here for four hours anyway. Do you want to walk out feeling: ''Ugh! What a headache! That was not so good''? Or do you want to walk out feeling, ''Wow, that was fantastic'' '? Might as well give it everything.''</p>
        <p>And that explains exactly what a concertmaster does.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 25, 2000, Thursday  An article in the arts pages last Thursday about the retirement of Raymond Gniewek as concertmaster of the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra included an erroneous historical reference from the company. Mr. Gniewek was the orchestra's second American-born concertmaster; Nahan Franko was the first, from 1899 into the early 1900's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 25, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in the arts pages last Thursday about the retirement of Raymond Gniewek as concertmaster of the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra included an erroneous historical reference from the company. Mr. Gniewek was the orchestra's second American-born concertmaster; Nahan Franko was the first, from 1899 into the early 1900's.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
