<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Levy Is Named Chancellor on 7-0 Vote; 2-Year Contract Expected</title>
    <meta content="18LEVY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D8173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Levy Is Named Chancellor on 7-0 Vote; 2-Year Contract Expected</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Board of Education votes unanimously to make Harold O Levy first businessman and noneducator to be named chancellor of New York City school system in its 102-year history; board officials say that they expect to award Levy with two-year contract; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After voting unanimously to make Harold O. Levy the first businessman and noneducator to be named chancellor of the New York City school system in its 102-year history, Board of Education officials said yesterday that they expected to award Mr. Levy a two-year contract to manage the country's largest school system.</p>
        <p>That means that Mr. Levy, who since January has been interim chancellor, is likely to remain chancellor until at least the summer of 2002, well after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani leaves office, whether or not the mayor runs for or wins a seat in the United States Senate. Mr. Giuliani, who had opposed Mr. Levy's appointment to the interim post, reversed course on Tuesday and endorsed him for the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After voting unanimously to make Harold O. Levy the first businessman and noneducator to be named chancellor of the New York City school system in its 102-year history, Board of Education officials said yesterday that they expected to award Mr. Levy a two-year contract to manage the country's largest school system.</p>
        <p>That means that Mr. Levy, who since January has been interim chancellor, is likely to remain chancellor until at least the summer of 2002, well after Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani leaves office, whether or not the mayor runs for or wins a seat in the United States Senate. Mr. Giuliani, who had opposed Mr. Levy's appointment to the interim post, reversed course on Tuesday and endorsed him for the job.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said that among his first priorities as permanent chancellor would be to deliver a plan to overhaul the Board of Education's sprawling bureaucracy and to create partnerships in the community among school employees, parents, businesses, other educational institutions and political leaders, aimed at improving the city's schools. He also announced that Judith A. Rizzo -- the deputy chancellor of instruction under Rudy Crew when he was chancellor, who had been recently thinking about leaving the board -- would remain as his chief education deputy.</p>
        <p>In a short address to the board after his election, Mr. Levy said: ''I come to the job as a business person but also as somebody who loves education and is very pleased to have an opportunity to contribute to what I believe is the most important function in our society today. The system that I begin to lead now is a system that has had enormous successes and has proven beyond any possible doubt that it is capable of creating greatness. That is a greatness that I want to achieve again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy also expressed his thanks for Mr. Giuliani's support. ''I am determined that the people represented at this table will not regret the decision that they took today,'' he added.</p>
        <p>After the meeting, Mr. Levy received lukewarm support from Ninfa Segarra, one of Mr. Giuliani's two representatives on the board, who said her vote reflected a show of support for a chancellor who already had the promised votes of a majority of the seven-member board. In that, she echoed the mayor's comments yesterday, saying that many areas of disagreement remain between the Board of Education and City Hall.</p>
        <p>''It would not be a positive thing for the system if he walked in with a split vote,'' Ms. Segarra said, referring to Mr. Levy. ''We wanted to show that the mayor is willing to work with the new chancellor. That's an important indicator for the city.''</p>
        <p>The Board of Education conducted a nationwide search for a chancellor, producing scores of applicants but no one who was willing to compete directly against Mr. Levy, the interim chancellor. One speaker at yesterday's session, Michael Meyers of the New York Civil Rights Coalition, sharply criticized the board for failing to find any qualified minority candidates for the job.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Levy's selection is, in my considered judgment, the triumph of cronyism,'' Mr. Meyers said.</p>
        <p>But other speakers, including Cynthia Cummins, a member of a South Bronx parents group, supported Mr. Levy. Ms. Cummins said she believed that he could help to change ''the persistent educational failure'' in many Bronx schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy will receive a salary of $245,000 a year, plus other benefits that remain to be determined. Among them are likely to be a housing allowance as the board prepares to study the sale of the Brooklyn brownstone bought several years ago to serve as the chancellor's residence.</p>
        <p>Board officials and Mr. Levy have had only informal conversations about the structure of a contract. But William C. Thompson Jr., president of the board; Terri Thomson, the Queens representative; and Ms. Segarra each said Mr. Levy would be offered a two-year contract. The longest contract that the board could legally offer the new chancellor would extend for three years, or one year beyond the end of the terms of the current board members, which end in June 2002.</p>
        <p>Asked what Mr. Levy needs to do now as chancellor, Mr. Thompson said simply, ''Run the school system.''</p>
        <p>''He will be held to the same standards that every other chancellor has been held to,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''Do reading and math scores go up? Is he recruiting teachers? It will be a lot more than just putting out fires.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy will be only the second chancellor to manage the system since new governance laws that took effect in 1996 gave the chancellor greater power over community school boards.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson alluded to the issue of merit pay, which has divided members of the board. ''Now, we've got to make the final extension of that into the classroom,'' he said, by negotiating a contract with the teachers' union that ''allows us to reward performance.''</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, president of the United Federation of Teachers, said Mr. Levy's appointment ''is a positive development for kids, and therefore it's a positive development for teachers.''</p>
        <p>She, too, said that she and the chancellor disagreed on some subjects. ''But those differences are in how things should be accomplished,'' she said, ''and not what should be accomplished.''</p>
        <p>''He has shown himself to be a strong steward, and he wants to run the school system,'' she said. ''Lots of people think he is a breath of fresh air. But to do this, he needs more than management theory. If he doesn't have people around him who understand what works educationally, it will be much harder for him.''</p>
        <p>One of the primary responsibilities for Mr. Levy in his first year is likely to be helping to reach a new contract with the school system's 78,000 teachers, represented by the federation. Their contract expires in November, and the union has asked the city to open early negotiations on a new contract. But City Hall has not responded to that request, and an attempt by union officials and Mr. Levy to negotiate some added benefits for teachers who work in the summer school session met with fierce resistance from City Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson indicated that he wanted Mr. Levy to take an active part in those negotiations. The last teachers' contract ''was negotiated without the Board of Education at the table,'' Mr. Thompson said.</p>
        <p>''That was a major mistake, and an opportunity lost,'' he said. ''We won't lose that opportunity again. If the board is not at the negotiating table the next time around, we will not approve that contract.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
