<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diversifying the Suburbs: More Than a Box</title>
    <meta content="18NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prospect Heights (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giovannini, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markow, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markow, Aleksandr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Design Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD61F3BF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diversifying the Suburbs: More Than a Box</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH GIOVANNINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Giovannini, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>PROSPECT HEIGHTS, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Doug Garofalo remodels home of Aleksandra and Andrew Markow in Prospect Heights, Ill, giving it a daring design that flouts architectural conventions of the suburbs; floor plan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are places architects fear to tread, and suburbs that are chockablock with colonials, ranch houses, McMansions and good-taste design committees often give them pause. ''I didn't think there was anything you could really do in the suburbs,'' said Doug Garofalo, a Chicago architect. ''All those cliches about how everybody is wealthy, white and conservative, with two and a half kids and a dog, weren't encouraging.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garofalo, 41, helped design one of the most radical structures recently built in New York, the computer-generated, amorphously shaped Korean Presbyterian Church in Sunnyside, Queens. In the leafy suburbs of Chicago, he might have expected a sort of autoimmune reaction to his designs. But the suburbanites who have come calling on his firm haven't played into the Ozzie and Harriet stereotype befitting an Eisenhower era, marshmallow-salad neighborhood. ''They are first-generation, self-made immigrants -- Polish, Thai, Chinese, Ukrainian entrepreneurs used to taking risks -- and they're not here to fit in and disappear,'' he said. ''They had no interest in Cape Cod or any other vernacular style. That isn't their culture; they all had progressive attitudes. They didn't want to just melt into the pot.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are places architects fear to tread, and suburbs that are chockablock with colonials, ranch houses, McMansions and good-taste design committees often give them pause. ''I didn't think there was anything you could really do in the suburbs,'' said Doug Garofalo, a Chicago architect. ''All those cliches about how everybody is wealthy, white and conservative, with two and a half kids and a dog, weren't encouraging.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garofalo, 41, helped design one of the most radical structures recently built in New York, the computer-generated, amorphously shaped Korean Presbyterian Church in Sunnyside, Queens. In the leafy suburbs of Chicago, he might have expected a sort of autoimmune reaction to his designs. But the suburbanites who have come calling on his firm haven't played into the Ozzie and Harriet stereotype befitting an Eisenhower era, marshmallow-salad neighborhood. ''They are first-generation, self-made immigrants -- Polish, Thai, Chinese, Ukrainian entrepreneurs used to taking risks -- and they're not here to fit in and disappear,'' he said. ''They had no interest in Cape Cod or any other vernacular style. That isn't their culture; they all had progressive attitudes. They didn't want to just melt into the pot.''</p>
        <p>His clients, Andrew and Aleksandra Markow, for whom he designed a new version of their home in Prospect Heights, defied the suburban stereotype. ''I don't mind having Georgian and colonial houses around me, but that's not my style,'' said Mr. Markow, a contractor who was born in Poland. ''America is more conservative and less contemporary than Europe, especially in the Midwest. We're a little behind here.''</p>
        <p>A street-side view of their remodeled 2,000-square-foot, three-bedroom split-level house reveals a large, angular, two-story prism, plain and abstract, rising out of its own sloping shadow. The split-level roof is dog-eared up at one corner, to accommodate a high window. With another (yellow) Dryvit wing hovering over the garage to the left, and a glass entryway in between, the facade owes much to Hans Hoffmann. Something has happened here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Markow began cultivating an interest in contemporary design as a teenager in Poland. ''Except for Frank Lloyd Wright, I didn't really find a modern style here,'' he said. ''And American colonial doesn't speak to me.''</p>
        <p>Twelve years ago, he gave up his position as a biochemical researcher at Northwestern University to start his contracting company. ''Somewhere deep inside was a love for design, and becoming a contractor was a way of getting closer to the field,'' he said. His wife, also a chemist, left the lab to raise their two young children.</p>
        <p>They had extended the original house into the rear yard in the early 1980's, but the spaces inside remained small, closed and surprisingly dark. ''Coming home every day was kind of boring,'' Mr. Markow said. Several years ago, with the birth of their second child, the couple decided they needed larger, brighter bedrooms for the children, along with a playroom, another bedroom and a music room that would double as a home office. They were ready to trade in their tidy but conventional version of domesticity for something bolder. Mr. Markow would act as his own contractor, but he needed the right design.</p>
        <p>The Markows decided to think outside the box. They wanted to open up the dark middle of the house to get more light and to create a central gathering space. But that gathering space would displace the bathrooms, pantries and laundry often parked in the middle of a house.</p>
        <p>Remembering Mr. Garofalo from a project he had worked on a decade ago, Mr. Markow approached the architect with his ideas. ''I noticed that the diagonal views down the street across the fronts of houses were really pretty nice,'' Mr. Garofalo said. So he oriented his two-story addition to the side yard, which guaranteed a sunny south exposure. To do so, however, meant they would have to tear down the upper bedroom portion of the split-level house.</p>
        <p>Adding to suburban houses has been a national pastime since America's first suburbs were built. Usually, the houses are left picture-perfect in front, while sprouting casual additions in back. The Markows had already added in the rear, and Mr. Garofalo liked that their intervention wasn't seamless: the horizontal ranch-style dormers in the back didn't match the lines of the original split level. Aiming for gothic eccentricity rather than classical unity, Mr. Garofalo built on the irregularity. Taking the mismatched roofs as a point of departure, he developed the existing set of discordant dormers into a choppy topography of cresting gables. He folded and hinged the sloping planes into a set of butterfly roofs.</p>
        <p>''We liked that hybrid quality of the house facing the backyard and wanted to keep it, but we had to think of a way to glue it all together,'' Mr. Garofalo said. ''The roof was the opportunity. If you squint, you can still see the shapes relate to the surrounding roofs, with their valleys and gables, though ours evolved into a system closer to a landscape than a traditional roof.''</p>
        <p>The architect structured the turbulent roofscape with a thin steel truss system inside; the trusses support a ceiling whose complex faceting follows the roof topography. Midway through completion of the production drawings of the house, Mr. Garofalo started using computers with animation software, which confirmed the idea of connectivity and fluidity in the roofscape. The structure looks like a Cubist's interpretation of a house of seven gables.</p>
        <p>''With their interest in bringing in light, Andy and Aleksandra were adamant about opening up or removing sections of the existing house,'' Mr. Garofalo said. ''So we started thinking of perforating the house at all levels right away.'' The architect likens the porous quality of the house's interior to ancient Indian houses, with their subtle, continuous gradient between public and private spaces. He was socializing the interior of the typical suburban house by blurring its boundaries. He also choreographed a steel-and-plexiglass ramp and bridge that wind their way  over the central space to the music room at the peak. This large central living ''tube'' gives the house a large-scale open room at its core. Thinking big paid off with a heart space, an indoor piazza, onto which all other rooms flow.</p>
        <p>The Markows were able to bring this unconventional renovation in for $100 a square foot, for a total of $275,000. ''We really searched for the best products and prices, and made big savings,'' Mr. Markow said. ''I didn't ask Doug to do this, because it takes a lot of time.'' The couple called dozens of companies for competitive prices on the glass entry doors. They originally planned to put Kalwal translucent windows on the ceiling, but found a Wisconsin company making a similar window for 25 percent less. ''That saved us $3,000 or $4,000,'' Mr. Markow said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garofalo had specified a Swedish prefinished floor called Karss, ''but we were able to find a really great prefinished floor out of Finland for $4.50, rather than $8 or $9,'' Mr. Markow said. ''And we really didn't sacrifice quality.'' The couple also went through hundreds of catalogs for lighting and furniture, consulting the architect on final choices.</p>
        <p>''As a contractor, I know where to hunt,'' said Mr. Markow, who used Sweet's Catalogue, the Building and Construction Blue Book and the annual Architects' First Source for Products. ''We searched through a lot of magazines, also a great source, and we did some research on the Internet,'' he added.</p>
        <p>And the neighbors? ''The guy on the other side of the street, who just remodeled his split-level into a Georgian, said that he loved it,'' Mr. Markow said. ''Our new design is something different on the street that really strikes people. And inside, there's always something interesting going on with the sunlight. I never feel bored.''</p>
        <p>The unusual structure now recalls an earlier era when Chicago suburbs welcomed architectural experiments. Frank Lloyd Wright designed many of his masterpieces in nearby Oak Park, and the locally famous Keck brothers (building as Keck &amp; Keck from the 1930's through the 1950's) did suburban houses that gestured to the landscape. Before formulas set in, suburbia was the petri dish.</p>
        <p>DESIGN NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
