<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees' Swoon Is Nothing Nine Runs Can't End</title>
    <meta content="18YANK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2D7173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees' Swoon Is Nothing Nine Runs Can't End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Chicago White Sox, 9-4; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernie Williams was still in his T-shirt and long underwear when Chuck Knoblauch shouted across the clubhouse to tell the cleanup hitter that he was batting second last night. Williams did a double take, skipped a few steps to peek at the lineup posted on the clubhouse door and softly said, ''Cool.''</p>
        <p>Williams was happy to be hitting second for the first time this season after Joe Torre juggled the lineup to try to spark a moribund offense and find a suitable replacement for Derek Jeter. Now Torre plans on leaving Williams in that cozy spot for at least another game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bernie Williams was still in his T-shirt and long underwear when Chuck Knoblauch shouted across the clubhouse to tell the cleanup hitter that he was batting second last night. Williams did a double take, skipped a few steps to peek at the lineup posted on the clubhouse door and softly said, ''Cool.''</p>
        <p>Williams was happy to be hitting second for the first time this season after Joe Torre juggled the lineup to try to spark a moribund offense and find a suitable replacement for Derek Jeter. Now Torre plans on leaving Williams in that cozy spot for at least another game.</p>
        <p>The switch-hitting Williams hammered two homers, including a grand slam, hitting one homer from each side of the plate, to help the Yankees cruise to a 9-4 victory over the White Sox and terminate a five-game losing streak. After managing 11 runs in their previous five games and not winning since Jeter left last Thursday's game with a strained abdominal muscle, the Yankees erupted for almost as many runs in one night, possibly pacifying George Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>''If it doesn't work one way, you have to do something to get it started,'' Williams said. ''Joe has been characterized as having the Midas touch. Everything he does works for him. This proves some of that.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees could exhale after finally ending their longest losing streak in 12 months. Roger Clemens pitched like a stopper on a night on which he did not have to be so dominating. He permitted two runs and four hits in seven innings, while striking out nine, walking none and tossing only 87 pitches. But even if Clemens had fired a shutout, the focus would have remained on the disappointing offense's cranking out 15 hits for one fun night.</p>
        <p>''We knew this day would come,'' said Torre. ''But it's nice to do it.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he was ''playing with things'' by moving Williams, inserting Shane Spencer into the cleanup spot, batting Jorge Posada fifth and using Tino Martinez in the sixth position. Torre had toyed with moving Williams behind Chuck Knoblauch to give Knoblauch better pitches and liked how Spencer had been swinging, so he made the changes against the left-handed Jim Parque. Presto, the Yankees responded.</p>
        <p>Williams now has eight career grand slams and homered from both sides of the plate for the sixth time in his career. Spencer stroked three singles and Posada reached base three times. Knoblauch and Paul O'Neill, who remained in their usual spots, were also critical. Knoblauch had two hits, scored twice and studied plenty of pitches, and O'Neill had two doubles and also scored two runs.</p>
        <p>''All we need is one big inning,'' Knoblauch said before the Yankees burned about 10 bats in a streak-busting ritual. ''A few bloop hits. Something has to happen.''</p>
        <p>Finally, something did happen for the Yankees in the first inning, and Knoblauch started it. He lashed a liner off first baseman Paul Konerko's glove and raced to third with a tainted triple as the ball rattled around right fielder Magglio Ordonez. It was New York's first extra-base hit in 28 innings.</p>
        <p>Williams lined out to shortstop, but O'Neill slapped a double past first base and into the seats along the right-field line. Spencer, the cleanup man for the second time this season, punched a single to right and Posada knocked in the second run with a sacrifice fly to center. O'Neill doubled in the third, Posada walked and they both scored when Chris Singleton misplayed Jim Leyritz's liner to center field, putting the Yankees ahead, 4-0.</p>
        <p>Clemens was firing fastballs, getting ahead of hitters and doing what the Yankees want and need him to do. Even after plunking Jose Valentin in the first, which might have been payback for Clay Bellinger getting hit on Tuesday, Clemens stranded him at second by retiring Frank Thomas on a groundout and striking out Ordonez with a split-finger fastball. He did not face more than four batters in any inning and was much different from the pitcher who was pounded for six runs in Detroit six days ago.</p>
        <p>''What I didn't have in Detroit, I had tonight,'' Clemens said.</p>
        <p>Williams belted his first homer to left field off Parque in the fourth to give Clemens a 5-0 edge and he followed that with a towering grand slam to right off Tanyon Sturtze's 0-2 fastball in the fifth. The Yankees had a 9-1 bulge and Williams even hopped out of the dugout for a curtain call. For Williams, that was cool. Just like batting second.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER, who threw a ball 50 feet and ran yesterday, will swing a bat today and might take batting practice tomorrow, but the Yankees are still not sure if he will play this weekend against the Indians. . . . JORGE POSADA showed off a catcher's mitt with a fishnet webbing like the glove YOGI BERRA used for DON LARSEN's perfect game in the 1956 World Series. Berra arranged to have the webbing stitched in Posada's glove. ''I told him that I don't know if I'm going to use it,'' Posada said. ''He started laughing. It's tough to tell Yogi Berra I'm not going to use something he made for me.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
