<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Effort to Oust Assembly Speaker Upsets Democrats' Show of Unity</title>
    <meta content="18COUP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragman, Michael J (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver, Sheldon (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manton, Thomas J (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E4D7173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Effort to Oust Assembly Speaker Upsets Democrats' Show of Unity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Second-ranking member of New York State Assembly, Michael J Bragman, says he will try to overthrow Speaker Sheldon Silver, and Silver retaliates by stripping Bragman of his title of majority leader; fight leaves Democrats agog; if Bragman is elected to replace Silver, it would leave Capitol's ruling troika, governor and leaders of Assembly and Senate, without member from New York City for first time since 1974; most Democrats predict Silver will survive, but few rule out Bragman's chances, especially if he wins support of Republican minority in Assembly; if Bragman can force leadership vote, it will be partly referendum on Silver's ruling style, which has been criticized as secretive and inclined to hoarding power; Bragman himself is not well-liked, with reputation for hardball tactics bordering on meanness; Bragman's most influential supporter is Thomas J Manton, who has long feuded with Silver; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The State Assembly suddenly dissolved into open warfare today, as the second-ranking member, Michael J. Bragman, announced he would try to overthrow Speaker Sheldon Silver in a showdown vote Monday. The speaker retaliated by stripping Mr. Bragman of his title of majority leader.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary turn of events -- the last overt attempt to topple a  speaker was in the 1960's -- left Democrats agog. Coming the day after the party displayed a united front at its state convention in nominating Hillary Rodham Clinton for the Senate, this fight extends far beyond the walls of the Assembly chamber to gubernatorial and regional politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The State Assembly suddenly dissolved into open warfare today, as the second-ranking member, Michael J. Bragman, announced he would try to overthrow Speaker Sheldon Silver in a showdown vote Monday. The speaker retaliated by stripping Mr. Bragman of his title of majority leader.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary turn of events -- the last overt attempt to topple a  speaker was in the 1960's -- left Democrats agog. Coming the day after the party displayed a united front at its state convention in nominating Hillary Rodham Clinton for the Senate, this fight extends far beyond the walls of the Assembly chamber to gubernatorial and regional politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver may have hurt himself by trying to undermine State Comptroller H. Carl McCall's undeclared candidacy for governor in 2002, and promoting Andrew Cuomo, the secretary of housing and urban development. Mr. McCall has wide support among elected officials, and he demonstrated his popularity Tuesday with a speech at the convention that brought down the house.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the election of Mr. Bragman, whose district is near Syracuse, would be a seismic shift in tradition that has dictated for generations that when the Democrats control the Assembly, the speaker must be from New York City. The defeat of Mr. Silver would leave the Capitol's ruling troika, the governor and the leaders of the Assembly and Senate, without a member from New York City for the first time since 1974.</p>
        <p>Democrats frantically conducted head counts late today, with many acknowledging that their tallies were barely more accurate than a reading of tea leaves, as fence-sitters nervously tried to decide which side to embrace. Most Democrats interviewed predicted that Mr. Silver would survive, but few ruled out Mr. Bragman's chances, especially if he won the support of the Republican minority in the Assembly.</p>
        <p>Many Democrats said Mr. Bragman had hurt his chances by reaching out to Republicans, an alliance many Democrats, including those with no love for Mr. Silver, recoil from. At an impromptu news conference, Mr. Bragman denied conspiring with Republicans or making them any promises.</p>
        <p>But he said: ''I know that there are members of the Republican conference who also want change, and I respect that. But that is not a part of this effort. If they choose to vote when the time comes to vote, if there is a vote, well then, that's fine and I would be appreciative of that.''</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki would not  comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman said he had the support of most Democrats, who have a 98-to-52 advantage in the Assembly. ''We will call for a vote to replace the speaker and to elect a new speaker,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Silver loyalists insisted that the speaker held control. ''The notion that the Democrats are dissatisfied with Shelly Silver is hallucinatory,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester County Democrat. ''There's no rationale for the candidacy, and no votes for it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver tapped into his deep reservoir of favors owed, calling on allies like Dennis Rivera, president of 1199, the powerful hospital workers' union, and Randi Weingarten, president of the United Federation of Teachers, to make calls to wavering Assembly members. The speaker's aides said to expect dissenters to be stripped of committee chairmanships and leadership posts, and the extra pay they bring.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman spoke to reporters accompanied by perhaps his most influential supporter, Thomas J. Manton, the Queens Democratic leader, who has long feuded with Mr. Silver and who gives Mr. Bragman a major foothold in New York City.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bragman can force a leadership vote -- a question in some doubt today -- it will be partly a referendum on Mr. Silver's ruling style, which has been criticized as secretive and inclined to hoarding power.</p>
        <p>''I have felt for a long time that I am not as productive as I could be, that whatever intelligence I may have, whatever talent I may have, whatever energy I may have, is not being used appropriately,'' said Assemblyman Martin A. Luster, a Democrat from Ithaca who was one of the few to speak openly in favor of Mr. Bragman. ''More often than not, I feel more like an ornament standing around at the speaker's press conferences.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver does not socialize much with the Assembly members, a fact that produces some grumbling, while Mr. Bragman does. But Mr. Bragman is not well liked either, having gained a reputation for hardball tactics bordering on meanness.</p>
        <p>''People are wary of Bragman, but he's perceived to be someone you go to when you have a problem, you need a favor, you need something to get fixed,'' said an Assembly member from New York City who described himself as a fence sitter, leaning toward Mr. Silver.</p>
        <p>''But this is not just about being liked. This is also about promises that are being made, about committee chairmanships, about young careers getting fast-tracked, about pork spending in individual districts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman is a powerful fund-raiser who has curried favor among his colleagues by spreading money around. He is also a conservative, which could put off many of the New York City members. The people identified today as his supporters were mostly upstaters and conservatives, who resent the city and consider it a sinkhole for taxpayers' money.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Silver has been adept at using issues and campaign money to rebuff Republican attempts to reduce the Democrats' majority, his broader leadership has been called into question, as in his persistently chilly relations with Mr. McCall.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats in both camps say Mr. Silver's attempts to push Mr. Cuomo could persuade black legislators to consider going for Mr. Bragman. Top black Assembly members did not return phone calls today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman and aides to Mr. McCall said the comptroller had no role in Mr. Bragman's plans, and people close to Mr. Silver said the speaker believed that to be the truth. But a few Assembly members said they did not think the comptroller had dissuaded those who looked to him for guidance from throwing in their lots with Mr. Bragman.</p>
        <p>In 1998, when most party leaders wanted to unite behind Peter F. Vallone, the New York City Council speaker, as their candidate for governor, Mr. Silver tried to block Mr. Vallone, and promoted the chances of District Attorney Charles J. Hynes of Brooklyn, widely viewed as no more than a nuisance candidate.</p>
        <p>Many Democrats say privately  they doubt Mr. Silver wants a Democratic governor -- or, for that matter, a Democratic majority in the State Senate -- because he would no longer be unchallenged as the most important Democrat in Albany. But people close to Mr. Silver say the real reason he undercut Mr. Vallone was that Mr. Vallone had met with Mr. Bragman in 1997, when he first began planning a coup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manton, a former United States representative, resented Mr. Silver's attempts to undercut Mr. Vallone. But it was unclear how much influence he had over the Queens delegation, which includes one of the speaker's fiercest defenders, Assemblywoman Catherine T. Nolan.</p>
        <p>Several officials said Mr. Bragman set the coup attempt in motion on Tuesday, at the convention, perhaps emboldened by Mr. McCall's showing and by Mr. Silver's being so wrapped up in organizing the event.</p>
        <p>Still, the timing was odd, and it perplexed many Assembly members. Speakers are elected at the start of each two-year term, and in some respects it is more difficult to replace one midterm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver is also fresh from budget talks with Governor Pataki and the Republican-controlled State Senate, where he was widely seen as a winner. And while he was viewed as vulnerable a few years ago, when the Republicans were riding high, since the Democrats' victories in the 1998 elections and the passage of a pay raise for legislators a month later, he has been considered secure.</p>
        <p>Usually, a speaker is chosen by the majority party's conference in an informal closed session. When a candidate emerges with a majority -- in this case, 50 of the 98 Democrats -- the Assembly is convened and the entire party conference unites behind that candidate in a formal vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bragman introduced a motion today to change the Assembly rules to allow the removal of a speaker at any time. He said that if the motion passed, he would then make a motion to remove Mr. Silver. Mr. Silver's allies insisted he might be able to prevent a vote on the rules change.</p>
        <p>Each motion requires 76 votes, a simple majority of the State Assembly. Many Republicans, whose distaste for Mr. Silver is intense, would surely go along. But relying heavily on Republican votes could leave Mr. Bragman ruling through a rump Democratic faction, and beholden to the Republicans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
