<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Around the World With Artists and Happy Campers</title>
    <meta content="18REVU$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOK REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Eve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">burkhart, bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hunt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramljak, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">monroe, michael w</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">mason, arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ferrand, franck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">goad, philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">todd, pamela</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">jacques garcia: decorating in the french style (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">melbourne architecture (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">airstream: the history of the land yacht (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">turning wood into art (book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">bloomsbury at home (book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EEDC163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Around the World With Artists and Happy Campers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eve Kahn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Eve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eve Kahn reviews five design book: Airstream by Bryan Burkhart and David Hunt, Turning Wood Into Art by Suzanne Ramljak, Michael W Monroe and Arthur Mason, Jacques Garcia by Franck Ferrand, Melbourne Architecture by Philip Goad and Bloomsbury at Home by Pamela Todd; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AIRSTREAM: THE HISTORY OF THE LAND YACHT</p>
        <p>By Bryan Burkhart and David Hunt  Chronicle Books, 144 pp., 125 illustrations, $19.95</p>
        <p>PERHAPS the machine age's only design to remain in production little altered is the Airstream trailer, with its distinctive bread-loaf shape and aluminum shell. Its endurance is due largely to a former ad man named Wally Byam, who from the 1950's through the 70's made a global publicity magnet out of a bankrupt trailer manufacturer he had bought in 1936. Long after his product's Art Deco curves went out of fashion, he led hundreds of cars pulling Airstreams across continents, besting harsh terrains and entertaining journalists all the way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AIRSTREAM: THE HISTORY OF THE LAND YACHT</p>
        <p>By Bryan Burkhart and David Hunt  Chronicle Books, 144 pp., 125 illustrations, $19.95</p>
        <p>PERHAPS the machine age's only design to remain in production little altered is the Airstream trailer, with its distinctive bread-loaf shape and aluminum shell. Its endurance is due largely to a former ad man named Wally Byam, who from the 1950's through the 70's made a global publicity magnet out of a bankrupt trailer manufacturer he had bought in 1936. Long after his product's Art Deco curves went out of fashion, he led hundreds of cars pulling Airstreams across continents, besting harsh terrains and entertaining journalists all the way.</p>
        <p>Half of this book covers the history of Airstream Inc., and the other half deals with the caravans' adventures. The main attractions throughout are the kitschy pictures. (The text sounds a little too much like authorized corporate biography: ''Airstreamers may express their brand loyalty in upgrades of newer models, but it's a loyalty that grows out of commitment to each other.'') In two-page spreads of old ad campaigns, happy campers appear parked by trout ponds or tropical sands, and in the book's plentiful documentation of the caravans, Airstreams incongruously pass the Great Pyramids or the Tower of Pisa or a crowd of African Pygmies. (These plus some bonus extra images also appear in a boxed set of postcards -- send your friends pictures of trailers unfazed by Oaxacan mud! -- which Chronicle is selling separately for $15.95.)</p>
        <p>TURNING WOOD INTO ART: THE JANE AND ARTHUR MASON COLLECTION</p>
        <p>By Suzanne Ramljak, Michael W. Monroe and Arthur Mason  Abrams, 224 pp., 141 illustrations, $49.50</p>
        <p>I NEVER met a bowl I did not like,'' Arthur Mason writes, explaining why he and his wife, Jane, have bought more than 600 turned-wood vessels from the world's growing population of artistically inclined lathe operators. The couple recently donated one-fifth of their collection to the Mint Museum of Craft &amp; Design in Charlotte, N.C., which will display the objects from May 20 to Oct. 8.</p>
        <p>This book, the exhibition's catalog, gives its narrow topic a surprisingly interesting, well, spin.</p>
        <p>The featured pieces all involved a trace of lathing. But the materials range from humble plywood to woods few of us have heard of, like cocobolo, and the surfaces may have undergone harsh sandblasting and scorching or opaque lacquering. The shapes are mostly shallow cones and hemispheres, although some of the artists preferred to warp their woods or leave burls unpolished or carve tableaus like a miniature Pompeii.</p>
        <p>The unpretentious introductory essays discuss the evolution of fine lathing, particularly its revival since the 1950's, and the artists' philosophies and methods. A little more technical detail would have been welcome: how, for example, does one hone a mass of pine cone slices embedded in epoxy into a polka-dotted receptacle the size of a shot glass?</p>
        <p>JACQUES GARCIA: DECORATING IN THE FRENCH STYLE</p>
        <p>By Franck Ferrand  Flammarion, 264 pp., 200 illustrations, $60</p>
        <p>THE Parisian interior designer Jacques Garcia no doubt has  eclectic and prolific talents. He has drawn on precedents as varied as Mogul opium dens and French portrait galleries for commissions ranging from chateaus to gyms. (Last fall, he made his American debut with the opulent, quasi-Viennese restaurant Danube, in TriBeCa.) But has any designer ever really been, as Mr. Ferrand suggests, ''forged to exercise the arcane crafts connected with capturing the spirit of place, taming its vibrations and rousing its soul''? And could any interior really represent ''manifestations of the secret joy felt by a man listening to the faintest of inner voices''?</p>
        <p>Some insights do emerge from Mr. Ferrand's purple prose, which was translated from French. He implies, for example, that Mr. Garcia is especially fond of objects that once belonged to royalty -- covering a screen, say, with the last pieces of fabric woven for the bedroom of Louis XVI at Versailles -- because he grew up impoverished in Paris's suburbs. As a teenager at decorative arts school he learned to ape his upper-crust classmates, and soon duchesses were inviting him to tea. Partly inspired by their homes, he perfected his fringed, tasseled, gilded, paneled, damasked and muraled mode.</p>
        <p>The book is loosely organized into sections on his private and commercial clients, but often the lush pictures do not relate to the adjacent text, and captions leave out basics like the rooms' locations and dates of execution. The text itself meanders from career moves to inventive room layouts to Mr. Garcia's personality quirks (''terribly self-confident yet avid for reassurance''). Fans of Mr. Garcia will of course want this volume beside their canopied bedsteads, and other enthusiasts of history-driven, over-the-top decor will also be tempted.</p>
        <p>MELBOURNE ARCHITECTURE</p>
        <p>By Philip Goad  Watermark Press (Antique Collectors' Club), 288 pp., 360 illustrations, $29.95</p>
        <p>WHERE else but Melbourne would a kangaroo-shaped finial top a back-street cottage, or where would a legislative chamber be lined with columns carved from Tasmanian freestone? And yet over the last two centuries, architects there have also excelled at importing ideas,  from Louis Sullivan's deep-set archways in Chicago to the de Stijl movement's ornament-stripped walls and roofs in Holland. Melbourne has preserved its motley streetscape, too; how many American cities founded, like Melbourne, in the 1830's can still boast both original colonists' cottages and a tail-fin-trimmed Art Deco pub now serving as a McDonald's?</p>
        <p>Mr. Goad gives brief, lively descriptions of 448 landmarks in this chronological guide, which design-minded tourists will want to take along (although armchair travelers will probably be frustrated by the small grainy photographs). Landscape connoisseurs will be intrigued as well, since Mr. Goad often mentions plantings around notable buildings, like the pine tree beside the  city's main war memorial that grew from seeds pocketed by a soldier at Gallipoli.</p>
        <p>The same publisher and distributor have already brought out a similar volume on Sydney, and a Brisbane guide is imminent.</p>
        <p>BLOOMSBURY AT HOME</p>
        <p>By Pamela Todd  Abrams, 192 pp., 100 illustrations, $27.50</p>
        <p>UNFAITHFUL spouses, nervous breakdowns, decorating schemes that allowed for maximum creativity -- these are a few things that the flamboyant Bloomsbury households had in common.</p>
        <p>Virginia Woolf, for instance, let her literary printing press take over the dining room, and her sister, the painter Vanessa Bell, plunked down easels in any corner she pleased and encouraged guests to do likewise. Bell and her live-in coterie of lovers and ex-lovers did one another's portraits and painted right on the walls and furniture in intense hues inspired by Post-Impressionism.</p>
        <p>Ms. Todd has drawn on these paintings, plus various memoirs and diaries, to competently sum up the circle's life stories and domestic habits, down to the kedgeree or kippers they sometimes served for breakfast. The chapters cover various geographic regions where ''Bloomsberries'' congregated, especially Sussex and the south of France, and the somewhat cloying text rambles, too: Ms. Todd keeps re-identifying Bloomsbury hangers-on like the Russian mosaicist Boris Anrep and reiterating her praise for Bell's skill at creating ''an apparently easy atmosphere of informality'' and ''an apparently effortless atmosphere of congenial calm.''</p>
        <p>The quotes from the group's writings are evocative, though, and the illustrations include photographs of the members relaxing between artworks in their menages a trois -- or quatre.</p>
        <p>BOOK REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
