<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poll Finds Voters Skeptical About Role in Nominations</title>
    <meta content="Y18POL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times/cbs News Poll</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7DB173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poll Finds Voters Skeptical About Role in Nominations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows Americans have little sense of power over presidential nominating process; only fifth of them say primary voters selected Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore; vast majority of those polled say they would prefer single national primary to present system, which they feel confers too much influence to states holding early presidential primaries; nearly 60 percent of public calls presidential campaign dull, rather than interesting; poll shows overall interest in campaign has dropped sharply in two months since nominations of two major parties were decided (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans have little sense of power over the presidential nominating process, with only a fifth of them saying primary voters selected Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore as the candidates for president, the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows.</p>
        <p>A vast majority of the 947 adults interviewed last week said they would prefer a single national primary to the present system, which they said confers too much influence to states holding early presidential primaries. Seventy-five percent favored a national primary, while 20 percent said the present system was preferable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans have little sense of power over the presidential nominating process, with only a fifth of them saying primary voters selected Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and Vice President Al Gore as the candidates for president, the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll shows.</p>
        <p>A vast majority of the 947 adults interviewed last week said they would prefer a single national primary to the present system, which they said confers too much influence to states holding early presidential primaries. Seventy-five percent favored a national primary, while 20 percent said the present system was preferable.</p>
        <p>Nearly three-fifths of the public called the presidential campaign dull, rather than interesting. Republicans, perhaps because three-fourths of them expect to win the White House in November, were less critical. They divided evenly on the question.</p>
        <p>But overall interest in the campaign has dropped sharply in the two months since the nominations of the two major parties were decided. Only 15 percent of those surveyed said they had discussed the campaign in the previous day. In mid-March, 49 percent told pollsters for Harvard's Joan Shorenstein Center on the Press, Politics and Public Policy that they had talked about the campaign that day.</p>
        <p>While respondents agreed that voters had little influence over either party's choice, they had different explanations of who made the Republican and Democratic decisions. For Mr. Bush, the public thought campaign money was most important, while for Mr. Gore, they said it was the support of party leaders. Both judgments reflected the attention those factors drew during the nomination contests.</p>
        <p>While 21 percent said the voters had the most influence in picking Mr. Bush, 26 percent said party leaders were decisive, and 44 percent credited his success to ''people who contributed money.''</p>
        <p>Concerning Mr. Gore, 20 percent said the voters were decisive for his candidacy, while 48 percent said party leaders had the most say and 24 percent said contributors held the most influence.</p>
        <p>The telephone poll had a margin of sampling error of plus or minus three percentage points.</p>
        <p>The public support for a national primary in the poll, which was conducted from May 10 through May 13, was not unusual. The Gallup Poll has found comparable majorities for the idea since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Respondents who were asked to discuss their reasons for supporting a national primary generally contended that it would make the process shorter, neater and, surprisingly, cleaner.</p>
        <p>Annette Scott, a nurse's assistant from Miami who is a Democrat, said,  ''A single primary day would eliminate the money spent digging up dirt on each other.''</p>
        <p>Glenda Tager, a homemaker in Lexington, S.C., who is a Republican, said, ''With one day, they would spend less money, and people wouldn't have to listen to so much negative campaigning.''</p>
        <p>But the depth of the support for the concept was not tested because the poll did not pose the arguments against such a plan that wouid be raised if the parties or Congress seriously considered a national primary.</p>
        <p>Thomas Mann, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, said yesterday that politicians and academics are generally hostile to a one-day national primary because they say it would require tremendous resources available only to a candidate already perceived as a front-runner.</p>
        <p>And, he said, ''It removes any real opportunity for a sequential testing for the candidates and a learning process for the voters.''</p>
        <p>Republican leaders are considering a third option, with small states voting first and the biggest states holding their primaries last. They argue that this is the only way to forestall the national primary they see developing as states seek political influence by seizing the earliest possible dates.</p>
        <p>But this plan, which was also presented to respondents without arguments pro or con, did not impress those surveyed. Thirty-six percent said it would be better than the present system, but 49 percent said it would be worse.</p>
        <p>About half of those surveyed said they were satisfied with the candidates who emerged, while half said they wanted more choices. People who said they would vote for Mr. Bush were slightly more content; 58 percent of them said they were satisfied with the choices now, compared with 52 percent of Mr. Gore's supporters.</p>
        <p>Some questions tapped, quite deeply, into traditional reservoirs of hostility or at least skepticism about the electoral system.</p>
        <p>For example, 33 percent agreed with the statement: ''It makes no real difference who is elected president -- things go on as they did before.'' Similar findings were typical in 1996. But 20 years earlier, in 1976, only 19 percent agreed.</p>
        <p>Similarly, 64 percent of those surveyed said that people like themselves had ''not much'' to say about what government does. Since the Times/CBS News Poll first asked the question in 1990, only once did it draw a higher response. And in February, at the peak of the primary season, just 48 percent expressed that sense of powerlessness.</p>
        <p>The dismay came through in some  follow-up interviews. Jane Marawar, a homemaker in Austin, Tex., said, ''It's important to vote, but money seems to be running the election process.'' Mrs. Marawar, a Democrat, said she did not vote in the Texas primary on March 14, a week after Mr. Gore was credited with wrapping up the nomination. By then, she said, ''the die was cast.''</p>
        <p>''People think 'the nomination is already decided, why should I bother, why should I get involved?' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Scott, the Miami Democrat, said: ''I didn't feel I had much of a say. It just seems whomever the party sent out, we were expected to accept. It wasn't as if there were a variety of people to choose from. It just seems like the candidate was prepackaged, endorsed by the party and that's the way it is, take it or leave it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
