<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mattel Names Kraft Chief To Top Post</title>
    <meta content="Y18TOY$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mattel Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kraft Foods</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barad, Jill E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckert, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D9173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mattel Names Kraft Chief To Top Post</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mattel Inc names Robert A Eckert, chief executive of Kraft Foods, as its new chairman and chief executive; he succeeds Jill E Barad, who resigned in February; Eckert says he understands his charge is to 'build value for shareholder'; Wall Street hails Eckert's selection; his photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Invading the world of Jell-O and Miracle Whip to revive its battered toy business, Mattel Inc. announced yesterday that it had named Robert A. Eckert, the chief executive of Kraft Foods, as its new chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert, 45, takes the position left by Jill E. Barad, who resigned in February after failing to turn around a troubled software company that Mattel bought for $3.8 billion a year ago. Losses from the software company, the Learning Company, were $183 million in the fourth quarter of last year and erased earnings for Mattel,  which makes toys under the Barbie, Hot Wheels and Fisher-Price brand names. As Ms. Barad stepped down, Mattel, based in El Segundo, Calif., reported a loss of $82 million, or 21 cents a share, for the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Invading the world of Jell-O and Miracle Whip to revive its battered toy business, Mattel Inc. announced yesterday that it had named Robert A. Eckert, the chief executive of Kraft Foods, as its new chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert, 45, takes the position left by Jill E. Barad, who resigned in February after failing to turn around a troubled software company that Mattel bought for $3.8 billion a year ago. Losses from the software company, the Learning Company, were $183 million in the fourth quarter of last year and erased earnings for Mattel,  which makes toys under the Barbie, Hot Wheels and Fisher-Price brand names. As Ms. Barad stepped down, Mattel, based in El Segundo, Calif., reported a loss of $82 million, or 21 cents a share, for the year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Barad's repeated promises of improvement for the Learning Company hurt Mattel's credibility with investors. The stock price has lost nearly three-quarters of its value over the last two years, trading at $11 a share in recent weeks, compared with a high of $45.625 in March 1998.</p>
        <p>Wall Street applauded the choice of Mr. Eckert, under whose watch Kraft has grown faster than the rest of the food industry, which has been in the doldrums. Investors sent Mattel's share price up $1.50, to $12.75.</p>
        <p>''My mandate from the board is to build value for the shareholder,'' Mr. Eckert said yesterday in a telephone interview, adding that he plans to do that by cutting costs, building brands and developing managers. ''I learned how to do that at Philip Morris and Kraft,'' he said, ''and it is challenging to do those three things simultaneously. But when we do that, the company will be back on track with the investment community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckert said a close look at Mattel's  profit margins and operating expenses showed room for improvement. ''We will take a hard look at manufacturing costs,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said he left Kraft for Mattel to run what he called ''one of the greatest consumer brand names in the world.''</p>
        <p>Philip Morris, the parent company of Kraft, said Mr. Eckert, who had been at Kraft for 23 years, would be replaced by Betsy D. Holden, 44, the executive vice president of Kraft Foods. Both she and Mr. Eckert rose through the ranks at Kraft, with stints in the cheese division and other packaged-food divisions. A Philip Morris spokesman, Christopher Kircher, said the company wished Mr. Eckert well.</p>
        <p>''Losing your C.E.O. is not a positive,'' said Marc Cohen, an analyst at Goldman, Sachs. ''But this is a company that I think has pretty deep management and, more importantly, doesn't change strategy. It's not a stand-alone company without any oversight.''</p>
        <p>Philip Morris is widely considered to be among the companies interested in acquiring Nabisco Group Holdings, which owns 80.4 percent of Nabisco Holdings, the maker of Oreo cookies, Wheat Thins and other food products. Combining the two companies would create a monolith in the marketplace. Many food manufacturers say huge size is essential to working with supermarket chains, which have gone through their own wave of consolidation over the last few years.</p>
        <p>While many executives have announced plans to depart Mattel in recent months, including Pleasant Rowland, the founder of the American Girl doll line that Mattel bought in 1998, Mr. Eckert said he was pleased with the management team he would be inheriting. ''They are doing a wonderful job,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Asked what his management style was, Mr. Eckert said: ''I try to be just another person.'' His decision to leave Kraft, he said, came because ''it was a time in my life and my career to make a change, and this came along.'' The prospect of further consolidation in the food business did not affect his decision, he said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, after meeting informally with Mattel employees, he said he would begin to quickly read his way through the Harry Potter books, a highly successful series by J. K. Rowling that sold licensing rights for toys to Mattel earlier this year. Hasbro, Mattel's chief competitor, got the rights for trading cards and other novelties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
