<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Game Draws a Range of Protests</title>
    <meta content="18RAID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Simon &amp; Schuster Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Bonnie Rothman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDB163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Game Draws a Range of Protests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BONNIE ROTHMAN MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bonnie Rothman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Planned release by Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive of new CD-ROM game, Panty Raider: From Here to Immaturity, has drawn protests from Christian right, national advocacy groups for women and girls and group of hard-core gamers; object of game is for player to strip cartoon supermodels down to their underwear, photograph them and deliver photos to sex-starved aliens threatening to blow up earth; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE scheduled release on Saturday of a new CD-ROM game, Panty Raider: From Here to Immaturity, has drawn protests from a wide range of organizations: groups on the Christian right, national advocacy groups for women and girls, and a group of hard-core gamers. Many of them are using phone calls, e-mail, letters and even prayer in an effort to  halt the distribution of the game.</p>
        <p>The object of the game is for the player to strip cartoon supermodels down to their underwear, take their photographs and deliver the photos to three sex-starved aliens before the aliens blow up the earth in ''hormone-driven anger.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE scheduled release on Saturday of a new CD-ROM game, Panty Raider: From Here to Immaturity, has drawn protests from a wide range of organizations: groups on the Christian right, national advocacy groups for women and girls, and a group of hard-core gamers. Many of them are using phone calls, e-mail, letters and even prayer in an effort to  halt the distribution of the game.</p>
        <p>The object of the game is for the player to strip cartoon supermodels down to their underwear, take their photographs and deliver the photos to three sex-starved aliens before the aliens blow up the earth in ''hormone-driven anger.''</p>
        <p>To accomplish that goal, the player uses pickup lines supplied by the game, clothes-dissolving goop and bait, like credit cards and a lunch of tiny breath mints, which a  press release says ''no self-respecting supermodel can resist.'' Created by Hypnotix for Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive, the game was rated M by the Entertainment Software Review board, indicating that the game is aimed at adults.</p>
        <p>But Carlton Kendrick, a family therapist in Boston, said adults were not the intended audience. ''Anybody who hasn't been lobotomized knows that this game is not being geared toward mature teens or grown-ups,'' said Mr. Kendrick, a consultant for  the FamilyEducation Network, which operates a group of Web sites and issued a statement calling for Simon &amp; Schuster to halt the game's release. ''This is aimed at pubescent little boys who are trying to sneak onto Web sites and see porn.''</p>
        <p>The protests seem to have been sparked by Dads and Daughters, a national group based in Duluth, Minn., whose mission is to urge fathers to help their daughters develop self-esteem without regard to how they look. The group took up the cause against Panty Raider and asked its members to send letters of protest.</p>
        <p>Joe Kelly, founder of the group, said the protest had ''gotten the biggest response on any actions we've done.'' Mr. Kelly said the game treated women as objects and made fun of anorexia. He said it sent the message that ''I'm a male, I have sex on my mind -- if I don't get it, I'm going to kill somebody.''</p>
        <p>Groups like the National Center for Policy Research for Women and Families and the Center for Health and Gender Equity have also denounced the game as offensive. The American Family Association has asked members to pray that Viacom, the parent company of Simon &amp; Schuster, will choose not to release the game.</p>
        <p>''This game is not for kids at all,''  said Peter Binazeski, a spokesman for Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive. ''It is for mature adults only and is being marketed accordingly.'' He described the problem of the product's  getting in the hands of children as ''a retail issue,'' and added, ''I think a parent is the one who should be there watching.'' Mr. Binazeski said that he had received only five letters protesting the game's release but that many e-mail messages had been sent to the company's Panty Raider Web site.</p>
        <p>''Protest letters outweigh support 60-40,'' he said.  ''We've gotten quite a few e-mails from people saying it's hysterical.''</p>
        <p>Some adult male gamers are not thrilled either. ''Please don't accuse us of not getting the joke of Panty Raider or of being politically correct zealots,'' Chris Kramer wrote in an article for DailyRadar.com about the game's release. ''We're as P.C. as Panty Raider is funny: not at all.'' He called the premise of the game ''heinously stupid.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Kay, senior editor of MyVideoGames.com, said that even though the premise of the game was ''unusually dumb,'' calls for censoring it were even more worrisome.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kay said the game's list price, $19.99, indicated that even Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive did not consider Panty Raider much of a game. Most high-profile games sell for $40 and up, he said, so the low price indicates that Panty Raider may be headed ''straight for the bargain bins.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Binazewski said, ''It's considered a casual game, not a game you'd play for hours and hours, and it's priced accordingly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
