<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils' Special Teams Will Miss Madden</title>
    <meta content="18DEVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2D7173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils' Special Teams Will Miss Madden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New Jersey Devils special teams preparing for third game of Eastern Conference championship series against Philadelphia Flyers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the Devils' hallmarks this season has been special teams. Today, they learned that one of their best penalty killers would miss Game 3 and possibly the rest of the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>The rookie John Madden, who led the National Hockey League with six short-handed goals in the regular season, injured his right knee when he was leveled by Philadelphia's Keith Primeau late in Game 2 on Tuesday night and had to be helped off the ice. Madden had a magnetic resonance imaging test today and, while the exact nature of the injury was not revealed, the Devils said he would miss at least Thursday night's game at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the Devils' hallmarks this season has been special teams. Today, they learned that one of their best penalty killers would miss Game 3 and possibly the rest of the Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>The rookie John Madden, who led the National Hockey League with six short-handed goals in the regular season, injured his right knee when he was leveled by Philadelphia's Keith Primeau late in Game 2 on Tuesday night and had to be helped off the ice. Madden had a magnetic resonance imaging test today and, while the exact nature of the injury was not revealed, the Devils said he would miss at least Thursday night's game at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''It didn't turn out to be as bad as it appeared,'' Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' president and general manager, said. ''The injury to his knee will not require surgery. The injury is, in fact, similar to the injury suffered by Sergei Brylin in Game 2 of the Florida series.''</p>
        <p>Brylin's injury, diagnosed as a bruise, sidelined him six games. Madden's replacement will be Steve Brule, who will center the checking line that has Jay Pandolfo on the left wing and Claude Lemieux on the right.</p>
        <p>''We were looking for someone good in draws, and he's good on face-offs,'' Coach Larry Robinson said of his decision to go with Brule. The Flyers dominated the Devils on face-offs, 42-26, on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''It was a tossup between the two who was going to stay with the club after training camp,'' Robinson said of Madden and Brule, ''and I don't feel uncomfortable with Brule, just like I didn't feel uncomfortable with Scott Kelly in place of Brylin.''</p>
        <p>Brule, who has never played in the N.H.L., said, ''I'm pretty good on face-offs and I kill penalties.''</p>
        <p>''I'll go out there and do my best, but I don't kill penalties as well as Mad Dog,'' he said of Madden.</p>
        <p>''We'll miss Mad Dog,'' said Pandolfo, who is probably the Devils' second-best penalty killer. ''He's a big part of the p.k., but we've got other guys who can do it.''</p>
        <p>The Flyers had their own casualty from Tuesday's fierce-hitting 4-3 victory, which evened the four-of-seven-game series at 1-1. Daymond Langkow, who scored the winning goal 1 minute 58 seconds into the last period, was knocked out 39 seconds later by Scott Stevens, who delivered a vicious open-ice hit.</p>
        <p>The Flyers said today that Langkow had sustained a concussion, but they didn't rule him out of Game 3.</p>
        <p>Coach Craig Ramsay said after the Flyers' practice today in Voorhees, N.J., that if Langkow could not play, Mark Recchi would move from right wing to center on the top line and Simon Gagne would move to right wing opposite John LeClair.</p>
        <p>Most people in hockey were rather surprised at the lack of physical play in the opening game of the series, a  4-1 Devils victory. There were only four minor penalties in the game, a huge contrast to the second encounter in Philadelphia, in which 10 penalties were assessed, 5 to each team.</p>
        <p>Two penalties were to the Devils' Randy McKay and Primeau for fighting, a rather unusual practice in the playoffs. The only other postseason fight was between the Devils' Patrik Elias and Toronto's Darcy Tucker in the elimination of the Maple Leafs. That fight occurred after the game's outcome was no longer in doubt.</p>
        <p>McKay and Primeau fought midway through the second period, an act some considered foolish on the part of Primeau because he had just returned from a concussion. With that, the Flyers sent notice that this series would be physical from here on.</p>
        <p>The series may get even more physical if Philadelphia's Eric Lindros returns from a concussion. Lindros, who has been out since March 13, may play if the series is extended to six games.</p>
        <p>He skated for 20 minutes on Tuesday, and before Game 2 at First Union Center he said: ''This is the best I've felt in a long time. I'm looking forward to getting back into action.''</p>
        <p>Lindros said he had not had a headache for at least a week. Lindros had hoped to return against the Penguins, but his attempt ended during a drill in practice May 4, when he collided with the minor league defenseman Francis Lessard. If he experiences no further setbacks, Lindros will be examined again on Monday by Dr. James Kelly, and he could start practicing with the team the next day.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
