<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Nemesis Converts The Pope</title>
    <meta content="18WITC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Irondale Ensemble Project</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niesen, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fo, Dario</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pope and the Witch, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DC163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Nemesis Converts The Pope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews The Pope and the Witch, Dario Fo play presented by Irondale Ensemble Project under direction of Jim Niesen at Theater for the New City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The playful but dangerous irreverence of the court jester pervades ''The Pope and the Witch.''</p>
        <p>And why not? The author is Dario Fo, the septuagenarian Italian actor and playwright who won the Nobel Prize for literature in 1997. A Communist, a satirist, he aims his sarcasm and slapstick comedy at authority, and in ''The Pope and the Witch'' he takes dead aim at the highest levels of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The playful but dangerous irreverence of the court jester pervades ''The Pope and the Witch.''</p>
        <p>And why not? The author is Dario Fo, the septuagenarian Italian actor and playwright who won the Nobel Prize for literature in 1997. A Communist, a satirist, he aims his sarcasm and slapstick comedy at authority, and in ''The Pope and the Witch'' he takes dead aim at the highest levels of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>In a literal sense, the weapons include guns, a child's bow and arrow, a knife, poison, heroin, truth serum and a canary filled with TNT. But Mr. Fo fights with ideas, too. And here he is battling for the church to change its opposition to abortion and to the legalization of drugs.</p>
        <p>Though the issues are serious and weighty, Mr. Fo's approach -- abetted by the talents of the Irondale Ensemble Project and its artistic director, Jim Niesen -- is light, loony and playful. And while ''The Pope and the Witch'' may raise hackles, as it did when presented in San Francisco a few years ago, this high-spirited, intelligent production, playing through Sunday at the Theater for the New City in the East Village, may be savored as an example of Mr. Fo's style and as a polemic worthy of attention in a city where recent change in the hierarchy of the Catholic Church has refocused attention on its tenets.</p>
        <p>''The Pope and the Witch'' is enlivened by a radio-controlled toy car, balloons, cell phones tucked in clerical underwear, a sly Oz-like reference to a puppet pope, topical jokes about Manuel Noriega and violence in American schools, and a shaggy dog story about beans that ends with the creation of the Green Party.</p>
        <p>But these are only the amusing means that accompany the telling of its story of the Pope (played by Terry Greiss, the executive director of Irondale) and the Witch (Heidi K. Eklund).</p>
        <p>At the outset, the nameless pope, with 100,000 orphans waiting in St. Peter's Square and the world's press assembled for a news conference in the Vatican, is in the throes of paranoia, believing that the appearance of the children is sponsored by manufacturers of condoms in a plot to embarrass the Church.</p>
        <p>The witch, in nun's habit, turns up as an aide to the doctor summoned to treat the pope, and before long the Holy Father is seized with a paralytic affliction that, among other names, is known as ''a crucifixion stroke,'' leaving him with his arms outstretched.</p>
        <p>And who besides the little witch, who favors abortion and legalization of drugs, can alleviate his distress? By the time matters play themselves out, the pope, in mufti, will have paid a visit to the little witch's clinic, where she dispenses free heroin from clean needles, all courtesy of a  mysterious benefactor. And she and the pope will encounter a couple of gun-toting Mafiosi trying to learn who has been hijacking their drugs.</p>
        <p>With the aid of some injections, the pope will be induced to dispense information, and by the finish back at the Vatican, evil machinations in the church hierarchy will be exposed.</p>
        <p>The issues are worthy of consideration; the performances, especially by Mr. Greiss and Ms. Eklund, are admirable and, as interpreted by Mr. Niesen's direction, Mr. Fo's indomitable spirit, championing the unfortunate, the poor and the powerless, shines through.</p>
        <p>THE POPE AND THE WITCH  By Dario Fo; translation by Ed Emery; directed by Jim Niesen; sets by Ken Rothchild; costumes by Christianne Myers; lighting by Herrick Goldman; original music by Walter Thompson; music performed live by the Walter Thompson Orchestra; stage manager, Maria Knapp. Presented by the Irondale Ensemble Project. At the Theater for the New City, 155 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Christian Brandjes (First Cardinal and First Gangster), Damen Scranton (First Nun, Second Gangster, Third Cardinal and Drug Addict), Terry Greiss (the Pope), Sven Miller (the Professor), Heidi K. Eklund (the Healer), Michael-David Gordon (Second Cardinal, Swiss Guard and Drug Addict) and Patrena Murray (Assistant, Brazilian Nun and Car Bomb).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
