<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revealing a Japanese Garden As Serene Melting Pot</title>
    <meta content="18NATU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HUMAN NATURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Botanic Garden</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DA163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revealing a Japanese Garden As Serene Melting Pot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Raver column hails Japanese Garden at Brooklyn Botanic Garden as it prepares to reopen after a yearlong, $3 million renovation; says it remains true to spirit of the original garden; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRYING to see through the gates, shuddering at the sound of jackhammers and buzz saws, worrying about 85-year-old cherry trees dangling their roots in the drained pond. It was like pacing the halls during a beloved's interminable operation. But now the vigil is over and worrywarts can relax: the Brooklyn Botanic Garden is about to reopen its Japanese Hill-and-Pond Garden, and the patient never looked better.</p>
        <p>Like the ducks and herons that showed up as soon as the water returned in April (who told them?) and the three turtles basking on a rock (how did they escape the turtle roundup last summer?), people will flock back to the Japanese Garden on Wednesday, when the gates are thrown open on the yearlong $3 million renovation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRYING to see through the gates, shuddering at the sound of jackhammers and buzz saws, worrying about 85-year-old cherry trees dangling their roots in the drained pond. It was like pacing the halls during a beloved's interminable operation. But now the vigil is over and worrywarts can relax: the Brooklyn Botanic Garden is about to reopen its Japanese Hill-and-Pond Garden, and the patient never looked better.</p>
        <p>Like the ducks and herons that showed up as soon as the water returned in April (who told them?) and the three turtles basking on a rock (how did they escape the turtle roundup last summer?), people will flock back to the Japanese Garden on Wednesday, when the gates are thrown open on the yearlong $3 million renovation.</p>
        <p>There are interesting things to quibble over, like a few lollipop grafted cherry trees that may never learn to weep, and the vibrantly orange-red torii gate, but over all, the restoration has remained true to the spirit of the original garden, designed by Takeo Shiota in 1915.</p>
        <p>''It was a very experimental, dynamic time, when young designers were reinventing the Japanese garden,'' said Annie Van Assche, an art historian at the Japan Society Gallery on East 47th Street.</p>
        <p>And the Brooklyn garden, the first public Japanese garden in America, ''incorporates many of the classical conventions,'' Ms. Van Assche added, like terraced hillsides and a cascading waterfall, and the borrowed scenery of hills and trees reflected in water.</p>
        <p>But it takes liberties, too, like the bronze cranes standing in the pond. ''You would never see a crane sculpture in gardens in Japan,'' Ms. Van Assche said. And that torii gate, she said, modeled after the great Miyajima gate that stands on its own in the Inland Sea of Japan, framing the islands in the far distance, is a bit epic for a little Brooklyn garden. (So maybe Mr. Shiota, a young immigrant himself, was missing home.)</p>
        <p>As restorers examined the interpretations of the garden passed down as truths by ''experts'' over the years, they found them to be legends that dispelled like mist. Yet like Gilbert &amp; Sullivan's ''Mikado,'' they tell a story in themselves about what Americans understood -- or misunderstood -- about this exotic land.</p>
        <p>There's a jarring newness to the fresh wooden posts, the orange-red paint, the clunky bluestone benches of the amphitheater dedicated to the garden's first benefactor, Alfred T. White. ''It's going to take me a little while to accommodate myself to those pilings that edge the pond,'' said Archie Hobson, a book editor and garden guide, who married Susan Lacerte, the director of Queens Botanical Garden, by the Shinto shrine 13 years ago. ''I was used to a more natural edge. And I'm not happy to see the bird sculptures come back, or those bright azaleas.''</p>
        <p>Those birds are replicas of the original bronze cranes that stood in the pond, by Turtle Island, when the garden first opened, so they are just as faithful to Mr. Shiota's design as the tall pines that evoke eternity, the flowering cherries that speak of the evanescence of life. The posts were not, but they hold the shoreline, which time, as well as each person's interpretation of the garden, tend to blur.</p>
        <p>The Japanese waterfall ''is actually an Italian grotto built with Manhattan schist,'' said Mr. Hobson, who learned this from Marc Keane, a consultant brought over from the University of Kyoto to advise restorationists on authenticity. The five-tiered waterfall, with an echo chamber to magnify the sound of rushing water, is like something you might see in a Long Island diner. But what do you expect from stone masons longing for the old country?</p>
        <p>As Mr. Hobson said: ''We don't have to be Deadeye Dick about it. We don't have to be defensive. This is an American garden in Brooklyn. The water drowns out the traffic.'' It's our garden. And grottos are just fine with us.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keane is an American landscape architect who so fell in love with Japan he now lives in Kyoto. When he went back to Japan, he left quite a few ripples, good and bad, depending on your personal mythology.</p>
        <p>''I've seen the Miyajima gate twice, and it was not orange -- it was vermilion,'' said Elizabeth Scholtz, who directed the botanic garden for eight years, and is the vessel of all its arcane history. ''It was orange originally, but when Dr. George Avery went to Japan in 1960, he came back with the theory that the Japanese do not like painted wood. So he caused it to be scraped.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Avery ran the garden from 1945 to 1969; Ms. Scholtz steered it through the budget crunch of the 1970's. Around that time, a gardener handed her an article in Scientific American about the Miyajima shrine, which had a picture of the torii gate in glorious color -- vermilion, not orange.</p>
        <p>So Ms. Scholtz decided to paint the gate scarlet. ''So it would stand out in the landscape,'' she said. ''As if to say, 'We may be suffering financially, but look at us!' ''</p>
        <p>Then the interloper, Mr. Keane, came along and stuck in his two cents: an authentic torii gate would be more orange.</p>
        <p>And forget that cockamamie story that the lake echoes the shape of the Chinese character for heart -- or is it mind?</p>
        <p>''He just tossed that aside,'' said Ms. Scholtz, who rather liked that story. ''He said it was an irregular shape because it fit the contours of the land.''</p>
        <p>Sure enough, when they went back to the 1910 plan of the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, before the Japanese garden was built, why, there was a pond with a squiggly shape.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keane also debunked the long-told theory, first espoused in a walking guide written by Bunkio Matsuki, in 1930, that various parts of the garden represented heaven, man and earth. ''I was so relieved when he said that,'' Ms. Scholtz said. ''Because I could see that heaven was the top of the hill. But where was man?''</p>
        <p>In short, it soon became clear that no one but Mr. Shiota, who left no records of his work, really knew the true meaning of the garden, nor understood the complexities of centuries of Japanese design, with its mixture of Shinto and Buddhism, borrowed from the Chinese (who loved that orange-red paint).</p>
        <p>''In the Shinto religion, the gods, or kami, reside in nature,'' Ms. Van Assche said. ''They could be in a tree, a rock, a piece of moss. They were never represented in human form, until Buddhism came to Japan.''</p>
        <p>And the kami are here.</p>
        <p>''The pine grove in front of the Shinto shrine always reminds me of camping in Maine and New Hampshire,'' said Ms. Lacerte, who worked in the Brooklyn garden for five years. ''It's very evocative for me. When I go hiking in the mountains, I feel like trees and rocks speak to me. I feel that comes out in the Japanese garden.''</p>
        <p>The wisteria is blooming lustily over the arbor that stands on sturdy locust posts in the pond. The torii gate has had what sounds like a root canal -- the rotting cores of its cypress posts dug out and replaced with fiberglass -- before its glossy paint job.</p>
        <p>The curving pond has been restored to its original shoreline, which had eroded, along with the surrounding slopes, after 85 years of rain. ''The erosion had been terrible,'' said Ralph Morgan, the director of capital projects standing by newly planted kurumi azaleas on the northern slope of the Japanese garden. Now, stone retaining walls hold soil and plants in place, and an ingenious drainage system designed by Vollmer Associates of New York channels torrential downpours away from the pond.</p>
        <p>The dreary stockade fence that kept visitors from glimpsing the mystery of pine, stone and water has been replaced by a graceful larch fence with a snow-cap top (to artfully catch the snow) and eye-level openings with views of every angle of the garden.</p>
        <p>A wide crushed gravel path, accessible to wheelchairs and baby carriages, now circles the pond, whose banks will soon be soft blankets of ferns, liriope and Japanese lilies. New grass covers Turtle Island, which, like Atlantis, was about to slide into the sea, and much-needed new trees -- pines, katsura and cherries, to name a few -- have been planted among the venerable originals.</p>
        <p>And now Judith Zuk, the current president of the garden, is putting her own mark on it by bringing the bronze cranes and lotuses back to the pond. Mr. Avery got rid of the exuberant flowers in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>''The lake was absolutely clogged with lotus,'' Ms. Scholtz said. ''And I think Avery decided they looked messy.'' He was also in the ''vanguard of the weed-killer movement,'' which used up those postwar chemicals, ''so he got rid of them,'' she added.</p>
        <p>These new lotuses, germinating in a greenhouse, hark back to seeds found in a broken piece of canoe more than 3,000 years old. ''They were found in the mud at the bottom of the river Kenmi in Chiba city,'' near Tokyo, Ms. Zuk said.</p>
        <p>America's flirtation with Japanese culture cooled during World War II, of course. The Shinto shrine was razed by an arsonist in 1937. And a few years ago, Madoka Yoshida, a grandniece of Mr. Shiota, came to visit the garden. ''She brought pictures of his birthplace, Ohtaki Chiba,'' Ms. Zuk said. ''It was a village with an Inari shrine like the one he designed here.'' Inari is the Shinto god of the harvest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yoshida brought a letter her great-uncle had written to her mother, in which he told her of the ''eye soothing'' lotus flowers in the pond. ''This garden is the pride of my life,'' he wrote. ''I believe it will live long and my soul will be always living in the garden.''</p>
        <p>Takeo Shiota died on Dec. 3, 1943, in a Japanese internment camp in South Carolina. And as his greatest work reopens this week, we think of him among the pines.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1000 Washington Avenue, is open Tuesday through Friday, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturday, Sunday and holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission, $3 for adults, $1.50 for those over 65 and students. Free Tuesday and Saturday, 10 a.m. to noon. Information, (718) 623-7200.</p>
        <p>HUMAN NATURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
