<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes The Defeat Is Not Due To Mistakes</title>
    <meta content="18CARD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleisher, Marty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodwell, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DC163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes The Defeat Is Not Due To Mistakes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Rodwell and Marty Fleisher win Cavendish Pairs competition in Las Vegas; diagramed deal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cavendish Pairs, which ended on Sunday in Las Vegas, proved to be a two-horse race. Steve Garner and Howard Weinstein of Chicago led into the final session but were overtaken in the stretch by Eric Rodwell of Naperville, Ill., and Marty Fleisher of Manhattan. These were the other standings:</p>
        <p>Third: David Berkowitz of Old Tappan, N.J., and Larry Cohen of Boca Raton, Fla.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cavendish Pairs, which ended on Sunday in Las Vegas, proved to be a two-horse race. Steve Garner and Howard Weinstein of Chicago led into the final session but were overtaken in the stretch by Eric Rodwell of Naperville, Ill., and Marty Fleisher of Manhattan. These were the other standings:</p>
        <p>Third: David Berkowitz of Old Tappan, N.J., and Larry Cohen of Boca Raton, Fla.</p>
        <p>Fourth: Bob Hamman of Dallas and Zia Mahmood of Manhattan</p>
        <p>The first-place winners and their supporters collected $262,780 out of a Calcutta pool that totaled $1,140,500.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal was entertaining for everyone except Guido Ferraro of Italy. He was the only player who failed to make a game on the North-South cards, and he had done nothing clearly wrong.</p>
        <p>North-South may choose to play in four hearts or four spades. Four hearts presented no problems at all, and sometimes made 12 tricks. Those who believe that the stronger suit should be preferred when the length is equal would choose hearts, since the eight is present. Oddly enough, it was the lack of the spade eight, an apparently insignificant card, that led to Ferraro's downfall as South in four spades.</p>
        <p>West led the diamond ace and shifted to the club king. South won with the ace and thought carefully. There was obviously the threat of a club ruff, so he would have liked to cash the top trumps. But lack of the eight meant that a 4-1 split could lead to the loss of two trump tricks together with two diamonds.</p>
        <p>South therefore led the spade jack and finessed, so that if it lost there would be a spade remaining in the dummy to deal with another diamond lead. West won with the queen and continued with a low diamond. This might seem to be a risky move, permitting South a chance to win with the queen, but it was crucial.</p>
        <p>As South did not know who held the king, he ruffed in dummy and reached this position:</p>
        <p>[Diagram]</p>
        <p>Although Ferraro did not know it, he was doomed, having no road back to his hand. Whatever he did, the defenders would score two ruffs, together with the trump trick and diamond trick they already had.</p>
        <p>The West player was Eddie Wold of Houston, and his brilliant play of a low diamond at the fourth trick was essential. If he had led the diamond king, South could have discarded a heart from the dummy in safety. As it was, Ferraro could not discard for fear that East would win and give his partner a club ruff.</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the bridge column on Monday misspelled the surname of one of the French players then in fourth place in the Cavendish Pairs competition in Las Vegas. He is Jean-Christophe Quantin, not Quantinand.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
