<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Central Park Summerstage, a World of Performers</title>
    <meta content="18STAG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DA163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Central Park Summerstage, a World of Performers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Schedule for 15th season of Central Park Summerstage is announced (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 15th season of Central Park Summerstage will present performers from all over the map in its series of free concerts from June 15 through Aug. 15. The series, presented by the City Parks Foundation at the Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 72nd Street, is announcing its schedule today.</p>
        <p>The season begins with a benefit concert by the Indigo Girls on June 13 at 7 p.m., with tickets costing $27.50, and the jam band Widespread Panic is to play a benefit concert on Aug. 1, with tickets at $30. But the other events are free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 15th season of Central Park Summerstage will present performers from all over the map in its series of free concerts from June 15 through Aug. 15. The series, presented by the City Parks Foundation at the Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 72nd Street, is announcing its schedule today.</p>
        <p>The season begins with a benefit concert by the Indigo Girls on June 13 at 7 p.m., with tickets costing $27.50, and the jam band Widespread Panic is to play a benefit concert on Aug. 1, with tickets at $30. But the other events are free.</p>
        <p>On June 15 Nile Rodgers is to revive his hit-making 1970's band, Chic. The Nuyorican Soul Orchestra, created by the Masters at Work production team, performs on July 2 with singers including Jocelyn Brown and Jody Watley. Angie Stone, rhythm-and-blues singer, is to perform on July 29 and Fishbone is to play its high-speed punk-ska fusion on July 8, along with the Persuasions, the a cappella group. The songwriters Randy Newman and Jonathan Richman are scheduled for June 29, and the rocker Joan Jett performs on July 4.</p>
        <p>Common, a rapper from Chicago, shares a bill with the Nigerian Afro-Beat drummer Tony Allen and his band on June 24. There's more Afro-Beat on Aug. 13 from Femi Kuti. The South African singer Miriam Makeba returns on July 12, with the songwriter Terry Callier opening.  Les Nubians, from Cameroon, and Amadou et Miriam, from Mali, perform on July 16.</p>
        <p>Chico O'Farrill's Afro-Cuban big band and the Cuban jazz group led by the bassist Cachao appear on June 18  and the salsa and jazz pianist Eddie Palmieri is to perform on Aug. 5. Milly Quezada and Los Hermanos Rosario sing Dominican merengue on July 9, and Toto la Momposina, a Colombian group, shares a bill with the Czech Gypsy group Vera Bila on Aug. 2. Brazilian rock -- by Nacao Zumbi and a percussion band, Funk 'n' Lata, from Rio de Janeiro -- is due on July 15.</p>
        <p>The Mississippi and Chicago blues of R. L. Burnside and Hubert Sumlin are scheduled for June 17; the Rebirth Brass Band, from New Orleans, performs on July 23. The reggae crooner Beres Hammond and the ''conscious reggae'' singer Anthony B are to appear on July 30. Roni Size and Reprazent, a drum-and-bass group, appear along with the sitar player Anoushka Shankar on Aug. 15.</p>
        <p>Simon Shaheen's Qantara plays Arab-jazz fusion music on a bill with Andalusian-Moroccan orchestral music by the Israeli Andalusian Orchestra on June 25. The Algerian rai singer Faudel performs on Aug. 6.</p>
        <p>On some Fridays there will be free dance performances, with choreographers like Elizabeth Streb (June 23) and Ronald K. Brown (July 21). On some Thursdays there will be readings and spoken-word performances, including an appearance by the trip-hop songwriter Tricky on July 6. The New York Grand Opera is to perform Verdi on June 28, July 19 and Aug. 9. Workshops and panel discussions are also part of the Summerstage lineup. The schedule is available at www.summerstage.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
