<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cannes Journal; Enchantment At Cannes, Outside The Awards</title>
    <meta content="18CANN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">kusama, karyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coen, Ethan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coen, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merhige, E Elias</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nolan, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Girlfight (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Memento (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">O Brother, Where Art Thou (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shadow of the Vampire (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannes International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DA163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1304" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cannes Journal; Enchantment At Cannes, Outside The Awards</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <dateline>CANNES, France, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell article reports that noteworthy films being shown at Cannes International Film Festival outside the main competition; reviews Karyn Kusama's Girfight, Chris Nolan's Memento, Joel and Ethan Coen's O Brother, Where Art Thou and E Elias Merhge's Shadow of the Vampire; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though one could lose several nights' sleep trying to catch all the films in competition at this year's Cannes International Film Festival -- and some of them, at over three hours, seem to last at least one night -- there are great movie finds outside the main event. Among them is ''Girlfight,'' from the writer and director Karyn Kusama, which is being shown in the highly regarded Directors' Fortnight series for new talent. Ms. Kusama's debut work is the story of a young girl (Michelle Rodriguez, in her acting premiere) who discovers a way to channel her anger and aggressions through training as a boxer, and the film is enchanting audiences at Directors' Fortnight the way it did at the Sundance Film Festival, where it was awarded the Jury Prize.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kusama discovered the boxing world three years ago through a friend who was training as a boxer. ''I went to Gleason's in Brooklyn,'' she said. ''There were people who took me in there and didn't swat me away. It was a very dramatic spot, a different world for me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though one could lose several nights' sleep trying to catch all the films in competition at this year's Cannes International Film Festival -- and some of them, at over three hours, seem to last at least one night -- there are great movie finds outside the main event. Among them is ''Girlfight,'' from the writer and director Karyn Kusama, which is being shown in the highly regarded Directors' Fortnight series for new talent. Ms. Kusama's debut work is the story of a young girl (Michelle Rodriguez, in her acting premiere) who discovers a way to channel her anger and aggressions through training as a boxer, and the film is enchanting audiences at Directors' Fortnight the way it did at the Sundance Film Festival, where it was awarded the Jury Prize.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kusama discovered the boxing world three years ago through a friend who was training as a boxer. ''I went to Gleason's in Brooklyn,'' she said. ''There were people who took me in there and didn't swat me away. It was a very dramatic spot, a different world for me.''</p>
        <p>''Girlfight'' wasn't the first story of an outsider that Ms. Kusama considered. The script she worked on before shooting ''Girlfight'' was considerably different. ''This other script was a perverse road movie,'' she said, ''much darker, before serial killers had become run of the mill.'' The script, which she ended up not making, trailed a pair of killers who travel across the country with a young girl in tow: ''It's told from the point of view of the girl,'' she said, ''and we never really see what they do.''</p>
        <p>She is attracted to young women growing up in broken or unusual family situations. ''I don't know where the interest in weird home settings comes from,'' she said, ''because I had a very normal upbringing. On some level I do want to be an outsider. I think as I get older, I'm more resistant to change and went back to Gleason's to fight -- I'm not good at getting hit -- when I could have quit to fight that part of me.''</p>
        <p>Many of the crop of films advertised on billboards here are not her cup of tea. ''It's a convention about conventionality,'' she said, ''but I have no problem going to festivals. I have to participate in some aspect, or it won't get seen, and going to festivals is the only way to get the word out. At the same time, I love things about this festival. I just wish I had time to go see a movie.''</p>
        <p>Tattooing the Clues</p>
        <p>Had Ms. Kusama gone to the market screening of ''Memento,'' a tart and engrossing crime film, she would probably have left the theater happy. Market screenings, for films hoping to attract a distributor, are often so packed they resemble passenger trains in third-world countries; if someone yelled fire in these crowded theaters, the resulting stampede would mean no one would be left to bid on David Hasselhoff movies. ''Memento'' is a slippery knot of a noir starring Guy Pearce as a man hunting his wife's killer. Because of  an injury, his memory disappears when he falls asleep, so he has clues and instructions tattooed all over his torso; he never knows where he is. Directed by Chris Nolan, ''Memento'' toys with linearity, both chronological and narrative, in a way that makes him an inheritor of the director Nicolas Roeg, whose delirious editing rhythms and broken storytelling wreaked havoc with movies in the 1970's. Mr. Nolan's smarts about the genre give ''Memento'' a stylish freshness that raises it above the rut that crime films have found themselves in -- it's one of the most enjoyable pictures in years. His previous film, last year's no-budget black-and-white film ''Following,'' toyed with expectations, too.</p>
        <p>Clooney and the Coens</p>
        <p>Joel and Ethan Coen have spent their careers cheating expectations in their films, peppering the lives of their marginal protagonists from both sides of the law with enough obstacles to blind a Raymond Chandler hero. Their film in competition here, ''O Brother, Where Art Thou,'' has a credit in its opening sequence that got probably the biggest laugh here: ''Based Upon 'The Odyssey' by Homer.''</p>
        <p>You could also tick off other, less literary references, including a big slice of the screwball comedy ''Sullivan's Travels'' and more than a passing nod to the legend surrounding the life of the blues guitarist Robert Johnson, but the main characters in ''O Brother, Where Art Thou'' are indeed seeking knowledge, treasure and the road home, and they do run into sirens. This may be the world's first picaresque hillbilly musical, with three louts on the run from a Southern prison and their intelligence at best a dim flicker behind their eyes.</p>
        <p>The filmmakers aren't out to make friends here. This athletic and tricky comedy isn't a politically correct look at the South of the 1930's, but it has as big a heart as ''The Big Lebowski,'' their absurdly lovable mystery starring Jeff Bridges. ''O Brother, Where Art Thou'' features the elements that delight Coen fans, such as repeated blows to the head that would make Tex Avery flinch and a ferocious amount of meaningless patter, particularly by George Clooney as a lowlife blade who constantly replenishes his hair with enough pomade to lubricate a Hudson Hornet. John Turturro and Tim Blake Nelson are the other parts of this convict trio. Mr. Clooney doesn't have the usual audience rapport at the start; it takes a while to get ahold of his character, but he broadens his perfect, sly double-takes and finds the right beats to keep up with the Coen regulars, Mr. Turturro, John Goodman and Holly Hunter. ''O Brother, Where Art Thou'' is a lush fable about forgiveness -- the mantra is ''looking for answers'' -- in which everything fits together. When Mr. Clooney says the devil is red with a pitchfork and the blues musician played by Chris Thomas King says he's white, they're both right: he turns out to be the wizard of the Ku Klux Klan, which gets its own musical number.</p>
        <p>Dafoe Is Really Dracula</p>
        <p>''Shadow of the Vampire,'' by E. Elias Merhige, is also in Directors' Fortnight. It's a comic fantasy in which F. W. Murnau (John Malkovich) is making his classic vampire film ''Nosferatu'' with his star Max Schreck, only Schreck is really Dracula, an actual vampire (Willem Dafoe). Murnau is a trippy perfectionist ham who will do whatever it takes to get his masterpiece finished, and Mr. Malkovich's flamboyant toughness is a boon. He's a showy sadist who knows that he has to have drama even in his real life. The movie feels a little leaden, despite a glorious turn by the British comedian Eddie Izzard as a silent film actor who can pop his eyes with the best of them. That is, until Mr. Dafoe shows up. With his parchment-pale countenance and devotion to character -- the strangest professional ever seen on a film set -- he is beloved by the crew despite the fact that he's eliminating them one by one. ''The German stage needs you,'' someone says after this real-life Nosferatu grabs a bat out of the night air and hungrily drains it. Mr. Dafoe uses his natural gravity for laughs; his Dracula is a vain lizard who hijacks the production with ideas of his own in this movie that intelligently mocks the self-absorption of the artist. Proof that all a viewer's time at Cannes isn't best spent just watching films at the main festival.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
