<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>National News Briefs; Fresh Leadership at 110 Livingston</title>
    <meta content="18THU3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DD173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>National News Briefs; Fresh Leadership at 110 Livingston</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says New York City Board of Education made sensible call when it promoted Harold O Levy from interim chancellor to permanent chancellor; notes Mayor Rudolph Giuliani had little choice in matter, with majority of board supporting Levy; says Levy has shown impressive management and personnel skills during his four months on job, as well as imagination and energy; says his ultimate goal will be to upgrade performance of system's students</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Board of Education made the only sensible call yesterday when it promoted Harold Levy from interim chancellor to permanent chancellor. Mayor Rudolph Giuliani had little choice but to go along with the decision. With a majority of the board supporting the interim chancellor, City Hall's appointees could not have blocked the appointment. The mayor would have risked voter disapproval and political embarrassment had they tried. Even so, yesterday's unanimous vote brings a welcome end to the uncertainty and political infighting that have dominated the school system since the former chancellor, Rudy Crew, was forced out by the mayor in January.</p>
        <p>During his four months on the job, Mr. Levy has shown impressive management and personnel skills, as well as imagination and energy. Now he must apply those skills to the more difficult challenges ahead. He must, for starters, ensure that the critical summer session runs smoothly and upgrades the performance of thousands of children in danger of failing. Even more important, he must make certain that the schools they return to in the fall have better-prepared teachers and smaller classes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Board of Education made the only sensible call yesterday when it promoted Harold Levy from interim chancellor to permanent chancellor. Mayor Rudolph Giuliani had little choice but to go along with the decision. With a majority of the board supporting the interim chancellor, City Hall's appointees could not have blocked the appointment. The mayor would have risked voter disapproval and political embarrassment had they tried. Even so, yesterday's unanimous vote brings a welcome end to the uncertainty and political infighting that have dominated the school system since the former chancellor, Rudy Crew, was forced out by the mayor in January.</p>
        <p>During his four months on the job, Mr. Levy has shown impressive management and personnel skills, as well as imagination and energy. Now he must apply those skills to the more difficult challenges ahead. He must, for starters, ensure that the critical summer session runs smoothly and upgrades the performance of thousands of children in danger of failing. Even more important, he must make certain that the schools they return to in the fall have better-prepared teachers and smaller classes.</p>
        <p>The need for more-qualified teachers is particularly pressing in low-performing schools, where the least experienced teachers are being required to do the most difficult jobs of all. Mr. Levy will need to negotiate a more flexible teachers' contract so that capable teachers can be shifted where needed, and he should develop a bold, new certification program that will allow the system to recruit and train talented teachers from the business and professional world.</p>
        <p>Other key tasks include holding principals and superintendents accountable for their schools' performance, streamlining the bloated bureaucracy at 110 Livingston Street and repairing the city's crumbling and sometimes dangerous school buildings.  Mr. Levy has gotten a jump on this last problem by sitting as a trustee on the board of the School Construction Authority instead of appointing a surrogate, as previous chancellors have done. As the system gets better at building and repair, the case for more money will be easier to make in Albany.</p>
        <p>If all these tasks are carried out expeditiously, the chancellor will have a fighting chance to reach the most important goal of all -- upgrading the performance of the system's students.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
