<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin Aims to Weaken Region Chiefs and Bolster Central Control</title>
    <meta content="Y18RUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2D7163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin Aims to Weaken Region Chiefs and Bolster Central Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Vladimir V Putin moves swiftly to gather reins of power in Kremlin hands; proposes legislation that would oust Russia's provincial governors from their seats in Parliament and, in some instances, permit him to fire them altogether; plan to redraw Parliament's upper house would replace its 178 governors and regional legislative leaders with lower-level appointees from each of nation's 89 regions; Putin goes on nationwide television to announce this and several other proposals that he says will strengthen and cement Russian statehood (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving swiftly to gather the reins of power in Kremlin hands, President Vladimir V. Putin proposed legislation tonight that would oust Russia's provincial governors from their seats in Parliament and, in some instances, permit him to fire them altogether.</p>
        <p>The plan to redraw Parliament's upper house, called the Federation Council, would replace its 178 governors and regional legislative leaders with lower-level appointees from each of the nation's 89 regions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving swiftly to gather the reins of power in Kremlin hands, President Vladimir V. Putin proposed legislation tonight that would oust Russia's provincial governors from their seats in Parliament and, in some instances, permit him to fire them altogether.</p>
        <p>The plan to redraw Parliament's upper house, called the Federation Council, would replace its 178 governors and regional legislative leaders with lower-level appointees from each of the nation's 89 regions.</p>
        <p>It is the latest in a series of moves by the new Kremlin administration to reassert central control over its sprawling territory, which in recent years has sometimes seemed to be drifting into a collection of autonomouos fiefs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin went on nationwide television tonight to announce that proposal and several others that he said were aimed at ''strengthening and cementing Russian statehood.''</p>
        <p>''A moment has come to separate partisan, regional and personal ambitions from the strict necessity to strengthen the state system and reinforce its power,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He stressed that the proposals, which would require Parliament's approval, are within the framework of the Constitution.</p>
        <p>Some are nevertheless sure to ignite controversy. But the Kremlin seemed confident -- and outside experts agreed -- that Mr. Putin could muster enough votes to push the proposals into law. Late tonight, wire services reported that leaders of both the left-wing Communist Party and the Western-oriented Union of Right Forces backed the initiatives.</p>
        <p>That impression of support was bolstered by the lopsided 325-to-155 vote earlier today in Parliament's lower house, the Duma, to confirm Mr. Putin's nominee for prime minister, Mikhail M. Kasyanov. The vote, the biggest majority received by any of Russia's seven prime ministers, suggests that Mr. Putin begins his term with an unusually strong political base in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin said tonight that his proposals were driven by the need to make the executive and legislative branches of government more effective. But one clear effect would be to shift power away from the regional leaders and back to Moscow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin said he would also seek authority to remove provincial leaders from office and dissolve regional legislatures that enact laws violating the federal Constitution. Noting that even he can be impeached for such violations, he called it ''outrageous'' that a fifth of provincial laws are at odds with federal law and that many provincial charters contradict the Constitution.</p>
        <p>''The consequences of such violations are catastrophic,'' he said. ''From such seemingly petty issues, drop by drop, separatism ripens, which sometimes becomes a stronghold for an even more dangerous evil, international terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Analysts agreed tonight that the presidency, already immensely powerful under the Constitution written in 1993 by President Boris N. Yeltsin,  would only become stronger if Mr. Putin's plans become law.</p>
        <p>Not only has the Federation Council become the weakling in the legislative system, but also some governors have all but become autocrats as the Kremlin's authority ebbed in the 1990's. A few have erected small empires based largely on corruption.</p>
        <p>''Putin is quite sure about Parliament and Moscow for the time being,'' Liliya Shevtsova, a political scholar at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace in Moscow, said tonight. ''He has no enemies, no opponents. So the major activity now is to curb the power of the feudals, the robber barons of the provinces.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
