<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Charged in Defacing of Church Statues</title>
    <meta content="18STAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">St Croix, Primus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barstow, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3D8173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Charged in Defacing of Church Statues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARSTOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barstow, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Primus St Croix, man who police say cited biblical commandment against graven images, is arrested on charges of vandalizing statues at several Catholic churches in Brooklyn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man who the police said cited the biblical commandment against graven images has been arrested on charges of vandalizing statues at several Catholic churches in Brooklyn, the authorities said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Primus St. Croix, 33, told investigators that he had smashed the statues with a sledgehammer as a protest against idolatry, Police Commissioner Howard Safir said. Yesterday afternoon Mr. St. Croix led detectives to Prospect Park in Brooklyn, where, he told them, he had hidden the hammer. ''He told us that he believed that God had told him to do it, that the Bible suggested to him that he should not worship graven images,'' Mr. Safir said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A man who the police said cited the biblical commandment against graven images has been arrested on charges of vandalizing statues at several Catholic churches in Brooklyn, the authorities said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Primus St. Croix, 33, told investigators that he had smashed the statues with a sledgehammer as a protest against idolatry, Police Commissioner Howard Safir said. Yesterday afternoon Mr. St. Croix led detectives to Prospect Park in Brooklyn, where, he told them, he had hidden the hammer. ''He told us that he believed that God had told him to do it, that the Bible suggested to him that he should not worship graven images,'' Mr. Safir said.</p>
        <p>Although statues have been vandalized outside a dozen Catholic churches and organizations in the last year, the police said Mr. St. Croix had confessed to participating in only five attacks. Mr. Safir, however, said that Mr. St. Croix might have been part of a larger group of perhaps a dozen people who shared his beliefs and carried out similar attacks at other churches in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The police said Mr. St. Croix acted as the elder spiritual guide for a small group of people who identified themselves as Rastafarians. ''We believe that he or his followers were involved in most of the desecrations,'' Mr. Safir said. ''We believe he was acting with others, and there will be further arrests.'' An anonymous tip led the police to Mr. St. Croix, who was arrested Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. St. Croix's arrest brought relief to Catholics, particularly at churches in Brooklyn that for months had braced for more attacks.  Surveillance cameras had been set up at some churches, reward money was collected, a restoration fund was created and the Police Department's hate crimes task force had spent hundreds of hours investigating.</p>
        <p>''It comes as good news, especially for the people of the affected parishes,'' said Frank DeRosa, a spokesman for the Roman Catholic Diocese of Brooklyn. ''But we are saddened by what appears to be the reason for the desecrations. The statues represent Jesus and they represent saints who in those images remind us of the life that we should live according to what God expects of us. In no way is this idolatry. We're not venerating a piece of plaster.''</p>
        <p>Mr. St. Croix faces charges of criminal mischief and aggravated harassment, both felonies. Prosecutors said that Mr. St. Croix would face up to seven years in prison if convicted, but some Catholic pastors yesterday appealed for mercy.</p>
        <p>''It's obvious the man is sick,'' said Monsignor John T. Peyton, the pastor at St. Rita's Church, where both hands were hacked off a statue of Our Lady of Fatima. ''He needs help, and what we have to do is help him to get the help that he needs.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Safir said that Mr. St. Croix had no history of mental illness, and Kevin Davitt, a spokesman for the Brooklyn district attorney, Charles J. Hynes, said that Mr. St. Croix told investigators that he was motivated by his belief in Rastafarianism, a religious sect that originated in Jamaica.</p>
        <p>Mr. St. Croix told investigators that he felt compelled, based on his understanding of Rastafarianism's teachings against graven images, to undertake a campaign of destruction against religious statues, Mr. Davitt  said. Mr. St. Croix also told investigators that his brand of Rastafarianism took a dim view of the Roman Catholic pope. In one case of vandalism, Mr. St. Croix said, he attacked a statue of Pope Pius X at a Knights of Columbus building after watching a documentary about Pope Pius XII, Mr. Davitt said.</p>
        <p>But other Rastafarians said yesterday that Mr. St. Croix had a seriously distorted understanding of their religion, and Catholic officials said it would be wrong to brand Rastafarianism as anti-Catholic.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure that there are many people who have an understanding of God in that religion who are not bent on destroying other people's religion,'' said the Rev. John P. Bolduc, a priest at St. Francis of Assisi/St. Blaise Church in Brooklyn, one of the vandalized churches.</p>
        <p>Mr. Safir said that Mr. St. Croix was an illegal immigrant who came to this country in 1991 from St. Lucia in the Virgin Islands, where he was baptized a Roman Catholic. A slight, muscular man with dreadlocks and a long beard, Mr. St. Croix most recently worked as a construction laborer. About two weeks ago, he moved to Harlem from an apartment building at 2020 Foster Avenue in Brooklyn. Our Lady of Refuge, one of the churches vandalized, is across the street, at 2015 Foster Avenue.</p>
        <p>The building superintendent at 2020 Foster Avenue, Pablo Guzman, said yesterday that Mr. St. Croix had lived in the building's dark basement amid a clutter of religious books and photographs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guzman said he became uncomfortable with the arrangement as Mr. St. Croix seemed to become increasingly fixated on religion. Friends of Mr. St. Croix, he said, would drop by on weekend nights and hold informal religious ceremonies into the early morning. They would pray, chant, stomp and burn incense, Mr. Guzman said.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Guzman recalled, Mr. St. Croix told him that he had quit his job as a barber because his religious beliefs barred him from touching hair. Mr. Guzman said he had asked Mr. St. Croix to move out soon after that.</p>
        <p>Although police officials did not disclose when they received the tip about Mr. St. Croix, Deputy Inspector Barbara Sicilia, who commands the police bias unit and oversaw the investigation, said that he had been under surveillance for some time. She said that he had recently moved into his girlfriend's apartment on  117th Street in Manhattan to avoid police scrutiny.</p>
        <p>But when detectives approached him on the street on Tuesday afternoon, he willingly agreed to go along for questioning. ''He came across very sincere, very intense, very cooperative,'' she said, adding that he had appeared relieved to finally get a chance to explain his actions.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly quoted from the Bible, she said, and he earnestly described his attacks as being in keeping with strict readings of Scripture. ''It was like he would wake up and God was telling him to go out there,  and he would go out there and do it,'' she said. ''It was as simple as that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
