<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life in the Slow Lane; Rural Residents Are Frustrated by Sluggish Web Access and a Scarcity of Local Information Online</title>
    <meta content="18RURA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenman, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DA163AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life in the Slow Lane; Rural Residents Are Frustrated by Sluggish Web Access and a Scarcity of Local Information Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE GREENMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenman, Catherine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of rural areas lack high-speed Internet access options like cable modems and digital subscriber line service that are increasing available in populous areas; rural Internet users also complain about difficulty of finding news and information about rural areas online; rural residents who use AOL or other national service providers must often pay toll charges to call access numbers; graphs showing how access to broadband services varies by area's population; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Debbie Wintz often surfs the Internet in the evenings, much of that time is actually spent folding clothes, feeding the cat or tidying up the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wintz, a real estate agent who lives in Pryor, Okla., about 40 miles northeast of Tulsa, uses a standard dial-up modem to connect through her local Internet service provider. The connection is never very fast -- 33 kilobits per second at most, although she has a 56K modem -- and at night it often  slows to a crawl. So Ms. Wintz occupies herself with other tasks until a Web page with a few links and pop-up messages finally appears on her screen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Debbie Wintz often surfs the Internet in the evenings, much of that time is actually spent folding clothes, feeding the cat or tidying up the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wintz, a real estate agent who lives in Pryor, Okla., about 40 miles northeast of Tulsa, uses a standard dial-up modem to connect through her local Internet service provider. The connection is never very fast -- 33 kilobits per second at most, although she has a 56K modem -- and at night it often  slows to a crawl. So Ms. Wintz occupies herself with other tasks until a Web page with a few links and pop-up messages finally appears on her screen.</p>
        <p>Like millions of other Americans, Ms. Wintz craves a faster Internet connection. But unlike millions of urban and suburban Americans, Ms. Wintz is stuck with dial-up service because there are no other choices in Pryor, population 8,300.</p>
        <p>While high-speed options like cable modems and D.S.L. (digital subscriber line) service are becoming increasingly available in populous areas, Ms. Wintz and other residents of more isolated communities are stuck in low gear, limited by the capabilities of local providers, which in turn rely on local phone networks to transmit data. For her and other rural Americans, the much-touted promise of a high-speed Internet seems as far off as the East or West Coast.</p>
        <p>''I understand that it's about profits,'' Ms. Wintz said, ''but I feel like we're being discriminated against. How come we always have to be last?''</p>
        <p>Broadband technologies like D.S.L. and cable modem service have been slow to reach rural America. According to a report issued last month by the Department of Commerce, the percentage of towns with fewer than 10,000 people that have access to D.S.L. service from their regional phone companies is closer to zero than 1. But that number is 86 percent for cities with more than 100,000 residents. About 1 percent of towns with fewer than 10,000 people had cable modem service, compared with 72 percent of cities with more than 250,000 residents.</p>
        <p>Even though some people who have tried to get high-speed access, particularly D.S.L., have been frustrated by poor service and other problems, people in rural areas would at least like to have the choice.</p>
        <p>The scarcity of high-speed connections is not the only complaint among rural Internet users. News and information about rural areas is often difficult to find online. It can be far easier to find the address of every coffee bar in Seattle, say, than the hours of the local library in a small town in rural eastern Washington. And rural residents who use national I.S.P.'s like America Online or EarthLink often find themselves paying toll charges to call access numbers.</p>
        <p>''If you're looking for free local access, you're better off going with a small local I.S.P.,'' said Laura Kelso, co-founder of Ubundle.com, a company that lets consumers customize their Internet and telecommunications services. ''Even America Online has a lot of areas where it's going to be a long distance call to dial up.'' Most big providers, she said, lack the necessary Internet connection points, known as points of presence, to cover rural areas.</p>
        <p>But above all, slow Internet transmissions and crowded phone networks are the biggest frustrations for many people in rural areas.</p>
        <p>David Haskin, a journalist in Barneveld, Wis., noticed how slow his dial-up connection became when he moved 35 miles out of Madison, Wisc., to Barneveld. The move also coincided with his getting a job as a Web content producer.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to be a Webmaster with a slow modem connection,'' he said. ''When I lived in Madison, I could get a 56K connection, but in the country, the calls have to go through central office switches so everything slows down.''</p>
        <p>Bob Holton, who lives in Fort Gibson, Okla., and works in nearby Muskogee, said he could not call his office between 8 p.m. and 10 p.m. because the phone lines in his area were tied up by young people on the Internet. ''The bottom line is that the infrastructure is old and noisy,'' he said, ''and the issues to fix it are cost and amortization of the equipment. It leaves me and everyone else in the area just dying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holton, who uses Azalea.net, a local I.S.P., also has an AOL account for e-mail, but he has to dial a number in Tulsa -- a long-distance call -- to gain access.</p>
        <p>The problems of Internet access in rural areas are attracting the attention of the Federal Communications Commission. Linda Kinney, assistant chief of the common carrier bureau, said the agency planned a survey this summer to determine whether rural areas were being properly served.</p>
        <p>Many of the larger telephone companies say they are working to increase local dial-up access. ''It's been a part of our strategy to continue reaching into smaller calling areas,'' said Rich Jeffers, a spokesman for Bell South, which covers nine southeastern states. Mr. Jeffers said Bell South's Internet service, BellSouth.net, was available to more than 80 percent of its customers through a local call. ''Our goal is to get it to 100 percent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Trish Primrose, a spokeswoman for AOL, said the company offered consumers who could not dial in to the service with a local number an alternative plan in which they could sign up with local I.S.P.'s and connect to AOL through their I.S.P.'s at a reduced rate of $9.95 per month.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, many rural communities have connected to the Internet through small local I.S.P.'s that sprang up to fill a need. The local I.S.P. is the only access available for a toll-free call in many areas because the larger I.S.P.'s have opted not to invest in the installation of network equipment in those areas.</p>
        <p>John Nunn, for example, started Twin County Internet Access, an I.S.P., in 1996  because he and his neighbors in Galax, Va., in the southwest corner of the state, were paying long-distance charges for access to I.S.P.'s like AOL and Netcom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn was also frustrated because there was little local information online. Mr. Nunn's I.S.P. provided local users with links to Virginia newspapers and even had its own advice column, ''Ask the Blonde,'' written by a local schoolteacher. (He has since sold the I.S.P. to NetAccess, a regional I.S.P.)</p>
        <p>But as broadband D.S.L. and cable Internet access spreads to metropolitan areas and suburbs, rural I.S.P.'s that were started to provide basic dial-up service find that they cannot meet the demand for faster access. Instead, they are usually forced to wait until their local phone networks or cable companies decide that their markets are worth the investment.</p>
        <p>The Mendocino Community Network, an I.S.P. in Mendocino, Calif., with about 5,000 customers, was built in part to foster economic growth in the community, which is about 125 miles north of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The Mendocino Community Network provides community residents with 150 hours of local dial-up access for $19.95 per month, and it donates I.S.P. services to local nonprofit organizations. The I.S.P. also functions as an active community service, featuring local news and events on its Web page and sending out electronic newsletters from movie theater and store owners. But without broadband Internet access, the community is at a disadvantage, said the network's manager, Rennie Innis.</p>
        <p>''One of the biggest complaints is the slow speed of the phone lines,'' Mr. Innis said. ''D.S.L. or cable access would be a real gift because how you operate your business depends on what the technology will allow. It's not just about faster speeds -- it's about people living where they want to live and still maintaining an urban quality job.''</p>
        <p>D.S.L. service is limited to customers who live within about three miles of a telephone company central office, which is more of a problem in rural areas than in cities or suburbs. But D.S.L. providers say new technology will help ease the distance limitations before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''We'll break through those limitations, which will justify a further reach into rural areas from an economic standpoint,'' said Hank Carabelli, president and chief operating officer of @Link Networks, based in Louisville, Colo., which sells broadband services to regional I.S.P.'s and businesses.</p>
        <p>Some broadband providers, like New Edge Networks and DSL.net, specialize in providing D.S.L. service to smaller markets through line-sharing agreements with local telephone companies and reseller agreements with local, regional and national I.S.P.'s. Although they are still in the testing stages, wireless technologies like multichannel multipoint distribution services and satellites are seen by some in the industry as effective ways to offer high-speed Internet access to rural areas without incurring the high costs of installing networks.</p>
        <p>Sprint Broadband Wireless Group is test-marketing Sprint Broadband Direct in Phoenix, a multichannel multipoint service the company says is 36 times as fast as a regular dial-up connection. It relies on radio transmission rather than phone or cable lines, and it works with a two-way digital transceiver installed on a rooftop that is pointed toward a radio tower to send and receive signals. Although the service is designed to reach people who do not have D.S.L. or cable access, it has a 35-mile limit, which does not help many rural residents.</p>
        <p>Some people in rural areas are hopeful about satellite technology, which does not pose the same distance limitations as other broadband solutions. Hughes Network Systems, which has about 8.5 million subscribers on its DirectTV satellite service, said it expected to add two-way high-speed Internet access later this year. ''We discovered we could hit a low cost for this two-way terminal and offer it to consumers for about the same cost as a dial-up account,'' said Paul Gaske, executive vice president of the Consumer Division at Hughes. Prices have not been announced.</p>
        <p>The two-way transmission will work with an antenna that transmits and receives satellite data. Downloading will run at 400K; uploading, 128K to 256K.</p>
        <p>Regardless of what speeds are involved, larger I.S.P.'s have generally been slower than local and regional I.S.P.'s in building their networks to provide rural residents with local Internet access. There are a few larger I.S.P.'s, however, that are focusing specifically on rural markets.</p>
        <p>For the past two years, for example, OneMain.com, based in Reston, Va., has been acquiring small, local I.S.P.'s, in addition to building Internet connection points in rural areas, in an effort to become the leading national I.S.P. for rural communities. ''In 65 percent of the rural markets, you can't access America Online with a local phone call,'' said Stephen E. Smith, chairman and chief executive of One Main. ''We think there's a lot of growth potential because they've been largely ignored.''</p>
        <p>OneMain.com also designs its I.S.P. affiliates as local portals and tailors contentgeographically, through agreements with local newspapers and merchants. ''People don't want to dial up from Bakersfield, Calif., and read information about Roanoke, Va.,'' Mr. Smith said. ''We built our networks around geographical content, which is what the larger I.S.P.'s can't do because they've outsourced nationwide networks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said One Main had 800,000 customers and planned to provide Internet access to more than 65 markets by the end of this year. Many of OneMain affiliates will also offer D.S.L. access, Mr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>Another I.S.P., OneWorldOnline.com, based in Provo, Utah, offers potential users cash incentives to persuade other people in the area to fill out forms saying they will sign up once a local connection is established. When a local I.S.P. affiliate is established, the original customer gets $25 for each subscriber the customer signed up for the service. ''Our rural approach has been to go and identify the customers first, then go and put a point of presence in,'' said David Nemelka, chief executive of OneWorldOnline.com.</p>
        <p>ISP Channel, a subsidiary of SoftNet Systems, a broadband Internet access company based in San Francisco, is entering into partnerships with smaller cable television operators to provide rural areas with broadband Internet service via cable networks. Customers who sign up with ISP Channel buy or lease cable modems, which are connected to their home cable service. Each customer's modem sends data to the cable operator, where ISP Channel provides a connection via high-speed telephone lines to the Internet. Downloading speeds average 500K, and uploading speeds average about 100K, according to ISP Channel's president, Jonathan Marx.</p>
        <p>ISP Channel also provides Web-building services to cable operators who want to build local Web sites. ''A lot of other I.S.P.'s have national content, but we provide local,'' said Larry Brilliant, chief executive of SoftNet Systems, ISP Channel's parent company. ''We've found that people really like to do business locally and to know who they're working with.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marx said ISP Channel had agreements to reach 2.4 million homes in 22 states. It is available in parts of California, Arizona, Mississippi and Florida. But the service will not benefit rural residents who do not already have cable service.</p>
        <p>Even if problems of low-speed access are solved, however, people in smaller communities could still local information hard to find online. But several companies, including Streetmail.com and Koz.com, are working with smaller I.S.P.'s to fix that.</p>
        <p>Streetmail.com, based in Waltham, Mass., for example, hires correspondents in small communities around the country and has a central editing group at its headquarters to produce local newsletters, which it then puts out with local I.S.P.'s. A recent newsletter for Cape Lookout, N.C., for example, included an opinion poll about what the local drawbridge's hours of operation should be.</p>
        <p>''Many small I.S.P.'s have wanted this kind of thing but aren't organized enough to create editorial content,'' said Barbara Johnson, chief executive of StreetMail. ''We've used the Internet to connect in all kinds of ways around the globe. We're only now turning to connect ourselves to where we live.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
