<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; 'Gosh, He Hits the Ball A Long Way'</title>
    <meta content="18ANDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pga Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicklaus, Jack</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">PGA Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DC153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; 'Gosh, He Hits the Ball A Long Way'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>'Gosh, He4</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the tee of the 166-yard eighth hole at Valhalla, Tiger Woods lofted a 9-iron that stopped about 12 feet from the cup. Jack Nicklaus then hit a 6-iron. When his ball rolled up and bumped into Woods's ball, he looked over at Woods and smiled.</p>
        <p>''I kept turning my club upside down,'' the 60-year-old Golden Bear said later, with a smile. ''I told him, 'Turn yours upside down so it looks like we are playing the same club.' Gosh, he hits the ball a long way.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the tee of the 166-yard eighth hole at Valhalla, Tiger Woods lofted a 9-iron that stopped about 12 feet from the cup. Jack Nicklaus then hit a 6-iron. When his ball rolled up and bumped into Woods's ball, he looked over at Woods and smiled.</p>
        <p>''I kept turning my club upside down,'' the 60-year-old Golden Bear said later, with a smile. ''I told him, 'Turn yours upside down so it looks like we are playing the same club.' Gosh, he hits the ball a long way.''</p>
        <p>Woods launched a typical number of 300-yard drives in opening his quest for consecutive Professional Golfers Association titles with what Nicklaus called ''the easiest 66'' you would ever see. But the Golden Bear was most impressed by the reigning 24-year-old United States Open and British Open champion's 9-iron at that eighth hole.</p>
        <p>''Tiger played a club that would leave him short of the little hollows in the green,'' he said. ''Rather than taking an 8-iron and just putting it in there, he aimed it over the bunker, carried the bunker, but played it short. I thought that was a very intelligent shot, but I never thought you could do it with a 9-iron.''</p>
        <p>Until yesterday, Jack Nicklaus had never played golf with Tiger Woods in competition, but before the 1996 Masters, when Woods was still an amateur, Nicklaus and Arnold Palmer had played a practice round with him. That's when Nicklaus predicted that Woods would win as many Masters as the combined total he and Palmer had won, meaning 10.</p>
        <p>Woods has already completed a career Grand Slam of the four majors at a younger age than Nicklaus did (at 26), but Nicklaus's total of 18 major pro titles remains a monument to his stature as history's best golfer. And here they were together in the same threesome with Vijay Singh, the winner of the Masters this year.</p>
        <p>Even as Nicklaus struggled to a five-over-par 77 before their huge gallery, his career stature upstaged Woods. Singh, also with a 77, was virtually invisible on the Valhalla course, which Nicklaus designed.</p>
        <p>''It was an honor playing with Jack,'' Woods said. ''Everybody was yelling, 'Jack, Jack,' and he's waving. I just walked up to my ball, marked it, then lined up my putt, made it or missed it and went to the next tee. 'Jack, Jack, look over here, Jack.' No one saw me. It was kind of nice. But you could tell Jack's mind really wasn't there initially.''</p>
        <p>Some of those cheers for Nicklaus were the gallery's way of sending condolences. His 90-year-old mother, Helen, died Wednesday in Columbus, Ohio, after a long illness.</p>
        <p>''My mother would always say: 'I hope I don't pass away this week. It's such a big week, I don't want to mess up your week. I want you to play,' '' Nicklaus said. ''I had no desire to be here, I promise you, but I think the P.G.A. of America, Valhalla, the tournament, my pairing, were all things that were important and that is what she would have wanted me to do, so that is what I did.''</p>
        <p>And after his first up-close-and-personal look at Woods in a tournament round, Nicklaus had only glowing words for him.</p>
        <p>''Phenomenal control, phenomenal concentration,'' Nicklaus said. ''That was a real treat to watch.</p>
        <p>''I didn't see anything wild. He hit a couple of off-line shots that upset him for two seconds, then he focused on what he was going to do to get back in play. Reminded me a little of what I used to do; hit a bad shot, get upset with myself, get it over with and get on with the business at hand. He does that very well.''</p>
        <p>Nicklaus remembered having played with another career Grand Slam golfer, the late Gene Sarazen, in the first two rounds of the 1971 P.G.A.</p>
        <p>''I think Gene was 66, 67,'' he said. ''It was a real privilege for me to play with him and he had the opportunity to watch me in the prime of my career. And now I had the opportunity to watch Tiger in the prime of his career in competition. It was something I wanted to do. I don't mind the shoe being on the other foot. It was on the other foot long enough.''</p>
        <p>Nicklaus, Woods and Singh will be playing together again in today's second round.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, I can shoot a little bit better score,'' the Golden Bear said. ''I said earlier in the week that Tiger and Vijay were going to be in a pro-am this week whether they wanted to or not. The only trouble was, I didn't get enough strokes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
