<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cast Into the Wilderness by Choice, He Found a Friend in the Landscape</title>
    <meta content="18KENT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/arts/18KENT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rockwell, Norman, Museum (Stockbridge, Mass)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glueck, Grace</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, Rockwell (1882-1971)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DF143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cast Into the Wilderness by Choice, He Found a Friend in the Landscape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Glueck reviews exhibition of works by Rockewell Kent at Norman Rockwell Museum in Stockbridge, Mass; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So highly charged was Rockwell Kent's life that it often reads better than his art. A painter, illustrator and commercial artist, he was also a wilderness buff challenged by chilly climates, a hotblooded leftist who gave his work to the Soviet Union, a lover to many women and husband to several, a father of five, a prolific writer, a designer of books, textiles and ceramics, an architect handy with tools -- in short, an overachiever who in his span of 89 years (1882-1971) seems to have had it all and then some.</p>
        <p>Even celebrity. At one point in the 1930's he was as famous for his illustrations as Norman Rockwell (1894-1978) was for his. Although their work, their lives and their political outlook were as night and day, they had something else in common besides fame: people would get their names confused.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So highly charged was Rockwell Kent's life that it often reads better than his art. A painter, illustrator and commercial artist, he was also a wilderness buff challenged by chilly climates, a hotblooded leftist who gave his work to the Soviet Union, a lover to many women and husband to several, a father of five, a prolific writer, a designer of books, textiles and ceramics, an architect handy with tools -- in short, an overachiever who in his span of 89 years (1882-1971) seems to have had it all and then some.</p>
        <p>Even celebrity. At one point in the 1930's he was as famous for his illustrations as Norman Rockwell (1894-1978) was for his. Although their work, their lives and their political outlook were as night and day, they had something else in common besides fame: people would get their names confused.</p>
        <p>''I take my hat off to him, and so do 99 out of 100 of the people east, west, north and south, and all around the world, who tell me they love my work,'' Kent wrote in a 1936 magazine salute to his near-namesake. ''I let myself be Norman, murmur 'Thanks,' and hurry to talk of other things.''</p>
        <p>In the same magazine, Norman Rockwell rejoined: ''The conviction has been growing in me that I should change my name. A drastic step, but certainly nothing of comparison with the difficulty of sustaining the burden of another's fame.''</p>
        <p>Who could foresee that, more than 60 years after these words were written, Kent would be the subject of a show, ''Distant Shores: The Odyssey of Rockwell Kent,'' at -- of all places -- the Norman Rockwell Museum. Why? Because the museum, founded in 1969, is devoted to the art of illustration (with the emphasis, of course, on Norman Rockwell's). The show thus gives more than an obligatory nod to Kent's superb talent as a graphic artist. His black-and-white drawings for the famous 1930 Lakeside Press edition of Herman Melville's ''Moby-Dick,'' some of which are shown here, have long been enshrined in the illustrators' pantheon.</p>
        <p>But the real focus of the show, organized by Constance Martin, research associate and curator at the Arctic Institute of North America at the University of Calgary, is on Kent as a landscapist and his views of the rugged terrains for which he had a deep spiritual affinity.</p>
        <p>In his youth Kent gave up the study of architecture for that of art, studying with William Merritt Chase, Robert Henri and Kenneth Hayes Miller. He became an assistant to the land scapist and naturalist Abbott Handerson Thayer (1849-1921), and it was at the Thayers' uninsulated, often unheated house in New Hampshire that Kent learned the pleasures of a spartan winter. ''There is discomfort, even misery in being cold,'' he later wrote, ''and yet do you know I love this misery and court it.''</p>
        <p>Richard V. West, director of the Frye Art Museum in Seattle, suggests in a catalog essay an earlier artistic antecedent for Kent's work: that of the Dresden painter Caspar David Friedrich (1774-1840), whose desolate icescapes Kent might have observed during a visit to Dresden in his youth.</p>
        <p>From 1905 through the 1930's Kent lived and worked in five locales: Monhegan Island, Me.; Newfoundland; Alaska; Tierra del Fuego, off the southern tip of South America; and Greenland. And though he is often derided as a hard-shell realist who never responded to the major abstract movements of his day, at their best the spare but color-charged landscapes he produced in these places have an evocative power that time has made more evident.</p>
        <p>Among the outstanding works in the show, which offers more than 90 paintings, prints and drawings, is a Monhegan scene, ''Late Afternoon'' (1907). It takes its strength from a huge, pale orange-fading-to-white sun that broods like a Cyclops eye over a quiet stretch of coast and low-lying hills, in deep russet-brown with purple shadows.</p>
        <p>In ''Alaska Winter'' (1919), the stark stump of a broken tree near a humble cabin looms forlornly against a distant ridge of snowy sawtooth mountains, suggesting the resolute spirit of man vs. nature. And ''Icebergs, Greenland'' (1932-33) makes brilliant theater of a sweep of thawed land and rocks presided over by a cluster of frosty ice formations, against a sky whose nuanced white clouds echo the icy shapes.</p>
        <p>Throughout, Kent's work has an appealingly stylized period quality. Yet some of the paintings seem slick and illustrational. And they can be corny as well. His occasional depiction of klutzy, superhuman forms to represent totemic beings are a little over the top, like ''North Wind'' (1919), a nude (but genderless) Viking god sprinting through the air past a frieze of frozen mountains.</p>
        <p>His use of figures to represent human attitudes like sorrow or fear in some cases strike the viewer as ludicrous. ''House of Dread'' (1915) depicts the stark exterior of a house perched on a rock near the sea. From one of its windows a blobby figure appears to be falling; against the facade below leans another blob, a figure in which desolation can be read.</p>
        <p>Such was the force of Kent's personality that it sometimes invited trouble, and this particular painting comments on a calamitous stay in Newfoundland with his wife and their family. In 1914, drawn northward as usual and wanting to settle in a quiet spot, he moved to Brigus, Newfoundland, a seaport village where he hoped to establish an art school.</p>
        <p>Things went well at first, but Kent's admiration of German culture and particularly German music was his undoing. As he wandered through the local landscape in search of subject matter, he was apt to burst out in German song. It was the eve of World War I, however; anti-German sentiment abounded, and the Newfoundlanders did not take kindly to these Teutonic expressions. Adding insult to injury, he posted on his studio door a sign adorned with a German eagle that read, ''Bomb Shop, Wireless Plant, Chart Room.'' Convinced that he was a spy, locals brought pressure on the government to have him expelled from the area. He and his family were forced to leave.</p>
        <p>To the end of his life, he remained a recalcitrant personality, an antiwar, pro-labor political activist, a defender of the Soviet Union and a candidate for Congress on the American Labor Party ticket. At one point he was summoned before the Senate investigations subcommittee led by Senator Joseph R. McCarthy and took the Fifth Amendment when asked if he was a Communist. After the hearing, he denied that he was.</p>
        <p>Still, he lost friends and exhibition opportunities, and found that hospitality had chilled in the worlds of art and culture that he had once loved to frequent. His conservative aesthetic and his radical politics combined to kill sales of his work, and in 1960, disappointed by rejection, he made a gift of more than 80 of his paintings, along with major manuscripts and illustrations, to the Soviet Union. His work is still on view in the State Hermitage Museum of St. Petersburg, which has lent to this exhibition.</p>
        <p>The show provides a welcome re-examination of the Kent phenomenon. If he still comes off best as a graphic artist, the paintings look a lot better than they did when abstraction ruled the art world.</p>
        <p>''Distant Shores: The Odyssey of Rockwell Kent'' remains at the Norman Rockwell Museum, Route 183, Stockbridge, Mass., (413) 298-4100, through Oct. 29.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
