<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Tiger and His Pals, Air Time Is Shared Time</title>
    <meta content="18SAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pga Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Turner Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">PGA Championship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DF153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Tiger and His Pals, Air Time Is Shared Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir's TV Sports column holds first-round performance of TNT-CBS coverage of PGA Championship showed unusual propensity for fairness to the field with Tiger Woods in contention (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 2:17 p.m. yesterday, Eastern time, Tiger Woods birdied the 18th hole to tie Scott Dunlap for the lead in the P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>Then I turned the TV off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 2:17 p.m. yesterday, Eastern time, Tiger Woods birdied the 18th hole to tie Scott Dunlap for the lead in the P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>Then I turned the TV off.</p>
        <p>What else was left to watch?</p>
        <p>I had tuned in at 1:06, when TNT was showing highlights of the first-round performances of Woods and Jack Nicklaus up to that point. Vijay Singh, the defending Masters champion, was their tee-time buddy, too. But except for showing him stand with his pals, TNT did not offer one Singh shot in that montage.</p>
        <p>But face facts: he's only Vijay, just the defending Masters champion, not Tiger or the Golden Bear. There would be no shots of the leader board until 16 minutes into the telecast, as if TNT, which is tweaking CBS's production, wanted to create first-round suspense. You saw Tiger pile up birdies, but you did not know where he stood for much too long.</p>
        <p>The first-round performance of TNT-CBS showed an unusual propensity for fairness to the field with Tiger in contention. Granted, he played only four live televised holes, but the evidence of this strategy was abundant.</p>
        <p>*Not every one of Tiger's shots were seen, including, shockingly, his tee shots on the 16th and the 17th. Nicklaus's same shots were also ignored.</p>
        <p>*Cameras did not track his purposeful walks from greens to tees or the rise and fall of his chest during breathing.</p>
        <p>*The only celebratory fairway march covered like the arrival of a royal by TNT-CBS was Nicklaus's as he walked to the 18th green.</p>
        <p>*Other golfers received nearly equal treatment. Fairness was the plan, sort of. So, over to Greg Norman. To Phil Mickelson. On Singh! On Clarke! On Love! On Funk!</p>
        <p>''We don't just sit there looking at him looking at his yardage book,'' said Lance Barrow, CBS's coordinating producer for golf. ''There are no rules about covering Tiger. You hope you're being fair to everybody.''</p>
        <p>But, he added: ''I don't think you get too tired of watching Tiger. He's the only golfer who takes golf to the front page of a lot of newspapers.''</p>
        <p>Whether yesterday's reasonably fair coverage can be maintained today on TNT, and during the weekend on CBS, remains an open question.</p>
        <p>Tiger becomes irresistible in the fourth rounds of majors. At the British Open, ABC showed him on screen for 69 minutes 19 seconds out of four hours. At the United States Open, NBC showed him for 93:23 out of nearly four hours.</p>
        <p>For sheer Woods nuttiness, the Golf Channel's first-round Buick Open coverage was unequaled. Rather than follow the leader, Woody Austin, live -- he would be the leader with a round of 63 -- the all-golf network offered viewers taped coverage of primarily Tiger, who finished seven strokes back.</p>
        <p>David Feherty, the CBS reporter-analyst, is so enamored of Woods that you may believe he does not want to see another golfer.</p>
        <p>Woods's talent and shotmaking have ''redefined my job.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not not qualified,'' Feherty said. ''He's deleted some of my greatest memories.'' Admiring one of Woods's shots at the Buick Open, Feherty said, ''It's like he skipped a generic generation.''</p>
        <p>The Dennis Miller Report</p>
        <p>Minutes before his first ''Monday Night Football'' game on July 31, Dennis Miller stepped out of the booth to pray to his late mother.</p>
        <p>''I'm standing in the hallway, dripping sweat, my eyes are half shut and I feel a nudge,'' he said yesterday by telephone. ''And I'm saying, 'I can't even have a Kodak moment.' It's Paul Tagliabue and I'm thinking, 'It's the commissioner and he's asking me to move.' ''</p>
        <p>Two games with Al Michaels and Dan Fouts, and Miller said he refuses to ''vivisect'' his work on a weekly basis. ''I'm doing it as a four-month gig,'' he said. ''Either they'll fire me or hire me. I really adopt what G. Gordon Liddy said, 'Just tell me what corner you want me to stand on.' ''</p>
        <p>Miller is beginning to understand what his impact is, although he refuses to compare it to the influence once wielded by Howard Cosell.</p>
        <p>''I have no feeling I can make a dent like he did,'' he said. ''But I'm starting to come to peace with the fact that my strength here might be the polarization of tribes.''</p>
        <p>In a bizarre reference last Monday, Miller said the former Rams Coach Dick Vermeil used to cry ''more frequently than Sylvia Plath being pepper sprayed.'' At halftime, he said, ''a guy in the bathroom excoriated me'' for using the late poet's name. ''He was indignant I would say that.''</p>
        <p>Miller prepares by reading information about the teams playing and by meeting with the coaches. He does not call assistant coaches or watch video.</p>
        <p>''I can only get myself in trouble by doing that,'' he said. ''It's better for me to hear Dan say, 'That's a short set,' and ask him what it is. That's part of the fakery of TV. People can't admit they don't know something.''</p>
        <p>Although ABC's hiring of Miller has focused more attention on ''Monday Night Football'' than the program has received in many years, he denied that he is already more prominent than Michaels, who is in his 15th season.</p>
        <p>''I've handed Al some untidy packages,'' he said. ''He reminds me of that lady from Far Rockaway who comes in to Bloomies for Christmas to wrap packages. An amazing talent, like being the Red Adair of ribbons. I've handed some unkempt packages to Al and they come back like Gomer's footlocker.''</p>
        <p>One element of Miller's repertory from his HBO program -- the trademark rant -- will not appear in any form on ''Monday Night'' because it is exclusive to the cable network. ''I wouldn't do it,'' he said. ''It'll never be done. That's my HBO job.''</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
