<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parent of United Airlines Lowers Earnings Estimate</title>
    <meta content="Y18AIR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/business/18AIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ual Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levere, Jane L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFDA143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parent of United Airlines Lowers Earnings Estimate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE L. LEVERE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levere, Jane L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>UAL Corp, parent of United Airlines, lowers its third-quarter earnings estimate, citing thousands of canceled flights that have come amid dispute with its pilots; airline also announces several efforts to placate its disgruntled passengers, including frequent-flier bonuses and elimination of certain service fees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, lowered its third-quarter earnings estimate yesterday, citing the thousands of canceled flights that have come amid a dispute with its pilots.</p>
        <p>The airline also announced several efforts to placate its disgruntled passengers, including frequent-flier bonuses and elimination of certain service fees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, lowered its third-quarter earnings estimate yesterday, citing the thousands of canceled flights that have come amid a dispute with its pilots.</p>
        <p>The airline also announced several efforts to placate its disgruntled passengers, including frequent-flier bonuses and elimination of certain service fees.</p>
        <p>James E. Goodwin, UAL's chairman and chief executive, said in a statement that the company expected third-quarter earnings to be lower than the range of $2.60 to $3.20 a share announced on July 19, when it reported its second-quarter results.</p>
        <p>''Although booking patterns remained strong through early August despite poor operating performance, booking levels have since fallen on the adverse publicity surrounding the cancellations that occurred in early August,'' Mr. Goodwin said. ''While our operating performance has improved somewhat, the reduced booking levels continue, and as a result, revenues are not as strong as we had previously anticipated.''</p>
        <p>Brian Harris, an analyst with Salomon Smith Barney, reduced his third-quarter earnings estimate to $2.10 from $2.95, and his fourth-quarter estimate to $1 from $1.35.</p>
        <p>Sam Buttrick, an analyst with PaineWebber, expects that United's labor and operational problems will have a $250 million impact on its third-quarter pretax profit. He lowered his third-quarter estimate to $1.90 from $2.60, and his fourth-quarter estimate to 95 cents from $1.10.</p>
        <p>''With the recent publicity, everyone who flies knows United isn't a good choice,'' he said. ''Although operations have improved in recent days, as a practical matter, the damage has been done.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Buttrick said he did not expect the airline's current labor problems to alienate passengers permanently. ''The airline business is fundamentally a network business,'' he said. '' People choose United for its network, and that's not changed.''</p>
        <p>United's management and its pilots' union have been negotiating a new contract since December 1998. With few signs of progress seen, the pilots have been declining to work overtime.</p>
        <p>As a result of a shortage of pilots, as well as weather and air traffic control problems, United said it completed only 90 percent of its scheduled flights during the first two weeks of this month.</p>
        <p>United management and its pilots continued their discussions this week after talks were recessed last Friday. Kathie White, a spokeswoman  for the union, said that although agreement had been reached in some areas, ''the major issues remaining are big.'' She said these included wages, benefits, working conditions and job security.</p>
        <p>United declined to comment on the talks.</p>
        <p>The bonus frequent-flier mileage will be given to United's top travelers. Frequent-flier program participants who fly 25,000 to 50,000 miles a year will receive an additional 25 percent bonus for flights taken between May 1 and Dec. 31, while those who fly more than that will receive an additional 100 percent bonus.</p>
        <p>United also is waiving its regular $75 service fee for passengers who change plans if their outbound flight is affected by a delay or cancellation; passengers must travel before Sept. 30 and return within seven days of their original return flight. Passengers flying before Sept. 30 who choose to postpone their travel may also do so without penalty; new travel must be completed by March 31, 2001.</p>
        <p>AMR's American Airlines, United's archrival, said it was evaluating United's bonus mileage offer, which was reported yesterday in The Wall Street Journal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
