<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="18CLAS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DD143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="5223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''DON GIOVANNI.'' The Berkshire Opera Company has been attracting attention and loyal patrons over the years for its imaginative, well-cast productions, presented at its summer residence in Pittsfield, Mass., the Koussevitzky Arts Center of Berkshire Community College, a modern and wonderfully intimate theater with excellent sight lines from every seat. Tomorrow night the company presents Mozart's ''Don Giovanni'' with what promises to be a strong roster of singers, including Stephen Powell in the title role, Philip Cokorinos as Leporello, Rachel Rosales as Donna Anna and Barbara Shirvis as Donna Elvira. Joel Revzen conducts. The production is the work of the imaginative director Robin Guarino. Berkshire Opera Company, Koussevitzky Arts Center, Berkshire Community College, 297 North Street, Pittsfield, Mass.; tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets are $20 to $60. (413) 443-7400 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''DON GIOVANNI.'' The Berkshire Opera Company has been attracting attention and loyal patrons over the years for its imaginative, well-cast productions, presented at its summer residence in Pittsfield, Mass., the Koussevitzky Arts Center of Berkshire Community College, a modern and wonderfully intimate theater with excellent sight lines from every seat. Tomorrow night the company presents Mozart's ''Don Giovanni'' with what promises to be a strong roster of singers, including Stephen Powell in the title role, Philip Cokorinos as Leporello, Rachel Rosales as Donna Anna and Barbara Shirvis as Donna Elvira. Joel Revzen conducts. The production is the work of the imaginative director Robin Guarino. Berkshire Opera Company, Koussevitzky Arts Center, Berkshire Community College, 297 North Street, Pittsfield, Mass.; tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets are $20 to $60. (413) 443-7400 (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARD MUSIC FESTIVAL. ''Beethoven and His World'' is explored in a second weekend of performances and discussions under the tutelage of the artistic directors, Leon Botstein and Robert Martin, and others. Take it from a veteran of these events: pack up some grub in your old kit bag if you intend to take everything in, for the events come hot and heavy. Today Michael P. Steinberg guides a symposium at 10 a.m. and 1:30 p.m. A chamber concert follows at 8 p.m. Tomorrow there are concerts of chamber music by Beethoven's teachers and contemporaries at 10 a.m. and by Beethoven at 1:30 p.m. An orchestral concert follows at 8 p.m., with Beethoven famous (the Seventh Symphony) and mildly infamous (''Wellington's Victory''), conducted by Mr.  Botstein. On Sunday a panel discussion at 10 a.m. is followed by a chamber and choral concert at 1:30 p.m. and the great Missa Solemnis at 5 p.m., again led by Mr. Botstein. The problem for the faint of heart: it all seems worthwhile on some level. Discussions are in the Bertelsmann Campus Center, chamber concerts in Olin Auditorium, orchestral concerts in the festival tent. Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-3226. Tickets range from $15 to $25; admission is free to panel discussions and symposiums (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. There is no better place in New York City to experience chamber music with the proper intimacy than at the concerts presented by Bargemusic, the rewarding weekly series that takes place on an acoustically ideal and commodious barge in the shadow of the Brooklyn Bridge. The performers this weekend are especially fine. Tonight and tomorrow night the superb pianist Randall Hodgkinson, the excellent clarinetist Thomas Hill and the lovely lyric soprano Jayne West perform songs and sonatas by Spohr, Bernstein, Britten and Brahms. On Sunday Ravel's captivating work for voice and chamber ensemble, ''Chansons madecasses'' will be performed by the baritone Chris Pedro Trakas and an impressive roster of instrumentalists on a program that includes piano trios by Weber and Dvorak. Enjoy the music while taking a spectacular view of Lower Manhattan. Bargemusic, Under the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m.; and Sunday at 4 p.m. Tickets: $27 regular admission; $25 for the elderly; $15 for students. (718) 624-4061, or (718) 624-2083 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>BRIDGEHAMPTON CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL. The flutist Marya Martin has drawn some of New York's finest chamber music players to her festival in the Hamptons, and she has assembled some inventive programs. In the first of two programs during this closing weekend of the festival's 17th season, Ms. Martin and her colleagues will offer a recent flute work by Derek Bermel, the Mendelssohn Piano Trio No. 2 and works by Busch and Koechlin, with Branford Marsalis on alto saxophone. The season finale, on Sunday, looks at the music of Eastern Europe and includes the Martinu Flute Trio, the Borodin D major Piano Trio, Arvo Part's popular ''Fratres'' and the Dvorak Quintet (Op. 81). Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 6:30 p.m., the Bridgehampton Presbyterian Church, Montauk Highway, Bridgehampton, N.Y., on Long Island, (631) 537-6368. Tickets: $25, $20 for the elderly (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS. This enterprising chamber music series, now in its 85th season, offers concerts in an open-sided barn where the sounds of nature and the music of man interact freely. Like last weekend's programming, the concerts this weekend take in both ancient and modern works. The extraordinary vocal ensemble Lionheart opens the weekend with a program called ''Paris: 1200,'' which promises medieval plainchant and polyphony. The Colorado String Quartet, on Sunday, takes care of the modern end of the spectrum with a program that includes two Shostakovich Quartets (Nos. 5 and 15) and a recent work by Katherine Hoover. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m. Maverick Concerts, Maverick Road between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., just outside Woodstock. (914) 679-8217. Tickets: $15, $5 for students (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART. The conductor Emmanuel Krivine presides over a program in which the principal draws are a pair of concertos played by young soloists. Stewart Goodyear, a pianist, is new to New York audiences but has performed with the Philadelphia and Cleveland Orchestras and is also pursuing a composition career. He will be heard in Mozart's great D minor Concerto (K. 466). Joshua Bell is, of course, a known quantity: fairly callow not long ago, his playing has matured nicely in recent seasons. He will play the Vieuxtemps Violin Concerto No. 5. Mr. Krivine will begin and end the program with Mozart Symphonies: No. 32 in G (K. 318) to start, No. 35 in D (K. 385) to conclude. Tonight and tomorrow at 8, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center. (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $25 to $45 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL. The Yale Summer School of Music retreats north to this lovely spot, and the public reaps much of the benefit at concerts in the quaint Music Shed. Tonight, the festival offers large-scale chamber works, including the Poulenc Sextet and Wagner's ''Siegfried Idyll,'' performed by festival fellows and faculty members. Tomorrow, the New World Jazz Orchestra presents ''Norfolk Ballroom,'' with works by Gershwin, Porter, Piazzolla and others. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000. Remaining tickets, $12 to $30; $5 for ages 18 to 25; free to those under 18 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>SKANEATELES FESTIVAL. As many other festivals wind down, it may be time to dig out the map and start exploring. Tucked away in Skaneateles, near Syracuse, this event is directed by Diane Walsh, a pianist. Tonight, Ms. Walsh performs a solo recital, with two Beethoven sonatas (Op. 78 and Op. 109), Bach's Fourth Partita and Beach's Variations on Balkan Themes. Tomorrow, Hugh Keelan conducts the festival orchestra in Mozart's Violin Concerto No. 4, with Hilary Hahn as soloist, and Beethoven's First Symphony and excerpts from ''The Creatures of Prometheus.'' Tonight at 8, St. James Episcopal Church, East Genesee Street; tomorrow night at 8, Brook Farm, Route 41A, south of Skaneateles, (315) 685-7418. Tickets: tonight, $10 to $16; tomorrow, $20 and $25; free to those under 13 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD FESTIVAL. It is a weekend of relatively unfamiliar conductors leading the Boston Symphony Orchestra; well, unfamiliar as maestros, anyway, in the case of Itzhak Perlman, who conducts as well as plays violin tomorrow. The program includes Mozart's 29th Symphony, Beethoven's Violin Romances and Brahms's Fourth Symphony. Tonight, Adam Fischer conducts Kodaly's Dances of Galanta, Liszt's Piano Concerto No. 1 (with Jean-Yves Thibaudet as soloist) and Tchaikovsky's Fourth Symphony. On Sunday, Federico Cortese conducts works of Verdi, featuring the Tanglewood Festival Chorus, and Brahms's Piano Concerto No. 2 (with Nelson Freire as soloist). Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, and Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Tanglewood, Lenox, Mass., (413) 733-2500. Tickets: tonight, $14 to $58; tomorrow, $15 (lawn); Sunday, $14 (lawn) to $40; (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS TROCKADERO DE MONTE CARLO. The lads are back and looking their fabulous tu-tu best. New to New York this season are ''Raymonda's Wedding'' (tonight) and ''Russian Dance'' (matinee and evening tomorrow), in a repertory that ranges wide, from Merce Cunningham's ''Cross Currents'' to ''Dying Swan.'' If all goes as planned, the roster of diva-ballerinas at this all-male ballet company will include that little darling Maya Thickenthighya, the imposing Margeaux Mundeyn and the forever-molting Ida Nevasayneva. Tonight (and Monday through next Friday) at 8; tomorrow (and next Saturday) at 2 and 8 and next Sunday at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $38. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 242-0800 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>BRYANT PARK PRESENTS AUGUST DANCE. This enterprising festival will present dances by Nicholas Leichter. Jazz by the Kelly Friesen Quartet opens the show. Tonight at 6. Free. Bryant Park, Avenue of the Americas at 40th Street; (212) 768-4242 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CELEBRATE BROOKLYN! Donald Byrd and his high-energy dancers, The Group, in choreography that is filled with intelligence and daring. Tonight at 8. Requested donation: $3. Prospect Park Band Shell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn; (718) 855-7882 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>''DANCE AT THE WHITE BARN THEATER.'' Lucille Lortel began to present dance at her White Barn theater in 1949 with performances by Katherine Dunham's company. This exhibition of archival photographs, costumes and memorabilia chosen by Lynn Garafola, curator of the show, spans a wide range of dance personalities and styles, from ballet and modern to ethnic and Broadway musical theater dance. The exhibit runs through Sept. 3. Fridays through Sundays, 7 to 10 p.m. Free. White Barn Theater, Newtown Turnpike, Westport, Conn.; (203) 227-3768 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>DELI DANCES IN TIMES SQUARE. The ''menu'' includes dance by more than 40 choreographers, performed in an empty building. Today at 12:30 p.m. and 8 p.m. Free. At 135 West 42nd Street; (212) 765-6574;  www.tonysilvadanceandmusic.com (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ECHOES DANCE CO. Directed by Jamie Philbert and Shani Collins, Echoes Dance Co. will present ''Testify,'' dance with words about a woman who has died without the support of her community, produced by DADD (Dance of African Descent Downtown). Tonight at 8 p.m. Tickets: $5. Judson Memorial Church, 55 Washington Square South, Greenwich Village; (718) 941-3339 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>BIANCA FALCO AND ELISE KNUDSON. The choreographers promise suspended bodies that ''ricochet, morph and divide.'' Bring the Alka-Seltzer. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 for students and artists. Dumbo Arts Center, 30 Washington Street, Brooklyn; (212) 539-3597 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>HUDSON RIVER FESTIVAL: SAIGON WATER PUPPETS. An ancient art form of great charm and irresistibly raucous humor, presented in a stunning outdoor setting. Tonight at 7; tomorrow and Sunday at 3 p.m. Free. World Financial Center Plaza, Battery Park City; (212) 528-2733; www.hudsonriverfestival.com (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL. At the Ted Shawn Theater, O Vertigo Danse from Canada will perform Ginette Laurin's aerial ''Chagall'' and dreamlike ''En Dedans.'' Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 (family matinee) and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $35 to 40. At the Doris Duke Studio Theater, the Liz Lerman Dance Exchange from Takoma Park, Md., will present the world premiere of ''In Praise of Fertile Fields.'' Commissioned by the Pillow, the dance was drawn from the beauties of area gardens and will be performed by Ms. Lerman's usual mix of professional and amateur dancers, young and old, including a few local gardeners. Tonight at 8:15; tomorrow and Sunday at 5 p.m. Tickets: $16. Free outdoor dance on the Inside/Out Stage will be presented by the tap dancer Clare O'Donnell (tonight at 6:30 p.m.) and Chet Walker's ''Broadway Evolutions'' program for the Pillow school (tomorrow at 6:30 p.m.). Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, George Carter Road, Becket, Mass.; (413) 243-0745;  www.jacobspillow.org (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER OUT OF DOORS: SOUNDS OF KOREA. Touring Asia in the early 1960's, Alvin Ailey was struck by the freshness and imagination of Korean dance. New Yorkers will have a chance to see for themselves with Sounds of Korea, a program of Korean percussion and dance. Sunday at 5 p.m. Free. Lincoln Center Plaza; (212) 875-5108; www.lincolncenter.org (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK INTERNATIONAL FRINGE FESTIVAL AT CHARAS/EL BOHIO: Loka Maer, from New York City, invites her audiences to ''mesmerize your mucked-up mind'' in ''Dream Play,'' tomorrow at 3:30 p.m.; Sunday at 3:30 p.m. Vis Plastica, from Vienna, creates organic beings out of inorganic matter in ''Perpetuum Mobile -- Heart Beats and Brain Waves,'' tonight at 8:30. Keiko Yamamoto, from Allentown, Pa., explores the shadow reality of life in ''Cave Theory,'' tonight at 5; tomorrow at 3 p.m.; Sunday at 6:45 p.m. Charas/El Bohio, 605 East Ninth Street,  East Village. Tickets $12; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FRINGE FESTIVAL AT CONTEXT: New York's own Sharon Fogarty presents ''Heaven,'' about a burned-out choreographer in heaven, tonight at 9:45; tomorrow at 5 p.m.  New York's own Jody Oberfleder, with Kim Irwin and an all-woman cheerleading squad, in ''Wanted: X-Cheerleaders,'' tonight at 8. Context, 28 Avenue A, at Third Street, East Village. Tickets: $12; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FRINGE FESTIVAL AT ROD ROGERS STUDIO: Michi Broman from Seattle, who gets raucous with audio, video, dance and monologue in ''Gretl,'' tonight at 8:30; tomorrow at 4 p.m. Abena Appiah-kubi Koomson, from Brooklyn, unites her ancestral worlds of Ghana and America in ''Cozi Sa Wala: Magic Words,'' tomorrow at 2:30 p.m.; Sunday at 7 p.m. North Wind/Turkey Timber, from New York City, takes a look at finding the turkey in one's heart, tomorrow at 10:30 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. Rod Rogers, 62 East Fourth Street, Lower East Side. Tickets: $12; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FRINGE FESTIVAL AT ST. MARKS STUDIO THEATER: Karen Effenberger and Andrea Lesjak, from Munich, in ''As If About to Fall,'' about skiers, tonight at 7; tomorrow at 2:15 and 11:15 p.m. Theater Rusticle, from Toronto, explores the perils and beauties of the journey home in ''Now the Day Is Over,'' tomorrow at 7:15 p.m.; Sunday at 7:30 p.m., St. Marks Studio Theater, 94 St. Marks Place, between First Avenue and Avenue A, East Village. Tickets: $12; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>FRINGE FESTIVAL AT UNIVERSITY SETTLEMENT: Tony Silva Dance and Music, from New York City, presents the multimedia ''Air Born'' today at 5:45 p.m.; tomorrow at 5:15 p.m. Vicdog3D, from Los Angeles, features Vickie Mendoza and her multimedia ''Three Worse Flowers,'' tonight at 9:30; Sunday at noon. WSA, from New Haven, presents a reimagining of translation from inside the collaborative process in ''Translation/2'' tomorrow at noon; Sunday at 2:15 p.m. Caroline Jauch and Company, from Brooklyn, promises magic as well as blood in ''The Handless Maiden'' tomorrow at 9 p.m.; Sunday at 4:30 p.m. John Wyszniewski, from Brooklyn, wraps movement around language in ''Full Frontal Facts'' tonight at 7:30; tomorrow at 2 p.m.; Sunday at 7:15 p.m. University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side. Tickets: $12; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>OTHER FRINGE FESTIVAL EVENTS: Kunsterwerk-Blend, from London, in a Dadaesque kindergarten in ''Yo-Land,'' tonight at 8:30; tomorrow at 6:30 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., WOW Cafe, 59-61 East Fourth Street, East Village. Stratton Gonzalez Dance Theater, from New York, in ''A Place in Line,'' about immigrants' contribution to American culture, tomorrow at 7 p.m.; Sunday at 5:30 p.m., Present Company Theatorium, 16-198 Stanton Street, at Ridge Street, Lower East Side. Tanztheater Homunculus, from Vienna, in the burlesque ''Sommerfrische,'' Sunday at 9:45 p.m., Henry Street Settlement, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side. Cy.ancal, from Linz, Austria, gets cynical about monotony, on a sound carpet, in ''With the Clearness Comes the Cold,'' tomorrow at 12:30 p.m., Paradise, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village. Tickets: $12 for each event; (212) 420-8877 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>RETURN OF THE SUN DANCE COMPANY. Reconstructed works by Isadora Duncan and dance by Rina Rinkewich, who directs the company. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m. Tickets: $10. New York Performance Works, 128 Chambers Street, at West Broadway, TriBeCa; (718) 855-2080 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>URBAN BUSH WOMEN. Go down home with the Urban Bush Women, an all-female company that brings an urgent, unexpected poetry and humor to the most mundane -- and exalted -- of everyday events. Tonight at 7; free food will be served at 6. Free. La Plaza Cultural community garden, Ninth Street and Avenue C, East Village; reservations necessary: (212) 674-8194 (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
