<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Profits Are Finally Where They Ought to Be</title>
    <meta content="18MOSB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Profits (Industry-wide)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mosbacher, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7D8143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Profits Are Finally Where They Ought to Be</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert A. Mosbacher</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mosbacher, Robert A</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by former commerce secretary Robert Mosbacher on outlook for US oil industry, which he says has been unfairly blamed for recent runup in prices; says industry has been squeezed for too long and that it is high time for them to enjoy good returns along with most other American industries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Too many people are accusing the oil and gas industry of greed, blaming oil companies for both the runup in the price of gasoline, which has moderated since last spring, and for more recent rises in home heating and energy prices.</p>
        <p>The truth is the American oil industry is not the instigator of higher prices. In the case of oil, producing nations including those of the Middle East decided last spring to cut production to force prices up, since some were having trouble meeting their debts. Natural gas prices rose because of reduced supply as American and Canadian companies, hurt by previously low prices, cut back on drilling. As for gasoline prices, they had been depressed for decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Too many people are accusing the oil and gas industry of greed, blaming oil companies for both the runup in the price of gasoline, which has moderated since last spring, and for more recent rises in home heating and energy prices.</p>
        <p>The truth is the American oil industry is not the instigator of higher prices. In the case of oil, producing nations including those of the Middle East decided last spring to cut production to force prices up, since some were having trouble meeting their debts. Natural gas prices rose because of reduced supply as American and Canadian companies, hurt by previously low prices, cut back on drilling. As for gasoline prices, they had been depressed for decades.</p>
        <p>What's wrong with American oil companies finally making a profit? A year ago, pitting oil against the rest of American industry in a contest of earnings was like putting a weekend duffer against Tiger Woods. Indeed, for two decades, it has been a rarity for analysts to recommend oil stocks as a top pick for investors.</p>
        <p>Now oil prices have increased by 100 percent since last year. In the first quarter of 1999, crude oil was  $11.50 a barrel; now oil producers receive $30 a barrel. Virtually all of this additional price per barrel can go to the bottom line.</p>
        <p>If the cost of producing the oil is between $7 and $12 per barrel, which it is for the majority of oil companies, any amount they receive above that figure is potential profit. When they get $30 a barrel, close to $20 of this might become pretax operating income. But this does not mean that in the long term, oil companies' bottom lines are being fattened inordinately.</p>
        <p>In the first half of 1999, most oil companies had only a small net income. Many, with high costs or debt, had net losses. From 1977 through 1999, net income in the oil industry was equal to only 9.7 percent of net investment, as opposed to 11.5 percent for all of American industry.</p>
        <p>Take a more recent snapshot. From 1994 through 1998, oil company profits averaged 7.2 percent, or about half of the 14.2 percent average for all the companies on the Standard &amp; Poor's list of 500 industrial stocks.</p>
        <p>The pattern was little better in the first quarter of this year, when oil companies' profit margin was 5.9 percent, compared with 7.3 percent for all industries. And in some lucky businesses -- banks, publishing, broadcasting and electronics -- profits were 13 percent.</p>
        <p>In the second quarter of 2000, however, as the rising price of crude oil had its effect, most oil companies had large profit increases over the same months a year earlier. Exxon Mobil, Chevron and BP Amoco all reported profit increases of well over 100 percent. But these and all oil companies had a long way to come from what was, for them, starvation a year ago. And rises like this won't continue.</p>
        <p>Analysts of the oil industry expect that over the next couple of years, profits should level out on a plateau compatible with earnings for the rest of the companies in the S.&amp; P. 500.  But it will be the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries that will really determine what happens, because OPEC has considerable power over the price of crude oil.</p>
        <p>And in the future, as current sources of oil run dry, energy companies will have to spend increasing amounts drilling and developing in deeper and more hazardous regions. They will also have to commit huge sums to develop synthetics and find new sources of natural gas. Of course, all of this will make it more difficult for oil companies to maintain a healthy bottom line.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the future bodes well for oil and gas companies, compared with their dismal recent past. And it is high time for them to enjoy good returns along with most other American industries.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Mosbacher, chairman of the Mosbacher Energy Company, was commerce secretary under President George Bush.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert A. Mosbacher, chairman of the Mosbacher Energy Company, was commerce secretary under President George Bush.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
