<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corporations Underwrite The Democrats' Convention</title>
    <meta content="Y18DON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEMOCRATS: THE MONEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5DB153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corporations Underwrite The Democrats' Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barely an hour after Vice Pres Al Gore issues call for reforming campaign financing, he heads back to fund-raising circuit for concert that raises $5.2 million for Democratic Party; party officials are quick to note that event raises only 'hard' dollars, money party can use directly for Gore's candidacy, as opposed to unrestricted contributions known as soft money that are focus of most reform measures; concert is only fundraiser held by Democratic National Committee during convention, but candidates and congressional fund-raising committees courted contributors ceaselessly all week in soft-money extravaganza underwritten by scores of corporations that have already contributed millions of dollars and from which party hopes to reap millions more; entertainment and telecommunications industry have largest presence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barely an hour after Vice President Al Gore issued a call for reforming the ways political campaigns are paid for, he headed back to the fund-raising circuit for a concert that raised $5.2 million for the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>In his acceptance speech tonight, Mr. Gore vowed to ''get all the special-interest money -- all of it -- out of our democracy'' and promised to make legislation to reform campaign financing the first bill he would send to Congress as president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barely an hour after Vice President Al Gore issued a call for reforming the ways political campaigns are paid for, he headed back to the fund-raising circuit for a concert that raised $5.2 million for the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>In his acceptance speech tonight, Mr. Gore vowed to ''get all the special-interest money -- all of it -- out of our democracy'' and promised to make legislation to reform campaign financing the first bill he would send to Congress as president.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials were quick to note that the sold-out fund-raising concert at the Shrine Auditorium tonight featuring Barbra Streisand continued a tradition of celebrating the party's nominee at an event after the convention.</p>
        <p>And they noted that the concert tonight, also starring Whoopi Goldberg and Enrique Iglesias, raised only ''hard'' dollars, money collected in amounts from $150 to $20,000 that the party can use directly on Mr. Gore's candidacy -- as opposed to the large, unrestricted contributions known as soft money that are the focus of most reform measures.</p>
        <p>''The Democratic National Committee has always held a gala at the end of the convention to raise money and excitement for the ticket,'' said Jennifer Backus, a spokeswoman for the party.</p>
        <p>Ms. Backus said the event was consistent with the party's support for campaign finance reform because it collected only hard money. The $5.2 million raised tonight was the largest hard-money event in Democratic Party history, she said.</p>
        <p>Still, Senator Russell D. Feingold of Wisconsin, a Democratic co-sponsor of a measure to ban soft money in politics, was critical of the concert.</p>
        <p>''I would prefer there be no such events at our convention,'' Mr. Feingold said. ''It doesn't add to our message to have these events going on in Los Angeles.''</p>
        <p>The concert was the only fund-raiser that the Democratic National Committee held this week. But Democratic candidates and congressional fund-raising committees courted contributors ceaselessly all week in a soft-money extravaganza, underwritten by scores of corporations that have already contributed millions of dollars to Democratic committees and from which the party hopes to reap millions more.</p>
        <p>At a luncheon at the home of the children's entertainment executive Haim Saban, the most generous donors to the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee sipped lemonade and picked at a luncheon of chicken salad with the Senate minority leader, Thomas Daschle of South Dakota; Senator Robert G. Torricelli of New Jersey, the committee's chairman; Senator Dianne Feinstein of California; Senator Charles S. Robb of Virginia, and others.</p>
        <p>After playing a prominent role at the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia two weeks ago, telecommunications companies were big underwriters of events for the Democrats. Corporate giants like AT&amp;T, BellSouth, Verizon, SBC Communications, Sprint Telecommunications and Teligent sponsored more than a dozen costly receptions for top lawmakers this week.</p>
        <p>They entertained members of the House and Senate commerce committees, their legislative overseers, at Dodger Stadium on Tuesday evening. Among the sponsors of Dodger Day 2000 was the United States Telecom Association, a trade group whose president, Roy Neel, is a former chief of staff for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>They also helped underwrite a ''Mardi Gras'' party for Senator  John B. Breaux of Louisiana, and a nightclub show featuring the singer Sheryl Crow.</p>
        <p>Peter Knight, another former chief of staff for Mr. Gore and now deputy chairman of the Democratic National Committee, has lobbied on behalf of two telecommunications companies, Bell Atlantic and Leap Wireless.</p>
        <p>Communications companies rented out Spago restaurant in Beverly Hills for Senator Torricelli on Tuesday and for House Democratic leader Richard A. Gephardt on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Global Crossing, which donated $250,000 to both Republican and Democratic conventions, also paid for a dinner to honor Mr. Daschle on Wednesday. The company seeks federal approval to lay a telecommunications cable across the Pacific.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T, which has the most prominent presence here of any telecommunications company, gave $1 million in goods and services to each party for their conventions. The long-distance giant is the largest contributor to the Republican Party, having given $1.4 million since January 1999, and the fourth-largest to the Democrats, who received $993,000 over the same period.</p>
        <p>''These firms are the driving engine of the new economy and are in the process of becoming the driving force in political finance,'' said Fred Wertheimer, a longtime advocate of  campaign finance reform. ''They have a huge stake in government decisions, more so than almost any other sector of the economy.''</p>
        <p>Telecommunications companies rely on Congress and the executive branch for approvals of mergers, for access to the airwaves, for permission to offer local or long-distance telephone service.</p>
        <p>The explosion of telecommunications technology has made these companies enormously wealthy and they are spreading that wealth around elected officials without regard to party affiliation, Mr. Wert heimer said.</p>
        <p>Lonnie Taylor, the chief lobbyist for the United States Chamber of Commerce, said that communications companies support members of both parties because issues that concern them, including visas for foreign workers and privacy protection on the Internet, are generally not ideological and require bipartisan majorities for passage.</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS: THE MONEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
