<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honoring the Spiritual at a Shrine to the Material</title>
    <meta content="18GLUE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/arts/18GLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center (Ledyard, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glueck, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDE163EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honoring the Spiritual at a Shrine to the Material</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
      <dateline>MASHANTUCKET, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Glueck reviews Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center exhibition of artifacts from six Southwestern tribes on theme of rain; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The din of slot machines and the cries of croupiers cannot really be heard in the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, although it is just down the trail from its parent, the colossal Foxwoods Resort Casino. Nevertheless their proximity on this 1,400-acre reservation points up the anomaly that -- only in America! -- a gambling casino has hatched a serious museum.</p>
        <p>Staff members at the museum seem slightly uncomfortable with the casino's glittery presence, like a child painfully aware in public of a parent's gold tooth. They are quick to point out that the casino and museum are entirely separate endeavors. Yet there is no getting away from the truth that were it not for the casino and its undisclosed but estimated annual $700 million take (25 percent of the slot machine revenue goes to the state of Connecticut) there would be no research library and museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The din of slot machines and the cries of croupiers cannot really be heard in the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, although it is just down the trail from its parent, the colossal Foxwoods Resort Casino. Nevertheless their proximity on this 1,400-acre reservation points up the anomaly that -- only in America! -- a gambling casino has hatched a serious museum.</p>
        <p>Staff members at the museum seem slightly uncomfortable with the casino's glittery presence, like a child painfully aware in public of a parent's gold tooth. They are quick to point out that the casino and museum are entirely separate endeavors. Yet there is no getting away from the truth that were it not for the casino and its undisclosed but estimated annual $700 million take (25 percent of the slot machine revenue goes to the state of Connecticut) there would be no research library and museum.</p>
        <p>Nearly $200 million of the casino's profits went into the museum complex, a massive edifice of stone and glass designed by the New York firm of James Polshek &amp; Partners, which opened in 1998. Planned as a center for public education, it houses research libraries with some 35,000 books and documents on North American Indians, vast halls of life-size dioramas depicting the history and folkways of indigenous North Americans before European contact, and an art gallery devoted to their cultural heritage.</p>
        <p>Occupying a mere 4,200 of the complex's 308,000 square feet, the Mashantucket gallery appears to be the museum's smallest component. But it is an elegant one, well-suited to presenting ''Rain: Native Expressions From the American Southwest,'' its second special exhibition since the opening. The show was put together by a respected outside source, the Heard Museum of Phoenix, and appeared at the British Museum before coming to Connecticut. (In October the Mashantucket gallery will mount its first show drawn primarily from its own collections, ''Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark.'' ).</p>
        <p>As presented here, ''Rain'' explores the profound spiritual involvement of six southwestern cultures -- the Hopi, Navajo, Apache and Tohono O'odham of Arizona and the Zuni and Rio Grande Pueblos of New Mexico -- with the powerful but sparse resource that makes life and growth possible. On view are more than 120 objects expressing the theme of rain: paintings, pottery, kachina dolls, baskets, sculpture, jewelry, clothing, textiles, rattles and other musical instruments, bearing such ancient water symbols as clouds, butterflies, frogs, turtles, lightning and rainbows.</p>
        <p>Taking a cue from the practice of most ethnographical museums, the exhibition does not deal with its objects purely on aesthetic terms, but puts them in a context, here the highly particularized one of southwestern Indian belief. ''In this show our goal is to tell a cultural story, not necessarily an aesthetic one,'' said Steve Cook, assistant curator for ethnography at the museum. With a slight smile, he added, ''One of the driving forces behind  it was the urge to counter the classic Hollywood rain dance image.''</p>
        <p>The objects in this amply stocked but uneven presentation range from ancestral Pueblo water pitchers (650-1325 A.D.) to folksy narrative textiles depicting updated versions of Noah's Ark woven in the 1990's by Sadie Begay, a Dine (Navajo) who is a Christian. On the pitchers, the spiral designs evoking water are augmented by stylized ziggurat shapes that are rooted in antiquity, but that persist like other ancient symbols in contemporary work.</p>
        <p>A particularly outstanding exhibit is a textile (circa 1920) woven by a revered Dine medicine man, Hosteen Klah (1867-1938). His sophisticated design takes elements from the Navajo night chant, replete with references to rain and rain-related phenomena. Among them are evocations of a rainbow guardian that protects the elements in the textile, and two large figures with horns, the Mountain Sheep gods who bear on their backs sacks of black clouds filled with fruit and other earthly yields.</p>
        <p>Another key object is a richly allusive sand painting-made-permanent, ''Rain in the Line of the Sky'' (1993), by a contemporary Navajo, Joe Ben Jr. In it, the rain-making sky is depicted as a black ground (of pulverized coal), with a sun underlined by four triangles that symbolize clouds. A scintillating evening star stands for White Shell Woman, caretaker of rain. A bed of white clouds on the line of the sky also indicates rain: white and yellow for quiet, steady female rain on the left side; thunderous male rain on the right in blue and black. The artist ground his own materials for this impressive work, among them azurite, diamonds, gold, lapis and hematite.</p>
        <p>A lively contribution to comic relief is provided by Roxanne Swentzell of the Santa Clara Pueblos, in the form of ''It's Raining'' (1984), a large but squat ceramic sculpture of a humanoid creature. He is seated with hands protectively atop his head, wearing a jester cap and painted from head to toe in black and white horizontal stripes. It's a contemporary version of a sacred clown, called a ''Kossa'' in the Tewa language of Santa Clara. In ceremonies like the Corn Dance, the Kossa accompanies songs with descriptive gestures of such phenomena as rains, clouds or rivers. Given a sinister scowl, this one looks capable of all kinds of mischief.</p>
        <p>Kossas are shown in action in watercolors by J. D. Roybal of the San Idlefonso Clan. In one, of a pueblo corn dance (1968), they accompany women, depicted in their roles as connectors between this world and the hereafter. The women dance barefoot, emphasizing their connection to the earth.</p>
        <p>Kachina dolls, always associated with rain, assert a strong presence in the Hopi section of the show. Among them are a Sa'lakot male and female, tallest of the Kachinas, who appear at certain initiation ceremonies. Their headdresses of clouds and rain reach into the sky; rain falls from their eyes and rainbows run from their mouths. Both are dressed in eagle-feather robes; the male wears a kilt with cloud symbols.</p>
        <p>Rain evocations can be auditory, too, as demonstrated by displays of drums, rattles and even a fiddle made from the center stalk of the maguey cactus plant. These instruments are used to create sounds from thunder to the patter of a gentle fall.</p>
        <p>If some of the contemporary work seems a little slick and market-conscious, obviously made to appeal to commercial tastes, it doesn't vitiate the show's overall strength. There are marvelous objects here, put together in a strongly themed and inviting exhibition that holds promise for what's to come.</p>
        <p>''Rain: Native Expressions From the American Southwest'' is at the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail, Mashantucket, Conn., (800) 411-9671, through Sept. 4. Information: www.mashantucket.com.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
