<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peres Praises China After Visit to Bolster Ties With Ex-Critic</title>
    <meta content="18CHIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peres, Shimon (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jiang Zemin (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peres Praises China After Visit to Bolster Ties With Ex-Critic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Shimon Peres lavishly praises China as he finishes two-day visit intended to bolster Israel's ties with onetime adversary and shore up global support for continued peace talks; lauds Pres Jiang Zemin's efforts to dissuade Yasir Arafat from early declaration of a Palestinian state (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shimon Peres lavishly praised China today as he finished a two-day visit intended to bolster Israel's ties with this onetime adversary and shore up global support for continued peace talks.</p>
        <p>''I feel China is a very friendly country with a very profound understanding of events in the Middle East,'' Mr. Peres, a former prime minister who is now Israel's minister for regional cooperation, told reporters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shimon Peres lavishly praised China today as he finished a two-day visit intended to bolster Israel's ties with this onetime adversary and shore up global support for continued peace talks.</p>
        <p>''I feel China is a very friendly country with a very profound understanding of events in the Middle East,'' Mr. Peres, a former prime minister who is now Israel's minister for regional cooperation, told reporters.</p>
        <p>''I have great respect for President Jiang Zemin's call for patience,'' he added, alluding to remarks by the Chinese leader on Monday, after a meeting with Yasir Arafat, and repeated to Mr. Peres by officials during his visit.</p>
        <p>China's call for the Israelis and Palestinians to persist in a search for peace despite the breakdown of the Camp David talks last month, diplomats here said, was intended to dissuade Mr. Arafat from declaring a Palestinian state on Sept. 13, as he had said he would do. Such an act would be likely to provoke a strong  reaction from Israel, hurting the chances for peace.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday in Jakarta, Mr. Arafat said he was reconsidering the timing of declaring statehood after China and then Indonesia joined a long list of nations urging him to back off.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Peres praised Mr. Arafat for his apparent caution, calling it ''a wise step.''</p>
        <p>Israel has been delighted with China's moderate stance, which in Israeli eyes validates the courting of a country that until the late 1980's had championed Arab radicals.</p>
        <p>For the record, Israeli officials said Mr. Peres's visit, part of a quick Asian tour that also included Tokyo and Jakarta, was simply intended to inform leaders about the status of Israeli-Palestinian peace talks.</p>
        <p>But for Israel, the visit also offered a vital chance to shore up the budding friendship with China. Relations were jolted last month when Israel reneged on a $250 million contract to sell China's military an advanced airborne radar system after protests by the United States.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials welcomed Mr. Peres's offer on Wednesday to promote new Israeli investment and agricultural aid in China's underdeveloped hinterlands. And most important for Israel, China took a temperate line on the peace talks in successive meetings this week with Mr. Arafat and Mr. Peres, even as it reaffirmed support for eventual Palestinian statehood.</p>
        <p>Especially since 1992, when China gave Israel formal diplomatic recognition, Israel has cultivated ties with China, secretly selling weapons and offering agricultural and other aid.</p>
        <p>''The Israelis see enormous significance in their relations with China,'' said Michael Yahuda, professor of international relations at the London School of Economics. For one thing, he said, Israel sees friendly ties with this largest developing country as blunting the often hostile stance of much of the third world.</p>
        <p>In the past, China has been known to sell arms to archenemies of Israel, like Iraq and Iran. China has halted most such sales, but according to American intelligence agencies, it has continued to provide missile technology to Iran and Pakistan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peres said he had raised the missile issue with China's foreign minister and had been assured that China would abide by international agreements to bar transfers of long-range missile technology and nuclear arms. China has given similar ambiguous assurances in the past.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
