<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Undergoes More Tests and May Have Surgery to Treat Melanoma</title>
    <meta content="Y18MCC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000819T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Melanoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mayo Clinic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Skin Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tumors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DF153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Undergoes More Tests and May Have Surgery to Treat Melanoma</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain takes more tests for melanoma at Mayo Clinic, and will probably undergo surgery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doctors at the Mayo Clinic here examined Senator John McCain of Arizona today and recommended that he begin treatment immediately for the recurrence of a serious form of skin cancer, a McCain spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>The spokeswoman, Nancy Ives, said the results of three hours of tests were expected to be known on Friday, after which doctors would consult with Mr. McCain and determine a course of action that would probably include surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doctors at the Mayo Clinic here examined Senator John McCain of Arizona today and recommended that he begin treatment immediately for the recurrence of a serious form of skin cancer, a McCain spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>The spokeswoman, Nancy Ives, said the results of three hours of tests were expected to be known on Friday, after which doctors would consult with Mr. McCain and determine a course of action that would probably include surgery.</p>
        <p>After leaving the clinic with his wife, Cindy, Mr. McCain told reporters, ''I feel fine, thanks.'' He took no questions.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ives said Mr. McCain could undergo surgery, if needed, as soon as Saturday. She also said Mayo doctors planned to release a detailed report on Friday outlining Mr. McCain's condition, after which Mr. McCain would probably hold a news conference.</p>
        <p>The urgency for treatment arose after a routine examination of Mr. McCain at the Bethesda Naval Medical Center outside Washington on Aug. 3, when doctors found two spots -- one on his left temple, the other on his left arm -- that were confirmed through a biopsy to be malignant melanomas.</p>
        <p>Malignant melanoma is the deadliest and most aggressive form of skin cancer and the least common, but if caught early, it is highly curable.</p>
        <p>Because it was unclear whether the melanomas had spread, the doctors recommended additional tests, and today, Mr. McCain, who is 63, was administered blood work, a chest X-ray, an electrocardiogram, an echocardiogram, an M.R.I. and a CT scan. The seriousness of skin cancer is determined by how deep the cancer has grown and whether it has spread to other organs.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, who gave up his quest to win the Republican presidential nomination in March, has a history of skin problems and in 1993 had a melanoma removed from his shoulder. Medical records released by his presidential campaign said that Mr. McCain routinely had skin lesions or moles removed but that they were usually the most common and least threatening type of skin cancer.</p>
        <p>While he was speaking at the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia this month, blotches were evident at his temple. In the closing moments of his speech, Mr. McCain left an eerie and suggestive echo. He said: ''I will not see what is over America's horizon. The years that remain are too few, I trust, but the immortality that was the inspiration of my youth has, like all the treasures of youth, quietly slipped away.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ives said the speech, written by Mark Salter, who was a co-author of Mr. McCain's memoir, ''Faith of My Fathers,'' was not intended to portend ''anything dark about the senator's health,'' only the broad notion that the country's best times are always ahead.</p>
        <p>In any case, she said, the speech preceded the examination at the Naval Medical Center, ''so the timing is all wrong.''</p>
        <p>After the biopsy, Mr. McCain returned to Philadelphia for the final night of the convention and wore a bandage to protect the area.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's examination here came on the final day of the Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles, from which both Vice President Al Gore and his running mate, Joseph I. Lieberman, wished him well. Their sentiments echoed many others that aides to Mr. McCain said he had received over the last two days, including those from Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican presidential nominee, as well as scores of friends and other leading Republicans.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, Mr. McCain had toured Western states with Mr. Bush, and he had planned to resume campaigning next week. But his schedule is now uncertain, pending the treatment of his skin cancer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ives said it was uncertain if Mr. McCain's skin cancer had, in any way, been caused by the five years he spent in a prison camp during the Vietnam War. For much of the time, Mr. McCain was kept outdoors, and, as a fair-skinned person, was exposed to many hours of sunlight.</p>
        <p>Typically, fair-skinned people and those who have been sunburned at young ages are at greater risk to skin cancer, the American Cancer Society says.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. McCain qualifies under both risk groups, aides said, he has had checkups every three months, a vigilance that could mean that his latest problems are treatable.</p>
        <p>In an interview with The Associated Press, Dr. Charles McDonald, past president of the American Cancer Society, said: ''He probably just has another melanoma. Anybody who's had one, you have to keep very close eye on them. Nine times out of 10, they're going to develop another.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 19, 2000, Saturday  An article yesterday about the treatment that may face Senator John McCain of Arizona for skin cancer omitted a word in a quotation from his speech at the Republican National Convention. He said, ''The years that remain are not too few, I trust, but the immortality that was the inspiration of my youth has, like all the treasures of youth, quietly slipped away.'' He did not say, ''The years that remain are too few.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 19, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the treatment that may face Senator John McCain of Arizona for skin cancer omitted a word in a quotation from his speech at the Republican National Convention. He said, ''The years that remain are not too few, I trust, but the immortality that was the inspiration of my youth has, like all the treasures of youth, quietly slipped away.'' He did not say, ''The years that remain are too few.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
