<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. AGENT GAVE FAULTY TESTIMONY IN WEAPONS CASE</title>
    <meta content="18LEE.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Alamos National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messemer, Robert A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Wen Ho</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DB153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. AGENT GAVE FAULTY TESTIMONY IN WEAPONS CASE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FBI agent Robert A Messemer admits in federal court that he provided inaccurate testimony last December on a critical point that made Los Alamos National Laboratory scientist Dr Wen Ho Lee, who is accused of mishandling nuclear weapons secrets, appear deceptive when he had not been; issue is crucial because government has successfully argued that Lee be held without bail in part because his pattern of deceptions, along with fact that computer tapes containing vast amount of nuclear secrets remain unaccounted for, suggested that he was major threat to national security (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An F.B.I. agent admitted in federal court here today that he had provided inaccurate testimony last December on a critical point that made a Los Alamos scientist accused of mishandling nuclear weapons secrets appear deceptive when he had not been.</p>
        <p>The issue is crucial because the government has successfully argued since last December that the scientist, Wen Ho Lee, be held without bail in part because his pattern of deceptions, along with the fact that computer tapes containing a vast amount of nuclear secrets remain unaccounted for, suggested he was a major threat to national security.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An F.B.I. agent admitted in federal court here today that he had provided inaccurate testimony last December on a critical point that made a Los Alamos scientist accused of mishandling nuclear weapons secrets appear deceptive when he had not been.</p>
        <p>The issue is crucial because the government has successfully argued since last December that the scientist, Wen Ho Lee, be held without bail in part because his pattern of deceptions, along with the fact that computer tapes containing a vast amount of nuclear secrets remain unaccounted for, suggested he was a major threat to national security.</p>
        <p>In his written decision denying bail last December, the federal judge, James A. Parker, cited Dr. Lee's ''deeply troubling'' deceptions. Dr. Lee is trying for bail a third time,  and the government is now acknowledging what amounts to misleading testimony.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lee is the first person to be accused under the specific atomic energy statute cited in his 59-count indictment, and a growing number of  Asian-Americans and civil rights advocates have rallied to his side, saying he was singled out at least in part because of his Chinese ancestry.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Messemer, an F.B.I. supervisory special agent, had said under oath last December that when Dr. Lee improperly downloaded weapons secrets six years ago onto portable computer tapes he lied to a colleague, Kuok-Mee Ling, in order to get permission to use Dr. Ling's computer. Mr. Messemer testified that Dr. Lee told Dr. Ling that he was just going to download a resume, which was not true.</p>
        <p>But since then, Dr. Lee's defense lawyers have gained access to Dr. Ling's previous grand jury testimony, and it does not mention Dr. Lee speaking of a resume.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messemer today acknowledged that he had made ''an honest error'' on this critical point in his December testimony.</p>
        <p>''At no time did I intentionally provide false testimony,'' he said. ''I made a simple inadvertent error.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Messemer insisted that, in other areas, Dr. Lee had indeed been deceptive.</p>
        <p>There were, however, several other instances in which the defense appeared to show that the government had misled the judge in describing Dr. Lee's supposed deceptions. Mr. Messemer had testified at the December bail hearing that Dr. Lee had not disclosed certain contacts with Chinese scientists during officially sanctioned, professional visits to Beijing in the 1980's. But the defense lawyers have since obtained a report Dr. Lee filed after a 1986 trip in which he listed seven Chinese scientists with whom he had spoken.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messemer also acknowledged that, though Dr. Lee had clearly disclosed the contacts, he was never subsequently questioned about them. Mr. Messemer also disclosed that he had never consulted Dr. Lee's trip report before testifying in December. He still maintained that Dr. Lee had been deceptive because he had not been open about ''the full nature and scope'' of his contacts.</p>
        <p>The government contends that until Dr. Lee faced questioning a year ago, he failed to report a highly suspicious meeting with a Chinese scientist in his hotel room in a 1988 visit. The government also insists that Dr. Lee's downloading of the huge library of weapons secrets was itself a deliberate act of deception that took more than 40 hours of computer time and that he had knowingly violated rules on the handling of classified data.</p>
        <p>None of the statements in court here today or yesterday appeared decisive. The government presented weapons experts who insisted that Dr. Lee's downloading was unprecedented and a grave threat to national security because the data, in hostile hands, could alter the global balance of power.</p>
        <p>The defense offered its own experts who insisted that most of the information was already public and that its usefulness to another country was extremely limited.</p>
        <p>In one tense exchange, Paul Robinson, the president of the Sandia National Laboratories and a witness for the prosecution, said that one defense expert, Harold M. Agnew, a former director of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, had simply not understood the information Dr. Lee downloaded or had not understood the threat posed by Dr. Lee's actions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Agnew fired off a written affidavit to the court yesterday in response to that testimony, saying, ''What Paul said is a bunch of bull,'' and then rebuted parts of Dr. Robinson's testimony.</p>
        <p>In two other areas today, defense lawyers tried to show that government witnesses had provided misleading evidence in December. Mr. Messemer had said Dr. Lee failed to disclose correspondence with some Chinese scientists, saying he had only exchanged Christmas cards.</p>
        <p>Today, one of Dr. Lee's lawyers, Mark Holscher, produced a transcript of an interview with Dr. Lee and the F.B.I. on March 5, 1999, in which Dr. Lee did discuss correspondence with the Chinese scientists.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Messemer said in December that in the search of Dr. Lee's home, the F.B.I. had found letters that Dr. Lee had sent to several foreign scientific institutes seeking a job. The prosecution has said in previous filings that they believe the principal reason Dr. Lee improperly downloaded the nuclear secrets was to enhance his job prospects with the foreign institutes.</p>
        <p>But under questioning, Mr. Messemer acknowledged today that the F.B.I. had found some letters but had no evidence they were either mailed or received by the foreign institutions, which were in countries like Australia, France, Singapore and Switzerland.</p>
        <p>The bail hearing will resume on Friday. Judge Parker has allowed the examinations and cross-examinations of the witnesses, much of it in closed sessions because it involved classified information, to go on far longer than is usual at bail hearings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
