<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long Way From Home, But New York Dreamin'</title>
    <meta content="Y18CUO$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEMOCRATS: THE HOUSING SECRETARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EEDA153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long Way From Home, But New York Dreamin'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Housing and Urban Development Sec Andrew M Cuomo and New York State Comptroller H Carl McCall, both of whom want to run for governor of New York in 2002, make the rounds and present speeches at Democratic National Convention; Cuomo photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, the federal housing secretary who wants to be governor of New York, had just finished speaking to the Native American Caucus and was heading for the African-American Caucus when he was stopped by a delegate who had heard him speak to the California delegation.</p>
        <p>''I am going to put you on the spot,'' Mr. Cuomo declared, leaning in close to the Californian, as passers-by snapped photographs of the son of a New York celebrity. ''Who gave a better speech this morning, me or Ted Kennedy?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, the federal housing secretary who wants to be governor of New York, had just finished speaking to the Native American Caucus and was heading for the African-American Caucus when he was stopped by a delegate who had heard him speak to the California delegation.</p>
        <p>''I am going to put you on the spot,'' Mr. Cuomo declared, leaning in close to the Californian, as passers-by snapped photographs of the son of a New York celebrity. ''Who gave a better speech this morning, me or Ted Kennedy?''</p>
        <p>The delegate did not even stop for a breath: ''Ted Kennedy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo froze, shook the man's hand and moved on down the hall of the Westin Bonaventure Hotel, whispering over his shoulder to a reporter who had observed the encounter, ''California is Kennedy country.''</p>
        <p>Actually, at times this week, California seemed to be more like New York country, or rather, New York political country. No sooner had Hillary Rodham Clinton taken her campaign for senator from New York back to New York than Mr. Cuomo -- and the other New York Democrat who wants to run for governor in 2002, H. Carl McCall, the state comptroller -- plunged into their own political rounds, talking to state delegates and any delegation who would hear them, and of course, to reporters. Both men even got a chance to address the convention here, Mr. McCall on Wednesday and Mr. Cuomo tonight, though both speeches were given south of prime time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo insisted that his top concern here was not tending to any hope he might have to become the second New York governor named Cuomo, but rather advancing the campaign of Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>''As a cabinet member, my job here is to communicate the record and mobilize the Democrats to go forward. That's job No. 1,'' he said. ''Everything else is a distant second -- it being two years away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo has received pointed  reminders this week of both Mr. McCall's enduring popularity among Democratic leaders in New York, as well the lingering animosity some Democrats hold toward Mr. Cuomo's father, Mario. And Andrew Cuomo is still viewed in some quarters here as a bit of a political hot dog.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Cuomo's schedule of events is 23 pages long for the week, taking him today to the empty convention floor for an interview with Gabe Pressman of WNBC-TV, Channel 4 in New York, and to meetings with New York delegates. There he argued that the success of George W. Bush to date was proof that Mr. Cuomo would not be weighed down by his own father, who was defeated for a third term in 1994, should he run for office.</p>
        <p>''What we've learned in this election is the American people don't condemn a son for the acts of the father,'' Mr. Cuomo said. And then, referring to his own case, Mr. Cuomo said: ''If that were the case, this election would be over -- even if you thought Mario Cuomo's a negative in the state, which I don't believe it is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall has also been methodically tending to his own political future, meeting with New York Democrats and lining up future financial contributors in a state where, he said today, he has already raised $400,000 toward the 2002 race. Mr. McCall was loudly applauded when he appeared before the New York delegation, where he was repeatedly referred to as ''the next governor of the state of New York.''</p>
        <p>''I don't pay a lot of time paying attention to what Andrew Cuomo or anyone else is doing,'' Mr. McCall said today. ''Let met just tell you what I'm doing. I've just solidifying what I have. I've been relating to these folks for quite a while.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo suggested he was less than impressed with that. ''It's what I would have to believe,'' he said. ''I've been in Washington. His is the highest patronage office. It has to be that way. It can't be any other way. What does the Democratic Party establishment do for you? It's not a field operation. It's not your money-raising operation.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Cuomo, the high point today was his speech to the convention, an event that inevitably recalled the memorable keynote speech Mario M. Cuomo delivered in 1984 to Democrats in San Francisco. (It seemed that the four words Mr. Cuomo heard most often today were, ''I loved your father.'') But the younger Mr. Cuomo blanched at the suggestion that his speech invited comparisons to his father, quickly noting that his mission was limited to talking up Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''I have only five minutes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS: THE HOUSING SECRETARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
