<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bankruptices Defy Growth In Furniture</title>
    <meta content="Y18FURN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/business/18FURN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Heilig-Meyers Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Living.com Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD8143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bankruptices Defy Growth In Furniture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent bankruptcies of furniture sellers Heilig-Meyers Co and Living.com Inc show furniture business is joining retail clothing business in much more competitive arena where poor execution can lead to financial disaster; despite two bankruptcies, sales in furniture industry have been growing at more than 5 percent a year since 1992 and stand at $61 billion; with consumer spending starting to ease, growth in furniture sales is expected to slow to 2 percent to 3 percent this year, but analysts contend bankruptcies speak more to heightened competition than to overall weakness in industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two recent failures by furniture sellers show that the furniture business is joining the retail clothing business in a much more competitive arena where poor execution is increasingly fatal.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Heilig-Meyers Company, the largest furniture retailer in the country, with $2.3 billion in annual sales, announced that it was filing for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection and that it would close 302 stores, most in rural areas in the Southeast and California.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two recent failures by furniture sellers show that the furniture business is joining the retail clothing business in a much more competitive arena where poor execution is increasingly fatal.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Heilig-Meyers Company, the largest furniture retailer in the country, with $2.3 billion in annual sales, announced that it was filing for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection and that it would close 302 stores, most in rural areas in the Southeast and California.</p>
        <p>The news came the same day that Living.com, an Internet retailer with losses but glamorous partners like Starbucks and Amazon.com, said that it had filed for bankruptcy protection.</p>
        <p>Despite those announcements, the furniture industry is not moribund. Thanks to a strong economy that is driving home sales and a Martha Stewart-like national obsession with renovations, sales have been growing at more than 5 percent a year since 1992 and now stand at $61 billion.</p>
        <p>With consumer spending starting to ease, growth in furniture sales is expected to slow to 2 percent to 3 percent this year, but analysts contend the bankruptcies speak more to heightened competition than to overall weakness in the industry.</p>
        <p>''What happened at Heilig-Meyers is extremely unfortunate, because it didn't have to be,'' said Jerry Epperson, a furniture industry analyst and a managing director of Mann, Armistad &amp; Epperson, an investment banking firm in Richmond, Va. ''The industry is having the best of times.''</p>
        <p>Living.com's was the less significant of the two bankruptcy filings because selling furniture over the Internet is an experiment that many feel will not pan out soon.</p>
        <p>''The need for the consumer to touch and feel and sit and judge comfort cannot be addressed over the Web,'' said Jeff Butler, a principal at the retail consulting firm of Kurt Salmon Associates.</p>
        <p>While Heilig-Meyers faced numerous problems, including a lack of cash flow caused by an unwieldy string of acquisitions, the merchant was struggling because it still hewed to the old school of furniture retailing. Traditionally, furniture stores were more banks than merchants. That is, they made money not so much by selling sofas and chairs but by offering credit to low-income people to buy merchandise and then making a profit on the terms of the loan. This focus on financing as opposed to product explains why many older furniture chains were grim places with ugly stock and dim lighting.</p>
        <p>Such operations have been hit hard by credit card companies that lowered income requirements, allowing even relatively poor customers to shop wherever they liked, and by a huge increase in competition.</p>
        <p>For starters, there has been an explosion of rent-to-buy retailers. Such retailers offer higher prices, but if customers fail to make a payment for a large-screen TV or recliner, it does not hurt their credit record -- the companies simply repossess the rental item.</p>
        <p>The low- to mid-price category, meanwhile, is also undergoing startling change. Rooms to Go, a chain of furniture stores founded in 1990 that offers discounts to buyers willing to pay for a package of merchandise for one room, is already the third-largest furniture seller in the country, with $720 million in annual sales. In addition, nonfurniture retailers like Costco, Sam's Club, and Lowe's  sell some furniture, much of it at  competitive prices.</p>
        <p>The competition in the mid- and upper-price range has also increased with chain stores like Pottery Barn and Crate and Barrel, which sell lifestyle and ambience with their leather club chairs and pewter picture frames.</p>
        <p>''The customer wants to buy in a place that makes them feel good and comfortable,'' said Gerald Birnbach, chairman of the Rowe Companies, which supplies to those chains and others like J. C. Penney and Jordan's in Massachusetts. ''They are talking about value, but not prices.''</p>
        <p>''This industry is retarded when it comes to change,'' he added. ''That is why the young aggressive ones are catching the upswing. The ones doing it the same old way are going dead.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
