<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G. C. Myers, 69, Demographer Who Profiled Aging Globally</title>
    <meta content="Y18MYE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">George Carleton Myers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, George Carleton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saxon, Wolfgang</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D6143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="391" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G. C. Myers, 69, Demographer Who Profiled Aging Globally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WOLFGANG SAXON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saxon, Wolfgang</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr George Carleton Myers, sociologist and demographer who compiled and interpreted facts and figures about elderly worldwide, died on Aug 10 at age 69; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Carleton Myers, a sociologist and demographer who compiled and interpreted facts and figures about the elderly worldwide, died on Aug. 10 at his home in Burnsville, N.C. He was 69.</p>
        <p>The cause was pancreatic cancer, said Duke University, from which he retired as professor emeritus of sociology in 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Carleton Myers, a sociologist and demographer who compiled and interpreted facts and figures about the elderly worldwide, died on Aug. 10 at his home in Burnsville, N.C. He was 69.</p>
        <p>The cause was pancreatic cancer, said Duke University, from which he retired as professor emeritus of sociology in 1997.</p>
        <p>Dr. Myers founded the Center for Demographic Studies at Duke in 1972 and, as its director for the next 25 years, built it into an internationally known research center.</p>
        <p>In his specialty, medical demography, he provided projections concerning the elderly, including data on health and causes of death.</p>
        <p>''Every significant development in the demography of aging on the world scene over the past three decades has been either organized by George Myers or he has been a participant in it,'' said George L. Maddox, director of the Center for the Study of Aging and Human Development at Duke, in Durham, N.C.</p>
        <p>Dr. Myers was the author or co-author of some 100 publications analyzing demographic trends and findings from surveys.</p>
        <p>Central to his influence was his role as a coordinator for the Committee of Centers of Population Research, the International Network on Healthy Life Expectancy and the population activities unit of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe.</p>
        <p>Dr. Myers served as a consultant to government agencies and as an editor for professional journals dealing with aging and gerontology. He lectured at universities as far away as Australia and China.</p>
        <p>Born in Brooklyn, George Myers graduated from Yale University in 1953 and did postgraduate work at the University of Stockholm.</p>
        <p>He received his Ph.D. in 1963 from the University of Washington. He taught at Cornell University until 1968, when he was named a professor in the sociology department at Duke.</p>
        <p>Dr. Myers, who also had a home in Deerfield Beach, Fla., is survived by his wife of 46 years, Pauline Kraebel Myers; two sons, George C., of Westerly, R.I., and Peter D., of Baltimore; two daughters, Marie Lloyd of Chapel Hill, N.C., and Kathleen A. Myers of Raleigh, N.C.; and seven grandchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
