<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Try to Shore Up The Pillar That Was Labor</title>
    <meta content="Y18LAB$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEMOCRATS: THE UNIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DB153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Try to Shore Up The Pillar That Was Labor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Organized labor has always been one of strongest pillars supporting Democratic Party, but cracks are showing in the labor pillar as national convention draws to a close; union leaders and members are concerned that party is becoming too centrist, and are wary about issues like China trade agreement and school vouchers; Democratic leaders have spent much of week scurrying from delegation to delegation offering reassurances to union representatives; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Organized labor has always been one of the strongest pillars supporting the Democratic Party. Or, as John J. Sweeney, the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., enthused on Sunday while addressing a cheering throng of union members here for the Democratic National Convention:</p>
        <p>''Look at you -- 1,500 strong, 30 percent of the delegates to this convention and 100 percent of the soul of the Democratic Party.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Organized labor has always been one of the strongest pillars supporting the Democratic Party. Or, as John J. Sweeney, the president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., enthused on Sunday while addressing a cheering throng of union members here for the Democratic National Convention:</p>
        <p>''Look at you -- 1,500 strong, 30 percent of the delegates to this convention and 100 percent of the soul of the Democratic Party.''</p>
        <p>But cracks are showing in the labor pillar as this convention draws to a close.</p>
        <p>Many of the union officials and union members who showed up here are still deeply upset about the trade deal the Clinton administration negotiated with China. They remain implacably convinced that the agreement, which organized labor bitterly fought, threatens American jobs.</p>
        <p>Other union officials and members here say their party has become too centrist on social matters and less firmly committed to goals like maintaining affirmative action programs and opposing school voucher plans.</p>
        <p>Party leaders are concerned about such talk, doubly so since members of a group that makes up another pillar, black Democrats, have also expressed concern here about the party's ideological direction. The party bigwigs have spent much of the week scurrying from delegation to delegation trying to reassure disgruntled union members, lest union support flag for the Gore-Lieberman ticket, with grievous consequences on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>Just this morning, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut met for the second time with Bob Chase, president of the National Education Association, to reassure members of the powerful teachers union that while he had supported experimental voucher programs in the past, he would now go along with Vice President Al Gore in opposing them.</p>
        <p>''It was a good, productive meeting,'' Mr. Chase said in a statement issued by his office.</p>
        <p>This is the calculus the party leaders cannot escape: In the last presidential election, when Bill Clinton won a second term going away, 23 percent of all voters came from union households, and they voted Democratic 63 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>Will they do it again?</p>
        <p>Yes, say delegates from one of the country's most heavily unionized states, Michigan, where one of every two households has a union member. But sometimes their doubt is unmistakable.</p>
        <p>''I'm with Al Gore and Joe Lieberman all the way, every step,'' said Clarice Squillace, a retired auto worker from Eastpointe. ''I'm not happy with the China trade thing but I'm resigned to it because it's a done deal.</p>
        <p>''Can we get our people to turn out on election day? I don't know. I'll do everything I can to build the excitement. We've got to convince people there really are big differences between the two tickets. That's the key.''</p>
        <p>Rick Flynn, a National Education Association member from Sterling Heights, struck a similar note as he discussed how to turn out a big vote for the Gore-Lieberman ticket.</p>
        <p>''I've thought about this,'' Mr. Flynn said. ''It's the issues that will do the job, the differences between the two tickets. If you can make them clear, I believe we can drum up the kind of excitement we've seen here on the floor of the convention. I just wish I could bottle this excitement and take it back home.''</p>
        <p>Was he concerned that the Democratic Party was becoming too centrist, edging too close to things like school vouchers?</p>
        <p>''Whatever you think on a particular issue or issues, the center is where you win,'' he said. ''I'm comfortable with Al Gore and Joe Lieberman. Why not? Ted Kennedy and Jesse Jackson got up there on the podium the other night and praised them to the skies. If it's O.K. with a pair like Ted and Jesse, it's sure as heck O.K. with me.''</p>
        <p>For Lana Boldi, a United Auto Workers official from Grand Rapids, the China trade deal was a stinging blow. ''But as much as I disagree with that,'' she said, ''I disagree with George W. Bush even more on just about everything he stands for. You weigh it all out, and you go with Al Gore easily, whatever serious differences you may have with him.</p>
        <p>''There isn't any other real choice. You can't throw in with somebody like Ralph Nader just because he says the right things on something like China trade. That's just throwing a vote away.'' Mr. Nader is running on the Green Party ticket.</p>
        <p>Until just before the convention opened here, the enthusiasm of the U.A.W. for Mr. Gore was considerably less than overwhelming. The union held back on endorsing him -- its president, Stephen P. Yokich, is a Michigan delegate -- until just about the last moment. And in an auto state like Michigan, which also happens to be one of the important Midwestern swing states in Election 2000, that hurt -- and still hurts. The latest Michigan poll has Mr. Gore trailing Governor Bush by eight points.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore won the endorsement of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. leadership earlier on though, again, there was much concern about his support for the China trade agreement. Another powerful union, the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, still has not committed to a candidate. Its president, James B. Hoffa, is being heavily courted by both the Gore and Bush camps, as well as by Mr. Nader, who is drawing 5 percent to 10 percent of the vote in some big labor states, mainly at Mr. Gore's expense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa was welcomed as an onlooker at the Republican Convention in Philadelphia. And here in Los Angeles, he is listed as a ''superdelegate'' in the Michigan delegation.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader, said here at midweek that organized labor's vote would be crucial not only in the presidential race but, ultimately, in whether the Democrats regain control of the House and Senate.</p>
        <p>He noted that in 1994, when the Democrats lost 52 seats in the House and, with that, control of the House, turnout by union members was only 13 percent. But turnout was 23 percent, he said, in 1996, when the party regained nine seats, and in 1998, when it regained five more seats.</p>
        <p>''Our base has not come home yet,'' Mr. Gephardt said. ''We will have to work on that. The Republican base has accepted George Bush much sooner.''</p>
        <p>His view of the base?</p>
        <p>''When we talk about the base,'' he said, ''we are talking about yellow-dog Democrats -- like union members -- who are mostly white males, and who we have not done particularly well with.''</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS: THE UNIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
