<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Hands Ravens' Lewis a Fine of $250,000, but Doesn't Suspend Him</title>
    <meta content="18NFLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/sports/18nfll.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Jacinth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lollar, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DF153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Hands Ravens' Lewis a Fine of $250,000, but Doesn't Suspend Him</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Football League fines Baltimore Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis $250,000 for lying to police about his involvement in incident that resulted in stabbing deaths of Richard Lollar and Jacinth Baker outside Atlanta nightclub after Super Bowl last January; Comr Paul Tagliabue, in letter to Lewis's lawyer and NFL Players Assocation, addresses criticism from news media and others that Lewis should have been suspended; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Football League fined Baltimore Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis $250,000 yesterday for lying to the police about his involvement in an incident that resulted in the stabbing deaths of two men outside an Atlanta nightclub after the Super Bowl last January.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Paul Tagliabue also said Lewis would be fined another $250,000 if he violated the terms of his 12-month probation in Fulton County, Ga. It was there on June 5 that Lewis pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor count of obstruction of law enforcement officers and interference with a law enforcement investigation in connection with the death of the two men the night of Jan. 31.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Football League fined Baltimore Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis $250,000 yesterday for lying to the police about his involvement in an incident that resulted in the stabbing deaths of two men outside an Atlanta nightclub after the Super Bowl last January.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Paul Tagliabue also said Lewis would be fined another $250,000 if he violated the terms of his 12-month probation in Fulton County, Ga. It was there on June 5 that Lewis pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor count of obstruction of law enforcement officers and interference with a law enforcement investigation in connection with the death of the two men the night of Jan. 31.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Lewis's lawyers and the N.F.L. Players Association, made public by the N.F.L. yesterday, Tagliabue addressed criticism from the news media and others that Lewis should have been suspended. Tagliabue said that since Lewis was wrongly charged with murder, he had already suffered significant harm to his reputation as well as financial damage. Therefore, a suspension was not warranted, Tagliabue said.</p>
        <p>A fine, however, was warranted, Tagliabue said, because no N.F.L. player should lie to the police.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Lewis was not entirely truthful and candid with the police in his initial interview, and he counseled others that night to say nothing about what had happened,'' Tagliabue said in the letter. ''This misconduct no doubt fueled a public perception that he had something to hide. In doing so, he put his own livelihood and reputation needlessly at risk, and he caused great harm to other N.F.L. players and to the league.</p>
        <p>''The unlawful obstruction related to a very serious occurrence -- a double homicide,'' Tagliabue wrote. ''The homicides resulted from an altercation at which Mr. Lewis was clearly present, aspects of which he observed, and which involved associates or friends whom he had brought to and from the scene of the incident. In short, the obstruction here impaired or impeded an investigation of serious criminal conduct in circumstances that plainly led a wide segment of the public to view Mr. Lewis's conduct very negatively.</p>
        <p>That negative perception, in turn, negatively affected other N.F.L. players and the league itself.''</p>
        <p>The amount is the largest nonsuspension fine levied against a player by the league office.</p>
        <p>A person close to Lewis said the Pro Bowl linebacker was angry at the amount of the fine and would appeal it.</p>
        <p>Ravens officials privately are furious at the amount. They say Tagliabue made the number so high because he wanted to appease the public, mainly the news media. They say Lewis has suffered enough financially, paying over $1.5 million in legal fees and court costs.</p>
        <p>In May, Lewis and two friends went on trial in Atlanta, charged with malice murder, felony murder and aggravated assault with a deadly weapon.</p>
        <p>The prosecution's case crumbled, however, and murder charges against Lewis were dropped in exchange for his plea to obstruction of justice for lying to the police. As part of the deal, Lewis testified against the two co-defendants, Reginald Oakley and Joseph Sweeting, who were later found not guilty.</p>
        <p>Lewis met with Tagliabue earlier this summer, and in the weeks following the commissioner spoke to a number of people involved with the case. Tagliabue determined that Lewis should be hit with a hefty fine.</p>
        <p>One of the main reasons was Tagliabue's determination to make it clear to other players, and especially fans, that N.F.L. players should be held accountable for their actions.</p>
        <p>''When an N.F.L. player engages in and admits to misconduct of the type to which Mr. Lewis had pled here,'' Tagliabue wrote, ''the biggest losers are thousands of other N.F.L. players, present, past and future. Such admitted misconduct clearly contributes to the negative stereotyping of N.F.L. players. While such stereotyping is extremely unfair -- whether it afflicts N.F.L. players or other groups in society -- it is nonetheless an obvious and detrimental consequence of wrongful misconduct such as Mr. Lewis admittedly engaged in here.''</p>
        <p>Both league and Ravens officials maintain that Lewis has been a model citizen since the trial. He spoke to the league's rookies this off-season and in a passionate speech took responsibility for deceiving the police, but denied any participation in the murders. Lewis, as part of a personal conduct policy, has been meeting regularly with a counselor.</p>
        <p>The fine for Lewis comes only months after the N.F.L. refined and expanded its personal conduct policy. The changes were made in light of the Lewis case, as well as the case involving Carolina receiver Rae Carruth, who has been accused of masterminding the murder last year of his pregnant girlfriend.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
