<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the shadow of a recall, Firestone faces questions on how to celebrate its centennial.</title>
    <meta content="Y18ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/18/business/18adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3DA143EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the shadow of a recall, Firestone faces questions on how to celebrate its centennial.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Claudia H. Deutsch</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marketing professors and crisis management experts are debating whether Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co is right to downplay it centennial in wake of massive recall of tires; Firestone was planning to celebrate centennial is a big way (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIMING, as they say, is everything.</p>
        <p>This was supposed to be a jubilee year for Firestone. One hundred years ago, on Aug. 3, 1900, to be exact, Harvey S. Firestone established the Firestone Tire and Rubber Company, and Firestone was planning to celebrate that fact, in a big way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIMING, as they say, is everything.</p>
        <p>This was supposed to be a jubilee year for Firestone. One hundred years ago, on Aug. 3, 1900, to be exact, Harvey S. Firestone established the Firestone Tire and Rubber Company, and Firestone was planning to celebrate that fact, in a big way.</p>
        <p>Press kits went out to the media, point-of-purchase displays to dealers. A special Web site, www .Firestone100.com, made its debut in March, full of tales of past Firestone glories, as well as a catalog of Firestone-related merchandise. And, of course, there was the inevitable price promotion, offering tires that would normally sell for more than $40 each at the cut-rate price of four for $100. One hundred dollars, one hundred years -- get it?</p>
        <p>Then it all came crashing down. Firestone tires have been implicated in 62 deaths and countless injuries. Now Firestone's ad campaign is revolving around notices in 41 newspapers, detailing the mechanics of a huge tire recall.</p>
        <p>So, is Firestone's 100th-anniversary celebration dead in the water? Should it be?</p>
        <p>A few isolated birthday-theme ads were cropping up on local television stations last week, and a few dealers were still advertising the four-for-$100 promotion in newspapers. Whether they were stubbornly supporting Firestone, or whether the ads had been scheduled too far in advance to pull, was hard to determine.</p>
        <p>Throughout this week, Bridgestone/Firestone reacted to questions about the centennial celebration as though it were an I.R.S. investigation. It refused to make marketing people available for interviews, and its public relations people refused to discuss whether the anniversary celebrations remained anywhere on the burner, let alone the front or back.</p>
        <p>Advertising executives who represent Firestone refused to answer questions, even if they had nothing to do with the recall. Even Cullen O'Brien, an account executive with Laughlin/Constable Inc., which designed Firestone's 100th-anniversary Web page months ago -- and thus, could not possibly be accused of insensitivity in terms of spreading anniversary cheer in light of a giant recall -- responded to a reporter's questions with a terse: ''Call Bridgestone/ Firestone. I will conclude this conversation right now.''</p>
        <p>But one thing is certain: There is certainly no all-out anniversary ad blitz. And marketing professors and crisis management experts are having a lively debate over whether the company is right to downplay its birthday now.</p>
        <p>In one corner stand those who say that anything smacking of celebration had best be shunned. Susan Fournier, an associate professor specializing in marketing at the Harvard Business School, even thinks the company should dismantle the Firestone100 Web page.</p>
        <p>''Lighting candles on a cake right now just seems so opportunistic,'' she said. ''A birthday is a time for saying, 'Aren't you glad we were born.' It's an appreciative event, and a lot of people just don't appreciate how slow this company has been to tackle its problems.''</p>
        <p>Then, of course, there is the question of money. ''Every company has a budget, and Firestone should be devoting all of its advertising funds to the recall,'' said Gita V. Johar, an associate professor of marketing at the Columbia Business School. ''They can always let the dealers bring up the 100-year heritage in conversations with customers.''</p>
        <p>Or, others say, they can bring it up later. ''Right now, Firestone's customers are worried about safety, not discounts or history,'' said Sanjay Dhar, a professor of marketing at the University of Chicago's Graduate School of Business. ''Let Firestone spend its money on road safety campaigns, and celebrate its 101st anniversary next year.''</p>
        <p>But face it -- a 101st anniversary simply does not have the cachet of a centennial. And other marketing experts say the company should still play the birthday for all it's worth.</p>
        <p>''They've got to forget price promotions, or anything that looks like they are patting themselves on the back,'' said Gary Armstrong, a professor of marketing at the Kenan-Flagler Business School of the University of North Carolina. ''But they should try to create a campaign that focuses on 100 years of safety, and good relationships with customers.''</p>
        <p>Actually, that might be a bit dicey in itself. There's the little matter of the huge recall of Firestone 500 radial tires in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>With enough deftness, some say, Firestone could even turn that into a virtue. ''The 100-year anniversary establishes a tremendous credibility at a time that they have none,'' said Robert Marston, a New York public relations consultant who masterminded Procter &amp; Gamble's centennial celebration for Ivory Soap in 1979. ''They should get the C.E.O. out there, apologizing to the public, tackling the issues of the recall. But a 100th anniversary comes just once, and they should use it.''</p>
        <p>And how, exactly, should they do that? ''They should take the approach of 'every company with a proud tradition of 100 years of service will stumble from time to time,' '' Mr. Marston said. ''They should say, 'Together we surmounted the problems of the Firestone 500 and together we can get through this.' ''</p>
        <p>Even Firestone dealers agree to disagree. ''My job is to find replacement tires for my customers, and I'm losing sleep over that,'' said one dealer, who insisted on anonymity. ''Who's going to think of birthdays at a time like this?''</p>
        <p>Jerry M. Bauer, that's who. His dealership, Bauer Built Inc. in Durand, Wis., has sold Firestone tires since 1945, and a few months ago he contributed $5,000 to Habitat for Humanity in Firestone's honor.</p>
        <p>''No one should object to their promoting their company,'' Mr. Bauer said. ''Sure, they've got a problem now, but that's no reason to back away from 100 years of success.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
