<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old MetroCards as Origami, Not Litter</title>
    <meta content="18ORIG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Makman, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Lynda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDB153EF93BA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old MetroCards as Origami, Not Litter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richardson, Lynda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Makman, also known as Professor Putter, magician, has come up with about thirty uses for old MetroCards; creations include 'metro pigeon' which he calls 'official New York City bird' and 'metro shooter, which sends tightly-wadded piece of paper sailing through the air; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of the nearly seven million New Yorkers who ride the subways and buses every day, perhaps only one, Michael Makman, thinks of making a boomerang or a frog or even a crown when he sees a discarded MetroCard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman is Professor Putter, a magician with a handlebar mustache and fly-away hair, who may well have too much time on his hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of the nearly seven million New Yorkers who ride the subways and buses every day, perhaps only one, Michael Makman, thinks of making a boomerang or a frog or even a crown when he sees a discarded MetroCard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman is Professor Putter, a magician with a handlebar mustache and fly-away hair, who may well have too much time on his hands.</p>
        <p>He takes old MetroCards and turns them into little winged things, perhaps an airplane or a ''metro pigeon,'' which he gleefully calls ''the official New York City bird.'' One of his latest creations is the ''metro shooter,'' which sends a tightly-wadded piece of paper, also known as a spitwad, sailing through the air from two MetroCards that are taped together and folded a certain way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman, 49, has come up with about 30 uses for the discards, from boats and dogs to a ''metro razz'' that emits a loud funny noise when you blow hard between two MetroCards. The projects are listed in Mr. Makman's new book, ''MetroCard Mania With Professor Putter'' (Price Stern Sloan, 1999), which has skill levels from easy to advanced and step-by-step directions as well as diagrams.</p>
        <p>''It's a book that's found its time,'' Mr. Makman pronounced the other day in his tiny Upper West Side apartment, flicking a miniature version of an Australian boomerang from the palm of his hand. ''People are throwing the cards away. Instead of throwing them away, you can actually make them fly. And once you start thinking this way, then all of a sudden, you start off on a trend, a theme and you want to fill in the slots. There's so little new in the world.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. It became evident last week that some New Yorkers have mastered methods of using MetroCards for illicit gain. Nine ticket booth agents were charged with stealing $98,678 by selling new MetroCards containing falsified fares they had transferred from discarded cards. Authorities said the scam involved bending a used-up MetroCard along its magnetic strip in a certain way that tricked the token booth machine into providing a free fare.</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman wants to appeal to the kinder, gentler New Yorker. He said the cards could be recycled for good clean fun, emphasizing the added benefit of fewer MetroCards littering subway stations.</p>
        <p>MetroCards were not always Mr. Makman's obsession. When the reusable electronic cards were introduced in 1994, Mr. Makman was reluctant to give up on the subway token. He hated the thought of yet another card in his wallet. (The MetroCard, incidentally, is made of 100 percent polyester, not plastic, but that's another story.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman began to see the MetroCard's potential two years ago when he was standing inside a moving C train, absent-mindedly bending and snapping a MetroCard. The sound popped in the ear of a woman who sat nearby. She glared beams of hate at him.</p>
        <p>''She said, 'Do you mind?' '' he recalled. ''I realized that I was doing it right in her ear. Wow! How loud! And I thought, this is great.''</p>
        <p>Thinking like a magician, Mr. Makman at first wanted a deck of MetroCards, 52 of them. Now, he has a collection of nearly 3,000 used cards. He describes himself as one of the busiest children's entertainers in New York City, performing mostly at birthday parties. Just in case inspiration strikes while on the job, he always carries a small stack of old MetroCards and a pair of scissors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Makman dreams of a whole series of books, using transit cards from other cities like Chicago, Boston and Washington.</p>
        <p>Albert W. O'Leary, a spokesman for New York City Transit, counts himself as one of Mr. Makman's biggest fans.</p>
        <p>During a stressful week for Mr. O'Leary not too long ago -- a train had derailed in Brooklyn -- the magician sent Mr. O'Leary a pile of spent MetroCards and some instructions. Following the magician's directions, Mr. O'Leary  made a MetroCard tower that rose 11 levels high on a conference table; it collapsed two weeks later.</p>
        <p>''He's quite the guy,'' Mr. O'Leary said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
