<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Attacks the Lawyers Pursuing Suits Over Tires</title>
    <meta content="Y25TIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DA1531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Attacks the Lawyers Pursuing Suits Over Tires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich., Aug. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Attacks the Lawyers Purs</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials of the Ford Motor Company lashed out today at plaintiffs' lawyers suing the automaker and Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., accusing them of endangering public safety by calling for a broader recall of tires and of distributing Ford documents out of context to journalists.</p>
        <p>At a news conference this afternoon at Ford's headquarters here, executives again rejected lawyers' calls for a wider recall of 15-inch Firestone tires and for a new recall of 16-inch Firestone tires. Only the tires already recalled pose an unusual risk of failure, said Tom Baughman, Ford's engineering director for North American light trucks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Officials of the Ford Motor Company lashed out today at plaintiffs' lawyers suing the automaker and Bridgestone/Firestone Inc., accusing them of endangering public safety by calling for a broader recall of tires and of distributing Ford documents out of context to journalists.</p>
        <p>At a news conference this afternoon at Ford's headquarters here, executives again rejected lawyers' calls for a wider recall of 15-inch Firestone tires and for a new recall of 16-inch Firestone tires. Only the tires already recalled pose an unusual risk of failure, said Tom Baughman, Ford's engineering director for North American light trucks.</p>
        <p>Ford officials said that dealerships were being mobbed by customers insisting on replacements for tires not covered by the recall, draining the supply of new tires and forcing people with hazardous tires to continue driving on them.</p>
        <p>''A broader recall is wrong,'' said Helen Petrauskas, Ford's vice president for safety and environmental engineering. ''It's wrong because many good tires will be delivered and used to replace good tires -- and people who have tires which should be replaced will have to stand in line and wait.''</p>
        <p>Ralph Hoar, a consultant for plaintiffs' lawyers who is coordinating much of the litigation against Ford and Firestone, said that the two companies should prove that the tires not recalled are safe by releasing all of their raw data on the production and failure rates of many sizes of tires. ''It's Ford's and Firestone's responsibility to restore public faith in them and in this process,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Federal regulators reiterated today that they had made no decision on whether the recall undertaken by Ford and Firestone was broad enough and would continue to investigate many Firestone tires. Congressional committees are also beginning to look into the tire problem.</p>
        <p>Ford said it would put extensive information on tire failures on its  Web site, www.ford.com, by Friday morning. The data, including a series of charts, shows that the failure rates for the tires being recalled, particularly tires made in Decatur, Ill., are up to hundreds of times those for other Firestone tires. Last week, Ford put the data on its media site, which is available only to reporters with passwords.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoar said that Ford should make its files available to the public rather than calculating failure rates and other information in ways that might serve the automaker's interest.</p>
        <p>Jason Vines, a Ford spokesman, said that Ford and Firestone had replaced 13.3 percent of the 6.5 million recalled tires in the last two weeks. That is an unusually fast pace in an industry that normally takes as long as two years for a recall and often only persuades 50 percent to 60 percent of customers to bring in their vehicles for work. But the pace of the recall has failed to satisfy angry Explorer owners at Ford and Firestone dealers.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Petrauskas also accused plaintiffs' lawyers of distributing documents out of context to journalists with little familiarity with the engineering process through which automobiles are designed. The documents involve potential safety problems that Ford engineers identified in designing the Explorer. Mrs. Petrauskas said that engineers at any automaker analyze vehicle designs for possible safety problems and then fix them before putting vehicles into production, and she said that Ford did this with the Explorer.</p>
        <p>''I'm really struck that somehow it's being held against us'' that Ford engineers tried to identify potential safety problems in early prototypes, she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Petrauskas's comments were indicative of a common worry at Ford that plaintiffs' lawyers will dribble out documents for months whenever the recall fades from public attention. The lawyers ''have a lot of documents,'' fretted a senior Ford executive in an interview last weekend. Mr. Hoar said that Ford had been more selective than plaintiffs' lawyers in releasing information by refusing to make raw data available and by labeling some of its boxes of filings with regulators as proprietary information that cannot be included in the public docket.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
