<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Got a Little List</title>
    <meta content="25EATI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D81431F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Got a Little List</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out column with brief summaries of previous reviews of 12 Manhattan restaurants with interesting wine lists; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Great wine lists should reflect a restaurant's identity and ambitions while offering bottles that complement the food at all price levels. These 12 places have some of the most interesting wine lists in New York. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Becco</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 397-7597</p>
        <p>355 West 46th Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>With a menu and a wine list that are decidedly unusual, Becco is one of the more intriguing restaurants in New York. Its dependable Italian food is served two ways. You choose a Caesar salad or antipasto plate and then either unlimited servings of the three pastas of the day, or any of a dozen enticing main courses, like osso buco or whole roasted fish of the day. The wine list is a fabulous value, with dozens of interesting, primarily Italian wines. Best of all, every last one costs $18. If you have an ingrained need to spend more money, Becco also has a reserve list, ranging from $22 to $180.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Great wine lists should reflect a restaurant's identity and ambitions while offering bottles that complement the food at all price levels. These 12 places have some of the most interesting wine lists in New York. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Becco</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 397-7597</p>
        <p>355 West 46th Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>With a menu and a wine list that are decidedly unusual, Becco is one of the more intriguing restaurants in New York. Its dependable Italian food is served two ways. You choose a Caesar salad or antipasto plate and then either unlimited servings of the three pastas of the day, or any of a dozen enticing main courses, like osso buco or whole roasted fish of the day. The wine list is a fabulous value, with dozens of interesting, primarily Italian wines. Best of all, every last one costs $18. If you have an ingrained need to spend more money, Becco also has a reserve list, ranging from $22 to $180.</p>
        <p>2. Cite</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 956-7100</p>
        <p>120 West 51st Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>If you visit this large, boisterous Art Deco restaurant and you see the wine flowing like water, it must be after 8 p.m., when one of New York's great wine deals goes into effect. From 8 to midnight, Cite, one of Alan Stillman's stable of restaurants, which also includes the Post House, Smith &amp; Wollensky and the Park Avenue Cafe, will pour as much as you wish of four different wines, which usually include Champagne, a decent white and a couple of decent reds for one low price. Along with the wine, Cite serves fine sirloin and other steakhouse staples. Sides like creamed spinach and french fries are top notch.</p>
        <p>3. Danube</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 791-3771</p>
        <p>30 Hudson Street, at Duane Street</p>
        <p>TriBeCa</p>
        <p>$$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Vienna never looked so good. In a decorating frenzy, David Bouley has summoned up a time and a place -- the Hapsburg Empire circa 1900 -- that shimmer in a seductive golden haze. He has created a fevered dream of a restaurant, with dense fabrics, opulent colors, lacquered woodwork and jeweled, gilded walls decorated in Gustav Klimt's most flamboyant manner. Austrian wines flow through the menu in an exotic stream. There's a Weingartner riesling dressing and a zweigelt sauce on braised beef cheeks. Diners who ask for the wine list, which offers about 250 choices, half of them Austrian, soon find themselves in the thickets of gruner veltliner, Muller-Thurgau and blauburgunder.</p>
        <p>4. Enoteca i Trulli</p>
        <p>++</p>
        <p>(212) 481-7372</p>
        <p>124 East 27th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Enoteca i Trulli, the wine bar next to I Trulli, offers the terrific opportunity to sample the restaurant's extensive selection of Italian wines with a short list of inexpensive yet delicious dishes. The handmade pastas are prepared by the proprietor's mother and include superb fettuccine with rich Apulian meat sauce and lasagnas that differ from day to day. The rest of the menu is simple and inviting, like panzerotti, a small calzone stuffed with tomato, cheese and anchovy, and hearty broccoli-and-pasta soup. For dessert: a few biscotti and a taste of the wine bar's many grappas.</p>
        <p>5. Esca</p>
        <p>** [Rating: 2 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 564-7272</p>
        <p>402 West 43rd Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>In a city that has seen seafood in every possible form, it takes a little ingenuity to make the idea of fish seem fresh. Esca pulls off the trick by giving the food a regional Italian focus. Esca draws on the rich maritime cuisine of Naples and the Amalfi coast. It also borrows a little from Istria on the northern Adriatic, in a menu within a menu of raw fish served with fragrant olive oil, herbs and vegetables. Fritto misto Amalfi-style and zuppa de pesce lead the list of highly traditional main courses. Lamb and chicken are on the menu. But would anyone skip Dover sole in almond pesto to get to them? The stellar wine list, a budget-priced tour of every corner of Italy, also provides a brilliant diversion when the food sags a bit.</p>
        <p>6. Harry's of Hanover Square</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 425-3412</p>
        <p>1 Hanover Square, at Pearl and Stone Streets</p>
        <p>Lower Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This restaurant and saloon, long a landmark for Wall Street workers, is fittingly housed in the landmark India House, which was built in 1851. Harry's menu, with dishes like steak Diane, fillet of sole amandine and shrimp fra diavolo, might variously be described as classic, traditional or old-fashioned. There's nothing frumpy about Harry's wine cellar, though, which is one of the best in the city and is known for having the lowest prices for expensive wines.</p>
        <p>7. Holy Basil</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 460-5557</p>
        <p>149 Second Avenue, near Ninth Street</p>
        <p>East Village</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>What sets Holy Basil apart from many Thai restaurants is the graceful balance of the cooking. Nearly every dish is a study in control, with flavors and textures unfolding in careful relation to one another. Yum pla muok, for instance, a beautifully presented spicy squid salad, makes perfect use of chili peppers. The heat contrasts with the freshness of lime juice and the pungency of garlic and onions, resulting in an ensemble of flavors playing in unison. Holy Basil also offers a terrific list of wines that go exceptionally well with the food. Wine descriptions are helpful, though occasionally over the top.</p>
        <p>8. Judson Grill</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 582-5252</p>
        <p>152 West 52nd Street, in the Equitable Building</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Bill Telepan, the chef, is committed to freshness; it is the key to the quiet but eloquent flavors he offers on his contemporary American menu. He presents perfect seasonal dishes like pan-fried summer vegetables with mozzarella, basil-mint oil and aioli. Main courses currently include tomato crusted Atlantic salmon with plum tomato-gold squash stew, spinach and thyme; and roasted Maine lobster with sweet corn, stewed cabbage and potato puree. The wine list is intelligently chosen, with sections for affordable special values and big-deal wines bought at auction.</p>
        <p>9. N 33 Crosby</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>(212) 219-8856</p>
        <p>33 Crosby Street, near Broome Street</p>
        <p>SoHo</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>At N 33 Crosby, a small but stylish tapas bar, you can pick and choose among small dishes, like olives mashed with capers, garlic, olive oil and anchovies; octopus and steamed potato cubes; and of course the ubiquitous Spanish omelet with onions and potatoes. N 33 Crosby is also one of the best places in New York to taste sherries, the fortified wines made in the Andalusia region of southern Spain. Try a delicate, flavorful manzanilla with boquerones, anchovies that taste like pickled herring. It's a classic combination.</p>
        <p>10. Tabla</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 889-0667</p>
        <p>11 Madison Avenue, at 25th Street</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Tabla is the newest restaurant in Danny Meyer's growing empire and, as with all of his restaurants, the wines are beautifully chosen and fairly priced. What's especially interesting about Tabla's wines is that they match the unusual menu of American foods transformed by Indian spices. The current menu includes chilled corn soup flavored with star anise, clove, ginger and fines herbs; and rice flaked halibut with watercress, lime and watermelon curry. The restaurant's wine list has a fine selection of rieslings, sauvignon blancs, pinot noirs, Rhones and zinfandels.</p>
        <p>11. Veritas</p>
        <p>*** [Rating: 3 stars]</p>
        <p>(212) 353-3700</p>
        <p>43 East 20th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Small, spare and elegant, Veritas could be called a wine cellar with a restaurant attached. Because at Veritas wine is more important than the food. The 1,300 entries on the wine list include rarities like a Chateau Margaux 1900 as well as a Mouton-Rothschild 1945 and Lafite-Rothschild 1953, and they are offered at extremely reasonable prices. The chef, Scott Bryan, one of four owners, serves clean, unfussy food that works well with the wine. Sweetbreads are extraordinary, or try the lobster salad served with asparagus, fava bean puree and sherry vinegar. The main courses are more straightforward than the appetizers, robust, powerful and surprisingly simple.</p>
        <p>12. Wild Blue</p>
        <p>* [Rating: 1 star]</p>
        <p>(212) 524-7107</p>
        <p>1 World Trade Center</p>
        <p>Lower Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This intimate, romantic restaurant atop the World Trade Center offers spectacular views of New York Harbor. When night falls, Wild Blue feels like a plush space capsule hurtling through the cosmos. The down-the-middle American menu walks a thin line between simple and austere. In spirit it is an updated chophouse for the weary business diner, with a few interesting twists. Those who plunge into the wine list will find a lot to like, about 1,500 bottles, mostly French and Californian; also abundant selections from Germany and Italian wines from the Piedmont. Bargains galore, plus 29 half-bottles and 47 wines by the glass.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>EATING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
