<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico Court Makes History By Siding With Congress</title>
    <meta content="Y25MEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF1231F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico Court Makes History By Siding With Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Aug. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexican Supreme Court orders Pres Ernesto Zedillo to turn over to Congress secret banking data relating to questionable financing of Zedillo's 1994 campaign; decision to uphold congressionanl authority marks clear declaration of independence from all-powerful executive branch (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a ruling that justices described as a judicial watershed, the Mexican Supreme Court ordered President Ernesto Zedillo today to turn over to Congress secret banking data relating to questionable financing of Mr. Zedillo's 1994 campaign.</p>
        <p>The decision was the first in modern history in which the court, the weak sister in Mexico's system of government, has ruled in a constitutional dispute between two competing federal powers. The court's decision to uphold a congressional challenge to presidential powers marked a clear declaration of independence by the court from the all-powerful executive branch, which has dominated the judiciary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a ruling that justices described as a judicial watershed, the Mexican Supreme Court ordered President Ernesto Zedillo today to turn over to Congress secret banking data relating to questionable financing of Mr. Zedillo's 1994 campaign.</p>
        <p>The decision was the first in modern history in which the court, the weak sister in Mexico's system of government, has ruled in a constitutional dispute between two competing federal powers. The court's decision to uphold a congressional challenge to presidential powers marked a clear declaration of independence by the court from the all-powerful executive branch, which has dominated the judiciary.</p>
        <p>Ruling in a suit filed by opposition lawmakers last year, the court found that Congress had every right to demand full disclosure by Mr. Zedillo's government about the dealings of Banco Union, a bank that oversaw millions of dollars in donations to the president's 1994 campaign even as it was sliding into bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Zedillo later intervened in Banco Union's case, turning its liabilities into public debt and arguing that bank secrecy laws barred any public accounting.</p>
        <p>In today's ruling, the court gave Mr. Zedillo 30 days to turn over to Congress a series of files from Banco Union. The court's 11 justices endorsed the order unanimously. In a statement hours later, Mr. Zedillo's office pledged to comply.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, this is a profoundly historic decision,'' Olga Sanchez Cordero, the justice who presided over the previous deliberations in the constitutional challenge, said at a news conference. She said it marked the first time the court had refereed a dispute between two branches of the federal government, and it limited bank secrecy laws by stipulating that they may not be used to shield potentially illegal transactions in which taxpayers must pay for the reckless management of private assets.</p>
        <p>Since Mexico's independence from Spain in 1821, its judicial system has been hobbled by frequent presidential interference, and three presidents in this century have simply dismissed the entire high court. One was Mr. Zedillo himself, who in his first month in office dismissed all 26 justices, installing the new 11-member court as part of a judicial reform that he says has strengthened the court's autonomy.</p>
        <p>Last year, the justices elected a new chief justice, Genaro Gongora Pimentel, who has championed initiatives aimed at increasing the judiciary's power and independence. Under his influence, the court's powers to broker constitutional challenges have been growing.</p>
        <p>It has ruled in constitutional disputes between two cities, between cities and states, between states and the federal Congress. But it had never ruled in a dispute pitting the Congress against the presidency, Justice Sanchez said today.</p>
        <p>The ruling comes eight weeks after Mr. Zedillo's governing party suffered its first defeat in seven decades of presidential voting, and some analysts suggested that the July 2 election of an opposition candidate, Vicente Fox Quesada, had strengthened the court's willingness to rule against Mr. Zedillo.</p>
        <p>In his statement, Mr. Zedillo said he had already ordered the treasury secretary and the president of the National Banking Commission to turn over the Banco Union files requested by Congress.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
