<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Yankees Dawdle While the Mets Wait</title>
    <meta content="25SAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/sports/25SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shea Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0D91531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Yankees Dawdle While the Mets Wait</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports Business column on New York Yankees' long delay in deciding about new stadium; notes this has left New York Mets out on limb, because Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani is waiting for Yankees' plan so he can address both teams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Someday, perhaps, the Yankees will decide where their next home will be after their lease at Yankee Stadium expires in 2002. Only then will the Mets, who know where they want to put their retractable roof stadium, get their city financing.</p>
        <p>When will that day come?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Someday, perhaps, the Yankees will decide where their next home will be after their lease at Yankee Stadium expires in 2002. Only then will the Mets, who know where they want to put their retractable roof stadium, get their city financing.</p>
        <p>When will that day come?</p>
        <p>Maybe not until the Nets and the Devils move into a Newark arena, which won't be until 2004.</p>
        <p>Until then, the Mets' $500 million, retro Ebbets Field project, which the co-owner Fred Wilpon unveiled 28 months ago, will continue to idle.</p>
        <p>''It's a factor, definitely, the Yankee issue,'' said Dave Howard, a senior vice president of the Mets. ''The mayor recognizes that he has two interested teams and he has to address both in some way.''</p>
        <p>How far have financing talks between the city and the Mets gone? ''There have been proposals; we've thrown ideas back and forth,'' Howard said.</p>
        <p>Some time ago, the Mets may have thought the Yankees' leadoff position in the stadium game would have yielded a better deal for the Mets to piggyback on. After all, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani bleeds Yankee blue pinstripes.</p>
        <p>But that was before the extended study and the dawdling by the Yankees, an excruciatingly long period of indecision that has stalled the Mets' deal.</p>
        <p>All this idling has delayed the mayor's publicly having to justify using public money to help finance $1.5 billion in stadium expenditures for both teams.</p>
        <p>Lonn Trost, the Yankees' chief operating officer, insisted that the elongated study -- remember it has been six years since the West Side option was first broached -- was necessary, but it is not the reason the Mets' stadium deal has not happened.</p>
        <p>''We're not powerful enough to hold up the Mets,'' Trost said. ''Fred's good people. We went to the same high school. But I don't know what's holding up his deal.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in another land not far from the Bronx and Flushing, a governmental entity has begun financing talks with a sports organization, which like nearly every other, prefers not to spend all its own money on the cost of building a new home.</p>
        <p>This one is moving at the speed of light, unlike the Yankee-Met slowdown.</p>
        <p>On Monday, after only four months of intensive talks, Michael Torpey, the chief of staff for Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, wrote to the YankeeNets owners saying the governor would commit $75 million to the cost of a $325 million arena for the Devils and the Nets to be built in downtown Newark by 2004.</p>
        <p>The sum fell short of the YankeeNets' request by $49 million, but still, here was an actual government official responding to a concrete plan with a figure that the YankeeNets hope is not a final offer.</p>
        <p>''We expect there to be an opening beyond what is described in the letter,'' said Harvey Schiller, the chairman of the YankeeNets, which has moved with alacrity on the Newark project, a contrast to how long the Yankees have been studying their stadium project.</p>
        <p>But study they must, said Trost, who would not give a date by which all the cramming will end.</p>
        <p>''The general perspective is, we've given up all options but to stay in the Bronx, but that's wrong,'' Trost said. ''People don't know the landscape of the Bronx or the West Side or the attractiveness of New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>As to whether robust home attendance in the Bronx necessarily means the team can't leave the borough, Trost said, ''I totally disagree.''</p>
        <p>The delays don't ire the Yankees, because they are responsible for them. The Mets are not. In 1998, when Wilpon proudly showed off his stadium design, he was hoping to conclude financing talks within a few months and have his ballpark ready by 2002. Then he amended it to 2003.</p>
        <p>Now, that can't be done. Said Howard: ''It's a 30- to 36-month construction cycle. You need a deal before you build, so '03 is not feasible.''</p>
        <p>Since 1998, new stadiums have opened in San Francisco, Seattle, Phoenix, Houston and Detroit. New ones will open next year in Milwaukee and Pittsburgh. The Massachusetts legislature has even approved money for a new Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>Mad, Mad Marketing</p>
        <p>If team names and logos can embody the worldview of a league, the XFL introduced eight yesterday that described a venture screaming for attention. Still, they fall short of the ultracartoonish styling of the World Wrestling Federation, which owns the football league with NBC.</p>
        <p>The New York/New Jersey Hitmen points to the influence of ''The Sopranos,'' but true XFL style would only have been served by the ''Gravanos.'' Then there are the Rage, the Maniax, the Xtreme, the Outlaws, the Enforcers, the Thunderbolts and the Demons, winners from a master list of 53.</p>
        <p>Three teams sport logos depicting psychotic males, including the Hitmen's: a hybrid of a rabid Dick Tracy and Ray Nitschke in a studded helmet. A figure with hair afire and eyes in a dazed, hypnotic swirl aptly represents the Memphis Maniax.</p>
        <p>The league's publicity notes: ''The maniacal eyes of the team mascot is just a preview of how the MANIAX opponents will feel after they've been AX'd.'' You don't feel that way about the Seattle Seahawk? Gosh, remember when the Oakland Raider seemed ready to ride a Harley into Pete Rozelle's office?</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call them psychos,'' said Basil DeVito, the XFL's president. ''We were looking for variety.''</p>
        <p>Drew Pearson, the New York/New Jersey general manager, had a successful National Football League career as a mere Cowboy wearing what seems to him now a wimpy star logo. He said: ''The Hitman represents what the New York/New Jersey franchise will be about. We'll play with reckless abandon and with an in-your-face attitude.''</p>
        <p>But can a player play like a logo?</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
