<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unusual Lineup Makes for Bad Baseball but a Good Victory</title>
    <meta content="25YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/sports/25yank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5D61531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unusual Lineup Makes for Bad Baseball but a Good Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Texas Rangers, 8-7; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ball was launched hard off the bat and appeared headed for center field. Chad Curtis thought he had led off the Rangers' ninth inning with an exclamation, until pitcher Mariano Rivera raised his glove and denied Curtis a leadoff single. The ball knocked Rivera backward, leaving him with an expression somewhere between a smile and a grimace.</p>
        <p>''He's not going to get any uglier than that, so it might help him out a little,'' the Yankees' Jorge Posada joked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ball was launched hard off the bat and appeared headed for center field. Chad Curtis thought he had led off the Rangers' ninth inning with an exclamation, until pitcher Mariano Rivera raised his glove and denied Curtis a leadoff single. The ball knocked Rivera backward, leaving him with an expression somewhere between a smile and a grimace.</p>
        <p>''He's not going to get any uglier than that, so it might help him out a little,'' the Yankees' Jorge Posada joked.</p>
        <p>The same could be said for the game. Fielding a lineup that turned a few heads, the Yankees ended a messy homestand with a sloppy 8-7 victory over the Texas Rangers yesterday at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The last week has lacked aesthetics. The Yankee bullpen blew its third lead of the homestand on Wednesday night before the team rallied in the ninth for a victory. In all, the Yankees won five of eight games at the Stadium and now will travel to the West Coast to play Oakland tonight.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had their share of highlights yesterday, from Glenallen Hill's love-in with the fans in the bleachers to Andy Pettitte's persistence to Jose Canseco's footwork to Jason Grimsley's two hitless innings of relief. But the Yankees and the Rangers also combined for three errors and numerous mental blocks.</p>
        <p>''It was a good game to win, because we definitely didn't play a good ballgame,'' said Pettitte (16-6), who won his seventh straight decision.</p>
        <p>The lineup was less than a thing of beauty. With Bernie Williams (sore rib cage) and Paul O'Neill (hip pointer) resting, Manager Joe Torre started an outfield of Hill, Clay Bellinger and David Justice, who returned after missing three games with a sore neck. Posada played first with Chris Turner catching. Jose Vizcaino started at second base.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees had Pettitte and his knack for run support on their side. The team is averaging 7.48 runs in Pettitte's 25 starts, including 11.17 in his previous six starts. Torre joked that other pitchers were jealous and said before the game, ''If it happens today with the little bit of a skeleton lineup we have, then you know Andy Pettitte has an angel on his shoulder.''</p>
        <p>That angel could have sprouted horns when Pettitte fell behind by 4-1 in the third inning, as his teammates appeared out of sync. Posada closed his glove too soon on a throw to first in the first inning for an error, and then he started an unusual sequence in the third. Ricky Ledee's grounder bounced off Posada's glove and to Vizcaino, who threw the ball past Pettitte at first base, allowing one run to score. Curtis, who had stopped running at third, jogged home unimpeded when Turner chased the ball to the backstop.</p>
        <p>Yet, Pettitte was confident that his team would score off the Texas starter Matt Perisho.</p>
        <p>The Yankees batted around for five runs in the third on the legs of Canseco. With Posada on first and Canseco, who has a sore left heel, on second, and three runs already in during the inning, Turner laid down a sacrifice bunt. Canseco raced to third and beat Perisho's throw.</p>
        <p>Then, when Bellinger hit a grounder to third with the bases loaded and one out, Canseco looked like a tight end as he rambled home. He saw Texas catcher Robert Waszgis casually standing behind the plate. Third baseman Scott Sheldon threw home. That startled Canseco, who saw that the catcher was out of position, and apparently Waszgis, who was straddling the plate and failed to get the forceout.</p>
        <p>The Yankees led, 6-4, but Texas scored once in the fourth inning. Then, in the bottom of the inning, Hill punctuated the afternoon with a mammoth two-run home run. The ball caromed off the front of the center-field bleachers as Hill missed reaching the black seats for the second time in a week.</p>
        <p>Hill is batting .429 since his trade from the Cubs on July 20, with 12 homers in 70 at-bats. He batted .455 with 6 homers on the homestand and extended his career-high hitting streak to 13 games.</p>
        <p>''I come to the ballpark every day and the ball flies off the bat, but usually that happens in batting practice,'' Hill said. ''It feels good to have it happen in a game.''</p>
        <p>Torre says the team now expects every ball Hill hits in the air to carry for a home run. ''That's crazy,'' the manager said.</p>
        <p>''He's making this ballpark look like Enron Field or Coors Field,'' Pettitte said.</p>
        <p>Pettitte labored, but outlasted Perisho. Torre thought Pettitte was overthrowing. The Yankees' left-hander threw 93 pitches in the first four innings. But he retired the side in order in the fifth and sixth and left after allowing Curtis a double and Rafael Palmeiro a run-scoring single to lead off the seventh. Grimsley inherited an 8-7 lead and a 1-1 count on Gabe Kapler. He walked Kapler and then, throwing strictly sinking fastballs, retired the next six batters he faced.</p>
        <p>''He's the guy that saved the game,'' said Rivera, who earned his 27th save.</p>
        <p>Rivera preserved the lead and his own health by snaring Curtis's line drive in the ninth. Then, after Palmeiro singled, Posada threw out the pinch-runner Scarborough Green attempting to steal second base. A called third strike to Kapler ended the game and an exhausting, if unattractive, homestand.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>CHUCK KNOBLAUCH (sore right elbow) will play in a minor league game in Florida today, Manager JOE TORRE said. Knoblauch will most likely be the designated hitter. The Yankees want him to get at-bats before returning when rosters expand Sept. 1. . . . PAUL O'NEILL offered to play, but Torre gave him the day off. O'Neill was available to pinch-hit and could start tonight in Oakland.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
