<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feud Among Ulster's Protestant Guerrillas Claims Third Victim</title>
    <meta content="25ULST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rocket, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D81531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feud Among Ulster's Protestant Guerrillas Claims Third Victim</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Belfast man, 22-year-old Samuel Rocket, is third victim of week in feud between Protestant paramilitaries in Northern Ireland (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Belfast man gunned down overnight was the third victim this week in a feud among Protestant paramilitary groups that has brought British troops back onto the streets of Northern Ireland, officials said today.</p>
        <p>The police, who said they arrested six men after the killing and seized guns and ammunition, identified the latest victim as Samuel Rocket, 22. He was shot by masked men who burst into the living room of his home in full view of his partner and a 12-month-old baby and opened fire ''several times at close range,'' a police spokesman said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Belfast man gunned down overnight was the third victim this week in a feud among Protestant paramilitary groups that has brought British troops back onto the streets of Northern Ireland, officials said today.</p>
        <p>The police, who said they arrested six men after the killing and seized guns and ammunition, identified the latest victim as Samuel Rocket, 22. He was shot by masked men who burst into the living room of his home in full view of his partner and a 12-month-old baby and opened fire ''several times at close range,'' a police spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The killing happened hours before the coffin of Bobby Mahood, 48, one of two men killed earlier this week, was carried aloft through the Shankill Road area of Belfast, a Protestant stronghold, followed by sobbing relatives and hundreds of others. The deaths stem from rivalries among  the Ulster Volunteer Force, with which the police said Mr. Rocket's family was associated, and two other, allied groups, the Ulster Defense Association and the Ulster Freedom Fighters.</p>
        <p>The police blamed the Ulster Volunteer Force for the killings of Mr. Mahood and a second man, Jackie Coulter. Mr. Coulter's funeral is set for Friday.</p>
        <p>While the loyalist groups are all part of the Protestant movement that wants Northern Ireland to remain a part of Britain, there is a wide perception that the rivalries are fueled by a battle for Belfast's illicit drug traffic.</p>
        <p>''Less and less does it have anything to do with political considerations,'' said Ken Maginnis, a spokesman for the dominant Protestant group, the Ulster Unionists.</p>
        <p>The latest killing came despite efforts by the British authorities to clamp down on paramilitary leaders. British troops were ordered onto the streets late on Monday after a weekend of violence culminating in the killings of Mr. Mahood and Mr. Coulter. On Tuesday, British officials ordered the rearrest of Johnny Adair, a paramilitary leader linked to the Ulster Defense Association, who had been released last September under a form of parole set out by the province's peace agreement. The agreement permits the authorities to rearrest people they regard as instigators of violence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adair had served five and a half years of a 16-year term on terrorism charges. His supporters said today he planned to appeal his new arrest.</p>
        <p>British officials have said they do not regard this week's bloodshed as signifying the breakdown of the cease-fire underpinning the 1998 peace agreement. But politicians on both sides of the sectarian divide said today that rising levels of violence could jeopardize the fragile, broader peace between Catholics and Protestants.</p>
        <p>''The history of the north is that when these dynamics are unleashed within loyalism, the Catholic community ends up carrying the brunt of it,'' said Mitchel McLaughlin, chairman of Sinn Fein, the political voice of the Irish Republican Army.</p>
        <p>And Chris McGimpsey, an Ulster Unionist leader, said, ''This could completely destabilize the whole peace process.''</p>
        <p>Protestant leaders also said they were concerned that the violence could increase further as the rival militias seek reprisals. ''Once these funerals are over I would be fearful that there would be more attempts to equalize'' the tally of killings, said Mr. Maginnis of the Ulster Unionists.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
