<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Seeking a Victory, the Giants Will Not Press</title>
    <meta content="25GIAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/sports/25gian.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D91531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Seeking a Victory, the Giants Will Not Press</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants are 0-3 in preseason, but Coach Jim Fassel will not go to extraordinary means to defeat Baltimore Ravens in final preseason game; he will not play his starters after first quarter, because he is more concerned about protecting them from injury; in recent years, preseason records for Giants have not accurately predicted team's fortunes in regular season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the Giants have not gone without a victory in the preseason since the 1971 team went 0-6, Giants Coach Jim Fassel, whose team is 0-3, will not go to extraordinary means to defeat the Baltimore Ravens tonight in the final preseason game.</p>
        <p>Fassel will not play his starters after the first quarter, because he is more concerned about protecting them from injury. He will not throw his starters back in the game late in the fourth quarter at Giants Stadium to save a lead. And he will not trot out his newest formations or trick plays to enliven the offense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although the Giants have not gone without a victory in the preseason since the 1971 team went 0-6, Giants Coach Jim Fassel, whose team is 0-3, will not go to extraordinary means to defeat the Baltimore Ravens tonight in the final preseason game.</p>
        <p>Fassel will not play his starters after the first quarter, because he is more concerned about protecting them from injury. He will not throw his starters back in the game late in the fourth quarter at Giants Stadium to save a lead. And he will not trot out his newest formations or trick plays to enliven the offense.</p>
        <p>Fassel said he would not even kick an extra point after a touchdown to tie the score, should it come down to that in the final minutes. He would go for the 2-point conversion -- not just to try to win the game, but mostly to avoid putting his team through an overtime period.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, I'd go for 2,'' Fassel said. ''No overtime. The fact that we're 0-3 has no bearing on my decisions or how I use any player in this game. I've got to focus on Sept. 3, when the games begin to count.''</p>
        <p>It is interesting to note that the 1971 team did win its opening regular-season game, 42-40, against Green Bay. It then lost 10 of the next 13 games.</p>
        <p>Losing preseason records for the Giants have not accurately predicted the team's fortunes in the regular season. In the last 50 seasons, the Giants have lost more than they have won in the preseason 19 times, but the team then had a losing record in the regular season only nine times.</p>
        <p>Successful preseason records can be equally misleading. The 1973 team was 6-0 in the preseason, then went 2-12 when the games counted.</p>
        <p>''I want to win, don't get me wrong,'' said Fassel, who has been 1-3 in the preseason twice previously and was 2-2 last year. ''I want to see the first units play crisply. I want to see us eliminate the penalties we committed against the Jets. I want to see a great many things. But I want to get to the regular season without any more injuries, too.''</p>
        <p>Fassel's concern for the health of his club is well grounded. The Giants' lack of depth is alarming. This week in practice they moved the rookie defensive tackle Cornelius Griffin to defensive end to get him some experience at the position. Griffin will still play defensive tackle in a rotation with Keith Hamilton and Christian Peter, but the Giants could need help at end, too. So Griffin, the team's second-round pick this year, is now the principal backup at all four positions on the defensive line.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the lineup, Fassel will have to decide on a backup fullback for the starter Greg Comella, who was himself the backup last season. Craig Walendy is the favorite to win that job.</p>
        <p>Although the starters will play not much more than the first quarter, the Giants will hope that Mike Barrow, the new middle linebacker, looks more comfortable in his second preseason game than he did in his first game last week against the Jets. Left cornerback Dave Thomas also had a dreadful game, and he will be watched closely for progress.</p>
        <p>The Giants will be playing tonight without free safety Shaun Williams, who has resumed practicing on a limited basis after spraining his big toe last month. Williams hopes to play in the regular-season opener against Arizona on Sept. 3. He would be an important addition to a secondary that has looked disjointed, even if it is unlikely that Williams could be at his best after sitting out practice for a month.</p>
        <p>Williams has never started a National Football League game. But then neither has his replacement, Lyle West, who is smaller and less athletically gifted.</p>
        <p>Pete Mitchell, the pass-catching tight end, will also miss tonight's game and will not return until at least the Giants' second game on Sept. 10. His replacement, Dan Campbell, has also been out with a hamstring strain.</p>
        <p>While the Giants have squandered two first-half leads in the preseason, the Ravens have won their last 11 preseason games. Baltimore, which has been led by quarterback Tony Banks and linebacker Ray Lewis, is 3-0 this preseason.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
