<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Strongly Defends His Record as Chief of Halliburton</title>
    <meta content="Y25CHE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/national/25CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Halliburton Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D61531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Strongly Defends His Record as Chief of Halliburton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>CENTRAL POINT, Ore., Aug. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Cheney vehemently defends his work for Halliburton oil services company, bristling at suggestion he was less than successful as its chief executive; reiterates that he will not allow his retirement package to pose conflict of interest; photo; Cheney calls New York Times article on subject 'bad journalism' (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney vehemently defended his work in the oil services business today, bristling at any suggestion that he was less than successful as the chief executive of Halliburton and insisting once more that as vice president he would take steps to ensure his retirement package does not pose a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>''We went from being a second-tier, second-rank energy services company to being the biggest in the world,'' Mr. Cheney told reporters today. He complained that a front-page article in The New York Times today that characterized his record at Halliburton as mixed was ''a distortion,'' ''bad journalism'' and ''seriously flawed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney vehemently defended his work in the oil services business today, bristling at any suggestion that he was less than successful as the chief executive of Halliburton and insisting once more that as vice president he would take steps to ensure his retirement package does not pose a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>''We went from being a second-tier, second-rank energy services company to being the biggest in the world,'' Mr. Cheney told reporters today. He complained that a front-page article in The New York Times today that characterized his record at Halliburton as mixed was ''a distortion,'' ''bad journalism'' and ''seriously flawed.''</p>
        <p>''By any measure you want to use, Halliburton has been a great success story over the last few years, contrary to what your colleagues at The New York Times reported,'' he said after addressing the Future Farmers of America here at Crater High School in southern Oregon.</p>
        <p>An examination of Mr. Cheney's work at Halliburton that was published in The Times today questioned the success of the company's merger with Dresser Industries, the biggest deal he made; found that while the company's stock rose, it still underperformed most stocks in the industry; and described serious problems with a subsidiary that builds roads.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney did not discuss the central point of the article, that executives at Dresser found after the merger that projects at Halliburton were much less healthy than they appeared to be on the company's books and were sustaining losses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's five years at the helm of Halliburton have drawn a great deal of attention -- and criticism -- since he was tapped by Gov. George W. Bush of Texas last month to be his running mate. Democrats ridiculed the Republicans as the big oil ticket, because Mr. Cheney and Mr. Bush worked in the oil industry in Texas. In addition, Halliburton offered Mr. Cheney a retirement package that, as currently structured, would leave him with stock options that are not scheduled to vest until 2001 or 2002 -- meaning that as vice president he would have a great personal interest in the price of oil.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, who had earlier declined to be interviewed for the article, criticized the prominence the article gave to the company's problems with road construction, saying that the work represented only a small part of Halliburton's business.</p>
        <p>He also sought to point out projects that he said the company completed successfully, like Enron Stadium in Houston, an oil platform that the company built for Exxon in the Gulf of Mexico, and a natural gas complex in Nigeria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney acknowledged that there had been problems with the highway projects and said that many of them were exacerbated after the company got out of the road building business. ''We basically made a decision on my watch to get out of the road building business, and what you see there is the residue,'' he said, adding that once the decision was made many experts in road building left.</p>
        <p>And he said that he would find a way to handle his retirement package so that it would not pose a conflict of interest if he should be elected vice president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's business dealings have become a campaign issue. When he was met by an enthusiastic crowd at the grand opening of the new headquarters of the Kern County Republican Party in Bakersfield, Calif., a dozen protesters gathered across the street holding aloft signs that said ''Cheney Oil'' and ''Halliburton: $39 million.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
