<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harry Bronstein, 83, Official Who Widened Hiring by City</title>
    <meta content="Y25BRO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Obituaries; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Harry Bronstein</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronstein, Harry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pace, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDD1531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harry Bronstein, 83, Official Who Widened Hiring by City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pace, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harry Bronstein, veteran New York City official who was instrumental in changes that made it easier for women and members of minority groups to become police officers and sanitation workers, died on Aug 3 at age 83; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harry Bronstein, a veteran New York City official who was instrumental in changes that made it easier for women and members of minority groups to become police officers and sanitation workers, died on Aug. 3 in Los Angeles. He was 83 and lived in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronstein was the city's director of personnel and chairman of its Civil Service Commission from 1970 to 1974. He was assistant director of the budget when he was appointed to the personnel and Civil Service Commission posts by Mayor John V. Lindsay. He was reappointed in 1974 by Mr. Lindsay's successor, Abraham D. Beame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harry Bronstein, a veteran New York City official who was instrumental in changes that made it easier for women and members of minority groups to become police officers and sanitation workers, died on Aug. 3 in Los Angeles. He was 83 and lived in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronstein was the city's director of personnel and chairman of its Civil Service Commission from 1970 to 1974. He was assistant director of the budget when he was appointed to the personnel and Civil Service Commission posts by Mayor John V. Lindsay. He was reappointed in 1974 by Mr. Lindsay's successor, Abraham D. Beame.</p>
        <p>As Civil Service Commission chairman, Mr. Bronstein was one of the two key officials, the other being Police Commissioner Donald F. Cawley, who were involved in two changes in a Police Department qualifying examination that were announced late in 1973. The height requirement was dropped from the physical test and written test questions that were seen by some as culturally biased were screened out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronstein was also instrumental in creating a training program to prepare candidates, especially from minority groups, for the city's sanitation worker examinations.</p>
        <p>In 1974, Mr. Bronstein moved to a personnel post at the city's Health and Hospitals Corporation. In 1976, he moved to Los Angeles, where he was personnel director of Warner Communications for a time. He was born in East Harlem, grew up there and later attended Columbia University.</p>
        <p>In 1935, not long after graduating from high school, he entered city service as a $15-a-week clerk. He rose through the ranks to become chief budget examiner.</p>
        <p>In World War II, as an infantry sergeant, he took part in the Normandy invasion and received the Bronze Star.</p>
        <p>Surviving are his wife, Sylvia ; a daughter, Lynne Bronstein of Santa Monica, Calif.; a son, Elliot, of Los Angeles; and two sisters, Claire Raizner of Houston and Anne Fenton of Deerfield Beach, Fla.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
