<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Images of Tribal Africa, In a Hollywood Style</title>
    <meta content="25JOHN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beckwith, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Angela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DE1731F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Images of Tribal Africa, In a Hollywood Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews Passages, exhibit of photogrphs of tribal Africa by Carol Beckwith and Angela Fisher at Brooklyn Museum of Art; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Passages,'' at the Brooklyn Museum of Art, is like a giant walk-in issue of National Geographic magazine: it is entertaining, titillating and, in places, thrilling, but as art and anthropology it is egregious kitsch.</p>
        <p>Busy, crowded and noisy, the show consists primarily of 95 colorful photographs -- ranging in size from big to mural scale -- depicting tribal people from all parts of Africa wearing traditional costumes and doing traditional activities like dancing, courting, marrying, decorating their bodies, tending children, conducting funerals and so on. Several video monitors also show short films of dances and ceremonies, and a smattering of often stunning objects from the museum's African collections provides concrete references for some of the photographs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Passages,'' at the Brooklyn Museum of Art, is like a giant walk-in issue of National Geographic magazine: it is entertaining, titillating and, in places, thrilling, but as art and anthropology it is egregious kitsch.</p>
        <p>Busy, crowded and noisy, the show consists primarily of 95 colorful photographs -- ranging in size from big to mural scale -- depicting tribal people from all parts of Africa wearing traditional costumes and doing traditional activities like dancing, courting, marrying, decorating their bodies, tending children, conducting funerals and so on. Several video monitors also show short films of dances and ceremonies, and a smattering of often stunning objects from the museum's African collections provides concrete references for some of the photographs.</p>
        <p>The photographs and videos, all of high commercial quality, were produced collaboratively by two white Westerner photographers: Carol Beckwith, an American, and Angela Fisher, an Australian. The two women have known each other since 1978, and together and separately they have traveled into some of the most remote regions of Africa seeking out tribes whose traditions continue to flourish, apparently unaffected by outside influences.</p>
        <p>Viewed simply as transparent windows onto other worlds, the pictures are undeniably fascinating. One set of images shows what appear to be women dancing shoulder to shoulder, their faces bearing otherworldly, weirdly erotic makeup. In a video, they puff out their cheeks, grin bizarrely and roll their eyes as if possessed. The facts, as related by a museum label, are stranger: these are men of the Wodaabe tribe participating in a beauty contest by which they hope to win wives.</p>
        <p>Other photographs and videos show wonderful acrobatic dancers of the Bobo tribe in hairy, vividly colored full-body masks or naked Surma warriors fighting with six-foot poles in another courtship contest. But many photographs are captivating simply for the beauty of jewelry and costumes that they display, as in the sumptuous beadwork adorning the head, neck and shoulders of a young Masai bride.</p>
        <p>And yet nothing about the show leads to anything more than a superficial acquaintance with the cultures under observation. This is infotainment; worse, it is ethnocentric infotainment. Viewing the show is like  watching a human ''Wild King-dom'': ''As the dance of the Paka mask becomes more ecstatic,'' reads the museum label, sounding like a television narrator, ''the vibrant fabric panels begin to fly around, turning the mask into a blur of color. The Yoruba believe that the breeze stirred up by the whirling dance of an Egungun mask brings security and the promise of good fortune to those close enough to feel it.''</p>
        <p>And in the old National Geographic tradition, there is more than a little soft-core pornography to keep one interested. The show is full of images of attractive seminaked bodies, including lots of nubile, bare-breasted females. The effect of all this is to turn people into exotic objects, obscuring their human complexity.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is the way the show is structured. It is divided into five sections: birth and initiation, marriage, seasonal rituals, wealth and royalty, and death. In each section, images from an assortment of tribes are presented, making a confusing collage. Had sections been devoted to one tribe at a time, a more coherent and possibly deeper picture of a particular culture might have emerged. It is strange, too, how completely the show shuts out the troubles of modern Africa: the effects of colonialism, tribal warfare and AIDS, to mention just three that are reported in newspapers almost every day.</p>
        <p>Ms. Beckwith and Ms. Fisher are entitled to focus on places unaffected by such problems, but the Africa they present looks too good to be true. It is like a sanitized, Hollywood-style paradise of beautiful, sexy and noble savages.</p>
        <p>It all might have felt more real had Ms. Beckwith and Ms. Fisher allowed their presences to be seen and felt in their work. As it is, neither woman ever appears before the camera, and the viewer remains mystified as to who is taking the picture and under what circumstances. This is a shame because the story of the photographer's adventures and their relations and experiences with the people they photographed are what one most wants to know about.</p>
        <p>Among the materials handed out by the museum press office are some pages bearing brief reminiscences by Ms. Beckwith and Ms. Fisher, including a laugh-out-loud story about the time they were respectfully asked by members of the Surma tribe to reveal their breasts. A wonderful book is crying out to be written.</p>
        <p>This removal of the artist-adventurers from the picture is what accounts, at least in part, for the objectifying effect. The camera becomes a disembodied, godlike eye, and the human relationship between the photographers and their subjects, who are almost never identified by name, is edited out. In fact, Ms. Beckwith and Ms. Fisher must have proceeded with great tact and sensitivity, not to mention bravery; they have befriended people all over Africa and they donate profits from their books to African charities.</p>
        <p>The failure here is less moral than imaginative: it is the failure to imagine a kind of photography -- or, perhaps, a combination of writing and photography -- that would really do justice to the complexly layered experience of their amazing journeys.</p>
        <p>''Passages: Photographs in Africa by Carol Beckwith and Angela Fisher'' is at the Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, through Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
