<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Epidemic Proving Fatal To Foxhounds</title>
    <meta content="25FOXH$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/25/science/25FOXH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Leishmaniasis (Disease)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Millbrook (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EEDF1231F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Epidemic Proving Fatal To Foxhounds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>MILLBROOK, N.Y., Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epidemic of leishmaniasis has killed 21 foxhounds in Millbrook, NY, and has also been detected in dozens of foxhounds from roughly 40 kennels in 20 states and Canada; parasitic disease has not been found in other kinds of dogs or animals, or in humans, for whom it can be fatal; offers another reminder of how once-exotic diseases, like West Nile virus, are no longer all that unusual as possible threats to public health; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For months, no one could figure out why the foxhounds here were suddenly dying.</p>
        <p>One after another, the fit and feisty hounds of the Millbrook Hunt became haggard and lethargic. They lost weight and patches of hair. They developed enlarged joints, crusty skin lesions and ropelike knots underneath their skin. In all, 21 dogs out of a group of about 120 died, and another 20 or so became ill.</p>
        <p>This spring, researchers at North Carolina State University identified the culprit: a strain of a parasitic disease called leishmaniasis, which is normally transmitted by  sand flies and has killed humans in other countries, but had rarely been diagnosed in the United States.</p>
        <p>But that was not the only surprise researchers eventually uncovered. Far from being limited to Millbrook, the disease has been detected in dozens of foxhounds from roughly 40 kennels in 20 states and Canada. And though none of those dogs have died, the outbreak caused the cancellation of all fox-hunting events around the country last spring.</p>
        <p>As the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention analyzes the situation, the good news is that leishmaniasis has not been found in other types of dogs or animals, or in humans. But there are still more questions than answers about how the disease got to this country, how it is transmitted and what may lie ahead, offering another reminder of how once-exotic diseases, like the West Nile virus, are no longer all that unusual as possible threats to public health.</p>
        <p>''Today's world is so much smaller than it used to be,'' said Richard Falco, a medical entomologist at the Louis Calder Center of Fordham University in Armonk, N.Y. ''We're at the point where the urban and rural collide. So when these exotic diseases arrive, we sort of have everything set up to have a public health problem, and we really have to be on guard.''</p>
        <p>There are several similarities between the West Nile virus and leishmaniasis (pronounced leash-men-EYE-a-sis). Both only recently became widespread in this country. Leishmaniasis is typically found in warmer, coastal areas in places like Brazil, the Mediterranean, India and the Sudan. If untreated, some strains of leishmaniasis can be fatal in humans; West Nile has killed seven people in the New York area in the last year. And sand flies, found only in the Southern United States, even look like tiny mosquitoes, albeit with a nastier sting.</p>
        <p>But while West Nile has been detected in mosquitoes, birds, animals and humans across the Northeast, leishmaniasis appears to have spread no further than the foxhounds. And in the process, it has unnerved the tight-knit world of fox-hunting, which reveres its traditions and treats its hounds as members of an extended family.</p>
        <p>This spring, the Masters of the Foxhounds Association, the sport's national governing body, canceled all fox-hunting events and urged kennels to quarantine leishmaniasis-positive dogs. Now, with the fox-hunting season set to begin in only a month or so, many fox hunters are hoping they can resume their activities.</p>
        <p>''We're being super-cautious, because nobody knows all the answers,'' said Col. Dennis Foster, the organization's executive director. ''If there's any question, we don't do it, that's our philosophy.''</p>
        <p>Here in rural Dutchess County, where hunting is so ingrained that the Millbrook Vineyards and Winery sells a table wine called Hunt Country Red, life began to take on an inexplicably cruel cast a year ago, when the foxhounds began to die.</p>
        <p>At first, the hunt and its veterinarians believed that a tick-borne disease was responsible -- a logical theory, given the prevalence of Lyme disease in the area. But after months of frustration, hunt officials sent two of their sickest dogs, Signal and Nelson, to the North Carolina State University College of Veterinary Medicine, which has done extensive research on tick-transmitted diseases.</p>
        <p>Signal and Nelson had to be euthanized. But their cases helped researchers pinpoint leishmaniasis as the unexpected villain.</p>
        <p>''This should not be in the U.S.,'' said Edward B. Breitschwerdt, professor of medicine and infectious diseases at North Carolina State. ''We're truly dealing with a foreign animal disease that remains very unclear to all of us still.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. Breitschwerdt's staff continued to work on molecular tests, aided by some donations from the hunt, the Centers for Disease Control stepped in, testing people who had come into contact with the foxhounds in Millbrook and collecting samples from all 10,000 or so foxhounds around the country.</p>
        <p>While 12 percent of the 9,000 hounds tested so far have shown some blood-test evidence of infection, only 1 percent have been confirmed as being infected, said Dr. Peter Schantz, a veterinarian and epidemiologist in the centers' division of parasitic diseases.</p>
        <p>There are two other strains of leishmaniasis: mucocutaneous, a rare form that affects the mouth and the genitals, and cutaneous, which affects the skin and has been reported in dogs along the Texas-Mexico border.</p>
        <p>But the strain humans are most susceptible to is visceral leishmaniasis, the disease affecting the foxhounds. It can be cured in humans, but not in dogs; with drug treatments, however, dogs can live with the malady.</p>
        <p>The disease probably arrived in this country when an American soldier returned from Europe or Northern Africa with an infected dog. In fact, leishmaniasis was diagnosed in several soldiers in the Persian Gulf war. (It is named for Sir William Leishman, an English military surgeon.)</p>
        <p>And since hunting groups often travel, many foxhounds, including the Millbrook group, may have picked up the disease while participating in hunts in Georgia, Virginia or other warmer climates with sand fly populations, Dr. Schantz said.</p>
        <p>Yet there has been no evidence of any sand flies as carriers -- prompting speculation that the hounds may have passed on the disease by biting or some other method. Moreover, the disease may not manifest itself until years later.</p>
        <p>''It's a potential public health problem,'' said Dr. Schantz. ''We are a very mobile universe right now. People come and go with their pets, and pets are well-known reservoirs of a number of diseases. So I think we're going to pick up these things regularly.''</p>
        <p>Why the disease has attacked only foxhounds is still a mystery. But veterinarians suggest a few possible factors: inbreeding, extensive travel and the dogs' aggressiveness, which causes them to bite one another. And though unlikely, it is also possible that a carrier like a mosquito could eventually add leishmaniasis to its portfolio of infectious diseases.</p>
        <p>''At this point in time, this is a dog disease, and it's an epidemic,'' Dr. Breitschwerdt said. ''But I know what the potential of this epidemic might be, both for the foxhounds and for the people, and that's weighed on me tremendously.''</p>
        <p>There is no evidence that dogs can transmit the disease directly to humans. But the potential risk has been enough to cause some animal rights advocates, who have long disliked the sport, to call for a moratorium on fox-hunting activities.</p>
        <p>''It would be selfish on the part of the fox hunters to continue with their recreational activity when there's even a slim chance that this might be a threat to humans, domestic pets or wildlife,'' said Michael A. Markarian, executive vice president of the Fund for Animals.</p>
        <p>But in the Millbrook area, the reaction has been much more subdued,  with most people interviewed saying that they had either heard nothing or little about the outbreak, or that it was low on the ever-expanding list of diseases and hazards.</p>
        <p>One businesswoman, Kathie Kessler, who owns Eclectic Designs, an interior and architectural design store, said that her dog, a Labrador retriever, had been sickened by a mysterious ailment for several months; the symptoms included weight loss, vomiting and enlarged joints.</p>
        <p>And though she counts several hunt members as clients and proudly displays a charcoal fox-hunting sketch in her showroom, she had not heard of the disease until a visitor asked about it. ''I'll mention this to my vet,'' she said earnestly.</p>
        <p>The hunt, meanwhile, has worked with local health authorities and sent letters to local landowners and members assuring them that the infected dogs, now quarantined, have been improving with drug treatment and that fox-hunting can resume as scheduled this fall. Even so, the ordeal has been difficult to handle.</p>
        <p>''The lowest point for us was when we didn't know what we had,'' said Farnham F. Collins, joint-master of the Millbrook Hunt. ''Since then, I don't think we're all celebrating, but at least we know what we're up against.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For months, no one could figure out why the foxhounds here were suddenly dying.</p>
        <p>One after another, the fit and feisty hounds of the Millbrook Hunt became haggard and lethargic. They lost weight and patches of hair. They developed enlarged joints, crusty skin lesions and ropelike knots underneath their skin. In all, 21 dogs out of a group of about 120 died, and another 20 or so became ill.</p>
        <p>This spring, researchers at North Carolina State University identified the culprit: a strain of a parasitic disease called leishmaniasis, which is normally transmitted by  sand flies and has killed humans in other countries, but had rarely been diagnosed in the United States.</p>
        <p>But that was not the only surprise researchers eventually uncovered. Far from being limited to Millbrook, the disease has been detected in dozens of foxhounds from roughly 40 kennels in 20 states and Canada. And though none of those dogs have died, the outbreak caused the cancellation of all fox-hunting events around the country last spring.</p>
        <p>As the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention analyzes the situation, the good news is that leishmaniasis has not been found in other types of dogs or animals, or in humans. But there are still more questions than answers about how the disease got to this country, how it is transmitted and what may lie ahead, offering another reminder of how once-exotic diseases, like the West Nile virus, are no longer all that unusual as possible threats to public health.</p>
        <p>''Today's world is so much smaller than it used to be,'' said Richard Falco, a medical entomologist at the Louis Calder Center of Fordham University in Armonk, N.Y. ''We're at the point where the urban and rural collide. So when these exotic diseases arrive, we sort of have everything set up to have a public health problem, and we really have to be on guard.''</p>
        <p>There are several similarities between the West Nile virus and leishmaniasis (pronounced leash-men-EYE-a-sis). Both only recently became widespread in this country. Leishmaniasis is typically found in warmer, coastal areas in places like Brazil, the Mediterranean, India and the Sudan. If untreated, some strains of leishmaniasis can be fatal in humans; West Nile has killed seven people in the New York area in the last year. And sand flies, found only in the Southern United States, even look like tiny mosquitoes, albeit with a nastier sting.</p>
        <p>But while West Nile has been detected in mosquitoes, birds, animals and humans across the Northeast, leishmaniasis appears to have spread no further than the foxhounds. And in the process, it has unnerved the tight-knit world of fox-hunting, which reveres its traditions and treats its hounds as members of an extended family.</p>
        <p>This spring, the Masters of the Foxhounds Association, the sport's national governing body, canceled all fox-hunting events and urged kennels to quarantine leishmaniasis-positive dogs. Now, with the fox-hunting season set to begin in only a month or so, many fox hunters are hoping they can resume their activities.</p>
        <p>''We're being super-cautious, because nobody knows all the answers,'' said Col. Dennis Foster, the organization's executive director. ''If there's any question, we don't do it, that's our philosophy.''</p>
        <p>Here in rural Dutchess County, where hunting is so ingrained that the Millbrook Vineyards and Winery sells a table wine called Hunt Country Red, life began to take on an inexplicably cruel cast a year ago, when the foxhounds began to die.</p>
        <p>At first, the hunt and its veterinarians believed that a tick-borne disease was responsible -- a logical theory, given the prevalence of Lyme disease in the area. But after months of frustration, hunt officials sent two of their sickest dogs, Signal and Nelson, to the North Carolina State University College of Veterinary Medicine, which has done extensive research on tick-transmitted diseases.</p>
        <p>Signal and Nelson had to be euthanized. But their cases helped researchers pinpoint leishmaniasis as the unexpected villain.</p>
        <p>''This should not be in the U.S.,'' said Edward B. Breitschwerdt, professor of medicine and infectious diseases at North Carolina State. ''We're truly dealing with a foreign animal disease that remains very unclear to all of us still.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. Breitschwerdt's staff continued to work on molecular tests, aided by some donations from the hunt, the Centers for Disease Control stepped in, testing people who had come into contact with the foxhounds in Millbrook and collecting samples from all 10,000 or so foxhounds around the country.</p>
        <p>While 12 percent of the 9,000 hounds tested so far have shown some blood-test evidence of infection, only 1 percent have been confirmed as being infected, said Dr. Peter Schantz, a veterinarian and epidemiologist in the centers' division of parasitic diseases.</p>
        <p>There are two other strains of leishmaniasis: mucocutaneous, a rare form that affects the mouth and the genitals, and cutaneous, which affects the skin and has been reported in dogs along the Texas-Mexico border.</p>
        <p>But the strain humans are most susceptible to is visceral leishmaniasis, the disease affecting the foxhounds. It can be cured in humans, but not in dogs; with drug treatments, however, dogs can live with the malady.</p>
        <p>The disease probably arrived in this country when an American soldier returned from Europe or Northern Africa with an infected dog. In fact, leishmaniasis was diagnosed in several soldiers in the Persian Gulf war. (It is named for Sir William Leishman, an English military surgeon.)</p>
        <p>And since hunting groups often travel, many foxhounds, including the Millbrook group, may have picked up the disease while participating in hunts in Georgia, Virginia or other warmer climates with sand fly populations, Dr. Schantz said.</p>
        <p>Yet there has been no evidence of any sand flies as carriers -- prompting speculation that the hounds may have passed on the disease by biting or some other method. Moreover, the disease may not manifest itself until years later.</p>
        <p>''It's a potential public health problem,'' said Dr. Schantz. ''We are a very mobile universe right now. People come and go with their pets, and pets are well-known reservoirs of a number of diseases. So I think we're going to pick up these things regularly.''</p>
        <p>Why the disease has attacked only foxhounds is still a mystery. But veterinarians suggest a few possible factors: inbreeding, extensive travel and the dogs' aggressiveness, which causes them to bite one another. And though unlikely, it is also possible that a carrier like a mosquito could eventually add leishmaniasis to its portfolio of infectious diseases.</p>
        <p>''At this point in time, this is a dog disease, and it's an epidemic,'' Dr. Breitschwerdt said. ''But I know what the potential of this epidemic might be, both for the foxhounds and for the people, and that's weighed on me tremendously.''</p>
        <p>There is no evidence that dogs can transmit the disease directly to humans. But the potential risk has been enough to cause some animal rights advocates, who have long disliked the sport, to call for a moratorium on fox-hunting activities.</p>
        <p>''It would be selfish on the part of the fox hunters to continue with their recreational activity when there's even a slim chance that this might be a threat to humans, domestic pets or wildlife,'' said Michael A. Markarian, executive vice president of the Fund for Animals.</p>
        <p>But in the Millbrook area, the reaction has been much more subdued,  with most people interviewed saying that they had either heard nothing or little about the outbreak, or that it was low on the ever-expanding list of diseases and hazards.</p>
        <p>One businesswoman, Kathie Kessler, who owns Eclectic Designs, an interior and architectural design store, said that her dog, a Labrador retriever, had been sickened by a mysterious ailment for several months; the symptoms included weight loss, vomiting and enlarged joints.</p>
        <p>And though she counts several hunt members as clients and proudly displays a charcoal fox-hunting sketch in her showroom, she had not heard of the disease until a visitor asked about it. ''I'll mention this to my vet,'' she said earnestly.</p>
        <p>The hunt, meanwhile, has worked with local health authorities and sent letters to local landowners and members assuring them that the infected dogs, now quarantined, have been improving with drug treatment and that fox-hunting can resume as scheduled this fall. Even so, the ordeal has been difficult to handle.</p>
        <p>''The lowest point for us was when we didn't know what we had,'' said Farnham F. Collins, joint-master of the Millbrook Hunt. ''Since then, I don't think we're all celebrating, but at least we know what we're up against.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
