<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire'</title>
    <meta content="MB234319" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jordan, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DF1231F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE KEHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Kehr reviews Kevin Jordan film Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Directed by Kevin Jordan  90 minutes; R</p>
        <p>Directed by the newcomer Kevin Jordan, ''Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire'' is a wistful little movie with big soulful eyes -- the cinematic equivalent of a puppy dog. This independent production, made on a thrifty $40,000 budget, is cute enough, but like a lot of puppy dogs it seems a little too desperate to be liked.</p>
        <p>The soulful eyes in question belong to the Martini brothers, Derick and Steven, who wrote the script with Mr. Jordan and star as Chris and Tony Remi, siblings with radically contrasting personalities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Directed by Kevin Jordan  90 minutes; R</p>
        <p>Directed by the newcomer Kevin Jordan, ''Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire'' is a wistful little movie with big soulful eyes -- the cinematic equivalent of a puppy dog. This independent production, made on a thrifty $40,000 budget, is cute enough, but like a lot of puppy dogs it seems a little too desperate to be liked.</p>
        <p>The soulful eyes in question belong to the Martini brothers, Derick and Steven, who wrote the script with Mr. Jordan and star as Chris and Tony Remi, siblings with radically contrasting personalities.</p>
        <p>Chris, the elder, is sober and responsible -- an accountant, inevitably -- whose fidgety temperament earned the nickname Goat on Fire from his grandmother, who was half Italian and half American Indian. Smiling Fish was grandma's name for Tony, a carefree would-be actor  who easily attracts women with his lazy charm and sees no particular need to settle down.</p>
        <p>They live together in happy male squalor in the Los Angeles house they inherited from their parents, passing their time with affectionate roughhousing. But providence soon provides them with two perfectly matched prospective mates.</p>
        <p>The jittery, retentive Chris becomes involved with Anna (Rosemarie Addeo), a voluptuous, open-hearted Italian beauty who works as an animal handler on film sets.</p>
        <p>Irresponsible Tony finds himself unexpectedly cast as a potential head of household when he falls in love with Kathy (Christa Miller), a single mom who has moved to Los Angeles in hopes of finding a movie career for her aggressively adorable daughter, Nicole (Heather Jae Marie).</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan's direction emphasizes big bear hugs and heart-to-heart conversations along with a few artificial crises to create a vague sense of suspense. His main asset is Bill Henderson, a veteran bit player who shines here in the somewhat stereotypical role of a wise, elderly black sound engineer who instructs Chris in the ways of love. It's left to Mr. Henderson to serve up the film's bromides about romance and destiny (real love comes along only once, so you'd better grab it), but he does his job with warmth and poise.</p>
        <p>Like so many other American independent films, ''Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire,'' which opens today at the Angelika Film Center (Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village), is a study in delayed development, in which helpless, childlike men in their late 20's are rescued and redeemed by domineering, motherly women. As romantic fantasies go, it's hard to imagine anything more regressive.</p>
        <p>''Smiling Fish and Goat on Fire'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes strong language and mild sex.</p>
        <p>DAVE KEHR</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
