<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hedge Fund Founder Charged With Defrauding Its Investors</title>
    <meta content="Y25HED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Manhattan Investment Fund Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Michael W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D91531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hedge Fund Founder Charged With Defrauding Its Investors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hedge Fund Founder Charged With Defrauding</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael W. Berger, a hedge fund manager, was charged yesterday with defrauding 300 people who invested about $575 million in his fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger was charged with securities fraud and fraud under the Investment Advisers Act. He pleaded not guilty and was released on bail of $75,000 cash and a $100,000 bond secured by his home in the Hamptons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael W. Berger, a hedge fund manager, was charged yesterday with defrauding 300 people who invested about $575 million in his fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger was charged with securities fraud and fraud under the Investment Advisers Act. He pleaded not guilty and was released on bail of $75,000 cash and a $100,000 bond secured by his home in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger, an Austrian citizen, was also required to surrender his passport. His attorney, Sara Mogulescu, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger, 28, was the manager of the Manhattan Investment Fund Ltd., which bet that Internet and high technology stocks would decline at a time that they rose.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors from the United States attorney's office in Manhattan said that Mr. Berger reported annual fund earnings as high as 27.4 percent in 1997, when his company lost about $400 million.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors charge that Mr. Berger hid the losses from investors and from auditors by creating fake financial records and passing them off as the fund's actual returns. When auditors from the accounting firm Deloitte &amp; Touche asked for additional records to confirm Mr. Berger's reports for 1999, prosecutors said, Mr. Berger fired them.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year the Securities and Exchange Commission sued Mr. Berger and his management company for overstating the fund's holdings and using misleading account statements to raise more than $350 million from investors since 1996.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. froze the assets of the fund and the court appointed a receiver to review the figures. Peter H. Bresnan, the S.E.C.'s assistant chief litigation counsel, said when the fund was frozen about $35 million remained. Some investors had removed about $140 million, leaving overall losses of about $400 million, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bresnan said that for the most part the fund did not attract small investors. ''These were institutions and high-net-worth individuals predominantly from outside the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>According to prosecutors, investors had to contribute at least $250,000 to participate in the fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger opened his hedge fund in August 1995, and began to market it overseas in April 1996. Prosecutors said that he marketed the fund by predicting downturns in certain areas of the stock market; for example, in a March 1998, letter to investors, Mr. Berger predicted that ''economic momentum should deteriorate.'' He said the most vulnerable sectors included the Internet, telecommunications and drugstores.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors charged that the strategy resulted in tremendous losses when the value of these stocks increased. But they said that Mr. Berger was able to conceal the growing losses, and continued to attract new investors, by falsifying the fund  records. According to prosecutors, the hedge fund maintained an account with Financial Asset Management, although the fund's assets were held by Bear Stearns Securities, which served as the clearing broker.</p>
        <p>Beginning in September 1996, prosecutors charged, Mr. Berger began to falsify statements that were passed along to investors by the fund administrators.</p>
        <p>According to the charges filed with the court, Mr. Berger used statements from Bear Stearns as a template, but changed the heading to Financial Asset Management. They said Mr. Berger altered the fake statements and sent them to the fund administrator. The administrator also received statements from Bear Stearns that accurately reflected the fund's performance, prosecutors said. But they said that Mr. Berger told the administrator to disregard the Bear Stearns statements because they only represented a small portion of the fund's actual holdings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger wrote a monthly letter to investors that the administrator distributed along with the statements. In his March 10, 1999, letter, prosecutors said, Mr. Berger spoke of his ''bearish outlook towards the market,'' and noted that although the market had hit a new high ''an exhaustion point has been reached.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said Mr. Berger used the same techniques to fool the fund's auditors. They said when auditors for Deloitte &amp; Touche requested more documentation, Mr. Berger fired them on Jan. 6 and the accounting firm withdrew its annual audit opinions for 1996 through 1998.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
