<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Chalk'</title>
    <meta content="MB234341" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nilsson, Rob</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chalk (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DF1231F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Chalk'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE KEHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Kehr reviews Rob Nilsson film Chalk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Directed by Rob Nilsson</p>
        <p>135 minutes; not rated</p>
        <p>Filmed in 1993 by the members of a San Francisco theater group for the homeless, ''Chalk'' may be more interesting for what it represents than for the disappointingly generic down-and-out tale it relates.</p>
        <p>The film is the work of Rob Nilsson, one of the originators of the contemporary American independent film. (His ''Northern Lights,'' made in Minnesota, dates from 1978.) In 1991 Mr. Nilsson moved into the Tenderloin district of San Francisco with the intention of writing a screenplay about the area's inhabitants. As part of his preparation he founded a free acting workshop, the Tenderloin Action Group, open to any resident of a San Francisco shelter. Although the original project never got off the ground, Mr. Nilsson discovered a number of promising performers and wrote ''Chalk'' with the help of his longtime collaborator, Don Bajema, around the talents of the nonprofessional actors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Directed by Rob Nilsson</p>
        <p>135 minutes; not rated</p>
        <p>Filmed in 1993 by the members of a San Francisco theater group for the homeless, ''Chalk'' may be more interesting for what it represents than for the disappointingly generic down-and-out tale it relates.</p>
        <p>The film is the work of Rob Nilsson, one of the originators of the contemporary American independent film. (His ''Northern Lights,'' made in Minnesota, dates from 1978.) In 1991 Mr. Nilsson moved into the Tenderloin district of San Francisco with the intention of writing a screenplay about the area's inhabitants. As part of his preparation he founded a free acting workshop, the Tenderloin Action Group, open to any resident of a San Francisco shelter. Although the original project never got off the ground, Mr. Nilsson discovered a number of promising performers and wrote ''Chalk'' with the help of his longtime collaborator, Don Bajema, around the talents of the nonprofessional actors.</p>
        <p>Most of the movie takes place in a harborfront pool hall called the Crab Tree -- actually a Bay Area warehouse fixed up by Mr. Nilsson and his crew -- where the wily, ailing owner, Earl Watson (Edwin Johnson), urges on the sibling rivalry between his unsuccessful son, Jones (Johnny Reese), who is half Korean and half black, and TC (Kelvin Han Yee, a professional actor), an Asian-American whom Watson took under his wing when he was a child and developed into a world-class pool hustler. Jones urges TC to take on the legendary pool shark Dorian James (played by the wiry Mr. Bajema) for a $10,000 bet, secretly hoping that his brother will lose and his father's affection will return to him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nilsson's affection for the work of John Cassavetes is apparent in every dark, smoky frame of ''Chalk,'' which strives to capture the grit and authenticity of Cassavetes's 1976 ''Killing of a Chinese Bookie.'' But Mr. Nilsson doesn't have his elder's sense of structure -- though they seem improvised, Cassavetes's films were actually tightly scripted and carefully composed -- and much of ''Chalk'' feels aimless and repetitive.</p>
        <p>A former shipyard worker who became a drifter after the death of his wife, Mr. Johnson is cool and convincing as Watson, a character who combines Don King and King Lear.</p>
        <p>But many of the other characterizations suffer from excessive sentimentality -- revelations of soft interiors beneath tough exteriors -- and the film finally fails to escape the conventions of the Hollywood cinema it so proudly deplores.</p>
        <p>Seven years after its making, ''Chalk'' still has not found a national distributor and is being released theater by theater by members of the Tenderloin Action Group. It opens today at the Two Boots Pioneer Theater, 155 East Third Street, in the East Village.</p>
        <p>DAVE KEHR</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
