<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="25PUBL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, O J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luce, Henry 3d</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">american tragedy (tv program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDA1531F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene of CBS miniseries on O J Simpson trial, American Tragedy, is videotaped in New York studio where Judge Jery Sheindlin presides over People's Court; photo...Henry Luce III addresses luncheon for this year's Luce Scholars, 20 people in their 20's who hav ebeen chosen for a year of living and working in Asia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anchors Revisit O. J. Simpson Trial</p>
        <p>The O. J. Simpson trials took place in California, but scenes from the CBS miniseries about the criminal trial were videotaped in New York yesterday, in the studio where JUDGE JERRY SHEINDLIN presides over ''The People's Court.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anchors Revisit O. J. Simpson Trial</p>
        <p>The O. J. Simpson trials took place in California, but scenes from the CBS miniseries about the criminal trial were videotaped in New York yesterday, in the studio where JUDGE JERRY SHEINDLIN presides over ''The People's Court.''</p>
        <p>''We were next door to Judge Jerry's dressing room,'' said RIKKI KLIEMAN, an anchor on Court TV who is playing herself in the miniseries and was videotaped with FRED GRAHAM, Court TV's senior anchor.</p>
        <p>But when the miniseries -- ''American Tragedy,'' based on LARRY SCHILLER'S book and starring CHRISTOPHER PLUMMER, VING RHAMES and DIANA LaMAR -- is broadcast, viewers will never know that Ms. Klieman and Mr. Graham were not in California: '' 'The People's Court' stuff was on the opposite side of the room,'' Ms. Klieman said. She and Mr. Graham sat in front of a green screen.</p>
        <p>''The background that will show up behind us is the courthouse and the appropriate trees, because we were at treetop height'' when they anchored Court TV's coverage of the Simpson trial.</p>
        <p>Ms. Klieman's wardrobe was authentic, though: she said that she wore the same navy blue suit and pearls that she wore on the day Mr. Simpson was acquitted of the murders of his former wife, Nicole Brown Simpson, and Ronald L. Goldman.</p>
        <p>Recreating their on-camera roles brought back memories. ''It's the only trial I've ever covered where I personally just got more depressed and despondent as it went on because of the damage it was doing to so many aspects of society,'' Mr. Graham said.</p>
        <p>Then, recalling his position in the 1970's as the legal affairs correspondent for CBS News, he added, ''It seems to be my fate that I'm associated publicly with two of the great villainies of our time, Watergate and now O. J. Simpson. The difference is in Watergate, you felt the process was cleansing the nation. The O. J. Simpson thing was just degrading.''</p>
        <p>'I'd Never Been To Angkor Wat'</p>
        <p>So the grandson of a Presbyterian missionary to China introduced the son of a Presbyterian missionary to China at a lunchtime gathering at the New-York Historical Society yesterday.</p>
        <p>The grandson was HENRY LUCE III, the chairman and chief executive of the Henry Luce Foundation (which is named for his father, a founder of Time magazine). The son was ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE J. STAPLETON ROY, a former United States ambassador to China who now heads the State Department's Bureau of Intelligence and Research.</p>
        <p>And the lunch? It was for this year's Luce Scholars, 20 people in their 20's who have been chosen for a year of living and working in Asia.</p>
        <p>But not all the talk was about Asia. When HELENE REDELL, the Luce Scholars program director, mentioned that she had to go to Princeton after the lunch, Mr. Luce smiled benignly.</p>
        <p>A woman standing nearby pointed out that Mr. Luce, who graduated from Yale, might be more excited about a trip to New Haven. ''New Haven is absolutely the world's garden spot,'' he said, grinning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Luce said he had spent the summer going to some of the places the Luce Scholars will soon be going -- the Philippines, Hong Kong and Cambodia. Isn't that like going home to him? ''I'd never been to Angkor Wat,'' he said, referring to the temple in the Khmer ruins in Cambodia. ''We've just made a big grant to establish a new Center for Khmer Studies, because after the genocide they have practically nobody trained in their own culture.'' In the Philippines, he introduced last year's scholars to LUISA LOI PIMENTEL-EJERCITO, the wife of the Philippine president. ''Then we had a great old photo op with the president, JOSEPH ESTRADA. Then I had a dinner party for 60, the 20 scholars and 40 others.''</p>
        <p>How did he find Hong Kong? ''Unchanged. Absolutely unchanged,'' Mr. Luce said, adding, ''You can't find the word China on a sign anywhere, even on the way from the airport.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
