<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fine Quilts Of Provence: Les Boutis</title>
    <meta content="25ANTI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quilts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cabanel, Andre-Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pique des Provence (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5D61431F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fine Quilts Of Provence: Les Boutis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Cabanel collection of 2,000 Provencal quilts, which are subject of book of essays Pique des Provence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like a good man, a great antique  quilt from Provence is hard to find.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, a French antiques dealer spotted a fine old quilt at a weekend market in Provence and tried to buy it -- just at the very moment another man reached for it. The dealer courteously yielded his claim. He told the man, ''You take it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like a good man, a great antique  quilt from Provence is hard to find.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, a French antiques dealer spotted a fine old quilt at a weekend market in Provence and tried to buy it -- just at the very moment another man reached for it. The dealer courteously yielded his claim. He told the man, ''You take it.''</p>
        <p>Surprised by the dealer's courtesy -- such antique French quilts are scarce -- the man invited the dealer for coffee and introduced himself: his name was Andre-Jean Cabanel,  and he was an olive farmer from Nimes. He invited the dealer to see his collection of antique quilts from Provence.</p>
        <p>When the dealer visited Mr. Cabanel, he was the one to be surprised.</p>
        <p>''The dealer told me it was the most incredible thing he'd ever seen,'' said Ross J. Francis as he finished recounting the meeting. Ms. Francis is the vice president for development at Brunschwig &amp; Fils, the American textile company that will reproduce some of the patterns from Mr. Cabanel's quilts in its fall 2001 collection.</p>
        <p>''He said the farmer's house was filled with antique armoires, each stuffed with Provencal quilts,'' Ms. Francis said. ''Evidently, Monsieur Cabanel's mother had restored old quilts and he had admired them when they were brought to the house when he was a boy. He never married and had been collecting them for 40 years.''</p>
        <p>None were for sale, but word of their quality soon spread. The Cabanel collection was exhibited this summer in Alsace, at the Museum of Printed Textiles in Mulhouse, which had spent the previous year and a half restoring them. In November the show moves to the Musee de la Toile de Jouy in Jouy-en-Josas, a town outside Paris near Versailles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cabanel's quilts are also the subject of a book, ''Pique de Provence'' (Edisud Publishers, 2000). One of the contributors to the book is a dealer based in Washington, Kathryn Berenson, author of ''Quilts of Provence'' (Henry Holt, 1996). Ms. Berenson helped to catalog Mr. Cabanel's collection of 2,000 quilts.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Cabanel is a passionate collector,'' she said. ''He even trades truffles for quilts.''</p>
        <p>There are two kinds of antique quilts from Provence and neither is like American antique quilts, which are pieced together from scraps. The Provence quilts tend to be made of two large pieces of whole cloth, either cotton or silk, that are sewn together with some kind of filling element, like batting or cording, sandwiched between them.</p>
        <p>''These quilts are intensely quilted and the quilting shows up because the background is often a neutral or solid color,'' said Laura Fisher, a Manhattan quilt dealer who owns Laura Fisher, at 1050 Second Avenue, at 55th Street.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher specializes in American quilts, but currently she has several 19th-century Provencal quilts for sale, at prices from $150 to $2,000 apiece. ''There was a strong needlework tradition in Provence,'' Ms. Fisher said. ''It's like a three-dimensional sculpture in thread.''</p>
        <p>Quilting goes back to prehistory. In medieval times quilted cloth was used as insulation in winter garments as well as armor, to protect its wearer from arrows.</p>
        <p>''What distinguished the work of Provencal needle women was their vision of the decorative possibilities inherent in these lines of stitching,'' Ms. Berenson writes in her book. ''They developed the ability to realize complex, minutely detailed patterns in beautiful, well-proportioned motifs merely through the play of light and shadow on the surface of a textile.'' Today, these quilts are often called ''boutis.''</p>
        <p>In the 18th and 19th centuries, Provencal women hand-stitched their quilted bed covers with motifs inspired by the bounty of the region: sunflowers, pomegranates, lavender, artichokes and olives in patterns that completely fill the ground of the quilt.</p>
        <p>''The French started printing imported cotton in about 1640,'' Ms. Berensen said. ''By the 1680's, the Marseilles women were producing 40,000 to 50,000 quilts a year for export to Germany, England, Italy and Spain.''</p>
        <p>She said that the Marseilles community was so proud of the women's workmanship that it gave the quilts as gifts to royalty and as tokens of  appreciation. The French called these quilts ''confections'' or ''broderies de Marseille'' and refer to the stitching as ''embroidery from within.''</p>
        <p>They should not be confused with pieces woven on machine-driven looms to obtain a textured character.</p>
        <p>The Manhattan gallery Cora Ginsburg, at 19 East 74th Street, has an exceptional bouti for sale at the moment. It is a 19th-century, all-white wedding quilt from Marseilles, with flower baskets, artichokes, butterflies, birds and grapes depicted on it. At 86 by 81 inches, it is also unusually large. ''It's a museum piece,'' said Titi Halle, the owner. The price is $35,000.</p>
        <p>Bagley Home, an antiques shop at 155 Main Street in Sag Harbor, N.Y., has a smaller white wedding bouti, with perfect stitching. ''It has high definition,'' Terry Bagley said. ''It's exquisite, lightweight and warm.'' The price is $800.</p>
        <p>The more common bouti is a quilt made from gaily colored printed cottons that are stitched in tight rows or diamond patterns. In the early 17th century, the cottons were imported from India and nicknamed ''Indiennes.'' They were hand-printed with colorful flowers, mythic animals, exotic locales and scenes.</p>
        <p>Louis XIV did not want the French to import luxury goods and drain the country's coffers, so he banned importation of Indiennes. But he instructed his minister Jean-Baptiste Colbert to import the best artisans and dyers to establish textile businesses in France.</p>
        <p>''They produced French tapestries, laces, cottons, wools and upholstery,'' said Ms. Berenson, who is writing a book on Colbert. ''Cardinal Mazarin is known to have had dozens of French quilted bed covers.''</p>
        <p>Finding antique Provencal boutis is not easy. Ms. Berenson may have the largest stock in the United States and can be reached by e-mail: kwberenson@aol.com. In France, one of the best sources is Michel Biehn, 7 rue des Quatre-Otages, L'Isle-sur-la-Sorgue, in Provence (011-33-4-90-20-89-04).</p>
        <p>For those who fear the effects of daily wear and tear on an antique bouti, there are now reproductions on the market. The store Rue de France in Newport, R.I., sells contemporary French bouti covered in a 19th-century-style cotton, which reverses from a subtle floral pattern to a blue and tan stripe. The queen size costs $695, and it can be machine washed and tumbled dried. Information: (800) 777-0998, or on the Web at www.ruedefrance.com.</p>
        <p>The contemporary ones are very pretty, but nothing looks as great as a bouti that has weathered 200 years of good Provencal living.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
