<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="25POP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D71431F936A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="5144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>* AC/DC, SLASH'S SNAKEPIT, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741. Going nowhere and proud of it, AC/DC turns arrested development into a vocation, insisting that men will be boys. Angus Young, dressed in his schoolboy knickers though he is in his mid-40's, runs around the stage as he peals out primal hard-rock guitar riffs; Brian Scott screeches about girls, booze and sin; and sooner or later there's a shower of sparks. Slash, the lead guitarist for Guns 'n' Roses, has had plenty of time between albums to start his own hard-rock band, Snakepit. Tonight at 8; tickets are $38 and $48 (Jon Pareles).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>* AC/DC, SLASH'S SNAKEPIT, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741. Going nowhere and proud of it, AC/DC turns arrested development into a vocation, insisting that men will be boys. Angus Young, dressed in his schoolboy knickers though he is in his mid-40's, runs around the stage as he peals out primal hard-rock guitar riffs; Brian Scott screeches about girls, booze and sin; and sooner or later there's a shower of sparks. Slash, the lead guitarist for Guns 'n' Roses, has had plenty of time between albums to start his own hard-rock band, Snakepit. Tonight at 8; tickets are $38 and $48 (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>PAUL ANKA, Westbury Music Fair, 960 Brush Hollow Road, Westbury, N.Y., (516) 334-0800. The Backstreet Boys, 'N Sync and the rest of the current teeny-pop idols can only dream of a career like that of Paul Anka, whose songwriting skill sustained him well past his years as a squeal target. From ''Puppy Love'' to ''(You're) Having My Baby'' to the words for ''My Way,'' he has self-satisfied songs for every phase of life. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; tickets are $40 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>THE BRONX HORNS, Josie Robertson Plaza, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5108. A top salsa band needs a horn section that can punch out riff after riff, then send soloists skyward. The Bronx Horns, led by Mitch Frohman, came from Tito Puente's band, and there's no better pedigree. Tomorrow at 5 p.m.; admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* CHICAGO UNDERGROUND DUO, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. From time to time the basic sound of this hot, earnest young jazz group (it's usually more than two people, but we'll see) has all the newness of the Art Ensemble of Chicago 30 years ago -- to both positive and negative effects. But there's a resourcefulness here: the players use cheap electronics well, they mine a lot from simple vamps, and the disciplined, versatile trumpeter Rob Mazurek may yet become something like the Dave Douglas of the Midwest. Tomorrow night at 9; tickets are $8 in advance; $10 day of show. (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* ANDREW CYRILLE AND BILLY HART, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. These two drummers are contemporaries who have had curious, hither-and-yon careers in the mainstream as well as the woolly outback of jazz. In a really good programming idea, they have joined forces for four nights, playing percussion duets for a first set and then hitching up with a saxophonist for the second set. I still haven't heard a two-drummer setup in jazz that didn't work, and this one could work especially well. And look at the caliber of the saxophonists they're inviting: tonight, Dave Liebman; tomorrow, David S. Ware; Sunday, Joe Lovano. Sets through Sunday night are at 8 and 10; admission is $12 with a one-drink minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* ORRIN EVANS TRIO, Up Over Jazz Cafe, 351 Flatbush Avenue, near Seventh Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 398-5413. This young pianist from Philadelphia has been one of the most pleasant developments of the last few years in jazz. He likes to surprise his audiences: mid-improvisation, he'll take a liking to one note or phrase and repeat it until it seems to change shape. Or he'll be playing free, and then, with the rest of the group, snap back into the rhythm and harmony of the tune in an instant. He's a grandstander, but he's also keenly interested in where a small jazz group can go together; and his bassist Reid Anderson, and drummer, Nasheet Waits, are among the best in the business right now. Sets are tonight and tomorrow night at 9, 10:30 and midnight; cover charge is $15 a set (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>JON FADDIS QUINTET, Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080. It's not too often that Mr. Faddis, who leads the Carnegie Hall Jazz Band, steps out with his own groups anymore. He is one of the most seasoned players of his generation -- the one that emerged in the 70's. Stay out of his trumpet's line of fire, though, when he's heading for one of his atom-smashing high notes. His band this weekend includes the great saxophonist Jimmy Heath. Sets are tonight and tomorrow night at 9 and 11; cover charge is $25 plus a $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>GOGOL BORDELLO, YURI YUNAKOV, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, at the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700. Gypsy music, with its whiplash melodies and dizzying speed, adapts to New York City in this double bill. The saxophonist Yuri Yunakov was part of Bulgaria's most celebrated and ferocious wedding band, led by Ivo Papasov, until government harassment of Gypsy culture impelled him to emigrate. He has assembled American and Bulgarian musicians to play the breakneck, zigzagging, odd-meter dance tunes that used to keep parties going all night long. Gogol Bordello, led by a Ukrainian singer, Eugene Hutz, calls itself a Gypsy punk band, and Mr. Hutz doubles as a disc jockey between sets. Tomorrow night at 9; tickets are $12 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>DON HENLEY, Jones Beach Theater, Meadowbrook Parkway South, Wantagh, Long Island, (516) 221-1000. The beloved icon of uptight baby boomers brings his career-spanning set to the beach. Expect emotional new ballads about his recent marriage, some unfortunate reworkings of old Eagles hits and, of course, ''Boys of Summer.'' Tomorrow night at 8; tickets are $35 to $75 (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>J&amp;R MUSIC WORLD DOWNTOWN JAZZ FEST, City Hall Park, (212) 238-6305. Today's bill, which starts at 5 p.m., includes Jeff Golub, Leo Gandelman and Carla Cook, and closes with the redoubtable Joe Lovano, a tenor saxophonist who is one of the most generous improvisers of our time. Tomorrow's concert, beginning at 1 p.m., includes Soul Conversation, with J. K. and Mark Whitfield, and is headlined by Herbie Hancock, whose band has lately been terrific doing subversions of George Gershwin pieces. The concerts are free (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* AMEL LARRIEUX, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800. After singing with Groove Theory, Amel Larrieux released a superb debut album this year. She is a high-minded pop-soul songwriter, singing about ambition and integrity; the album floats her supple, girlish voice among twinkling starscapes of electric piano and phantom choruses of herself overdubbed. Onstage, she'll have to transform the songs from private studio musings to public pronouncements, and here's betting she will. Tonight at 9; tickets are $25 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* HUGH MASEKELA, EDDIE PALMIERI, Damrosch Park, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5108. Jazz gets an international infusion in this double bill. The South African flugelhornist Hugh Masekela has more to offer than his international hit ''Grazing in the Grass.'' For decades he has brought together the three-chord lope of South African pop with the zigzagging possibilities of jazz, and tunes like ''Stimela (Coal Train)'' suggest both the hard work and the innate dignity of South Africa's laborers. Latin pianists have a longstanding affinity for jazz, but Eddie Palmieri may well be the jazziest and most experimental of them all, plunging into modal harmonies and burly, splashing chord clusters, building suspense and then detonating it with rhythm. Tonight at 8; admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* MINGUS MAXIMUS, Lincoln Center Out of Doors Festival, Damrosch Park, (212) 875-5108. This double bill combines two sides of the Mingus repertory: the Mingus Big Band, which in its long-running engagement at the Fez has specialized in that great bassist's roustabout blues and workshoplike pieces, and the newer Mingus Orchestra, currently in weekly residence at the City Hall restaurant in TriBeCa, which dedicates itself to Mingus's more intricate, composerly pieces. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; free (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>JAMES MOODY QUARTET, Iridium, 48 West 63rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 582-2121. Mr. Moody is one of the stealth weapons of his generation in jazz. At this point you expect uncomplicated nostalgia, or at least a brave staying of the course, from a man who played on some of the most important bebop sessions of the 1940's. But his playing remains superb, and his career a wild affair: he's as comfortable cracking jokes and playing the showman as going head to head with imposing young players like Mark Turner, as he did in a memorable album a few years ago. Sets through Sunday night are at 8:45 and 10:45, with a 12:15 set tomorrow night; cover charge is $30, plus $10 minimum; $25 with $10 minimum on Sunday (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>JOHNNY PACHECO, Austin J. Tobin Plaza, World Trade Center, (212) 435-4170. The flutist and band leader Johnny Pacheco was born in the Dominican Republic but he fell in love with Afro-Cuban music early. He has been a prime mover in New York Latin music since the 1960's, when he helped start Fania Records; he went on to lead the Fania All-Stars, the band that defined New York salsa. His band can play courtly charangas or hard-driving mambos; luckily, there's room to dance. Tonight from 6 to 9; admission is free (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* CHARLIE PARKER JAZZ FESTIVAL, Marcus Garvey Park, 122nd Street and Mount Morris Park West, Harlem; Tompkins Square Park, Seventh Street and Avenue A, Lower East Side, (718) 786-1379. One of New York's reliably pleasant summer events has multiplied: in addition to the usual free concert near Charlie Parker's erstwhile Lower East Side apartment, there's one uptown. Both concerts are dedicated to two of jazz's guardian angels who died since last year's festival: Parker's widow, Doris, and the exemplary blues player and vibraphonist Milt Jackson. Tomorrow's show in Marcus Garvey Park includes the percussionist Bobby Sanabria with his Latin-jazz band Asencion; the marvelous singer Irene Reid's quartet; the drummer Winard Harper's band; David Glasser's Quartet, with Clark Terry as a guest; and finally the Lou Donaldson Quartet. Sunday's show in Tompkins Square Park opens with the young vibraphonist Stefon Harris and his quartet; the pianist Joanne Brackeen's trio; the singer Miles Griffith's quartet; Sphere, sparked by Kenny Barron and Gary Bartz; and finally James Moody's quartet with the trumpeter Jon Faddis as a guest. Both concerts are free and run from 2 to 7 p.m., rain or shine (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>D.J. ALEX PATTERSON, IMMERSION, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. When he's not creating pulsating, consonant ambient music as the Orb, Alex Patterson returns to his old job spinning other people's recordings (and probably a few of his own) as a disc jockey. He shares the bill with Immersion, the dance-music project of Colin Newman, the guitarist and singer from Wire, and his wife, Malka Spiegel, formerly of Minimal Compact. Tonight at 10. Admission is $14 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* PEDRO THE LION, IDA, T. W. WALSH, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3055. Most underground rock bands would cringe at being called uplifting; the word conjures images of saccharine, clean-cut choristers. It fits the artists sharing this bill, though, and they are clean-cut. But not saccharine. Pedro the Lion is David Bazan, a quietly devout son of a minister who pens small passion plays, and whoever he is working with at the moment. Ida is a New York-based quartet whose music delicately explores intimate profundities. T. W. Walsh is a Boston-based singer and songwriter with a handle on transcendence. Sunday night at 9; tickets are $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* DAVID RUDDER, S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, SoHo, (212) 243-4940. David Rudder is one of Trinidad's most important modern calypsonians. As his lyrics insist on the depth and importance of Trinidad's African heritage, his music follows through, drawing on ancient Afro-Trinidadian drumming along with the latest pan-Caribbean grooves, including touches of reggae. Tonight at midnight; admission is $22 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>PHAROAH SANDERS QUARTET, Sweet Basil, 88 Seventh Avenue South, above Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 242-1785. Mr. Sanders makes an awesome bellowing tone through his tenor saxophone, as he has done since the mid-60s, when he started appearing on John Coltrane records. Turned on at the right moment, it's beautiful: the sound of a musician going into overdrive. Afro-mysticism, jazz ballads, dance rhythms with tablas -- it's all an elaborate frame for his massive sound. Sets through Sunday night are at 9 and 11, with a 12:30 set tonight and tomorrow night; cover charge is $25 plus $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* SUMMER POP SPLASH, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, at the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700. Sweet melodies, ringing guitar chords, voices lifted toward heaven -- all the things that make pop sing will be present in abundance this evening, courtesy of some of the finest pop craftspeople New York has produced. Amy Rigby returns from her Nashville sojourn with material from her upcoming album, ''Sugar Moon.'' Richard Barone plays a set of his winsome songs, as does his former Bongos mate James Mastro in the Health and Happiness Show. Richard Lloyd adds his rougher-edged, righteous rock to complete the bill.Tonight at 9; admission is $12 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* CLARK TERRY QUINTET, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037. Playing with the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra on July 4, Mr. Terry played some fluegelhorn improvisations on Louis Armstrong material that were relaxed, swinging, purposeful and absolutely lovely -- the kind of solos you hope will be recorded and studied. After Basie, Ellington, lots of studio work and years of traveling around the world as a bandleader, he is a hard-core professional, with a sense of humor that gets him through any difficulties. But when he's on, he's really on. Sets through Sunday night are at 9:30 and 11:30. Admission: $20 plus $10 minimum; $15 plus $10 minimum on Sunday. (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>LUTHER VANDROSS, BOYZ II MEN, PNC Bank Arts Center, Garden State Parkway, Exit 116, Holmdel, N.J., (201) 507-8900. The ushers had better stock up on smelling salts for this loveman double whammy. Mr. Vandross has charmed the ladies (and impressed plenty of men) for two decades now, and he is as important as a songwriter and producer as he is as a Romeo. Boyz II Men are a generation younger, but they, too, are old hands at passing out flowers and winning hearts through harmonizing. Sunday night at 7. Tickets: $20.25 to $65.25 (Powers).</p>
        <p>MIKE VIOLA, RASPUTINA, PETE DONNELLY, Fez, 380 Lafayette Street, at Great Jones Street, East Village, (212) 533-2680. Lovers of top-notch New York bands will have to choose, tonight, between this show and the one at the Bowery Ballroom; both make an excellent case for the Big Apple's musical superiority. True, Pete Donnelly is from the Boston-based Figgs, but he also plays in the Candy Butchers, the ensemble Mike Viola assembled to play his pristine, Marshall Crenshaw-style pop. Rasputina is an only-in-New-York sort of band: three cellists making gothic pop. Two members of Rasputina have changed, so this is a chance to see how that affects its unique sound. Tonight at 8; tickets are $10, plus two-drink minimum (Powers).</p>
        <p>WARM-UP 2000, P.S. 1, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084. The clever folks at this groovy art museum have figured out a way to beat the lack of heat this summer: they had the design team called SHoP install an ''urban beach,'' complete with wading pools and deck chairs, where crowds can gather to hear D.J.'s instead of the screaming kiddies and tanning studs one encounters in the Rockaways. Giant Step sponsors this weekend's music, which probably means it will be smooth and funky. Featured artists include Nickodemus, Alton Miller and Ron Trent. Tomorrow at 3 p.m.; admission is $4; $2 for students (Powers).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
