<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Medical Fun Lost, Alas, In a Shuffle</title>
    <meta content="19ESSA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/science/19ESSA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuger, Abigail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Essay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DC173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Medical Fun Lost, Alas, In a Shuffle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABIGAIL ZUGER, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuger, Abigail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abigail Zuger Essay says 'fun' element in a doctor's practice is vanishing in era of reduced budgets and managed care (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let a doctor of a certain age talk long enough and you're bound to hear the gloomy pronouncement that medicine just isn't as much fun as it used to be.</p>
        <p>People often make the understandable mistake of assuming that ''fun'' in this context is simply an irritating code word for the money, autonomy and adulation doctors enjoyed before the managed care era. After all, how could continuous immersion in the worry and suffering of others ever create actual, literal fun?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let a doctor of a certain age talk long enough and you're bound to hear the gloomy pronouncement that medicine just isn't as much fun as it used to be.</p>
        <p>People often make the understandable mistake of assuming that ''fun'' in this context is simply an irritating code word for the money, autonomy and adulation doctors enjoyed before the managed care era. After all, how could continuous immersion in the worry and suffering of others ever create actual, literal fun?</p>
        <p>But in fact, it always has, from the moment the first Neanderthal medic popped a dislocated shoulder back into joint and smiled at a job well done.</p>
        <p>The fun of medicine is entirely distinct from the deeper rewards of easing pain and the like. These pleasures persist as always, cloaked though they are in paperwork, and reimbursable at ever less per year.</p>
        <p>What has gone missing is much less exalted stuff, experiences more on the order of winning at solitaire or acing the windmill in miniature golf. Medical fun is the fun of recognizing weird colors and interesting noises, of interpreting subtle diagnostic clues, of tapping on a patient's abdomen and hearing exactly the kind of thump you were expecting.</p>
        <p>They are little, almost childish pleasures, but when enough of them are erased they leave a big void.</p>
        <p>Picking up a heart murmur when you listen to a chest is fun. Suddenly, there it is: thump-whoosh, thump-whoosh, the blood telling you in a stage whisper that it is going through an abnormal valve, and what are you going to do about it?</p>
        <p>You can get the same information from a cardiologist's report, or an echocardiogram, of course, but hearing it with your own ears is a lot more fun.</p>
        <p>At least, so it was until occupational safety caught up with us all. For me to hear any but the loudest murmurs in my office now, I would have to bribe the hospital engineers to turn off a ventilation system that runs with such force the tissues tremble on the desk. Little whispers from the heart are no match for the hum of those fans -- which are, of course, operating entirely for my own good, ridding the air of particles like the germs that cause tuberculosis. So instead of hearing murmurs now, I read reports.</p>
        <p>Watching someone's skin turn colors at the flick of a switch is also fun. Most cases of ordinary ringworm fluoresce under ultraviolet light, and in the old days we would greet an itchy patient, darken the room, click on the black light and watch all those little round red spots glow bright green. Even the patient had a good time.</p>
        <p>But the dictates of the bottom line cut those portable ultraviolet lights out of most budgets long ago. Only dermatologists and podiatrists still have a few -- when they have time to use them. Otherwise they, like the rest of us, look at flaky skin and write prescriptions in sober black and white.</p>
        <p>My patient Donna crawled into the office recently with a fever and a wet, rattling cough. A chest X-ray showed she had pneumonia.</p>
        <p>When the sputum of someone with pneumonia is stained and examined under a microscope, the germs put on a mesmerizing perp walk. Some show up as tiny scarlet commas, others as plump pink globes. Some move in disorganized clumps, like tourists lost on Fifth Avenue; others glide by in elegant whorls, like fish in the sea. Still others, severely monogamous, waltz around in dignified purple pairs.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years ago I would have headed back to the microscope that was a fixture in every medical office with a sample of Donna's sputum to get a first-hand view of what was making her so sick.</p>
        <p>But thanks to a 1988 federal law called the Clinical Laboratory Improvement Act, anyone who uses a microscope for patient care must be a fully certified laboratory technician, and most doctors don't meet that criterion. So there aren't any microscopes in my office any more.</p>
        <p>It is hard to argue with the merits of this law, enacted to protect patients from misdiagnosis by sloppy labs. That it screened out us committed germ-watchers in the process was just one of those unfortunate things.</p>
        <p>So Donna's sputum went by messenger to a certified lab, where a certified technician examined it under a certified microscope and, later, an official piece of blue paper showed up on my desk.</p>
        <p>Donna did just fine. But for me, it was a little like being strong-armed out of a movie theater by the feds 15 minutes before the end of the show. Yes, they sent me a synopsis of the plot a few days later. Yes, all the necessary information was right there in my hand. But that doesn't mean I can't complain.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
