<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford and Another Tire Maker Facing New S.U.V. Problems</title>
    <meta content="19FORD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/19FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Continental Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DC143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford and Another Tire Maker Facing New S.U.V. Problems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co and Continental AG are preparing to replace Continental tires on 40,000 Lincoln Navigator full-size sport utility vehicles; plan to present information on problems associated with tires to regulators at National Highway Traffic Safety Administration at meeting in Washington, DC; Bridgestone Corp will reshuffle Firestone's management and will increase its line of bank credit (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as Firestone and Ford struggle to recall millions of defective tires on Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles, the Ford Motor Company and another tire maker, Continental A.G., are preparing to replace another brand of tire on 40,000 Lincoln Navigator full-size sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Continental and the Lincoln division of Ford said in a joint statement this evening that they planned to present information on problems associated with the tires to regulators at the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration at a meeting in Washington on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as Firestone and Ford struggle to recall millions of defective tires on Ford Explorer sport utility vehicles, the Ford Motor Company and another tire maker, Continental A.G., are preparing to replace another brand of tire on 40,000 Lincoln Navigator full-size sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Continental and the Lincoln division of Ford said in a joint statement this evening that they planned to present information on problems associated with the tires to regulators at the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration at a meeting in Washington on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The companies declined to make the information available tonight, but said in their statement that ''it is appropriate to point out that the information the companies will share with N.H.T.S.A. includes no reports of serious accidents, fatalities or serious injuries.''</p>
        <p>Katharina Konowalski, a Continental spokeswoman, said that the tiremaker planned to announce a ''customer satisfaction'' program, but not a recall, to replace the tires. ''It's not a safety-related issue,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But a person close to the Ford effort on the issue said that the automaker and Continental would discuss with regulators whether to call the tire replacement a recall. The tires have sometimes lost portions of their treads, and this has produced an above-average rate of property damage claims as well as requests by consumers to replace the tires under warranty, the person said.</p>
        <p>In another sign of the tire issues' spreading effects, Firestone's parent, the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, said that it would reshuffle Firestone's management and would increase its line of bank credit.</p>
        <p>The replacement of Continental tires is certain to increase regulators' scrutiny of other brands of tires as well. While tire makers have long blamed customer neglect or abuse for tire failure, and have said some tires inevitably fail, Firestone's admission last week that it ''made bad tires'' appears to have opened the floodgates for lawsuits and regulatory action against other companies.</p>
        <p>The tires involved are the 16-inch ContiTrac AS tires, which were installed on half the Navigators in the 1998 and 1999 model years, which were the first two model years for the $45,000 luxury sport utility. Lincoln offered 17-inch tires as an option on the Navigator in these two model years, then made the 17-inch tires standard equipment beginning in the 2000 model year. The 17-inch tires are not being replaced.</p>
        <p>The far larger recall of Firestone tires, to which 88 deaths have been linked, involves the smaller of two sizes of tires installed on Ford Explorers. Bridgestone/Firestone is recalling 15-inch tires in that case, but not 16-inch tires. Smaller tires can carry less weight than larger tires of the same pressure, so they are subject to more strain when mounted on large, heavy sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Ford's recommendation that the Explorer tires be inflated to 26 pounds per square inch has been criticized by some lawmakers and personal injury lawyers as insufficient. But the recommended pressure for the 16-inch tires on the Navigator is 30 pounds for the front tires and 35 pounds for the rear tires. Higher pressure tires can carry more weight.</p>
        <p>Ford documents given to Congressional investigators two weeks ago, which were quickly distributed to reporters, included a memorandum from Ford's Middle Eastern units more than a year ago warning that Continental tires on Lincoln Navigators there had sometimes failed. Another document in that collection showed that Ford had installed high-speed tires on its cars for sale in Saudi Arabia, but had not done so for its sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks sold there. By contrast, General Motors installs high-speed tires on all vehicles sold there, because the heat and fast driving there are a harsh combination for tires.</p>
        <p>Regulators opened a review last March of 47 million Firestone tires;  they have not endorsed Firestone's decision to recall only 14.4 million of these tires, of which 6.5 million are still believed to be in use. Also under review are 16-inch Firestone Wilderness tires for Ford Explorers and Ford Expeditions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
