<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Johnson, Feeling Scorned, Responds by Flaunting It</title>
    <meta content="19GEOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/sports/19GEOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDE143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Johnson, Feeling Scorned, Responds by Flaunting It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas George Sports of The Times column on Tampa Bay Buccaneers wide receiver Keyshawn Johnson in view of upcoming game against New York Jets notes that he remains fixated on Jets because they traded him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keyshawn Johnson can tell you about the first call and the last one he made to the Jets about his eventual trade, about conversations before it and after it with his former teammates, about contract fallout and about Wayne Chrebet and Al Groh and the lowdown on who said what and who did what and why.</p>
        <p>The first thing that strikes, as you listen to Johnson at today's news conference, is that the memories are so fresh, as if all of this happened in the last 24 hours. His body may be here but his mind remains fixated on the Jets, the team that traded him. Snubbed him. A team that thought it was better off without him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Keyshawn Johnson can tell you about the first call and the last one he made to the Jets about his eventual trade, about conversations before it and after it with his former teammates, about contract fallout and about Wayne Chrebet and Al Groh and the lowdown on who said what and who did what and why.</p>
        <p>The first thing that strikes, as you listen to Johnson at today's news conference, is that the memories are so fresh, as if all of this happened in the last 24 hours. His body may be here but his mind remains fixated on the Jets, the team that traded him. Snubbed him. A team that thought it was better off without him.</p>
        <p>And that is the crux of why Johnson cannot let this thing go. He in some ways remains stunned. And hurt.</p>
        <p>When the Jets arrive here to play Johnson and Tampa Bay on Sunday, it will be a big game because both teams are 3-0. It is big because Tampa Bay is playing like a Super Bowl team and the Jets are surfacing as a Super Bowl sleeper. It is growing most in interest and in curiosity, though, because Johnson gets to face his old team.</p>
        <p>Pure theater.</p>
        <p>''This is considered a big-time game and according to my history, big-time players show up in big-time games,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>Oh, he will show. He promises that.</p>
        <p>''Good for them,'' Johnson said when asked about the Jets. ''They're coming in here 3-0 and that makes it that much more interesting. I wasn't looking ahead, but we all knew that this was there.''</p>
        <p>Before the game and after it, he also promises that he will not shake hands with Groh, the man Johnson believes pushed him aside.</p>
        <p>''The communication broke down,'' Johnson said. ''But I have always been a guy that respected people. Even if I don't like you or have something to say about you that isn't nice, I'll tell it to your face even though you might not like it. If you are the head football coach, you are not going to allow a player you want to be traded. I don't think Al Groh fought for me till the end. And when you make a decision like he did, he should have told me himself and he didn't.''</p>
        <p>And about Chrebet and Dedric Ward, the receivers filling his shoes and facing the Buccaneers' wicked defense, Johnson said: ''I don't have to send them a message. The message is in the film where they see our defense.''</p>
        <p>Pure theater.</p>
        <p>Keyshawn Johnson is quite comfortable, thank you, in the spotlight. Throughout his news conference he flashed that blinding smile, turned easily left and right to questioners, was animated and thoughtful and funny, too. His biggest laugh was gained when he talked about the reputation he believes the Jets now disperse of him, one of ''a guy that can't be controlled, this outrageous character, a player that raises hell in the locker room.''</p>
        <p>He was waving his arms and rolling his head when he said it.</p>
        <p>Pure theater.</p>
        <p>It is clear that the Jets pondered trading Johnson, backed off and then ran full steam ahead. It is clear that Groh thought his team was better off with the extra No. 1 picks gained rather than with Johnson. No matter how this trade was handled, Johnson would have still felt abused. There may never be closure for Johnson, but this game is a huge first step.</p>
        <p>It is peculiar how his place with the Jets became shaky for some of the same reasons that he has been appreciated here. The bravado, the showmanship, it is welcomed here. And there are two reasons why: The Buccaneers desperately needed an offensive identity, a go-to guy, and Johnson is that. Also, he produces and he works hard, and that is all that the Buccaneers' regime -- chiefly Coach Tony Dungy and General Manager Rich McKay -- requires.</p>
        <p>''I talked to people at Southern California that knew Keyshawn and people that knew him with the Jets, from John Robinson to Bill Parcells and Bill Belichick, and they all had high regard for Keyshawn as a player and a person; there was not one thing that was alarming from them,'' Dungy said. ''If a guy comes here and wants to win, then the other stuff is fine. Keyshawn came here with an understanding that everything we do has to help us win. He said that's why he's here. It is hard to be somewhere for four years and then up and leave. As a professional, being forced to leave, that sticks with someone who is proud.''</p>
        <p>Johnson is helping Tampa Bay's younger receivers. He is making big third-down plays. He is showing Tampa Bay all of the traits it desires.</p>
        <p>After Johnson's first season, when he wrote his controversial book, ''Just Give Me the Damn Ball,'' Parcells stormed into a meeting with his coaches. He was livid. He told them they were going to get rid of Johnson. But then Johnson produced a startling training camp and preseason, catching everything in sight, leaping high and making mercurial plays. Later Parcells told his offensive staff, ''Get him the ball on every pass play or you'll be fired!''</p>
        <p>That is the Keyshawn factor.</p>
        <p>Pure theater.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
