<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y19BRI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/world/19BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD9173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: OFFER TO VOTERS  The European Union, in a policy coordinated with the United States, offered to lift sanctions on Serbia and provide aid if a candidate opposing President Slobodan Milosevic wins elections scheduled for Sunday and is allowed to take office. In a ''message to the Serbian people'' issued in Brussels, the Europeans urged Serbs to use their vote against Mr. Milosevic. On Saturday American officials made a similar offer. Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>MONTENEGRO: MILOSEVIC AWAITED  President Slobodan Milosevic is expected to make a campaign visit to northern Montenegro tomorrow, said the Yugoslav prime minister, Momir Bulatovic. Mr. Bulatovic, left, heads the pro-Milosevic opposition party in Montenegro, whose government is urging its people to boycott the vote on Sunday and is edging toward independence from Serbia.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: OFFER TO VOTERS  The European Union, in a policy coordinated with the United States, offered to lift sanctions on Serbia and provide aid if a candidate opposing President Slobodan Milosevic wins elections scheduled for Sunday and is allowed to take office. In a ''message to the Serbian people'' issued in Brussels, the Europeans urged Serbs to use their vote against Mr. Milosevic. On Saturday American officials made a similar offer. Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>MONTENEGRO: MILOSEVIC AWAITED  President Slobodan Milosevic is expected to make a campaign visit to northern Montenegro tomorrow, said the Yugoslav prime minister, Momir Bulatovic. Mr. Bulatovic, left, heads the pro-Milosevic opposition party in Montenegro, whose government is urging its people to boycott the vote on Sunday and is edging toward independence from Serbia.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: THE DOT-COM CHANCELLOR  Chancellor Gerhard Schroder presented a 10-point plan to increase Internet use by Germans. ''We do not want to divide society into users and non-users,'' Mr. Schroder said. By next year, all schools and public libraries will be equipped with personal computers and free Internet access. From October employment offices will offer free basic Internet training to the jobless.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: FOREIGN AIDE TO QUIT  Foreign Minister Lloyd Axworthy announced that he plans to retire from politics, deciding not to run in elections expected for next spring. Mr. Axworthy, one of the last liberal members of Parliament from western Canada, made his mark by pushing for a global ban on antipersonnel land mines. Mr. Axworthy may stay on as foreign minister until the end of the year.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: ALCOHOL BAN LIFTED  Mexico City officials abolished a 77-year-old ''dry law'' that banned the sale of alcohol on national holidays. The decision was made after officials had tested the idea by suspending the law for the Independence Day celebrations last weekend. The general director of the city government, Francisco Garduno, said residents behaved adequately, proving that there was no need for the government to retain the law. But the ban remains for rest of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Ginger Thompson (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>RWANDA: WRITERS ON TRIAL  A United Nations court began a landmark trial of three Rwandan journalists accused of fanning the country's genocide, in which about 800,000 people died between April and June 1994. But defense lawyers questioned the impartiality of two of the three judges and called on them to stand down.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SUDAN: ABDUCTED YOUNGSTERS  Sudan has asked Canada and Egypt to mediate the release of 6,000 child soldiers kidnapped by Ugandan rebels. The appeal came Sunday in Winnipeg at the close of the International Conference on War-Affected Children, which was sponsored by Canada and Unicef. Canada announced that it would spend $700,000 to help reintegrate children into Ugandan society after they are freed from the rebel group, the Lord's Resistance Army.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDIA: KASHMIR CLASHES  At least 12 people, including 10 separatist guerrillas, were killed and 12 were wounded in the state of Jammu and Kashmir, police and defense officials said. Ten militants of the Laskar-e-Taiba militant group were killed in a clash with Indian security forces some 160 miles north of Jammu, the state's winter capital, a defense official said. In a separate incident, two security forces personnel were killed and two were wounded when suspected guerrillas lobbed a grenade in the Dalgate area of Srinagar.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: REBELS PURSUED  Government troops pursued Muslim rebels through jungles in the third day of an assault to rescue 19 hostages, but officials held back from saying all captives were safe. Some Abu Sayyaf rebels fled to the coastlines of Jolo Island in an attempt to escape, Gov. Abdusakur Tan said. The rebels are believed to have bought speedboats with some of the more than $15 million ransom they received from Libya and Malaysia for freeing other hostages. Some 5,000 villagers fled to the Jolo capital, Zamboanga.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: TOWN RECAPTURED  The military announced that it had recaptured Chavakachcheri, on the northern Jaffna Peninsula, from the separatist Tamil Tiger rebels in one of a series of offensives to reclaim territory that it lost in April. The rebels, who are fighting for a separate ethnic Tamil nation in the country's north and east, consider the Jaffna Peninsula part of the Tamil people's historic homelands.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>JORDAN: 6 TERRORISTS DOOMED  A military court sentenced six men to death for conspiring to carry out terror attacks against American and Jewish tourists during New Year's celebrations in Jordan. The three-man tribunal acquitted six others and handed down prison terms ranging from life to 7 1/2 years for the remaining 16 men. Four of those sentenced to death are still at large. The verdicts can be appealed.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>IRAN: APPEALS BY JEWS  A court will announce its decision by Thursday on appeals by 10 Jews convicted of spying for Israel, a judiciary official said. ''The judges of the appeals court will probably decide by Wednesday or Thursday at the latest,'' said Hossein-Ali Amiri, head of the justice department in the southern city of Shiraz.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
