<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>United Way Faces Crisis As President Plans to Leave</title>
    <meta content="Y19UNI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/national/19UNIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Way</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beene, Betty S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DE143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>United Way Faces Crisis As President Plans to Leave</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Betty S Beene resigs as president of United Way of America, which is grappling with its worst crisis since 1992, when former president was charged with stealing charitable funds (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Betty S. Beene resigned last night as president of the United Way of America as it grappled with its worst crisis since 1992, when a former president was found to be stealing charitable funds.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beene announced her resignation to the United Way of America's executive board as it met behind closed doors in Alexandria, Va., to deal with a power struggle with a number of large United Ways, including those in San Francisco, Chicago, Boston and Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Betty S. Beene resigned last night as president of the United Way of America as it grappled with its worst crisis since 1992, when a former president was found to be stealing charitable funds.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beene announced her resignation to the United Way of America's executive board as it met behind closed doors in Alexandria, Va., to deal with a power struggle with a number of large United Ways, including those in San Francisco, Chicago, Boston and Washington.</p>
        <p>The large local United Ways operate regional centers that process pledges made by workers at major corporations. Processing these payroll gifts, and doling out money to small United Ways as well as individual social service charities, enhanced their power.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beene had championed a national pledge-processing center, which would have undercut regional operations. But the national processing center, built by Cap Gemini Group, Europe's largest information technology consulting firm, failed in its first test last November.</p>
        <p>Partly as a result, Mrs. Beene said in June that she would leave her post in December 2001, a move she said was designed to ease friction and encourage support for higher standards among the local United Ways.</p>
        <p>In March, leaders of the large local United Ways had sought Mrs. Beene's ouster. But United Way of America directors, meeting in Chicago, unanimously supported her.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beene will now leave on Jan. 31, 11 months early.</p>
        <p>''I urge each of us to affirm that the United Way system is more than  the sum of its parts,'' Mrs. Beene wrote in an e-mail letter sent last night to local United Way leaders that was intended to heal the breach.  ''Our United Way system is a national treasure that can continually renew itself to build a stronger, healthier, more compassionate America, community by community.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Beene, 53, had sought to impose national standards on the 1,300 local United Ways that included requiring a rigorous and public self-examination of their effectiveness every few years. The move drew intense opposition from some local United Way organizations. Several of the big United Ways have been holding back part of their dues to the national organization. The United Way in Rochester, the nation's most prosperous, even obtained the legal right to alternative names, like the organization's former brand, the Community Chest, in the event the United Way broke up.</p>
        <p>Since 1987, the United Way movement has been losing market share as the number of its donors shrank by more than 20 percent. But since Mrs. Beene was appointed in January 1997, donations had begun to rise faster than the rate of inflation.</p>
        <p>For two decades, charity watchers have been raising questions about whether there is a future for the United Way.</p>
        <p>Under Mrs. Beene, the United Way had slowly been gaining ground following the 1992 scandal in which one of her predecessors, William V. Aramony, had stolen charitable funds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
