<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last-Minute Wisdom for a Condemned Man</title>
    <meta content="19DYIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/arts/19DYIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000920T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Signature Theater Co (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaines, Ernest J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Kent</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lesson Before Dying, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DC173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last-Minute Wisdom for a Condemned Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Signature Theater Company production of stage adaptation of Ernest J Gaines's novel A Lesson Before Dying, at Peter Norton Space; Kent Anderson directs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the title suggests, ''A Lesson Before Dying,'' the 1993 novel by Ernest J. Gaines, is a peculiar combination of potent drama and tear-jerker. The story of a self-loathing schoolteacher, sent by his grandmother to counsel an unjustly convicted young man on death row, it is rife with prosaic sentimentality. The human dignity that the teacher seeks to instill in the prisoner and the pride of purpose that the teacher himself needs to learn are grandiose pursuits set in a race against time.</p>
        <p>But because it takes place in rural Louisiana in 1948, the cruel realities of the Jim Crow South give the novel its weight. And the inevitability of the execution gives the story a powerful, lumbering momentum. The waiting becomes excruciating, a slowly tightening noose for everyone: the hapless convict, the teacher, the entire black community and even the white jailers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the title suggests, ''A Lesson Before Dying,'' the 1993 novel by Ernest J. Gaines, is a peculiar combination of potent drama and tear-jerker. The story of a self-loathing schoolteacher, sent by his grandmother to counsel an unjustly convicted young man on death row, it is rife with prosaic sentimentality. The human dignity that the teacher seeks to instill in the prisoner and the pride of purpose that the teacher himself needs to learn are grandiose pursuits set in a race against time.</p>
        <p>But because it takes place in rural Louisiana in 1948, the cruel realities of the Jim Crow South give the novel its weight. And the inevitability of the execution gives the story a powerful, lumbering momentum. The waiting becomes excruciating, a slowly tightening noose for everyone: the hapless convict, the teacher, the entire black community and even the white jailers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaines's novel achieves this escalating sense of desperation through the observant narration of the teacher, Grant Wiggins, whose own paralysis is communicated by the emotional restraint of his language. This is a problem on the stage, where thoughts need to be spoken aloud, and Romulus Linney's adaptation of the novel, the opening production of the Signature Theater Company's 10th-anniversary season, hasn't tried to solve it. Necessarily, perhaps, the narrative here is pushed along not by rumination but by character interaction, the dialogue rife with exposition and pointed lessons.</p>
        <p>As directed by Kent Anderson, artistic director of the Alabama Shakespeare Festival, which commissioned the work and presented it this year, it's a baldly forthright production with its emotions on its sleeve, preachy against injustice and on behalf of human dignity. It isn't subtle, but then it isn't supposed to be; this is old-fashioned melodrama. Played on Marjorie Bradley Kellogg's unintrusive but effective set, a jailhouse storeroom, with the outside world -- escape -- depicted by looming blackboards and rudimentary lessons chalked on them, the production is propelled by the undeniable power of the circumstances. This results in a show that clunks a bit, like a jalopy with a flat tire, but it's a jalopy that's rolling downhill, with irresistible momentum and a cathartic explosion at the bottom.</p>
        <p>In the novel Grant is the sole representative of intellectual sophistication, and he's left to bounce off the simpler desires of the other characters. These include Jefferson, the prisoner, a barely literate former student so beaten by poverty and bigotry that he is resigned to his lot; Emma Glenn, a Wiggins family friend and Jefferson's godmother, who wants him to die with dignity and to reject the belief that he is the ''hog'' he was called during his trial; the Rev. Moses Ambrose, who wants Jefferson to accept God before he dies; and Grant's girlfriend, Vivian, who wants Grant to take pride in his place among his own people and not indulge his desire for the two of them to simply run off for a life somewhere else.</p>
        <p>Grant's eventual acceptance of the legitimacy of their desires constitutes his own journey, and in the novel it's an interior struggle. He's coping with his disdain for their inarticulate natures, their stubborn clinging to the limits of their experience.</p>
        <p>Onstage, a crisis that is solely internal inhibits drama -- a character in conflict needs resistance to be expressed -- and both the playwright and the director have pushed the secondary characters to higher levels of will and articulation. This is both effective and not; it deprives the play of Grant's subliminal ache, but it does add thunder.</p>
        <p>Jefferson, in particular, is nearly silent in the novel but becomes, very quickly, an engaged persona onstage. Jamahl Marsh gives a composed and appealing performance as the doomed man, but he's never the pathetic character of Mr. Gaines's novel. He isn't raised up to a pride that he has never had so much as he is restored to it.</p>
        <p>Ambrose, seen by Grant for most of the novel as an uneducated and feckless true believer, is here a formidable blunderbuss from the start, played with a bullying anger by John Henry Redwood. In the novel Emma  is the very emblem of indignantly stiff spine. Mr. Linney's version makes her feisty, and Beatrice Winde's portrayal gives her a cool wit to express her impatience and inner rage.</p>
        <p>In one of Mr. Linney's more interesting departures from the novel, he gives Grant's speech about why Emma wants him to help Jefferson to Vivian. Vivian is the play's most problematic role because she is made into its conscience. Tracey A. Leigh seems a bit unreal in it -- she plays Vivian as a woman without uncertainty -- but she does have pronouncements to make, righteous behavior to embody.</p>
        <p>As delivered by Grant in the novel, this crucial speech defines his own pain, his own bitterness at having to be courageous in the face of the black man's burden. In the play it is delivered to him, a bit changed in language but not meaning, as a lesson, a theme. What does Miss Emma want him to impart to Jefferson?</p>
        <p>''To be able to stand up to the white man. For her. That's the real reason she wants Jefferson to walk to that chair. Because if he doesn't, she will never live to see a black man stand up for her, or me, or any woman. That's what that old lady you think is a fool wants. Men standing up for her.''</p>
        <p>The key to the performance of Isiah Whitlock Jr., who plays Grant, is that he must respond to this speech rather than make it. His acting is full of indications of passionate distress -- the tight rein on his body language in the presence of the white sheriff, the voice of a preacher that rises to a tremolo when pleading with Jefferson or arguing with Ambrose -- but his inner turmoil is buried by the argumentative stance-taking of the script. His best moments come when he's alone onstage, addressing his students; in those clipped monologues he conveys both the discipline he wants to impart to them and his despairing fear that it will make no difference in their lives.</p>
        <p>Still, there is that powerful inevitability as the show draws to a close. In a quietly vivid final scene, melodrama most wisely exploited, Grant receives the news of Jefferson's electrocution as he stands at his classroom lectern. Behind him, at center stage, Jefferson himself sits erect  and composed in the electric chair. The final words of the novel, as Grant prepares to explain to his students what happened, are ''I was crying.'' Onstage, on opening night, Mr. Whitlock was. So were many in the audience.</p>
        <p>A LESSON BEFORE DYING</p>
        <p>By Romulus Linney, based on the novel by Ernest J. Gaines; directed by Kent Thompson. Sets by Marjorie Bradley Kellogg; costumes by Alvin B. Perry; lighting by Jane Cox; original music composed by Chic Street Man; sound by Don Tindall; production stage manager, Francys Olivia Burch; director of development, Kathryn M. Lipuma; general manager, Karalee Dawn; production manager, Bill Kneissl; director of marketing, Rick Berube; literary manager, Beth Whitaker. Presented by the Signature Theater Company, James Houghton, founding artistic director; Bruce E. Whitacre, managing director, in association with the Alabama Shakespeare Festival. At the Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: Beatrice Winde (Emma Glenn), Aaron Harpold (Paul Bonin), Isiah Whitlock Jr. (Grant Wiggins), Stephen Bradbury (Sam Guidry), Jamahl Marsh (Jefferson), Tracey A. Leigh (Vivian Baptiste) and John Henry Redwood (Rev. Moses Ambrose).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW  Correction:  September 20, 2000, Wednesday  A theater review yesterday about ''A Lesson Before Dying,'' by Romulus Linney, at the Signature Theater Company, misstated the surname of the play's director. As noted in the credits, he is Kent Thompson, not Anderson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 20, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A theater review yesterday about ''A Lesson Before Dying,'' by Romulus Linney, at the Signature Theater Company, misstated the surname of the play's director. As noted in the credits, he is Kent Thompson, not Anderson.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
