<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Is Unsettled After 4 Recent Killings of Staff Workers</title>
    <meta content="19NATI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/world/19NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guinea</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guinea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Guinea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Is Unsettled After 4 Recent Killings of Staff Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Killing in Guinea of fourth UN refugee worker in less than two weeks prompts agency's high commissioner for refugees to reassess how best to safeguard staff members worldwide who come to aid of refugees trapped in vortex of war, violence and chaos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The killing of a fourth United Nations refugee worker in less than two weeks is prompting the United Nations high commissioner for refugees to reassess how best to safeguard staff members worldwide who come to the aid of refugees trapped in the vortex of war, violence and chaos.</p>
        <p>The latest victim, Mensah Kpognon, a Togolese who directed the refugee agency's office in Macenta in southeastern Guinea, was killed on Sunday by unidentified attackers who tried to rob him first. His colleague, Sapeu Laurence Djeya, from Ivory Coast, was abducted and remains missing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The killing of a fourth United Nations refugee worker in less than two weeks is prompting the United Nations high commissioner for refugees to reassess how best to safeguard staff members worldwide who come to the aid of refugees trapped in the vortex of war, violence and chaos.</p>
        <p>The latest victim, Mensah Kpognon, a Togolese who directed the refugee agency's office in Macenta in southeastern Guinea, was killed on Sunday by unidentified attackers who tried to rob him first. His colleague, Sapeu Laurence Djeya, from Ivory Coast, was abducted and remains missing.</p>
        <p>The United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, said in a statement today that he was shocked by Mr. Kpognon's killing. Mr. Annan appealed to West African leaders to do whatever they could to secure Ms. Djeya's release.</p>
        <p>The high commissioner for refugees, Sadako Ogata, was in Herat, Afghanistan, when she learned of the attack. ''Why are innocent, unarmed humanitarians like Mensah Kpognon -- a father of four children who was simply trying to make the world a better place -- being struck down in the most brutal way?'' she said in a statement released here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kpognon, 50, had worked for the United Nations refugee agency since 1994. He held a master's degree in urban and regional planning from the University of Iowa.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 6, three United Nations refugee workers -- one from Puerto Rico, one from Ethiopia and one from Croatia -- were killed in their office in West Timor by rioters suspected of belonging to a militia opposed to independence for neighboring East Timor. The United Nations has since withdrawn its staff from West Timor, where 120,000 refugees from the eastern part of the island remain in camps.</p>
        <p>Now, following Mr. Kpognon's killing and the abduction of Ms. Djeya, the refugee agency began scaling back operations in Guinea, where 460,000 refugees, most of them from Sierra Leone and Liberia, are living. The agency's nonessential employees were told to stay home, and dependents of international workers were being evacuated to Guinea's capital, Conakry.</p>
        <p>''These killings over the last two weeks are going to prompt an overall review of security worldwide,'' Ron Redmond, the refugee agency's spokesman, said by telephone from its Geneva headquarters.</p>
        <p>Since 1992, 50 internationally recruited civilians and 148 local employees of the United Nations have been killed in line of duty. Thirty of those, including Mr. Kpognon, worked for the refugee agency.</p>
        <p>Of the 198 fatalities, 21 were caused by aircraft accidents, 107 by gunshot wounds and 16 by bombings, land mines and other malicious acts. Another 52 died in ethnic violence in Rwanda and Burundi, and 2 were killed during a hostage episode.</p>
        <p>Nicolas Bwakira, the director of the refugee agency's liaison office to United Nations headquarters, said about 80 civilians have been killed in Guinea, where tensions have risen between the government and refugees camped on its soil.</p>
        <p>Liberia has insisted that Guinea is giving refuge to rebels who have been fighting the Liberian government forces since July.</p>
        <p>The United Nations high commissioner for refugees has 5,000 staff members assisting 22.3 million refugees and displaced persons in 120 countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
