<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders See Daylight Down the Road</title>
    <meta content="19ISLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/sports/19ISLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goring, Butch</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D8173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders See Daylight Down the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders Coach Butch Goring expresses hope that team will make playoffs for first time since 1994 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in years, the Islanders can realistically talk about making the playoffs without eliciting giggles.</p>
        <p>Indeed, when Coach Butch Goring took his place upstairs next to General Manager Mike Milbury during preseason games against the Philadelphia Flyers last week, the discussions were not just centered on evaluating the young players but also included talk of implementing changes that could propel the team into the postseason for the first time since 1994.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time in years, the Islanders can realistically talk about making the playoffs without eliciting giggles.</p>
        <p>Indeed, when Coach Butch Goring took his place upstairs next to General Manager Mike Milbury during preseason games against the Philadelphia Flyers last week, the discussions were not just centered on evaluating the young players but also included talk of implementing changes that could propel the team into the postseason for the first time since 1994.</p>
        <p>For that to happen, Goring said, there would have to be some major changes, not the least of which centers on the power play.</p>
        <p>Last season, in winning only 24 games, the Islanders were 23rd over all in the National Hockey League, scoring 45 times in 320 power-play situations, a mere 14.7 percent.</p>
        <p>There is no chance for success unless the special teams improve, said Goring, whose team was 25th over all in short-handed situations, allowing 84 goals while scoring 8 in 420 situations.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the playoff teams they were all among the top 16,'' Goring said. ''We need to get in that area if we're going to succeed.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders showed some improvement through the latter part of last season, specifically going 3 for 5 against Toronto on the power play March 20; it marked the first time since Nov. 28, 1998 that the team had scored three power-play goals in a single game. They also scored three short-handed goals March 2 against Ottawa.</p>
        <p>Grafted onto that unit this year is Roman Hamrlik, a two-time All-Star, Garry Galley and Kevin Haller.</p>
        <p>On the down side, the Islanders were not able to replace Josh Green, who was traded, for another left-handed forward. That leaves the team rife with right-handed forwards and left-handed defensemen.</p>
        <p>''The power play is giving us some headaches because of that,'' Goring said, but added, ''We were really pleased with the power play the last one and a half months of the season.''</p>
        <p>The addition of Hamrlik, Galley and Haller should do a lot more than energize the power play.</p>
        <p>With Haller being teamed with Kenny Jonsson, Hamrlik with the 6-foot-9-inch Zdeno Chara and Galley with Eric Cairns in yesterday's practice, the Islanders' defense could actually be a unit to be reckoned with.</p>
        <p>How much of a force will be determined over the next four exhibition games, beginning with tomorrow night's lone home preseason game, against the defending Stanley Cup champion Devils.</p>
        <p>''I don't associate any negativity with the first two games,'' Goring said, referring to losses to the Flyers by 4-2 and 2-1. ''Over the next four I have an opportunity to sit up and watch. There's been such a dramatic change in the defense from last year. I have a fair idea who's going to stay but there's a couple of spots were looking at.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
