<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fidelity With Country Twang and Disco</title>
    <meta content="19MCGR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/arts/19MCGR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Faith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgraw, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DC173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fidelity With Country Twang and Disco</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews concert by country singers Faith Lee and Tim McGraw at Madison Square Garden; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al and Tipper Gore's big kiss at the Democratic National Convention isn't the latest public display of affection by a well-known couple from Tennessee. They're being outdone by Tim McGraw and Faith Hill, the married, multimillion-selling pop-country singers whose shared tour came to Madison Square Garden on Saturday night. Each sang an hourlong solo set; then, after a video about their marriage and children, they returned to share duets and clinches. Their image of lusty fidelity, translated into songs, is just what suburban America -- or at least the program directors of country radio stations -- wants to hear.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGraw and Ms. Hill follow the paths of the top 1990's country blockbusters, Garth Brooks and Shania Twain, while diluting their mild rebelliousness. Unlike their models, they grew up in the South -- Mr. McGraw in Louisiana, Ms. Hill in Mississippi -- before heading for Nashville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al and Tipper Gore's big kiss at the Democratic National Convention isn't the latest public display of affection by a well-known couple from Tennessee. They're being outdone by Tim McGraw and Faith Hill, the married, multimillion-selling pop-country singers whose shared tour came to Madison Square Garden on Saturday night. Each sang an hourlong solo set; then, after a video about their marriage and children, they returned to share duets and clinches. Their image of lusty fidelity, translated into songs, is just what suburban America -- or at least the program directors of country radio stations -- wants to hear.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGraw and Ms. Hill follow the paths of the top 1990's country blockbusters, Garth Brooks and Shania Twain, while diluting their mild rebelliousness. Unlike their models, they grew up in the South -- Mr. McGraw in Louisiana, Ms. Hill in Mississippi -- before heading for Nashville.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGraw puts country-style vocals, tight and twangy, into tunes that add a down-home veneer to 1970's rock. Jim Croce, Elton John, Bruce Springsteen and the Rolling Stones (via John Mellencamp) are at the center of the music; now and then, Mr. McGraw sings with a George Jones slide. In his songs, written by Nashville professionals, Mr. McGraw plays the nice guy who hit the road and had some fun before settling down. When he recalled young lust, the band shifted into Louisiana rhythm-and-blues.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGraw didn't sing his stereotype-slinging hit, ''Indian Outlaw''; it played just before he arrived onstage. He now prefers songs that present him as the most loyal man on earth. He never forgets his first crush. He sees the small-town girl he left behind everywhere he goes. He goes crazy when his woman walks out. He's so devoted that he tells the woman who left him that he could get to like her new boyfriend. (By contrast, Mr. Brooks busts up her wedding in ''Friends in Low Places.'') He'd clearly rather be a lover than a fighter, and the women who filled the audience whooped their approval.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hill, like Ms. Twain, showed off her navel and kept old-fashioned country music at arm's length. Her set was introduced with a thumping disco remix of ''This Kiss''; she wore psychedelic-patterned stretch pants. Ms. Hill has just about given up subtlety in her singing, emoting for the balcony soon after a song starts. She has shifted her vocal style from the country-tinged delivery of her first albums to a loose, throaty kind of rock belting, midway between Cher and Ms. Twain, that stands up to the power-ballad crescendo of her hit ''Breathe.'' Her video clip for the song, shown as she performed it, has her lolling around a bed like the clothed portion of a Playmate pictorial.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hill's songs repeatedly declared her love and passion -- ''red hot and no blues'' -- above music that had more power chords than steel-guitar glides. Like other pop divas, she brought on a gospel choir for one song. A few selections admitted that love doesn't always turn out happily ever after: the taunting ''What's in It for Me'' and ''It Matters to Me,'' which confronts a man who has turned cold. Yet even in those songs she was ready to be a loving helpmate as soon as her man made a few concessions.</p>
        <p>The closing McGraw-Hill duets seesawed between the marital bliss of ''It's Your Love'' and the new ''Let Me Love You'' (which may be country's first Santana-style bolero) and the bitterness of a man leaving his family because his wife has turned ''Angry All the Time.'' For the finale, after all the professions of lifelong passion, the couple returned to 1970's rock for Fleetwood Mac's definitive breakup song, ''Go Your Own Way.'' Then the couple promenaded around the stage, embracing at left, right and center for all to see.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
