<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="19DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DF143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oil Prices Approach $37 On Iraq-Kuwait Tension  Oil prices surged to their highest levels in a decade on fears that rising tensions between Iraq and Kuwait would disrupt the flow of crude oil from the Persian Gulf at a time when petroleum supplies are extremely tight.</p>
        <p>In New York, the price of crude oil for October delivery increased 96 cents, or 2.7 percent, to $36.88 a barrel, the steepest price for oil since the Persian Gulf war. In London, the price of Brent crude oil for delivery in November also reached a 10-year peak, rising 99 cents, to $34.97 a barrel. [Page C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oil Prices Approach $37 On Iraq-Kuwait Tension  Oil prices surged to their highest levels in a decade on fears that rising tensions between Iraq and Kuwait would disrupt the flow of crude oil from the Persian Gulf at a time when petroleum supplies are extremely tight.</p>
        <p>In New York, the price of crude oil for October delivery increased 96 cents, or 2.7 percent, to $36.88 a barrel, the steepest price for oil since the Persian Gulf war. In London, the price of Brent crude oil for delivery in November also reached a 10-year peak, rising 99 cents, to $34.97 a barrel. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>Genuity to Offer New Services  Genuity, one of the world's biggest Internet carriers, plans today to introduce its first major service offerings since the company was spun off from GTE this summer. Genuity is trying to offer services that are more sophisticated and profitable than providing raw Internet access. Shares of Genuity rose 63 cents, to $7.94. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Earnings Anxiety Pulls Down Stocks  Stocks fell on more warnings of less-than-stellar earnings from corporations and high oil prices. The Nasdaq composite index tumbled 108.71 points, or 2.8 percent, to 3,726.52. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 118.48 points, or 1.1 percent, to 10,808.52. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dropped 21.30 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,444.51. [C17.]</p>
        <p>End of Daewoo Deal Rattles Market  Unnerved by Ford Motor's decision to abandon a takeover of Daewoo Motor, investors sold off South Korean securities, pulling the stock market here down to an 18-month low. South Korea's benchmark stock index, which fell 3.4 percent on Friday on the Ford news, declined an additional 8 percent. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Barnes &amp; Noble in Yahoo Agreement  The online unit of Barnes &amp; Noble is making its biggest bid yet to woo the book chain's customers through a marketing agreement with the Web portal Yahoo, which will provide free Internet access to Barnes &amp; Noble customers. The deal will make the company the most prominent bookseller on the Yahoo site, replacing Amazon.com, which did not renew its three-year agreement with Yahoo. [C2.]</p>
        <p>NBC Adds One Ad and Pulls Another  During its presentation of the Summer Olympics, NBC is running a commercial it had rejected before the Games and pulling a second spot it had accepted pending viewer reaction. The commercial that will run, part of an antismoking campaign, shows black body bags stacked around an office building. The withdrawn spot, for Nike, intended as a spoof of horror movies, shows a woman under attack from a masked man, above, who wields a chain saw. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Levitt Seeks Support for Audit Plan  Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission, pleaded for smaller accounting firms to challenge the leadership of the accounting industry, which has opposed Mr. Levitt's efforts to strengthen rules to preserve auditor independence. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Marks &amp; Spencer Ousts Its Chief  Marks &amp; Spencer, once the flagship of British retailing, ousted its chief executive and other managers, seeking to reverse declining sales and a plunging stock price. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Brain Drain at U.S. Laboratories  Government research laboratories have been seedbeds for some of the most important advances in computing and other technology fields. But the lure of the private sector and its many start-up companies is so strong that national research laboratories are losing their best and brightest in growing numbers. [A1.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
