<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; As Euro Slides, So Do Earnings Across the U.S.</title>
    <meta content="Y19PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/19PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Multinational Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Profits (Industry-wide)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multinational Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E3D8173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; As Euro Slides, So Do Earnings Across the U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Beleaguered euro continues its relentless decline as impact of that currency's weakness spreads across American corporate landscape, cutting into sales and profits; euro falls to new intraday low of 85.10 cents and finishes the day in New York at 85.46 cents; adding to sales and profit problems of multinational companies is rising cost of oil and gasoline; it is sapping European spending power and, at the same time, raising corporate costs; what is making decline of euro extra painful for American companies is that this was supposed to be year currency of 11 nations bottomed out and then began to rally, after falling 13.7 perent in its debut year of 1999; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The beleaguered euro continued its relentless decline yesterday as the impact of that currency's weakness spread across the American corporate landscape, cutting into sales and profits.</p>
        <p>Gillette said that the drop in the value of several currencies, particularly the euro, would reduce the dollar value of sales by 6 percent in the third quarter, compared with a year ago. The news sent its stock down $2.19, or 7.3 percent, to $27.63.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The beleaguered euro continued its relentless decline yesterday as the impact of that currency's weakness spread across the American corporate landscape, cutting into sales and profits.</p>
        <p>Gillette said that the drop in the value of several currencies, particularly the euro, would reduce the dollar value of sales by 6 percent in the third quarter, compared with a year ago. The news sent its stock down $2.19, or 7.3 percent, to $27.63.</p>
        <p>Shares of DuPont, McDonald's, Colgate-Palmolive and other companies that do a major part of their business in Europe have also experienced declines after saying that they would be hurt by the weak euro. In trading yesterday the euro fell to a new intraday low of 85.10 cents and finished the day in New York at 85.46 cents.</p>
        <p>Adding to the sales and profit problems of these multinational companies is the rising cost of oil and gasoline. It is sapping European spending power and, at the same time, raising corporate costs, a fact that has particularly hurt DuPont.</p>
        <p>The decline in the value of the euro, or any other currency against the dollar, cuts into performance when sales and profits from abroad are translated into dollars. Hedging in currency markets can limit these impacts but can be expensive.</p>
        <p>What is making the decline of the euro extra painful for American companies is that this was supposed to be the year the currency of 11 nations bottomed out and then began to rally, after falling 13.7 percent in its debut year of 1999. With that view in mind at the beginning of the year companies would naturally choose not to hedge to protect themselves against a further decline in the value of the euro. Instead, the euro has plunged another 15.1 percent this year.</p>
        <p>''If you were expecting a bounce this year, you might not have hedged,'' said David Gilmore, a partner at Foreign Exchange Analytics in Essex, Conn.</p>
        <p>Susan Stalnecker, the treasurer at DuPont, said: ''The euro has not behaved the way people expected. I don't think, if you talked to anyone, they would be on the right side of this.''</p>
        <p>She said that DuPont's hedging strategy ''only works when there is not a lot of volatility'' in the foreign exchange market. ''In volatile times you are more exposed.''</p>
        <p>DuPont says it will lose 2 cents a share in earnings for the second half of the year because of the weakening euro.</p>
        <p>DuPont also showed the heavy impact that the rise in the price of oil was having. In its earnings warning on Sept. 7, DuPont's vice president for investor relations, Ann Gualtieri, said that 7 cents to 10 cents a share would be trimmed from earnings in the second half of the year because of higher energy costs.</p>
        <p>According to some analysts, more companies also seem to have decided to ride out currency fluctuations, rather than aggressively hedge against them. This is because of losses suffered from attempts to hedge in the past and the belief that there would be less volatility in the currency market now that Europe has a single currency for 11 nations.</p>
        <p>''Despite an increase in trade globally, there seems to be a reduction in the amount of hedging being done,'' said Robert White, executive vice president and treasurer at Standard Chartered Bank.</p>
        <p>Eric Kraus, vice president for corporate communications at Gillette, said the company looked ''for opportunity hedging -- but on a quarter-by-quarter, year-by-year basis, we don't do it.''</p>
        <p>''It is not a general practice,'' he added.</p>
        <p>He also said that Gillette made a decision not to hedge against a further decline in the euro this year because it was thought that the euro was already near its bottom and was set for a rally. This view, he said, made hedging ''an expensive undertaking at the time.''</p>
        <p>He also pointed out that it was not just the fall in the euro that was hurting companies with business in Europe this quarter. A sharp decline in the British pound is also cutting into sales and profits. Since the end of the second quarter in June, the euro is off 10.3 percent against the dollar while the British pound is down 7.1 percent. The average value of the euro so far this quarter, compared with the third quarter of 1999, is down 13.1 percent, which is the important comparison for year-to- year quarterly sales and profits. The average value of the British pound is down 7.4 percent so far this quarter compared with a year ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kraus said that if the euro had held at 95 cents to the dollar at the end of June, then overall sales in the third quarter would be projected to rise 3 percent in the third quarter, compared with the third quarter of 1999, rather than the flat result now forecast. If the value of the euro held at the $1.05 of the third quarter of 1999, then the dollar value of sales would have been up 6 percent.</p>
        <p>Edward Kerschner and Thomas Doerflinger of PaineWebber said in a commentary yesterday that the euro and oil prices would make it much tougher for companies with ''heavy exposure to Europe'' to meet current earnings forecasts for the third quarter. The report lists 100 companies in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index that have 18 percent or more of their sales from Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
