<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Genuity to Introduce First Major Internet Service Offerings</title>
    <meta content="Y19WIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Genuity (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gte Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DA173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Genuity to Introduce First Major Internet Service Offerings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Genuity Inc, one of world's first biggest Internet carriers, plans to introduce its first major service offerings since company was spun off from GTE Corp this summer; new suite of services is meant to help Genuity's corporate customers do business on the Internet; Genuity is trying to offer services that are more sophisticated and profitable than providing raw Internet access (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Genuity Inc., one of the world's biggest Internet carriers, plans today to introduce its first major service offerings since the company was spun off from the GTE Corporation this summer.</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, the new suite of services is meant to help Genuity's corporate customers do business on the Internet. Long one of the biggest carriers of Internet traffic, Genuity, formerly known as BBN, is trying to offer services that are more sophisticated and profitable than providing raw Internet access.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Genuity Inc., one of the world's biggest Internet carriers, plans today to introduce its first major service offerings since the company was spun off from the GTE Corporation this summer.</p>
        <p>Unsurprisingly, the new suite of services is meant to help Genuity's corporate customers do business on the Internet. Long one of the biggest carriers of Internet traffic, Genuity, formerly known as BBN, is trying to offer services that are more sophisticated and profitable than providing raw Internet access.</p>
        <p>For instance, a company that signed up for Genuity's suite of new products, to be called Black Rocket, could allow Genuity and its partners to manage the computers used for the company's Web site and perhaps other software applications, connect its offices to Genuity's Internet service, allow Genuity to manage digital security for the company's network and use software tools from Genuity to connect electronically to the company's customers.</p>
        <p>''Enterprises are accelerating their moves to do business on the Internet and with half a million open I.T. jobs in the country and the need for a highly technical staff, companies are realizing they can't piece together the staff they need,'' Paul R. Gudonis, Genuity's chairman, said yesterday. ''And now here comes Genuity with a complete solution.''</p>
        <p>With partners that include Sapient and PricewaterhouseCoopers, Genuity also plans to deliver services directed toward specific applications and industries. For instance, the company plans to offer a package of services meant to streamline the delivery of electronic content and media over the Internet.</p>
        <p>Genuity is hardly alone in trying to develop such services. Internet and telecommunications providers of all types are trying to scramble ''up the value chain,'' in business school parlance, by offering advanced services that are less prone to competition that drives down their prices than are their older products.</p>
        <p>For instance, providing raw communications pipes to corporations is becoming less profitable as more competitors enter that business. In response, companies like Genuity are trying to offer services like management of Web servers and management of specific applications like e-commerce software. Those sorts of new services build on the communications carriers' traditional expertise but are thought to be less prone to competition based simply on price.</p>
        <p>Genuity plans to support Black Rocket with a $20 million advertising and marketing campaign. GTE sold more than 90 percent of Genuity to the public this summer as part of a deal to win regulatory approval for GTE's acquisition by Bell Atlantic.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
