<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Growth Sets a Record In the Region</title>
    <meta content="19PORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/nyregion/19PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DE143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Growth Sets a Record In the Region</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Port Authority study reports that private employment and job creation in New York region hit all-time high in 1999, surpassing national rate of job growth for first time since 1983; growth rate was 2.8 percent for region and 2.4 nationally; map; graphs; region has finally made up for 600,000 jobs lost in 1989-92 recession (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Private employment and job creation in the New York region hit an all-time high in 1999, surpassing the national rate of job growth for the first time in nearly two decades, according to an annual economic study by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The findings, to be released today, are surprising because the region has lagged behind the nation -- and behind many other areas of the country -- in most economic indexes during the boom of the 1990's. But in posting a growth rate of 2.8 percent in private jobs last year, the New York region surpassed the national average -- 2.4 percent in 1999 -- for the first time since 1983. And the report said the trend was expected to continue through this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Private employment and job creation in the New York region hit an all-time high in 1999, surpassing the national rate of job growth for the first time in nearly two decades, according to an annual economic study by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The findings, to be released today, are surprising because the region has lagged behind the nation -- and behind many other areas of the country -- in most economic indexes during the boom of the 1990's. But in posting a growth rate of 2.8 percent in private jobs last year, the New York region surpassed the national average -- 2.4 percent in 1999 -- for the first time since 1983. And the report said the trend was expected to continue through this year.</p>
        <p>While most of the new hiring came in the region's dominant service sector, including support jobs in industries like finance, advertising and technology, last year's growth was more diversified than that of past years, with significant gains in construction, retail and wholesaling, and securities.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority report also noted that with the most recent surge of new jobs, the region had finally managed to make up for the 600,000 jobs it lost in the recession of 1989-92. Job creation in the years since then  made the New York region No. 3 last year among the 10 most populous metropolitan areas, behind Atlanta and Dallas-Fort Worth, in the rate of job growth, and No. 1 in the number of new jobs created.</p>
        <p>''The New York-New Jersey region closed out the 20th century with an economic boom,'' Robert E. Boyle, executive director of the Port Authority, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Another reason the findings are notable is the fact that job creation is usually driven by population growth, which has plodded in the New York region and in the rest of the Northeast. Eugene Spruck, the chief economist for the Port Authority, noted that the New York region averages an annual population growth of 0.3 percent, compared with a national average of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>''Generally you can't expect this region to have the population growth of other areas,'' Mr. Spruck said, ''and so that is why this development is so notable.''</p>
        <p>He said the 17-county region examined in the report had benefited as a leader in the areas where American job growth has been strongest: finance, construction, new technology and the Internet.</p>
        <p>Another recent report on New York City seems to echo the Port Authority study. The city comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi, noted in a report released last month that as of June,  New York had enjoyed 30 consecutive quarters of private job growth, surpassing the record of 20 quarters set in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority study examined economic indicators in the five boroughs of New York and in Nassau, Suffolk, Westchester and Rockland Counties. Also included were eight northern New Jersey counties: Bergen, Essex, Hudson, Middlesex, Morris, Passaic, Somerset and Union.</p>
        <p>In raw numbers, the region ended 1999 with 190,300 more jobs than it had in 1998. But more impressive,  Mr. Spruck said, is the fact that from 1992, when the recession ended, to 1999, 768,400 jobs were created. The  region posted a total of 7.737 million jobs last year, a record and the highest figure since the months before the recession struck in 1989, when there were 7.62 million jobs.</p>
        <p>Job growth in 1999 included a 4 percent increase in the service sector; a 2.7 percent increase in Wall Street brokerage firm jobs; a 2 percent in finance, insurance and real estate jobs; and an 8.9 percent surge in construction jobs.</p>
        <p>New York City's job growth rate was 2.8 percent in 1999, while the New York suburbs' was 3.5 percent and northern New Jersey's was 1.8 percent.</p>
        <p>''This tells me that we are working as a region, economically,'' said Mr. Spruck, pointing out that much of the business, consulting and support services around Wall Street and the advertising industry were spilling out into suburbs. ''There is a lot of county-to-county commuting in addition to city-to-county and county-to-city commuting.''</p>
        <p>Lewis M. Eisenberg, chairman of the Port Authority, said that because of the strong economy, the agency was accelerating its capital spending to nearly $1 billion in the region's airports, river crossings, rail systems and shipping channels.</p>
        <p>While the agency's study did not examine how wages rose or fell in 1999, Mr. Spruck speculated that an overall increase was likely because the region's service sector jobs were ''high-value jobs.''</p>
        <p>There probably were pay increases in low-wage jobs as well, he said, because low unemployment has forced employers to pay more than the minimum wage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
