<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thorpe Comes Up a Big Hand Short to a Flying Dutchman</title>
    <meta content="19SWIM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/olympics/18SWIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">van den Hoogenband, Pieter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thorpe, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosolino, Massimiliano</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krayzelburg, Lenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welsh, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Theloke,  Stev</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quann, Megan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Leisel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heyns, Penny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DD173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thorpe Comes Up a Big Hand Short to a Flying Dutchman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pieter van den Hoogenband of Netherlands wins gold medal in 200-meter freestyle in world record 1 minute 45.35 seconds at Sydney Olympics; Ian Thorpe of Australia wins silver medal and Massimiliano Rosolino of Italy bronze; Lenny Krayzelburg of US wins 100-meter backstroke; Matthew Welsh of Australia wins silver medal and Stev Theloke of Germany bronze; Megan Quann of US wins women's 100-meter breastroke, Leisel Jones of Australia wins silver medal and Penny Heyns of South Africa bronze; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even on the victory stand, with a gold medal around his neck, the national anthem of the Netherlands playing and his country's flag being raised above the pool, Pieter van den Hoogenband shook his head as if he could not believe he had beaten the great Ian Thorpe.</p>
        <p>Tonight's 200-meter freestyle was the Olympic race that would stop the nation, a local newspaper headline declared. At age 17, Thorpe was such an Australian hero after winning two gold medals on Day 1 of the swimming competition that a postage stamp had been issued in his name and strangers had begun to impersonate him. When he returned victoriously to the Olympic Village on Saturday night, he was halted by guards who told him that someone named Ian Thorpe was already inside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even on the victory stand, with a gold medal around his neck, the national anthem of the Netherlands playing and his country's flag being raised above the pool, Pieter van den Hoogenband shook his head as if he could not believe he had beaten the great Ian Thorpe.</p>
        <p>Tonight's 200-meter freestyle was the Olympic race that would stop the nation, a local newspaper headline declared. At age 17, Thorpe was such an Australian hero after winning two gold medals on Day 1 of the swimming competition that a postage stamp had been issued in his name and strangers had begun to impersonate him. When he returned victoriously to the Olympic Village on Saturday night, he was halted by guards who told him that someone named Ian Thorpe was already inside.</p>
        <p>Idolatry, of course, does not guarantee success. Favorites do not always win. It was van den Hoogenband, not Thorpe, who won the 200 freestyle, matching the world record of 1 minute 45.35 seconds that he had set a day earlier. If victory brought great surprise to the Dutch medical student, it brought sobering confirmation to the American swimmer Lenny Krayzelburg. He was up next in the 100-meter backstroke and he knew now that anything could happen.</p>
        <p>Krayzelburg immigrated to Los Angeles from the Soviet Union in 1989 as a teenager, his parents seeking to escape anti-Semitism and possible conscription of their son into some endless war. His father had pushed him, and he had become a world record-holder in the backstroke. He was a heavy favorite tonight, but if Thorpe could be beaten, nothing was certain.</p>
        <p>''I told Pieter he was my inspiration,'' Krayzelburg said. ''He was the underdog. He showed a great example that nothing is over until you swim the race.''</p>
        <p>As Thorpe could not, Krayzelburg controlled the 100-meter backstroke from the beginning, reaching the wall in an Olympic-record time of 53.72 seconds and covering his face with his hands. It had all seemed so improbable, coming to a new country, learning a new language, wanting to stop swimming and continuing only because his father would not let him quit. And now he was an Olympic champion.</p>
        <p>He did not break his own world record of 53.60 seconds, but records are ephemeral. A gold medal is forever.</p>
        <p>''This is Mount Everest,'' Krayzelburg said. ''It's great to know for the rest of your life you had this journey and it is completed. That is the most beautiful thing.''</p>
        <p>The United States won a second gold medal tonight when 16-year-old Megan Quann of Puyallup, Wash., upset the defending Olympic champion Penny Heyns of South Africa in the 100-meter breaststroke. Quann had promised at the United States Olympic trials that Heyns was ''going down,'' and impetuous youth was served victory in 1:07.05. Heyns was third in 1:07.55, just behind Leisel Jones of Australia.</p>
        <p>During the semifinals on Sunday, Quann's teammates at the Puyallup swim club dived into the water at the approximate moment she did in Australia, leaving a lane open for her. Later, Quann imagined victory as she had every night in recent months, taking a stopwatch to bed and visualizing her race stroke by stroke.</p>
        <p>''I can see the tiles at the bottom of the pool, I can hear the crowd cheering, I can taste the water,'' Quann said of her ritual.</p>
        <p>Judging by the hype and blitz of fawning news media coverage, millions of Australians had also visualized the 200 freestyle, and anything other than a Thorpe victory seemed unimaginable.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to win every race or break a world record,'' a gracious Thorpe said after finishing second in 1:45.83, nearly a half-second behind.</p>
        <p>Where his long, fluid strokes seemed unhurried in winning the 400 freestyle and the 4x100-meter freestyle relay on Saturday, tonight they seemed to lack urgency and stamina. Thorpe said he felt flat, perhaps inevitably, and he didn't reach van den Hoogenband until they turned simultaneously with 50 meters to go. The crowd of 17,500 cheered deafeningly, but Thorpe had nothing left and soon the cheering became the applause of consolation.</p>
        <p>''I don't think my performance had anything to do with expectation or hype,'' Thorpe said. He added: ''I gave it my best shot and came out with the best result possible tonight. I felt I would go faster. I was disappointed with the time, but not the result.''</p>
        <p>At the Atlanta Olympics, van den Hoogenband finished fourth in the 100 and 200 freestyle races. He took a year off, then returned and won six gold medals at the 1999 European championships, defeating the Olympic champion Aleksandr Popov of Russia in both the 50 and 100 freestyles. This year, Hoogie, as he is known, took a leave from medical school to concentrate on swimming. He is coached by Jacco Verhaeren, who also coaches the Olympic butterfly champion Inge de Bruijn and who advocates such cross-training methods as power lifting, cycling and rope climbing.</p>
        <p>''The whole year he was breaking world records, I was home training,'' van den Hoogenband said of Thorpe. ''He motivated me to train harder. Now I won. It's amazing.''</p>
        <p>Still, van den Hoogenband seemed unsure whether he could defeat Thorpe before Sunday's 200 prelims, saying he was hoping to win a silver medal, or a bronze. But he broke Thorpe's world record in the semifinals, and that seemed to both surprise and assure him.</p>
        <p>''I thought the world record would last only two minutes,'' van den Hoogenband said. ''Now it's two days. It's so weird.''</p>
        <p>As he and Thorpe made their final turn tonight, van den Hoogenband told himself, ''I really want this gold medal.'' In the final 25 meters, the water churning from furious windmill strokes, he began to draw away and to think, ''My God, I'm Olympic champion; I've got it.''</p>
        <p>Before the 100 backstroke, Krayzelburg did not feel that same sense of inexorable victory. He was as nervous as he had ever been the night before the race, and he could not eat lunch today.</p>
        <p>''I'd be lying if I said losing didn't cross my mind,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he had prepared for this moment since he was 9, living in Odessa in what is now Ukraine. He and 44 other swimmers were placed together from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. each day at a sports school, being lectured in the classroom and in the pool. Tonight, he credited the Soviet sports system with providing him the dedication and work ethic to become an Olympic champion.</p>
        <p>''In the States, people are afraid to challenge kids at a young age,'' said Krayzelburg, who will be 25 next week. ''They grow them slowly. In Russia, at 9 years old you have no choice. You either accept it or you give up.''</p>
        <p>Giving up is what Krayzelburg considered doing after his family immigrated to West Hollywood, Calif., in March 1989. He was 13, with no command of English and no pool in the neighborhood. His school, Fairfax High, did not even have a swim team. For a year, he endured a 50-minute bus ride each way to train at Santa Monica City College, but the long commute drained him.</p>
        <p>He wanted to quit, but Oleg Krayzelburg told his son: ''You have put in so many years in a tough system in the Soviet Union. You can't just quit. You have to continue and complete your journey.''</p>
        <p>He began training closer to home at the Westside Jewish Community Center in Los Angeles. The pool was only 25 yards long, half that of an Olympic pool, but the center offered him a job as a lifeguard. He later enrolled at Santa Monica City College, setting a national junior-college record in the 200-yard backstroke, then transferred to the University of Southern California, where Coach Mark Schubert told him, ''If you are willing to work, you can be the best backstroker in the world.''</p>
        <p>''That's all I needed to hear,'' Krayzelburg said.</p>
        <p>Oleg Krayzelburg has been his son's biggest fan and critic, exhorting him to break world records at every meet. Tonight, he was left almost speechless.</p>
        <p>''My dream was for Lenny to become an Olympian,'' he said. ''I feel like I was born again tonight.''</p>
        <p>On the medal podium, Krayzelburg said he thought about the past 11 years, training in the Soviet system, the sacrifices his parents made, the fact that he had nearly quit and was now draped with a gold medal. He dedicated the medal to his parents.</p>
        <p>''Our dreams have come true,'' said his mother, Yelena Krayzelburg. ''I'm the happiest mother in the world. Everybody loves my son.''</p>
        <p>The 200 backstroke is left to swim for a second gold medal, but Oleg Krayzelburg seemed satisfied tonight.</p>
        <p>''We can go home now,'' he told his son.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
