<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Book Maps a Nation's Spurts of Clean Living</title>
    <meta content="19BOOK$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/science/19BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS ON HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epstein, Randi Hutter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Engs, Ruth Clifford (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Books on Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Books on Science and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1DE173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Book Maps a Nation's Spurts of Clean Living</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randi Hutter Epstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Epstein, Randi Hutter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Ruth Clifford Engs, author of new book Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform; book traces nation's obsessions with food, diet and religion and describes a country of extremists, who embrace preventive health and rigid moral codes one generation only to rail against them the next; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the fall of 1977 the American Cancer Society organized the first national ''Great American Smokeout,'' urging smokers to quit for a day. Within five years, Jerry Falwell founded the Moral Majority and Jane Fonda sold millions of aerobics videos. Dr. Ruth Clifford Engs, a professor of applied health science at Indiana University in Bloomington sees a connection.</p>
        <p>In her new book ''Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform'' (Praeger), Dr. Engs shows how Americans' fervor for self-improvement occurs in spurts. And interest in health and religion usually occurs at the same time. Her book traces the nation's obsessions with food, diet and religion and describes a country of extremists, who embrace preventive health and rigid moral codes one generation only to rail against them the next.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the fall of 1977 the American Cancer Society organized the first national ''Great American Smokeout,'' urging smokers to quit for a day. Within five years, Jerry Falwell founded the Moral Majority and Jane Fonda sold millions of aerobics videos. Dr. Ruth Clifford Engs, a professor of applied health science at Indiana University in Bloomington sees a connection.</p>
        <p>In her new book ''Clean Living Movements: American Cycles of Health Reform'' (Praeger), Dr. Engs shows how Americans' fervor for self-improvement occurs in spurts. And interest in health and religion usually occurs at the same time. Her book traces the nation's obsessions with food, diet and religion and describes a country of extremists, who embrace preventive health and rigid moral codes one generation only to rail against them the next.</p>
        <p>So far, Dr. Engs say, Americans have experienced three so-called clean-living movements. Each one involved campaigns against tobacco, alcohol and premarital sex.  Dr. Engs tracks the cultural forces that prompt each movement and those that set off each rebellion against health, and the story is told in an appealing way for mass audiences. But it is being marketed for scholars and is listed at $69.50.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Dr. Engs described her findings: ''Our country was founded in an era of ferment. We were founded in an awakening, and we usually have them about every 80 years. They usually start with a conservative religious awakening that goes into health concerns, with alcohol as one thread, another thread is fitness, and another is some aspect of sexuality. There is also a concern about producing the perfect baby.''</p>
        <p>The question, she added, is why the fervor fades. Sometimes, Dr. Engs said, one generation believes healthy living will solve all society's woes, but when problems continue, the next generation loses faith. And eventually, new reformers start the cycle again.</p>
        <p>Though specifics vary, Dr. Engs shows similarities among the movements. Health zealots through the ages have urged Americans to exercise and avoid greasy food, meat, alcohol and tobacco. Many of these movements, she says, are prompted more by morality than new medical knowledge. In the 1830's, for instance, health reformers pleaded with Americans to quit smoking not so much because it was a health hazard but because it was considered ''morally depraved.''</p>
        <p>Whether a reader goes along with her theory, the book is chock full of amusing anecdotes and brief biographies of those she calls health fanatics. Mr. Falwell and Ms. Fonda continue a long American tradition of believers, preaching their gospel of moral or physical fitness.</p>
        <p>In the first ''Clean Living Movement,'' which the author says occurred from about 1830 to 1860, the Mormons and Seventh-day Adventists preached salvation through healthy living. Charles Grandison Finney, a Presbyterian preacher and lawyer-turned-evangelist crusaded against alcohol, coffee, tea and meat. At the same time, the American Temperance Society and the American Anti-Tobacco Society were founded.</p>
        <p>These were the days of Sylvester Graham, who started ''Grahamism,'' which advocated hard beds, cold baths, vegetarian diets, wheat bread and gave rise to the Graham cracker. He persuaded followers to avoid fried foods, butter, pastries and salt pork and to drink pure water only.</p>
        <p>Health advocates also condemned women's fashion of tight corsets and long dresses. They believed the outfits damaged internal organs and debilitated women so much that they would give birth to weak offspring. Amelia Jenks Bloomer, a women's rights advocate, designed a new outfit -- the ''bloomer'' -- suitable for outdoor exercise and physical activity. The Fowlers -- Orson; his brother, Lorenzo; and Lorenzo's wife, Dr. Lydia Folger Fowler -- wrote and published books and newsletters instructing couples on how to make better babies. They warned against marrying women with indigestion, liver complaints, melancholia or  heartburn. Those kind of folk, they said, should not have children. Truly ''superior  offspring,'' they added, could only be obtained when lovers engaged in a ''spiritual banquet of love.'' In other words, the woman had to have an orgasm.</p>
        <p>The First Clean Living Movement lost momentum to the Civil War.</p>
        <p>The second movement, from 1880 to 1920, included the founding of the Y.M.C.A., the New Thought Movement, which encouraged believers to replace negative thoughts with positive ones, and a new slew of fitness fanatics. Bernarr Macfadden was the exercise guru of the 1890's. He invented muscle-building machines, opened his own gym in New York City and in 1899 started a popular magazine, ''Physical Culture.'' ''Macfadden,'' writes Dr. Engs, ''popularized exercise and diet much the same way Sylvester Graham did in the first and Richard Simmons and Jane Fonda in the third Clean Living Movements.''</p>
        <p>The third movement got a foothold in the 1960's but emerged full force in the 70's with aerobic exercising, anti-smoking crusades and a resurgence of religious fundmentalism, Dr. Engs writes. She notes the recent rise of the Christian right, the fascination with alternative medicine, the growth of the health club industry, and new laws against smoking in public and tougher penalties for drunken driving. She believes that, like the ''clean living movements'' of the past, this one is doomed to die, too.</p>
        <p>Her prediction: the nation will lose interest in preventive health by 2005. And no matter what public health messages bombard today's children and despite an onslaught of new medical findings, health enthusiasm, like other trends, comes and goes. In other words, today's baby boomers may be training for triathlons but their children will grow to prefer martinis and cigarettes.</p>
        <p>BOOKS ON HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
