<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cost of Not Living On a $5.15 Minimum; Little Impact Seen in Raising Wage Now</title>
    <meta content="Y19WAG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/19WAGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D9173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cost of Not Living On a $5.15 Minimum; Little Impact Seen in Raising Wage Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <dateline>BURTONSVILLE, Md.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Raising of federal minimum wage is having little impact because many employers are already paying more than $5.15 minimum to attract workers; except for high school students, unskilled help gets average starting wage of about $7 an hour in suburban stretch between Baltimore and Washington; 10 states and District of Columbia have set their own minimum wages that are higher than federal mandate of $5.15; graph; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four years ago, the last time Congress agreed to raise the minimum wage, Lynn Martins was quick -- though far from eager -- to respond.</p>
        <p>On word that she would soon have to pay employees at her family-owned Seibel's Restaurant 50 cents more an hour, Ms. Martins printed up new menus virtually overnight, pushing the price of a basic hamburger up a dime to more than $3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four years ago, the last time Congress agreed to raise the minimum wage, Lynn Martins was quick -- though far from eager -- to respond.</p>
        <p>On word that she would soon have to pay employees at her family-owned Seibel's Restaurant 50 cents more an hour, Ms. Martins printed up new menus virtually overnight, pushing the price of a basic hamburger up a dime to more than $3.</p>
        <p>''I anticipated,'' she said. ''I raised prices prior to the rise even taking effect'' to try to blunt the impact on payroll costs that she knew was coming. Subsequently, Ms. Martins, who is very reluctant to lay anybody off, decided not to replace an employee who left, choosing instead to give a raise to another employee and ask that he do the work of two.</p>
        <p>But not this time. Despite the near-certainty that a Congressional conference committee will work out differences between House and Senate versions of the minimum-wage legislation, most likely raising the federally mandated minimum to $6.15 in two annual 50-cent increments, Ms. Martins sees no need to hurry.</p>
        <p>The labor market is so tight, at least in most urban areas, that many employers are already paying more than the $5.15 minimum to attract workers. In many cases, companies are already paying more than the proposed higher minimums. Except for high school students, unskilled help gets an average starting wage of about $7 an hour around here, in the suburban stretch between Baltimore and Washington.</p>
        <p>''The market has lifted it well above the minimum wage even with the increases,'' Ms. Martins said. She said she did not expect actually to benefit from Republican pledges to offset higher wage mandates with more-generous tax breaks, which, in any case, would be less useful than cash.</p>
        <p>Since she already pays as much as required by the prospective law, Ms. Martins said she could ''probably sit out the winter'' before raising menu prices or cutting the payroll. Besides, she added, her staff of 17 full-time and 30 part-time workers usually shrinks by half a dozen over the winter as business slows and more employees focus on school.</p>
        <p>Restaurants and retailers have traditionally been among the sectors of the economy most affected by Washington's wage mandates. But they are expressing little alarm about the proposed increase.</p>
        <p>Amazon.com, for example, the seller of books, music and video products over the Internet, said none of its 7,000 American employees, the bulk of them at some 10 distribution centers around the country, earn just the minimum. ''The best reading I have from human resources is we're not affected by this,'' said Bill Curry, a senior spokesman for the company, which is based in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Even the ailing Kmart Corporation, which has been forced into a major restructuring, expressed only mild regret at the prospect of a higher minimum wage. ''We'd prefer, if it needs to be increased, that it not be increased immediately,'' said Mary Lorencz, the director of media relations. Since the company did not budget for an increase this year, she said Kmart would prefer that the rise be delayed until the company's new fiscal year begins on Feb. 1.</p>
        <p>The version of the bill passed by the House calls for the first rise on Jan. 1, with the second 50-cent increment on Jan. 1, 2002. The minimum wage has been in place since 1938, when it was 25 cents an hour.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, today's prosperity seems likely to blunt only temporarily, not block, the economic forces that a higher minimum wage tends to unleash. Many companies may find profits eroded, in some cases to the point of failure, while hours are cut and prices are pushed up. Jobs may arguably be lost or the creation of new jobs slowed. The significance of these effects following previous increases in the minimum wage is a matter of debate, especially the effect on employment.</p>
        <p>''The impact is very different, depending on who you talk to,'' said Lee Culpepper, senior vice president of the National Restaurant Association and leader of a multi-industry alliance devoted to the minimum wage issue called the Coalition for Job Opportunities.</p>
        <p>Among the variables are whether a business is in a high-cost urban area or a low-cost rural one, whether employees are tipped or rely solely on wages and whether the enterprise is in one of the 10 states plus the District of Columbia that have their own minimums set higher than the federal one. In low-cost areas, employees are more likely to be earning the minimum than elsewhere, meaning that a mandated increase has greater impact.</p>
        <p>Employees who make tips are entitled to be paid a wage of at least $2.38 an hour -- half the regular federal minimum of $4.75 that prevailed before the last increase in September 1997 -- and their employer must make sure that earnings, including tips, reach $5.15 an hour. In practice, tipped employees often earn much more.</p>
        <p>Oregon and Washington, at $6.50, have the highest state minimums, followed by Connecticut, Rhode Island and the District of Columbia at $6.15. Connecticut is to go to $6.40 in January. In New York and New Jersey, the rate is set at the federal minimum.</p>
        <p>Delaware's minimum is to climb to $6.15 from $5.65 on Oct. 1, posing an immediate problem for Robert E. Ashby, proprietor of McGlynns Pub and Restaurant in Newark, Del., who has 110 employees in two locations and is now conducting his annual review of menu prices.</p>
        <p>''Our employees are already earning well above the federal minimum and we still have to go and give an increase,'' Mr. Ashby said. He said that the cost was magnified when the increase moved up the payroll ladder as he sought to maintain differentials for workers with more skills or seniority. And the impact can be quite subtle. In the last round of increases, for example, Mr. Ashby not only pruned staff hours but switched some setup work from morning, before the restaurant opened, to night. This saved him money because the employees involved had to be paid the full minimum when there was no opportunity for tips but could be paid only half as much if they did the same work at night while the restaurant was open.</p>
        <p>Even in hindsight, the effects of increases in the minimum wage arouse intense feelings. Mr. Culpepper, of the restaurant group, pointed to ''a price increase and a job impact'' from the two-stage 90-cent rise in 1996 and 1997. He cited government figures showing, for example, that employment growth at eating and drinking establishments slowed to 129,100 in 1997 from 276,400 in 1995 and that menu prices, which had long trailed general inflation, suddenly began to outpace inflation beginning in 1997.</p>
        <p>Those who favor higher minimums, however, question those conclusions. John Schmitt, an analyst at the Economic Policy Institute, a liberal research organization, said he found no evidence of job loss other than that related to normal business-cycle fluctuations for either of two groups thought most vulnerable: teenagers and less-educated adults.</p>
        <p>The industry's slackened job growth, he suggested, might reflect an inability of employers to find lower-paid workers. ''In a booming economy, they have trouble competing with other sectors that pay better wages,'' Mr. Schmitt said.</p>
        <p>In addition, a survey by the Jerome Levy Economics Institute of Bard College found that only 6.2 percent of 568 representative small businesses had their hiring or employment decisions affected by minimum-wage increases in 1996 and 1997.</p>
        <p>In return for supporting this year's legislation to raise the minimum, the House Republicans are seeking to include various items of tax relief that would soften the presumed burden on business. Among these items are raising the deduction for business meals for everyone to 80 percent from 50 percent, accelerating full deductibility of health insurance premiums paid by the self-employed and nearly doubling the amount of equipment that can be expensed immediately rather than depreciated. In addition, the proposal would repeal a surtax on sellers of alcoholic beverages, extend a credit for hiring disadvantaged workers and allow people who sell their businesses to pay capital gains taxes in installments.</p>
        <p>Further, the cash wage for tipped employees would be frozen at current levels in all states, and states would no longer be permitted to disallow credit for tips.</p>
        <p>Yet neither Ms. Martins nor Mr. Ashby, who have made little use of an existing provision in minimum wage regulations to pay teenagers as little as $4.25 for the first 90 days of work, were much aware of the Republican proposals or took appreciable comfort from them.</p>
        <p>Cash seemed paramount with Ms. Martins, whose revenue at Seibel's has just surpassed $1 million a year. She calculates that the proposed increase will cost her a relatively modest $2,400 in 2001 but a cumulative $30,000 in 2002.</p>
        <p>Kevin M. Murphy, a professor of economics at the University of Chicago Graduate School of Business who has studied the minimum wage, has no doubts that there will be noticeable effects, showing up perhaps well before President Clinton signs the bill.</p>
        <p>''It's probably not going to be as big as before, given the strength of the economy,'' he said. ''But certainly it will be something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashby, the Delaware restaurant owner, agreed. ''I have to cut hours or increase prices,'' he said. ''There's no other way of dealing with it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
