<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small Firms Urged to Back Independence in Auditing</title>
    <meta content="Y19AUDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/19AUDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Association of State Boards of Accountancy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Institute of Certified Public Accountants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levitt, Arthur Jr (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DA173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small Firms Urged to Back Independence in Auditing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission chairman, Arthur Levitt, pleads for smaller accounting firms to challenge leadership of accounting industry, which has bitterly opposed Levitt's efforts to strengthen rules aimed at preserving auditor independence, speech to National Association of State Boards of Accountancy, Boston; says that he asked to speak to annual meeting of American Institute of Certified Public Accountants in October, but that leadership of group has not responded; institute's leaderhip, with support of three of Big Five accounting firms, has bitterly opposed proposed SEC rule, which would limit consulting work that auditors can perform for their audit clients; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission, pleaded yesterday for smaller accounting firms to challenge the leadership of the accounting industry, which has bitterly opposed Mr. Levitt's efforts to strengthen rules aimed at preserving auditor independence.</p>
        <p>In a speech to the National Association of State Boards of Accountancy, meeting in Boston, Mr. Levitt complained of ''a stonewall by some of the profession's leadership to prevent truly independent oversight.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission, pleaded yesterday for smaller accounting firms to challenge the leadership of the accounting industry, which has bitterly opposed Mr. Levitt's efforts to strengthen rules aimed at preserving auditor independence.</p>
        <p>In a speech to the National Association of State Boards of Accountancy, meeting in Boston, Mr. Levitt complained of ''a stonewall by some of the profession's leadership to prevent truly independent oversight.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levitt said he had asked to speak to the annual meeting of the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants in Las Vegas next month, but that the leadership of the group had not responded.</p>
        <p>''I believe the time has come for the profession's own broader membership -- the smaller, independent accounting firms -- to stand up,'' Mr. Levitt said, adding that they could ''take back the spirit of the franchise that America's investors bestowed upon them long ago.''</p>
        <p>The institute's leadership, with the support of three of the Big Five accounting firms, has bitterly opposed the proposed S.E.C. rule, which would limit the consulting work that auditors can perform for their audit clients. Besides testifying against the proposal before the S.E.C., it has sought to rouse Congressional opposition and threatened to take the S.E.C. to court over any rule that is approved. There is no evidence of progress at reaching a compromise.</p>
        <p>Robert K. Elliott, the chairman of the institute and a partner at KPMG, a large accounting firm that is also opposed to the rule, said in a telephone interview that a majority of accounting firms, small as well as large, agreed with the institute's leadership. He declined to say whether Mr. Levitt would be allowed to speak to the membership meeting.</p>
        <p>''Any suggestion on his part that we are forsaking the public interest, we don't accept, and we find it unnecessarily adversarial,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levitt pointed to a Congressional report raising issues of auditor independence a quarter-century ago, adding that the profession had done little since then to strengthen independence of auditors, even as consulting became the largest revenue source for accounting firms.</p>
        <p>''In two and a half decades, where is the initiative?'' Mr. Levitt asked. ''If the leadership of the profession will not even stand up and establish self-regulation, how can the commission -- how can the American public -- expect anything less than a profession paralyzed by its own inaction?''</p>
        <p>The speech appeared to reflect a growing sense of frustration for Mr. Levitt, who had hoped that he would be able to make a deal that the accounting profession would accept. Instead, it is fighting bitterly, arguing that there is no evidence that independence has been compromised and saying that auditing firms benefit from having expertise available from their consulting staffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Elliott cautioned that public pronouncements might be overstated to improve negotiating positions. ''When you hold a poker hand, you keep a poker face,'' he said. ''While he's trying to encourage us to come to the table, he's keeping the pressure up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Elliott said that neither the institute nor KPMG were now at the table discussing possible compromises with the S.E.C. He said that he thought the issue was not one the S.E.C. should be tackling at all, instead leaving it to the Independence Standards Board, an organization that was established at the urging of the S.E.C. and includes public as well as industry representatives.</p>
        <p>The institute and its leadership see a future of expanded services for certified public accountants, who will, in the words of an institute document quoted by Mr. Levitt, ''deploy knowledge needed for strategic planning and investments, for marketing decisions, for monitoring internal and external communications, for conducting daily operations, for maximizing the productivity of employee behavior, and for measuring the effectiveness of operations, personnel and processes.''</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. chairman asked if the investing public would believe the auditor had ''only rigorous, objective analysis on his mind if he also must consider how his work impacts strategic planning, marketing, communications, and personnel decisions.''</p>
        <p>He also criticized the Internet venture recently approved by the institute, whose leadership owns a financial stake in the venture. It would allow accountants to order goods and services for their clients, while earning a commission for doing so. ''This seems to me to be a commercialization of the significant responsibilities well performed by America's professional auditors,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
