<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OFFICE SHORTAGE IMPERILS GROWTH IN NEW YORK CITY</title>
    <meta content="19OFFI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/nyregion/19OFFI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CROWDED CITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DB143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OFFICE SHORTAGE IMPERILS GROWTH IN NEW YORK CITY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, The Crowded City, on severe lack of office space in Manhattan and surrounding boroughs that is posing serious threat to city's ability to attract new business; city is suffering from perils of its own success amid Wall Street's boom, in contrast to early 1990's, when companies fled Manhattan amid gloomy recession and doubts about city's primacy as corporate and financial center; companies are again seeking New York address, but commercial space is becoming harder to find and cost of existing space is climbing; landlords in Manhattan have been able to raise rents to record levels, with rents in Midtown rising nearly 30 percent in last year alone; some companies are again finding that their future may be outside Manhattan; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lost in the noisy ebullience over New York City's thriving economy is a problem that some economists and elected leaders say could undermine the city's prosperity and cost thousands of jobs at everything from Internet companies to garment manufacturers.</p>
        <p>The problem is a severe lack of office space in Manhattan and the surrounding boroughs. According to a growing number of urban planners, corporate executives, developers and political officials, it is already posing a serious challenge to the city's ability to attract new business and to stop more companies from following the lead of Chase Manhattan Bank, U.S. Trust and more than 20 other companies that have agreed to move across the Hudson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lost in the noisy ebullience over New York City's thriving economy is a problem that some economists and elected leaders say could undermine the city's prosperity and cost thousands of jobs at everything from Internet companies to garment manufacturers.</p>
        <p>The problem is a severe lack of office space in Manhattan and the surrounding boroughs. According to a growing number of urban planners, corporate executives, developers and political officials, it is already posing a serious challenge to the city's ability to attract new business and to stop more companies from following the lead of Chase Manhattan Bank, U.S. Trust and more than 20 other companies that have agreed to move across the Hudson.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the New York of the early 1990's, when companies fled Manhattan amid a gloomy recession and doubts about the city's primacy as a corporate and financial center, New York today suffers from the perils of its success, the experts say. Wall Street is booming. Companies want a New York address once again, and job growth last year edged ahead of the national average for the first time in at least a decade. [Page B1.]</p>
        <p>Yet there is little vacant space available and, despite the demand, little new construction.</p>
        <p>As a result, landlords in Manhattan have been able to raise rents to record levels; rents in Midtown rose nearly 30 percent on average over the last year alone.</p>
        <p>''We should be growing at a faster rate with a more diverse group of industries that make this their world capital,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer. ''New York is in great demand by many types of businesses. Unfortunately, with real estate prices so high, we're at risk of losing some of those businesses. And the No. 1 reason is a lack of space.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the fabric of the city is being rewoven. Once-dowdy but vibrant industrial areas are being transformed, as advertising agencies and Internet and telecommunications companies plunge into the garment district south of Times Square, the printing district north of TriBeCa and even Long Island City in Queens and southern Brooklyn, pushing rents well beyond what many manufacturers in those areas can afford.</p>
        <p>And the psychological chasm that once separated Manhattan from what many considered the backwater New Jersey waterfront has closed. Companies as diverse as John Wiley &amp; Sons, which has been publishing books in Manhattan since Thomas Jefferson was president, and Chase Manhattan Bank, one of the city's financial pillars, decided to move all or part of their operations to New Jersey, where there is room to grow and costs are lower. Each new defection makes the western bank of the Hudson River that much more viable as a corporate haven.</p>
        <p>''In the long run, the present market is bad for New York City,'' said Douglas Durst, who heads one of New York's prominent real estate families. ''It's pushing companies outside the city and showing them they don't have to be here.''</p>
        <p>No economist would dispute the fact that losing companies to New Jersey has quantifiable effects on New York, including a loss of jobs and tax revenues. But some say that taking a wider view of the regional economy, there is little difference if a company is in Lower Manhattan or a mile away in Jersey City, where land and construction costs and taxes are lower. New York, after all, has always functioned as an incubator for new businesses that move to new locations as they grow.</p>
        <p>In January, Mr. Schumer formed a panel of corporate executives, state and city officials and urban planners to make recommendations to try to solve the problem. That a senator would seize on a mundane local issue like land use was seen by many urban planners and developers as a rebuke of city and state officials for having failed to do so.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Harding, the deputy mayor for economic development, said the Giuliani administration was well aware of the problem. The mayor and City Council recently increased the level of tax breaks and other incentives for companies that leave Manhattan for the other boroughs, a measure that they say makes Queens and Brooklyn more competitive with New Jersey. Joseph B. Rose, director of city planning, is leading an effort to rezone Long Island City and the far West Side of Manhattan to encourage new offices.</p>
        <p>''When you outpace the nation in job growth, you're doing something right,'' Mr. Harding said. ''We're exploding at such a record clip that we have to identify areas for development outside of Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>But until recently, the Giuliani administration relied primarily on offering tax breaks to major corporations -- like Credit Suisse First Boston, Merrill Lynch and Time Warner  -- that threaten to move outside Manhattan. Not enough has been done, critics say, to promote areas that have some land available for less expensive back-office development, like the Metrotech Center in downtown Brooklyn or near the Citicorp tower in Long Island City, or to build a transportation network that would make those areas competitive with the New Jersey waterfront. The Queens West complex on the East River, for instance, lacks convenient public transportation to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Although Mayor Giuliani addressed the issue in a speech last January, some corporate executives and relocation advisers say that he has not focused on the problem.</p>
        <p>''We haven't had a physical development policy for the city since the Koch administration,'' said Mitchell L. Moss, director of the Urban Research Center at New York University. ''Instead, we're building minor league stadiums on Coney Island and Staten Island and failing to encourage the development of major league office buildings.''</p>
        <p>A Quick Recovery  From a Glut To a Shortage</p>
        <p>The dearth of office space is a relatively new phenomenon for New York. For much of the last decade, the city suffered from a severe hangover from the last real estate boom. The city lost 300,000 jobs during the recession in the early 1990's, leaving many new skyscrapers empty and bankrupt. The average vacancy rate rose to 18 percent in Midtown office buildings, while one out of every four floors sat empty downtown.</p>
        <p>In 1995, in response to an outcry from the real estate industry, the Giuliani administration instituted a series of zoning changes and tax incentives in Lower Manhattan that were intended to spur the renovation of old office towers and the conversion of outmoded commercial buildings into apartment houses. The program took hold, and as the economy improved, office space filled up and rents began inching upward.</p>
        <p>Wall Street also expanded and tenants once again began looking for space downtown, where rents by comparison were cheaper and space more plentiful. The real estate market there improved so quickly that in 1997, carpenters were putting up walls for apartments at 10 Hanover Square in Lower Manhattan when Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company suddenly leased the entire 22-story building for office space.</p>
        <p>But there has been little new construction to ease the pressure, in part because of the memory of the 1980's, when so many speculative buildings, erected without a commitment from tenants, failed. Today, only a handful of lenders are willing to provide construction loans, and they demand that the developer have a major tenant lined up and provide cash up front, say $150 million for a $400 million skyscraper.</p>
        <p>The problem is made worse by the scarcity of development sites left in densely packed Manhattan. As a result, only a single major office tower has been completed in the last eight years, the Conde Nast building in Times Square.</p>
        <p>As any pedestrian can attest, there are skyscrapers under construction in Midtown for Reuters, Ernst &amp; Young, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, Bear Stearns, Random House and Time Warner. Two others are in the planning stages for The New York Times and the Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce. In each case, the towers would primarily be for single tenants and would be built on sites whose development in the 1980's was delayed by the recession.</p>
        <p>Most corporate tenants, however, are not big enough to justify a million-square-foot tower. New York developers and executives said that they would have little trouble filling speculative buildings with smaller tenants if only they could find the financing and development sites.</p>
        <p>''The memory of unfinished projects and bad loans lingers on,'' said David Tobin, a director of the Carlton Group, a commercial mortgage banker. ''Given what lenders are demanding today, developers are less inclined to build.''</p>
        <p>Last month, the vacancy rate downtown stood at 5 percent, while the annual asking rent hit $42.73 per square foot, up from a low of $25.57 in 1995, according to Insignia/ESG, a commercial real estate broker. (When adjusted for inflation, the low point was $27.92 in 1997.) In Midtown, the average rent topped $61 per square foot, nearly double the rate seven years ago, and the vacancy rate is only 3.1 percent. For a law firm or a publishing company leasing 400,000 square feet of space, that is a difference of $12 million a year from the rate in 1993.</p>
        <p>''This market kind of snuck up on people,'' said Stephen B. Siegel, president of Insignia/ESG. ''I don't think anyone anticipated how strong it was going to be.''</p>
        <p>A Transformation  Internet Businesses Displace Industries</p>
        <p>In the last two years, advertising agencies and Internet and telecommunications companies hunting for cheaper space have pushed into longtime industrial neighborhoods like the garment district, Chinatown, the printing district, Long Island City and even the Brooklyn waterfront from the Brooklyn Bridge south to Sunset Park. Bates North America, an advertising agency, led the charge when it leased a former garment showroom at 498 Seventh Avenue and 37th Street. Screaming Media and Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia took space in the old Starrett-Lehigh factory building on 11th Avenue and 26th Street.</p>
        <p>The 70-year-old printing district around Varick, Hudson and Canal Streets has all but disappeared as landlords rent to higher-paying white-collar tenants. More than two dozen garment factory buildings in Chinatown were converted to office and retail space in the last two years. At 150 Lafayette Street in Chinatown, Mad Science, an Internet company, shares a floor with a garment factory. As the jostling for space continues, some Manhattan developers say that the garment and printing districts no longer belong in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>But urban planners point out that some of the city's valuable and otherwise viable manufacturing jobs are in jeopardy throughout the city. Peter D. Colahan, president of the Colahan-Saunders Corporation, said that in the nine months since he moved his printing company from Varick Street to Long Island City, he had seen rents around him jump as Internet companies began vying for the same buildings as manufacturers.</p>
        <p>''The city has responded to the growth of the dot-coms,'' said Fred Siegel, a professor of history at the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art in Manhattan, ''but it hasn't responded to the secondary effects of the dot-coms on other districts.''</p>
        <p>Manufacturers who pay $8 a square foot in rent cannot compete with the Internet and telecommunications companies willing to pay two or three times that amount.</p>
        <p>''Space in the area is getting more difficult to find for manufacturers,'' Mr. Colahan said, ''and more expensive.''</p>
        <p>The Competition  Lately, New Jersey Seems a Lot Closer</p>
        <p>After sitting fallow for much of the 1990's, the New Jersey waterfront has become a genuine alternative for New York corporations. Since July 1998, more than 20 major corporations have signed deals to move some of their operations from New York to more than 5.5 million square feet of space in Jersey City, Hoboken and Weehawken -- the equivalent in square feet of more than half the entire World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>The tenants include U.S. Trust, the Cigna insurance company, Lord, Abbett &amp; Company and the Insurance Services Office. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company and Merrill Lynch have bought major development sites at the former Colgate toothpaste factory in Jersey City.</p>
        <p>William J. Pesce, the chief executive of Wiley, who signed a deal last month to move the 197-year-old publishing company and 900 employees to Hoboken, said the company was loath to cut its deep New York roots when it began looking two years ago. It was already paying top dollar to rent its building at Third Avenue and 40th Street and was facing a steep rent increase in 2003.</p>
        <p>Wiley was prospering, Mr. Pesce said, but the company wanted to improve its profit margins and invest in people and technology.</p>
        <p>He said he rejected a move to Baltimore, which would have cut his real estate costs by two-thirds but cost him many employees. He found a rare block of space in a factory near the Holland Tunnel, but there was little room to grow.</p>
        <p>So after some sharp debate among the directors, Wiley decided that the company's best choice was to move to a new building in Hoboken that would allow the publisher to nearly double its space and save money. Wiley expects to move in late 2002.</p>
        <p>Recently, Chase Manhattan made a similar decision, agreeing to move about 2,500 employees from 13 floors at 55 Water Street in Lower Manhattan to a building that the developer Samuel J. LeFrak is building at his 600-acre Newport complex in Jersey City. Unlike Wiley, Chase was looking for a quick, low-cost alternative.</p>
        <p>According to those involved in the search, Chase considered a new tower at Queens West, a project in Long Island City sponsored by the city, the state and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. But the executives said it was unclear when commercial development would begin at that site, which they thought did not have good transportation links to Manhattan. But as with Wiley, city officials did not urge the bank to reconsider Queens West, or to expand at Metrotech in Brooklyn, where Chase has back-office operations and 4,500 employees, though they did offer a tax break if the employees remained in New York.</p>
        <p>New Jersey officials were only too happy to give Chase an even more generous set of subsidies. More important, said executives involved in the decision, Mr. LeFrak offered to build the bank a new building within 18 months, a startlingly brief time by Manhattan standards.</p>
        <p>''The Wiley and Chase deals are as much a product of the lack of space in New York as pure price,'' said Stephen Siegel of Insignia/ESG.</p>
        <p>During the 1980's, New Jersey tried to lure New York financial companies to the waterfront in Jersey City by building PATH train and ferry links to Manhattan and offering a broad array of tax breaks. New York officials condemned the effort as poaching, and few companies took the bait. But many investment banks routinely threatened to move to New Jersey before extracting tax incentives from New York.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, however, the New Jersey waterfront has seemed a lot closer for corporations looking for office space, especially since it is as much as 30 percent cheaper. Potential sites in Queens and Brooklyn ''seemed out of the way and ill located,'' said one lawyer who has advised dozens of corporations on relocation issues.</p>
        <p>''One reason we chose Jersey City over a more remote location is that it is accessible to people who live in New York City,'' said Tom Block, a senior vice president for government affairs at Chase Manhattan, which has kept its headquarters and thousands of employees in New York. ''It would have taken six years to renovate our space at 55 Water Street versus building a state-of-the-art building in Jersey City in 18 months.''</p>
        <p>It is an open question whether New York could have held on to the Chase jobs. But corporate executives, urban planners and some city officials say that the city's fast-growing Internet ventures and other companies may stay and expand if there are alternatives in New York. Otherwise, they said, New York could become the equivalent of a one-crop economy in which the city's fortunes are tied exclusively to the wealthy international financial companies that can afford the rents in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I think New York City has an opportunity to look at how it's going to sustain the current economic prosperity,'' said Mr. Pesce. ''It would be a shame to lose the diversity of businesses in New York City as a result of our company and others leaving.''</p>
        <p>The Potential  Steering Developers To Open Territory</p>
        <p>Senator Schumer and others have called for a public-private partnership to develop swaths of land for office development through zoning, incentives and condemnation. In addition, they say that the sites need good transportation to Manhattan and high-speed telecommunication links, amenities that would require major government investment. Analysts like Jonathan Bowles of the Center for an Urban Future say that the city also has to develop a policy to deal with manufacturing.</p>
        <p>There is also some agreement about where the city might steer new development.</p>
        <p>''It's crucial to the city's ongoing prosperity that we identify new growth corridors for commercial activity,'' said Mr. Rose, director of the city's planning department. ''The most obvious locations are Long Island City, downtown Brooklyn and the West Side of Manhattan and parts of Hudson Square,'' which is the area between West Houston and Canal, west of Varick.</p>
        <p>After years of preparation, Mr. Rose said that the city expected to certify a rezoning plan for Long Island City within the next month. The city and state, however, are at odds over development on the West Side of Manhattan and the expansion of the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center. Office development there could also conflict with preparations for the city's bid for the 2012 Olympics. Community advocates are also worried about the effects rezoning would have on existing businesses and neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Barry Gossin, chief executive of Newmark &amp; Company, a real estate company, contends that the city needs to focus on a small number of areas for development rather that taking a scattershot approach. ''The city should focus on an area, create a critical mass, and build the infrastructure and attract the restaurants and other amenities that go along with it,'' he said. ''Jersey City has accomplished so much because they have finally achieved critical mass. Brooklyn never did it.''</p>
        <p>Developers contend that they also need subsidies and tax abatements in order to set rents at competitive levels and to make projects economically viable. But Stephen J. Spinola, president of the Real Estate Board of New York, acknowledged that it would be politically difficult to create a major incentive program when the economy is still generating new jobs.</p>
        <p>Ron Shiffman, a former city planning commissioner, and Adam Friedman, executive director of the New York Industrial Retention Network, an advocacy group, warn that any effort to encourage commercial development in Long Island City or Brooklyn could also pose enormous problems for manufacturers.</p>
        <p>''We have to be careful that in looking to retain the Wileys we don't push out manufacturers who are quite viable and provide important jobs,'' Mr. Shiffman said. ''The real issue is how we maintain a healthy balance in the kind of jobs the city needs and ensure that physical improvements are distributed equitably throughout the city.''</p>
        <p>Despite the renewed focus on what many are calling a commercial space crisis, developers and urban planners say little will happen unless there is a concerted effort on the part of the city's political leaders.</p>
        <p>''If they want to provide a place where people can grow in a friendly environment where rents are not as high as Manhattan,'' said Richard LeFrak, president of the LeFrak Organization, ''they have to have the political will to identify specific sites and make them a genuine alternative.''</p>
        <p>THE CROWDED CITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
