<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classical Ballet, With Just a Hint of Modern Dance</title>
    <meta content="19HARL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/arts/19HARL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE THEATER OF HARLEM REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dance Theater of Harlem</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DE173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classical Ballet, With Just a Hint of Modern Dance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews Dance Theater of Harlem's final program of season at City Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dance Theater of Harlem concluded its season at City Center on Sunday afternoon with a program that was shrewdly chosen to display the eclecticism of its repertory and the versatility of its dancers.</p>
        <p>Arthur Mitchell, the troupe's artistic director, welcomed the audience with a brief speech in which he noted that he made his debut as a dancer 45 years ago on that very stage. He then thanked everyone who participated in the City Center engagement, giving special praise to Fran Reiter, the company's former interim executive director and a former deputy mayor of New York, who joined him on stage to take a bow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dance Theater of Harlem concluded its season at City Center on Sunday afternoon with a program that was shrewdly chosen to display the eclecticism of its repertory and the versatility of its dancers.</p>
        <p>Arthur Mitchell, the troupe's artistic director, welcomed the audience with a brief speech in which he noted that he made his debut as a dancer 45 years ago on that very stage. He then thanked everyone who participated in the City Center engagement, giving special praise to Fran Reiter, the company's former interim executive director and a former deputy mayor of New York, who joined him on stage to take a bow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell grew up as an artist at City Center, dancing with the New York City Ballet in choreography by George Balanchine, and works by Balanchine have served as the core of the Harlem company's repertory. The matinee opened with one of Balanchine's greatest creations, his ''Serenade,'' to Tchaikovsky, a plotless meditation on the beauty of movement and the pangs of love. It received a lyrical performance.</p>
        <p>Ensemble sequences flowed smoothly, and even though this ballet is rooted in classical technique, the little skips in the quicker passages had an innocent joy that suggested some of the idyllic steps associated with the early days of modern dance.</p>
        <p>Among the soloists, Lenore Pavlakos looked vulnerable as a woman waltzing in and out of love; Tanya Wideman was gently playful in her allegros; Caroline Rocher was mysterious as what might have been an angelic guide; and Donald Williams and James Washington partnered the women in brief and unhappy romantic encounters. ''Serenade'' resembled a bittersweet dream.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Michael Smuin's ''Song for Dead Warriors'' was a terrifying nightmare. The ballet, to a stormy score by Charles Fox, concerns the oppression of American Indians and the way a young Indian man and woman are brutally attacked by a state trooper. The choreography is melodramatic, yet its sense of moral outrage is strong enough to prevent it from seeming merely bombastic. The production designed by Willa Kim, with constantly shifting slide projections by Ronald Chase, helps make the work a theatrical hallucination.</p>
        <p>Everyone danced with remarkable intensity. Lowell Smith, a guest artist with the company, made the state trooper a believably menacing bully. Kellye A. Saunders brought pathos to the role of the sexually abused heroine. And most powerful of all was Duncan Cooper, as the young man who loved her. His turns were fast; his leaps were high. Even more admirable was the way he made these physical feats convey anguish, rage and a desire for vengeance.</p>
        <p>The program, conducted by Joseph E. Fields and David La Marche, concluded with ''Dougla,'' for which Geoffrey Holder created the music and costumes as well as the choreography. The ballet, inspired by a wedding ceremony in Trinidad, emphasizes pageantry and parading. The characters who paraded through this celebration included Paunika Jones and Mark Burns as the newlyweds and Ms. Pavlakos, who was imposing as a matriarchal Woman in Green.</p>
        <p>DANCE THEATER OF HARLEM REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
