<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cadbury Reaches for Growing Market</title>
    <meta content="Y19FLAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/business/19FLAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Triarc Cos Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Snapple Beverage Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cadbury Schweppes Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD8173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cadbury Reaches for Growing Market</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG WINTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winter, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes's acquisition of Snapple Beverges from Triarc Cos Inc allows Cadbury Schweppes to enter growing noncarbonated beverage industry as Americans cut back on carbonated drinks and increase their sales of noncarbonated beverages (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone wondering why Cadbury Schweppes is so eager to break into noncarbonated beverages that it is willing to spend $910 million to acquire Snapple need only ask Nice N Easy Grocery Shoppes about its Woodstock days.</p>
        <p>Last year, in preparation for the 30th anniversary of the historic concert, the convenience store chain crammed its parking lots with 48-foot refrigerated trucks, filled with enough Coke and Pepsi to sate the sweaty hordes of high school and college students on a pilgrimage to upstate New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone wondering why Cadbury Schweppes is so eager to break into noncarbonated beverages that it is willing to spend $910 million to acquire Snapple need only ask Nice N Easy Grocery Shoppes about its Woodstock days.</p>
        <p>Last year, in preparation for the 30th anniversary of the historic concert, the convenience store chain crammed its parking lots with 48-foot refrigerated trucks, filled with enough Coke and Pepsi to sate the sweaty hordes of high school and college students on a pilgrimage to upstate New York.</p>
        <p>As expected, the fans poured in and cleaned out the shelves, bringing in a month's worth of business in four days. But while store managers had to scour the state to find enough juice, water and iced tea to cool the crowds, the cold soda sat in the trucks untouched. When the bonanza ended, Nice N Easy sent the fizzy drinks back and gave more shelf space than ever to the fruity flavors that sold so well.</p>
        <p>In the nonalcoholic beverage business, soda is still king, accounting for 82 percent of the 18.3 billion gallons of cola, bottled water and juices that Americans swallow every year. But it is fast losing share to a barrage of noncarbonated drinks that offer the only substantial growth in an otherwise flat industry.</p>
        <p>Americans cut back last year on the amount of soda they typically drink, nearly reversing a steady rise in per-capita consumption that has lasted more than two decades. If not for the growth in population, plodding along at about 2 percent a year, the total amount of soda sold might not have increased at all. As it was, the category grew a mere 0.5 percent over the last two years, stunted by consumer ''sticker shock'' after Coke and Pepsi ended a five-year price war by charging more at the supermarket.</p>
        <p>Noncarbonated beverages, by contrast, have raced along, growing as much as 20 percent a year since 1993. Propelled by outlandish packaging and a torrent of new flavors -- including herbal extracts that promise everything from wisdom to good karma -- juices, teas and bottled water accounted for 84 percent of all growth in the industry last year, according to Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The shift in consumer taste is so pronounced that noncarbonated drinks now outsell soda at 7-Eleven convenience stores, a reversal from the market dominance enjoyed by bubbly soft drinks just five years ago. In response, 7-Eleven has doubled the amount of space set aside for juices, bottled water and sports drinks while cutting back its soda coolers by a third.</p>
        <p>''The large soft-drink companies were pretty satisfied with the old system,'' said Jim Jackson, a 7-Eleven beverage category manager. ''Now they are sitting up and taking note.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, soft-drink makers, most notably Coke and Pepsi, have made inroads into the noncarbonated market, introducing bottled-water brands that now eclipse the anemic growth of their flagship colas. Before acquiring Snapple, Cadbury Schweppes's lacked a strategy for competing in the category, prompting analysts to speculate that the company would be among the hardest hit as tastes change.</p>
        <p>Still, soda represents roughly 90 percent of Coke and Pepsi's business, and even as both companies rush to recast themselves as more than just soft-drink makers, that figure is not expected to sink below 75 percent in the coming years. Soda prices are also expected to stabilize, and both companies have also pledged aggressive advertising campaigns and in-store promotions to prevent losing any more ground to noncarbonated drinks, leading many analysts to believe at least a partial cola comeback is imminent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
