<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WEST'S GOVERNORS BACK CLINTON PLAN FOR FIGHTING FIRES</title>
    <meta content="19FIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/national/19FIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Babbitt, Bruce (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickman, Dan (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DE143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WEST'S GOVERNORS BACK CLINTON PLAN FOR FIGHTING FIRES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Governors from Western states devastated by recent wildfires strongly endorse Clinton administration's firefighting plan that would place new emphasis on prevention and local decision-making; issue statement after meeting in Salt Lake City with Interior Sec Bruce Babbitt and Agriculture Sec Dan Glickman; say proposal would be first step in helping vast natural forests and grasslands in West avoid same fate as 6.7 million acres destroyed by fire during current year, one of worst on record; praise Pres Clinton for asking Congress in final budget to support plan with $2.8 billion, more than double $1.2 billion allocated for wildfire programs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Governors from Western states that have been devastated by wildfires this summer strongly endorsed a Clinton administration firefighting plan today that would place a new emphasis on prevention and local decision-making.</p>
        <p>After a meeting here with Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt and Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman, the governors said the proposal would be the first step in helping vast natural forests and grasslands, much of them in the West, avoid the same fate as 6.7 million acres that have been scorched by fires this year, one of the worst years on record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Governors from Western states that have been devastated by wildfires this summer strongly endorsed a Clinton administration firefighting plan today that would place a new emphasis on prevention and local decision-making.</p>
        <p>After a meeting here with Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt and Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman, the governors said the proposal would be the first step in helping vast natural forests and grasslands, much of them in the West, avoid the same fate as 6.7 million acres that have been scorched by fires this year, one of the worst years on record.</p>
        <p>The governors also praised President Clinton for asking Congress in his final budget to support the plan with $2.8 billion, more than double the $1.2 billion that is now allocated for wildland fire programs, even if it took a disastrous fire season to prompt the administration to act.</p>
        <p>''We've reached a meeting of the minds, which is remarkable,'' said Gov. Jim Geringer of Wyoming, referring to a proposal that Mr. Babbitt and Mr. Glickman presented to the president just 10 days ago. ''I certainly endorse it.''</p>
        <p>But even the amount Mr. Clinton is seeking will only go so far. More than half of the additional $1.6 billion requested is needed to repay emergency funds that were tapped for fire-fighting efforts this year.</p>
        <p>That would still leave more than $700 million for the states as they  develop their individual plans, assuming Congressional approval. Aides to the governors were expected to begin working out details with administration officials this week.</p>
        <p>Today's meeting, coming just seven weeks before the November elections, was notable as much for its style as its substance. Five of the six governors who met with the cabinet secretaries are Republicans, including several, like Gov. Marc Racicot of Montana, who have been highly critical of the administration's firefighting policies.</p>
        <p>Yet by standing together at the Governor's Mansion here, administration officials supporting Vice President Al Gore and governors with loyalty to the Republican nominee, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, provided a rare picture of bipartisan achievement and civility.</p>
        <p>The Republican governors -- Mr. Geringer, Mr. Racicot, Gov. Dirk Kempthorne of Idaho, Gov. William J. Janklow of South Dakota and Gov. Michael O. Leavitt of Utah -- and the lone Democrat, Gov. John Kitzhaber of Oregon, were unanimous in backing a proposal that would shift many of the decisions regarding the health of forests to locally based state and federal officials, something the Republican governors said they had been insisting upon for years.</p>
        <p>''History may show this to be one of the more significant meetings to occur, relating to fire management in the West,'' Mr. Leavitt said. ''These changes will have lots of implications down the line.''</p>
        <p>The meeting was also significant for what the secretaries and the governors did not talk about. As a ground rule for their talks and impetus for getting the proposal before Congress, they agreed to set aside several issues that divide them, including what role, if any, timber harvesting should play in efforts to maintain the health of a forest.</p>
        <p>The group also agreed not to discuss the administration's proposal to set aside an additional 43 million acres of roadless areas, which would effectively mean the land could not be mined or logged.</p>
        <p>However, the report to Mr. Clinton explicitly states, ''The administration's wildland fire policy does not rely on commercial logging or new road building to reduce fire risks.''</p>
        <p>Republicans have favored a greater role for logging than have Democrats and many forestry experts, who argue that removing large trees  does more to fuel fires than suppress them. Many Republicans also object to setting aside more roadless areas because of the impact it has on resource industries, recreational opportunities and state economies.</p>
        <p>But in the context of the administration's proposal, Mr. Racicot said asking how much to log was ''the wrong question.''</p>
        <p>''We have got to get away from tree harvesting and focus on forest health as the issue,'' Mr. Racicot said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt agreed. ''We have to sidestep the temptation to turn this into a political debate about logging and roadless areas,'' he said. ''They are not central to the issue of forest restoration.''</p>
        <p>The proposal was developed as a blueprint for how to prevent the kinds of wildfires that have burned so much of the West this summer. As Mr. Glickman told the governors, the administration is seeking to make firefighting programs more preventive, like national defense, than reactive, like the work of the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</p>
        <p>Past policies have focused on fighting fires long after they have broken out. In recent years, the administration has shifted the emphasis to include controlled fires and preventive clearing. The new plan expands on controlled burns and the thinning of underbrush and shrubs.</p>
        <p>But the proposal seemed to be written broadly enough to have a little something for everyone, which could be helpful in an election year.  Besides the administration's new strategies, the proposal also underscores the need for coordination among all levels of government. That is an element that the governors especially favor, in that it allows for local officials to make decisions about such things as how to use controlled burns, how much thinning to do and how to protect native wildlife. These have become particularly important decisions in the growing  areas throughout the West where people live close to fire-prone forests.</p>
        <p>As the proposal says, ''Each team will work closely with local communities to identify the best fit for each community.''</p>
        <p>Environmental groups say they generally favor Mr. Clinton's proposal but only if it holds the line against logging as a tool for fire prevention. Most environmental groups oppose any incursions -- even increased recreational activities that many Americans favor -- that alter the pristine nature of forests.</p>
        <p>''This is, in part, the way to go,'' said Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club. ''It's not the whole picture. They still have to add money for controlled burning and for educating people of the role fire plays in controlling the health of a forest.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Babbitt and Mr. Glickman said they believed that the scope of damage caused by fires this year -- 77,893 fires affecting 6.7 million acres so far -- had created enough urgency that Congress would act before the elections.</p>
        <p>''This shifts the model of the management of public lands,'' said Mr. Racicot, who is viewed by many Republicans as a possible successor to Mr. Babbitt in a Bush administration. ''We have committed ourselves to actions in the short-term and a long-term study of restoration. This is a moment of opportunity to move the agenda forward.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
