<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harvard Finds 2 Poems, and a Latin Romance Reignites</title>
    <meta content="19ARTS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/arts/19ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nicaragua</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dario, Ruben (1867-1916)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3DD173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harvard Finds 2 Poems, and a Latin Romance Reignites</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Simon Romero</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Discovery of two unknown poems by Nicaraguan poet Ruben Dario at Widener Library of Harvard University creates great interest in Latin America and Spain; Dario is widely considered to be the greatest Latin American poet of all time; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One wintry December day three years ago, David Whitesell, a rare-book cataloger at Harvard University, walked from his windowless office into the seemingly endless stacks in Widener Library. What he found on one shelf made his heart race, and in recent months his discovery has become the talk of literary circles in Latin America and Spain.</p>
        <p>Browsing through the stacks, Mr. Whitesell pulled down a book with attractive red binding by an obscure Argentine poet and leafed through its pages. Scribbled in the book's margins and blank pages were lines of verse in Spanish and the words ''Ruben Dario'' in black ink. Startled and in doubt, Mr. Whitesell put the book back on the shelf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One wintry December day three years ago, David Whitesell, a rare-book cataloger at Harvard University, walked from his windowless office into the seemingly endless stacks in Widener Library. What he found on one shelf made his heart race, and in recent months his discovery has become the talk of literary circles in Latin America and Spain.</p>
        <p>Browsing through the stacks, Mr. Whitesell pulled down a book with attractive red binding by an obscure Argentine poet and leafed through its pages. Scribbled in the book's margins and blank pages were lines of verse in Spanish and the words ''Ruben Dario'' in black ink. Startled and in doubt, Mr. Whitesell put the book back on the shelf.</p>
        <p>But after a sleepless night, he returned to the library and compared the scribbling with handwriting samples of Ruben Dario, a Nicaraguan modernist poet considered by many to be the equivalent of an Ezra Pound or Walt Whitman in the Spanish language.</p>
        <p>In an investigation corroborated by literary and rare-book specialists, Mr. Whitesell found that he had unearthed two unknown poems composed by Dario at the turn of the century in addition to several dozen books from the Nicaraguan writer's personal library that Harvard acquired from a Madrid bookseller in 1916, the year Dario died.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Whitesell made the discovery in 1997, it took until early this year for Harvard to gather the writings and the portion of Dario's library initially uncovered by Mr. Whitesell into an exhibition, ''Ruben Dario at Harvard: Books and Manuscripts from the Poet's Library.'' Eighty-four years after the poet's death, the exhibition has drawn the fascinated attention of literary journals, Web sites and newspapers from Barcelona to Buenos Aires.</p>
        <p>In Nicaragua the newspaper La Prensa heralded the discovery with a front-page headline and an article that analyzed the poems in detail. In Spain, the newspaper ABC commented that ''Harvard has so many books it doesn't even know what it has.'' In Argentina, La Nacion declared the find to be important simply because the poems and books survived Dario's ''chaotic life.'' And in Chile, La Tercera called the discovery a ''true intellectual detective adventure.''</p>
        <p>Why all the commotion?</p>
        <p>Carmen Boullosa, a novelist who reviewed the exhibition for the Mexican newspaper Reforma, considers 'Ruben Dario to be ''the greatest Latin American poet of all time,'' but says that the reasons for the furor are more complicated.</p>
        <p>''At a time when Latin America is plagued by violence and economic problems, Ruben Dario, who dreamed we would be improved, returns,'' she explained in a telephone interview from Mexico City. ''Just as impressive, Harvard has placed him next to its volumes of Milton, Donne, Montaigne.''</p>
        <p>Though his work is not widely known in English -- he is considered difficult to translate -- Dario's grip on Spanish-language writers is explained by his interesting bohemian life as well as his literary innovations. Born Felix Ruben Garcia y Sarmiento in a muddy village called Metapa in 1867, he adopted the nom de plume Dario as a young man and spent his adult years in Santiago, Chile; Buenos Aires; Madrid; and Paris.</p>
        <p>Dario is credited by many scholars as having set the foundation for innovation by such 20th-century Latin American writers as Octavio Paz and Gabriel Garcia Marquez. In works like ''Azul,'' published in 1888, and ''To Roosevelt,'' in 1904, Dario dispensed with the conventional structures that had isolated Spanish and Latin American writing from the modernist experimentalism then tearing through French and English poetry and literature.</p>
        <p>When Dario died in 1916 at age 49, his mistress in Madrid, Francisca Sanchez, apparently sold numerous volumes in his collection to a bookseller named Joaquin Medinilla to cover debts. More than 45 of Dario's books, identified by dedications to the poet or by the half-red binding  that Dario used for many of his volumes, were subsequently acquired by J. D. M. Ford, the professor who was in charge of Spanish and French acquisitions at the time, according to Mr. Whitesell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitesell, the cataloger who found the scribbled lines, said:  ''Finding unknown poems written by Dario is something that still makes me tremble.''</p>
        <p>''But I also could not believe my eyes when I found part of his personal library in the depths of Widener,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The two previously unknown poems were found in a book called ''Eglantinas'' by Pedro J. Naon, an Argentine writer who has since faded into obscurity. One is sixlines long and begins with the words ''Sadness, sadness''; the other is a longer poem called ''Epistolas,'' dedicated to a friend of Dario's in Paris, Amado Nervo.</p>
        <p>There are earlier versions of poems from Dario's 1905 ''Songs of Life and Hope,'' and a seashell-like sketch he made on top of the publisher's logo on a book's back cover.</p>
        <p>''It is not as if the poems themselves, which represent only a blip on the radar screen of Dario's career, are of great importance,'' said Jose  Antonio Mazzotti, a professor of Romance languages and literature at Harvard. ''More importantly, they show that Dario considered this book a minor work, which in effect it is, or else he wouldn't have written in it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitesell's discovery has been compared to the story line of a recent novel, ''The Club Dumas,'' by the Spanish writer Arturo Perez-Reverte, in which the intrigue of the rare-book world is laid bare. The book served as the basis for the screenplay for Roman Polanski's recent movie ''The Ninth Gate,'' starring Johnny Depp.</p>
        <p>''A discovery of this magnitude is quite rare,'' said Richard Ramer, a New York dealer of rare books written in Spanish and Portuguese. ''Given Ruben Dario's stature, I would say this is one of the most important discoveries in recent years.''</p>
        <p>Others say that the discovery  highlights the gulf between academic institutions in the United States and those in Latin America. ''It's telling of the resources gap between the United States and Nicaragua that Harvard would have little or no idea of the treasures it holds,'' said Paul Berman, a cultural critic who recently researched Dario as a fellow at the Center for Scholars and Writers at the New York Public Library.</p>
        <p>Harvard's budget for the year ended in June was almost $1.8 billion, nearly twice the federal budget of Nicaragua, which Pedro Zeas, an economic official at the United States Embassy in Managua, estimated at $901 million this year.</p>
        <p>The reawakened interest in Dario has stirred pride among Nicaraguan writers.</p>
        <p>''It is as if the glue that holds us together has become stronger,'' said Pablo Antonio Cuadra, a former editor of La Prensa and one of the country's most prominent poets, in a telephone interview from Managua. Julio Valle Castillo, a Nicaraguan poet who is preparing a screenplay based on Dario's life, welcomed the discovery as ''a glimpse into the creative process of our greatest subject.''</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
