<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin, Making a Gesture to Jews, Slips Into a Factional Morass</title>
    <meta content="Y19MOS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/world/19MOSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000920T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EEDB173BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin, Making a Gesture to Jews, Slips Into a Factional Morass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Vladimir V Putin visits site of bombed-out Marina Roshcha synagogue in Moscow to dedicate $12 million Jewish community center; hails new structure as symbol of new era of tolerance in Russia; his strong gesture of support for faith that suffered decades of persecution during Soviet times places him in middle of bitter feud within Russia's reviving Jewish minority and raises questions among critics about his motives; has effectively given government blessing to Chabad Lubavich movement, Hasidic sect that runs synagogue and has been locked in murky feud with more mainstream Russian Jewish Congress since 1999, when it formed Federation of Jewisgh Communities as rival group; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Protected by hundreds of policemen who all but sealed off a Moscow neighborhood, President Vladimir V. Putin visited the site of a bombed-out synagogue tonight to dedicate a $12 million Jewish community center -- a stone-and-glass demonstration, he said, of a new era of tolerance in Russia.</p>
        <p>It was a strong symbolic gesture of support by a Russian leader for a faith that suffered decades of persecution during Soviet times. But it also placed Mr. Putin once more in the middle of a bitter feud within Russia's reviving Jewish minority  -- and raised questions among critics about his motives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Protected by hundreds of policemen who all but sealed off a Moscow neighborhood, President Vladimir V. Putin visited the site of a bombed-out synagogue tonight to dedicate a $12 million Jewish community center -- a stone-and-glass demonstration, he said, of a new era of tolerance in Russia.</p>
        <p>It was a strong symbolic gesture of support by a Russian leader for a faith that suffered decades of persecution during Soviet times. But it also placed Mr. Putin once more in the middle of a bitter feud within Russia's reviving Jewish minority  -- and raised questions among critics about his motives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin spent about 90 minutes on the grounds of the Marina Roshcha synagogue, one of only two allowed in Moscow during Soviet times.</p>
        <p>In a speech, he praised what he called ''the general revival of folk traditions and spiritual values in Russia,'' a trend he said would only strengthen the nation. And he decried anti-Semitic practices of the past, expressing bewilderment at one point that Russian Jews were forced by discrimination to hide their faith and study Hebrew secretly.</p>
        <p>''Who will live here in such conditions?'' he asked. ''Our country's spiritual revivial is unthinkable without the understanding that Russian culture is a combination of the traditions of all the people who have lived in Russia for centuries.</p>
        <p>''Every person and every ethnic group has been adding the colors of their own discoveries, energy and talent to the palette of our common culture,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's comments were all the more symbolic because the Marina Roshcha synagogue, which remained intact during Soviet rule, had been attacked three times after the Soviet Union's collapse, virtually destroyed by a 1993 fire and by bombings in 1996 and 1998.</p>
        <p>The last attack was part of a wave of anti-Semitic protest, led by ultra-nationalists and supported by some of the Parliament's Communist majority, which was sharply denounced by President Boris N. Yeltsin.</p>
        <p>The executive director of the Federation of Jewish Communities in the Commonwealth of Independent States, Rabbi Avraham Berkowitz, said Mr. Putin's attendance had ''broken down a barrier that stood for 70 years'' of Soviet control.</p>
        <p>''We believe this will create an incredible wave of Jewish pride and awareness,'' he said. ''We believe the government is not anti-Semitic, and we believe the government will help us to flourish and grow. The message here -- to all minorities of all religions -- is that they will be given the opportuniuty to grow in a new democratic Russia.''</p>
        <p>Tonight's ceremony, which was attended by the American ambassador, James Collins, was the most explicit Russian commitment to religious freedom since then.</p>
        <p>But it was also notable because Mr. Putin effectively gave a government blessing to the Chabad Lubavich movement, the Hasidic sect that ran the synagogue, operates the community center and has a growing presence across Russia.</p>
        <p>The movement has been locked in a murky feud with the more mainstream Russian Jewish Congress since last year, when it formed the Federation of Jewish Communities as a rival group.</p>
        <p>Since then, the federation has elected a Lubavich rabbi, Berl Lazar, to be chief rabbi of Russia, a move to depose Rabbi Adolf Shayevich of the congress, who had long held that title.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shayevich has said a senior Kremlin official pressed him to resign in favor of Mr. Lazar. Mr. Shayevich was also absent from Mr.  Putin's inauguration as president in May, although representatives of the Lubavich movement were present.</p>
        <p>Some in the Jewish congress have suggested that the government is trying to split Russia's emerging Jewish movement, and therefore weaken it.</p>
        <p>Political experts here speculate that the Kremlin is actually taking aim at the president of the Russian Jewish Congress, Vladimir Gusinsky, the tycoon whose Media-Most journalistic empire is perhaps Mr. Putin's fiercest critic in the press, and who has been a regular target of Kremlin attacks.</p>
        <p>For their part, Lubavich officials say the notion of favoritism is fantasy -- and in fact, the evidence to support it is mostly anecdotal.</p>
        <p>In his speech tonight, Mr. Putin said the Federation of Jewish Communities had ''asserted itself as a constructive and influential organization'' that had already made itself felt in the Russian power hierarchy.</p>
        <p>Tonight the mainstream chief rabbi of Moscow, Pinchas Goldschmidt, praised the Lubavich movement for its work in building the community center and promoting a revival of Judaism. But he said he had ''strong reservations about their having let  themselves be used by forces outside the Jewish community against other parts of the community.''</p>
        <p>''The whole federation is a creation of forces near or inside the Kremlin,'' he said. ''It's unfortunate, but it's true.''</p>
        <p>Rabbi Lazar expressed surprise at that in an interview tonight. ''I think we've proven that we're not planning on being used,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 20, 2000, Wednesday  A picture caption yesterday with an article about President Vladimir V. Putin's dedication of a Jewish community center in Moscow included an erroneous identification from The Associated Press for the rabbi shown. He was Mordechai Eliyahu, former chief Sephardic rabbi of Israel, not Meir Lau, the current chief Ashkenazic one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 20, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday with an article about President Vladimir V. Putin's dedication of a Jewish community center in Moscow included an erroneous identification from The Associated Press for the rabbi shown. He was Mordechai Eliyahu, former chief Sephardic rabbi of Israel, not Meir Lau, the current chief Ashkenazic one.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
