<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Time For Rusch To Pass Big Test</title>
    <meta content="19SHEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/sports/19SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rusch, Glendon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DC143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Time For Rusch To Pass Big Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Mets pitcher Glendon Rusch notes that he will face Atlanta Braves on Sept 19 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no pregame pep talk planned, no advice he has been rehearsing for his star pupil. Al Leiter, the veteran left-hander who has been a mentor to Glendon Rusch this year, thinks Rusch is ready for the biggest start of his career.</p>
        <p>Besides, Leiter knows, composure in big games is usually something that comes only through experience. Rusch, who starts for the Mets against the Braves on Tuesday, has passed almost every test this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no pregame pep talk planned, no advice he has been rehearsing for his star pupil. Al Leiter, the veteran left-hander who has been a mentor to Glendon Rusch this year, thinks Rusch is ready for the biggest start of his career.</p>
        <p>Besides, Leiter knows, composure in big games is usually something that comes only through experience. Rusch, who starts for the Mets against the Braves on Tuesday, has passed almost every test this year.</p>
        <p>''You have to learn it,'' Leiter said. ''As much as someone tells you you're not supposed to feel pressure, it's there. We're human beings, not robots.''</p>
        <p>The last time he faced the Braves, at Shea Stadium on July 2, Rusch said he let the pressure affect him. He is hoping to be more relaxed this time and avoid a repeat of that game, when he allowed a season-high 13 hits in a blowout loss.</p>
        <p>Matched up with Tom Glavine, another left-hander whose command Rusch admires, Rusch let the Braves take him out of his game. They crowded the plate and he tried to back them off by pitching inside. When he missed his location, he was hit hard.</p>
        <p>''It taught me a lesson, not to veer away from my game plan,'' said Rusch, who is 10-10. ''Even if things are going bad and you're giving up a lot of hits, you've got to stick with what you do every time out. You can't change.''</p>
        <p>But it was a willingness to change that helped get Rusch to this point. There was a reason the Mets were able to get Rusch so easily in a trade last September, from Kansas City for Dan Murray, a nondescript right-hander. Rusch had regressed after two seasons in the Royals' rotation; he was mechanically flawed and afraid to throw his changeup.</p>
        <p>Last winter, the Mets flew him to New York to meet with the pitching coach Dave Wallace. Rusch emerged with a more compact delivery, which allowed him to stay on top of his pitches.</p>
        <p>Now, Rusch has an even won-loss record and a 4.09 earned run average, with 146 strikeouts to just 42 walks. The Mets' lack of run support for him (3.84 runs per game, second lowest in the National League) is helping, indirectly.</p>
        <p>''It's made me better in tight ballgames, forced myself to make quality pitches and keep the games close,'' Rusch said.</p>
        <p>Charting Hampton's Road</p>
        <p>There was some symbolism in Mike Hampton pitching at Turner Field tonight, because it represents one of the Mets' worst fears. There is some belief among the Mets that the Braves will try to lure Hampton as a free agent this winter, and the idea makes sense.</p>
        <p>The Braves have built a virtual dynasty around elite starting pitchers, and they are not all homegrown: Greg Maddux was signed as a 26-year-old free agent entering his prime, and Hampton just turned 28. Further, Hampton is from Florida and prefers a warm climate.</p>
        <p>Still, the Mets are more optimistic now about retaining Hampton than they were at midseason, because he seems more comfortable with his surroundings. Signing him will be the Mets' first priority this winter, with Baltimore's Mike Mussina, who can become a free agent, another option.</p>
        <p>Respecting Hampton's wishes, the Mets have not negotiated for a contract extension since talks broke off before spring training. But they will attempt to sign him after the season ends and before the free-agent period begins.</p>
        <p>Hurt But Helping</p>
        <p>The swelling in right fielder Derek Bell's bruised left knee returned during tonight's 6-3 loss, though it did not affect his performance. Playing for the first time since Friday, he had three hits, including a home run. The only concession he makes to the injury is that he now slides headfirst.</p>
        <p>''I'll be back tomorrow, because I'm a gamer and the team needs me,'' Bell said.</p>
        <p>Bell, who entered this season batting .151 in his career off Greg Maddux, is 4 for 8 off him this year, with a homer and two doubles. Maddux, who had precise control all night, came up and in on Bell the last time he faced him tonight, grazing the bill of Bell's helmet.</p>
        <p>Bell walked slowly to first, then homered off Kerry Ligtenberg in his next at-bat. The homer was his form of revenge for Maddux's pitch. When asked if he thought the pitch was intentional, Bell replied, ''You saw what happened my next at-bat, right?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: METS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
