<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day 3 of Los Angeles Transit Strike Is a Work-Day Headache for Poorest Angelenos</title>
    <meta content="Y19TRA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/19/national/19TRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5DD143BF93AA2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day 3 of Los Angeles Transit Strike Is a Work-Day Headache for Poorest Angelenos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Strike by Los Angeles transit workers enters third day; is hardest on city's poorest residents, who depend almost completely on transit system for transportation; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Compton Chester stood on Wilshire Boulevard, squinting in the morning sun, craning his neck for the bus that never came.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a clue what I'm going to do,'' said Mr. Chester, a 29-year-old office assistant for an entertainment company who has no car and depends on the Metropolitan Transportation Authority bus for his 45-minute commute from Koreatown to West Los Angeles. ''I feel foolish standing here. It's like waiting for Godot.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Compton Chester stood on Wilshire Boulevard, squinting in the morning sun, craning his neck for the bus that never came.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a clue what I'm going to do,'' said Mr. Chester, a 29-year-old office assistant for an entertainment company who has no car and depends on the Metropolitan Transportation Authority bus for his 45-minute commute from Koreatown to West Los Angeles. ''I feel foolish standing here. It's like waiting for Godot.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chester was hardly alone this morning as the third day and the first work day of a countywide public transportation strike left half a million commuters in the nation's second-largest city stranded without regular bus and subway service and dependent on a catch-as-catch-can network of smaller regional bus lines, car pools, taxis and their own tired feet. Transportation officials reported a 5 percent increase in morning rush hour freeway traffic, taxi drivers said business had doubled and streets were clogged.</p>
        <p>But unlike New York, for example, where commuters of all socioeconomic groups depend on public transportation and are affected in a strike, Los Angeles has a transit system used primarily by the poorest residents, including the legions of maids, janitors, nannies and service workers who commute from East Los Angeles to the gated enclaves of the Westside. Nearly 70 percent of the system's riders here have household incomes under $15,000 a year, nearly three-quarters of bus riders are black or Hispanic, and half do not have a car, truck or motorcycle in their household.</p>
        <p>''It's sad,'' said Kelly Taylor, 23, a security guard trying to get from midtown to Universal City in the San Fernando Valley to pick up his paycheck at his company's headquarters. He said he might give up and go home, but was worried about how he will get to his job at a Jewish school near Beverly Hills on Tuesday. ''I'd have to call my sister and get a ride,'' he said. ''I can't really miss work.''</p>
        <p>Some 4,300 bus drivers and subway and light rail operators walked off the job Friday night in a strike against the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, the regional agency that administers a public transit system covering 1,400 square miles with 2,000 buses, the nation's second-largest fleet after New York's, plus 59 miles of subway and light rail track. About 1,800 mechanics and 650 clerks honored the picket lines. Among the major sticking points was a plan to cut overtime pay for senior drivers and to require some 400 drivers to work four 10-hour days without overtime in an effort to help close a projected operating shortfall of $430 million over the next decade.</p>
        <p>''Our members deal with the riders every day and they care about them,'' said Goldy Norton, a spokesman for the United Transportation Union, which represents the drivers. ''But you can't expect that in the greatest boom we've had in years our members should take what amounts to an average 15 percent pay cut.''</p>
        <p>The average driver earns about $50,000 a year, but $7,000 of that typically comes from overtime and working holidays and weekends, and union officials say the agency's proposed wage increases of 8.1 percent over three years would not make up the difference in lost overtime. The unions have sought 4 percent increases for each of three years.</p>
        <p>But Marc Littman, a spokesman for the Transportation Authority, said the agency was willing to drop the overtime proposal if the union came up with other ways for saving an estimated $2 million a year in overtime payments out of the agency's $2.5 billion annual budget. Labor accounts for 70 percent of the agency's costs. The authority also is seeking the right to hire more part-time workers and newer drivers at lower wages, which the union also resists.</p>
        <p>''If they don't like our ideas, then come up with some of their own,'' Mr. Littman said. ''They've got to give us something.''</p>
        <p>Union officials said this morning that they were waiting for a formal invitation from state mediators before resuming talks at a Pasadena hotel. But late today, the transit authority said the union had agreed to return to the bargaining table on Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>The bus and subway system here has about 1.5 million boardings a day, compared with about 6 million a day in the New York City system, and virtually none of it was operating today. The agency had hoped to operate five ''lifeline'' routes along major arteries using private contractors, but those drivers honored the union picket lines, and the plan fell through. The separate Metro Link regional commuter rail system and bus lines in surrounding cities like Santa Monica were unaffected, and some were providing extra service to help take up the slack.</p>
        <p>But most regular riders were out of luck, and Mayor Richard J. Riordan last week implored residents to ''open up their hearts'' and pick up people stranded on street corners. Caltrans, the state transportation agency, announced that it would suspend highway repair work during peak travel periods for the duration of the strike.</p>
        <p>The transit strike is the seventh in Los Angeles in the last 28 years, what is believed to the be the highest number among big city transportation systems. The last was in 1994 and lasted nine days.</p>
        <p>Brian Taylor, an associate professor of urban planning and associate director of the Institute of Transportation Studies at the University of California at Los Angeles noted that transit ridership in Los Angeles was much higher than public perception would have it.</p>
        <p>''It can be almost callous to say, how does a strike affect the regional economy,'' Professor Taylor said. ''The significant effect is obviously on the people who are living at the margin. They're mostly going to make do. In poorer neighborhoods, there are extensive systems of car-sharing and informal taxi service.'' But, he added, ''Unlike auto workers and car owners, here you have an unusual situation where the consumer of the product is on average much poorer than the operator, and there really is a cost to the population served by this system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chester, the commuter, who cannot come close to affording a daily cab ride of $20 each way, said he sympathized with the drivers' concerns to a point.</p>
        <p>''It's really put me in a bad situation,'' he said. ''I understand that they have to maintain their standards of living and keep their heads above and whatever. But when something like this happens, it also really shows how close people like me are to the edge.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
