<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cutthroats Galore but No Doctors in Sight</title>
    <meta content="15JAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newbern, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bull (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D7103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cutthroats Galore but No Doctors in Sight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews new TNT television series Bull, starring George Newbern; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oh, those wacky rich people and their colorful nicknames. The hero of the new TNT series ''Bull'' is the grandson of a prospering investment firm's founder. The grandfather, Robert Roberts, is so imperious, heartless and soulless he is called the Kaiser behind his back. The grandson, Robert Roberts III, is nicknamed Ditto. Even his friends call him that, which seems a misfortune serious enough to offset all the silver spoons positioned in his mouth at birth. Ditto is also not a bad word to describe this routine drama.</p>
        <p>It is the first of a boomlet of shows and movies set on Wall Street, tapping into the feeling that everybody's an investor today. (Fox's fall series ''The Street,'' created by Darren Star of ''Melrose Place'' and ''Sex and the City,'' promises to be soapier.) But ''Bull'' simply plugs an all-purpose cast of types into a financial setting. If they were yelling ''Stat! Chem seven!'' instead of ''Dot-com I.P.O.!'' these people could be in a hospital show. The bright side: because the financial schemes are no more than background noise, there's no need to dig into ''Wall Street for Dummies'' before viewing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oh, those wacky rich people and their colorful nicknames. The hero of the new TNT series ''Bull'' is the grandson of a prospering investment firm's founder. The grandfather, Robert Roberts, is so imperious, heartless and soulless he is called the Kaiser behind his back. The grandson, Robert Roberts III, is nicknamed Ditto. Even his friends call him that, which seems a misfortune serious enough to offset all the silver spoons positioned in his mouth at birth. Ditto is also not a bad word to describe this routine drama.</p>
        <p>It is the first of a boomlet of shows and movies set on Wall Street, tapping into the feeling that everybody's an investor today. (Fox's fall series ''The Street,'' created by Darren Star of ''Melrose Place'' and ''Sex and the City,'' promises to be soapier.) But ''Bull'' simply plugs an all-purpose cast of types into a financial setting. If they were yelling ''Stat! Chem seven!'' instead of ''Dot-com I.P.O.!'' these people could be in a hospital show. The bright side: because the financial schemes are no more than background noise, there's no need to dig into ''Wall Street for Dummies'' before viewing.</p>
        <p>The handsome Ditto (George Newbern) is so sweet, soulful and independent you have to wonder how he turned up in the cutthroat Roberts family. In tonight's premiere, he and some friends leave the old firm to start a new one.</p>
        <p>Despite the current interest in Wall Street, it's hard to give a broker the life-saving adventures of a doctor, so ''Bull'' makes Grandfather Roberts actively evil. The veteran actor Donald Moffatt makes him smooth, silver-haired and silver-tongued; it is easy to see why he is so successful a manipulator. But his actions are those of a mustache-twirling villain.</p>
        <p>The versatile Malik Yoba (from the police show ''New York Undercover'') plays Corey Granville, an Ivy League-educated broker who has just sold $60 million worth of Brazilian bonds the company has been desperate to unload. The Kaiser insists that because Granville is black, he would never have made the sale if he had been negotiating in person instead of on the phone. ''There's a glass ceiling'' for blacks, he tells Ditto. Grandfather also orchestrates an illegal trade and gives the credit (and potential jail time) to Marissa Rufo (Alicia Coppola), a bright young broker with a working-class background and a family secret. ''How's she doing?'' she coos into a phone.</p>
        <p>Next to all this, Ditto's bolt from the firm seems like an act of social conscience. Yet when he rallies his friends to join him he sounds as if they are going off to audition for ''A Chorus Line.'' Stanley Tucci is also around, wasted as a character whose villainy is telegraphed with every move but who has been invited to join the new firm anyway.</p>
        <p>''Bull'' does have energy, with a swift style -- noisy, overlapping conversations and constant motion -- that works well for a generation that takes MTV and the Internet for granted. But the half-dozen main characters haven't defined themselves yet, and there's only a glimmer of hope that ''Bull'' will be given time for that to happen. Already, the producers of ''Bull'' and ''The Street'' must be kicking themselves for arriving a season too late. These shows about the Wall Street boom are turning up after technology stocks have tumbled and investors have become jittery. Ditto is young; there's still time for him to go to law school.</p>
        <p>BULL  TNT, tonight at 10</p>
        <p>Michael Chernuchin, Ken Horton and Eric Laneuville, executive producers; Doug Palau, supervising producer; Peter Giuliano and Gay Walch, producers; John Niss, associate producer; Janis Diamond, executive story editor. A production of Nooch Company in association with Warner Bros. Television.</p>
        <p>WITH: George Newbern (Robert ''Ditto'' Roberts III), Malik Yoba (Corey Granville), Ian Kahn (Marty Decker), Christopher Wiehl (Carson Boyd), Alicia Coppola (Marissa Rufo), Elisabeth Rohm (Alison Jeffers), Stanley Tucci (Hunter Lasky) and Donald Moffat (Robert ''the Kaiser'' Roberts).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
