<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Algerian Arraigned in Explosives Smuggling Case</title>
    <meta content="15TERR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haouari, Mokhtar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0D7113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Algerian Arraigned in Explosives Smuggling Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mokhtar Haouari, Algerian charged with helping group trying to smuggle explosives into United States, is arraigned in Federal District Court in Manhattan after arriving from Canada; he pleads not guilty (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mokhtar Haouari, an Algerian charged with helping a group trying to smuggle explosives into the United States, was arraigned in Federal  District Court in Manhattan yesterday afternoon after arriving from Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haouari, who pleaded not guilty at the arraignment, was arrested by Canadian police officers in Montreal on Jan. 10 after he was indicted by a grand jury in New York. After being held in Canada for several months, Mr. Haouari waived extradition proceedings and agreed to come to the United States to stand trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mokhtar Haouari, an Algerian charged with helping a group trying to smuggle explosives into the United States, was arraigned in Federal  District Court in Manhattan yesterday afternoon after arriving from Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haouari, who pleaded not guilty at the arraignment, was arrested by Canadian police officers in Montreal on Jan. 10 after he was indicted by a grand jury in New York. After being held in Canada for several months, Mr. Haouari waived extradition proceedings and agreed to come to the United States to stand trial.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have charged that Mr. Haouari helped another Algerian citizen, Ahmed Ressam, who has been charged with trying to smuggle explosives over the Canadian border in the trunk of his car. On Dec. 14, 1999, Mr. Ressam was stopped by customs agents as he crossed the border by ferry at Port Angeles, Wash.</p>
        <p>According to court papers, customs agents found bags of explosives hidden in the spare tire well of Mr. Ressam's car. Prosecutors said Mr. Ressam tried to run from the customs agents, but they caught him after a brief chase.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haouari has been charged with being a link between Mr. Ressam and another man charged in the case, Abdel Ghani Meskini. According to papers filed by prosecutors, electronic surveillance of Mr. Meskini's telephone in New York ''implicates Haouari and Meskini in a plot to have Meskini meet and assist Ressam in Seattle.''</p>
        <p>According to the papers, in another conversation Mr. Meskini said that both ''Meskini and Mokhtar knew Ressam, that Ressam was part of a well-organized group and that Mokhtar was part of the same 'network.' ''</p>
        <p>In the indictment, prosecutors charged that Mr. Haouari asked Mr. Meskini to travel to Seattle to help Mr. Ressam. Prosecutors also charged that Mr. Haouari provided false identification documents for members and associates of a terrorist group. Among the documents listed by prosecutors were United States immigration identification cards and French and Canadian passports.</p>
        <p>At hearings in Canada last July, Mr. Haouari's lawyer said his client wanted to face the charges as soon as possible. The lawyer said they were confident there was not enough proof to find his client guilty. At yesterday's appearance in Manhattan, Mr. Haouari's lawyer reserved the right to apply for bail later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
