<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tire Company Is Encouraged To Broaden Recall Plans</title>
    <meta content="15TIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Carolina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Condon, Charles M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D8113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tire Company Is Encouraged To Broaden Recall Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plantiffs' lawyers and safety advocates call on Bridgestone/Firestone to considerably widen scope of its recall of tires for sport utility vehicles and pickups; contend that tire maker and Ford Motor are misleading public about safety of many Firestone tires and of Ford Explorers equipped with them; lawyers' statements highlight escalating squabble over how to apportion limited numbers of replacement tires available; Charlie Condon, attorney general of South Carolina, sues Bridgestone, contending that his state should be among first to receive replacement tires, instead of being in recall's third and final tier; Ford and Firestone are trying to steer first batches to Arizona, California, Florida and Texas, where 85 percent of accidents involving tire failure have occured; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Plaintiffs' lawyers and safety advocates called on Bridgestone/Firestone today to considerably widen the scope of its recall of tires for sport utility vehicles and pickups. They contend that the tire maker and Ford Motor were misleading the public about the safety of many Firestone tires and of Ford Explorers equipped with them.</p>
        <p>The lawyers' statements highlighted an escalating squabble over how to apportion the limited numbers of replacement tires available. Ford and Firestone, a unit of the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, have tried to conduct the recall in stages, giving top priority to people in hot-weather states where Firestone's data indicates that its tires are most likely to fail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Plaintiffs' lawyers and safety advocates called on Bridgestone/Firestone today to considerably widen the scope of its recall of tires for sport utility vehicles and pickups. They contend that the tire maker and Ford Motor were misleading the public about the safety of many Firestone tires and of Ford Explorers equipped with them.</p>
        <p>The lawyers' statements highlighted an escalating squabble over how to apportion the limited numbers of replacement tires available. Ford and Firestone, a unit of the Bridgestone Corporation of Japan, have tried to conduct the recall in stages, giving top priority to people in hot-weather states where Firestone's data indicates that its tires are most likely to fail.</p>
        <p>But at a news conference here today, the lawyers and safety advocates urged consumers in all states to immediately replace all Firestone Wilderness AT tires on Ford Explorers, including many tires that have not been recalled.</p>
        <p>Separately, the attorney general of South Carolina, Charlie Condon, sued Bridgestone today, contending that his state should be among the first to receive replacement tires, instead of being in the recall's third and final tier.</p>
        <p>Tire dealers and Ford dealerships across the country have been swamped since last week's recall announcement with people angrily demanding replacement tires.</p>
        <p>Ford and Firestone are trying to steer the first batches to Arizona, California, Florida and Texas, where 85 percent of the accidents involving tire failure have occurred. They want to send the next batches to Oklahoma, Nevada, Alabama, Georgia, Louisiana and Mississippi, which have accounted for another 4 percent of the accidents. Ford and Firestone say there have been very few accidents elsewhere, including virtually none in New York, New Jersey or Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Ken Zino, a Ford spokesman, said that calls for a wider recall ran counter to the longstanding policy of regulators and automakers to give priority to motorists most at risk of injury. He criticized the plaintiffs' lawyers and safety advocates for urging people nationwide to seek immediate replacements of their tires. ''What we're trying to do is precisely the opposite, which is to try to get people to replace bad tires,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tom Baughman, a senior Ford engineer, said that Ford had been having more luck than expected in lining up alternative sources of tires. But replacement tires will remain scarce until at least early September, he said. Christine Karbowiak, a Firestone spokeswoman, said that the company hoped to replace all the recalled tires before next summer, a little faster than the one-year target set last week.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, the tire critics discounted assertions -- some by Ford, some by Firestone, some by both companies -- that problems with the tires resulted from poor manufacturing practices, hot weather, overloaded vehicles or inadequate tire maintenance by motorists.</p>
        <p>Instead, the lawyers and safety advocates accused Ford of doing a poor job of designing the Ford Explorer's suspension and setting technical specifications for the tires. The combination, they said, made the tires more likely to come apart at high speeds and the vehicles more likely to roll over as a result.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a design defect,'' said Joan Claybrook, a former vehicle safety regulator who is now the president of Public Citizen, a safety advocacy group.</p>
        <p>Ford strongly denied that there was anything wrong with the Explorer or the tire specifications. ''We've built Explorers with brands of tires other than Firestones and had absolutely no problems,'' Mr. Baughman said, blaming poor tire quality as the source of the problem.</p>
        <p>Firestone tires not covered by the recall have ''world-class'' safety records, he added, arguing that replacing them with other brands, as the critics proposed, would not improve motorists' safety.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Ford released an analysis of Firestone data showing that very high claims rates for injuries and property damage had been confined to the tires being recalled: 15-inch ATX and ATX II tires of the P235/75R15 size produced at various Firestone factories, and Wilderness AT tires of the same size made at Firestone's factory in Decatur, Ill.</p>
        <p>The lawyers and Public Citizen criticized Ford for not releasing warranty claims information too, and said that all 15-  and 16-inch Wilderness AT tires should be recalled.</p>
        <p>C. Tab Turner, a lawyer in Little Rock, Ark., who has a number of lawsuits filed against both companies, said at the news conference that the call for a wider recall was not motivated by a desire to strengthen plaintiffs in court. Ford has already replaced 16-inch Wilderness tires in hot-weather countries like Saudi Arabia, a fact he said could be used against the company in litigation.</p>
        <p>Firestone estimates that it has made 48 million ATX, ATX II and Wilderness AT tires. Last Wednesday's recall covered 14 million of these tires, but the company estimates that only 6.5 million of them are still in use because the ATX and ATX II tires have not been made since 1996.</p>
        <p>By contrast, most of the 5.6 million 15-inch tires and a large but undetermined number of the 16-inch tires that lawyers want in the recall are likely to be still on the road because they are all Wilderness tires, a brand made only since 1996, when it replaced the ATX and ATX II.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
