<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not All Water Damage Is Equal in Eyes of Insurers</title>
    <meta content="15INSU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D6113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not All Water Damage Is Equal in Eyes of Insurers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Insurance industry officials say that people who lost homes in northern New Jersey to combination of flooding, high winds and fallen trees will be able to receive more in disaster relief than owners of homes just damaged by flooded waters; difference in flood and homeowners insurance discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lucky ones in the flooded hamlets of northern New Jersey may turn out to be the people who suffered the most.</p>
        <p>Most residents in places like Jefferson Township and Newton and Sparta did not have flood insurance, which is offered by the federal government. One example: in Jefferson Township, which has a population of 22,000, 80 homes were covered, federal officials said yesterday. Nearly every home is covered by traditional homeowners' insurance, sold by companies like State Farm and Allstate, but those policies do not cover flood damage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lucky ones in the flooded hamlets of northern New Jersey may turn out to be the people who suffered the most.</p>
        <p>Most residents in places like Jefferson Township and Newton and Sparta did not have flood insurance, which is offered by the federal government. One example: in Jefferson Township, which has a population of 22,000, 80 homes were covered, federal officials said yesterday. Nearly every home is covered by traditional homeowners' insurance, sold by companies like State Farm and Allstate, but those policies do not cover flood damage.</p>
        <p>Clearly, a lot of people will have no one to turn to for help except the federal government if, as expected, it agrees to provide disaster assistance, which is separate from flood insurance and covers far more people. But most of the government aid would be low-interest loans.</p>
        <p>Yet the owners of homes that were damaged not only by the rushing flood waters, but also by winds that knocked out windows or blew down trees that caused damage to the structure, stand a chance of getting money from private insurance companies, industry experts said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The big issue for the insurers is what caused the damage: flood or wind or water. And while the three might seem like a package deal to the layperson, insurers determine the difference by which way the water was going when it hit a house.</p>
        <p>If the water was rising, it is considered a flood, which is covered only by flood insurance. If it was falling -- as rain tends to do -- and somehow got inside a house, say because windows shattered or a tree crashed through the roof, then the damage may be covered by homeowners' insurance.</p>
        <p>Of course, deciding what made everything soggy may, in some cases, require the hair-splitting skills of a philosopher. Even if a tree fell on a roof, a claims adjuster might say, the tree fell because its roots were washed away by the flood, meaning the result was caused by the work of rising water.</p>
        <p>Residents of northern New Jersey are not unlike most Americans when it comes to flood insurance. Federal insurance officials say that only a quarter of Americans living in the most dangerous flood zones, along ocean coasts and the banks of rivers like the Mississippi, have flood insurance.</p>
        <p>The percentage of purchasers is much lower where there is less risk, in places like Jefferson Township. ''People think, 'Well, it hasn't flooded here in years, I'll just take my chances,' ''said Mark Stevens, a spokesman for the National Flood Insurance Program in Washington. '' 'And if worst comes to worst,' they say, 'shucks, the Feds will come and bail us out.' '' But most floods are too small to qualify for federal help, he said, and thus victims without flood insurance get nothing. The people who are least likely to buy flood insurance, the authorities say, are ones like those who live in northern New Jersey, most of which is not regarded as a flood plain. But the federal flood officials argue that except for those living on mountain tops, almost everyone should have the coverage, which is essentially sold at cost.</p>
        <p>''You don't expect to have a fire in your house, but you buy fire insurance,'' said Carol Hector-Harris, a spokeswoman in New York for the Federal Emergency Management Agency, which oversees the flood insurance program.</p>
        <p>Flood insurance costs about $300 per $100,000 of coverage.</p>
        <p>The average homeowners' policy for a $150,000 house in New Jersey costs $463 a year. Adding flood insurance would roughly double the cost, which may explain why so many people forego it.</p>
        <p>But John Tiene, the executive director of the Insurance Council of New Jersey, a trade group in Trenton, said, ''The biggest reason is that people just don't think they're ever going to need it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
