<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Magnet for Explorers, Spiritualists and the Stars</title>
    <meta content="15KAKU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tibet</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schell, Orville</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Virtual Tibet (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Tibet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EED9103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Magnet for Explorers, Spiritualists and the Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews book Virtual Tibet: Searching for Shangri-La From the Himalayas to Hollywood by Orville Schell; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VIRTUAL TIBET  Searching for Shangri-La  From the Himalayas to Hollywood  By Orville Schell  340 pages. Metropolitan Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $26.</p>
        <p>Over the centuries, Tibet has been mythologized in the Western imagination as a magical, utopian realm. For 19th-century explorers trying to scale the daunting peaks of the Himalayas, it was a kind of alluring El Dorado -- one of the great unmapped places of the world, a place whose very isolation endowed it with a frisson of mystery and allure. For spiritualists like Alexandra David-Neel, who journeyed to Lhasa in 1924, it was a fairy tale realm where lamas practiced magic and astral projection. And for readers of James Hilton's 1933 novel ''Lost Horizon,'' Tibet was the inspiration for the never-never land of Shangri-La, a refuge from a desperate world, a paradise where nothing was wanting and no one ever grew old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VIRTUAL TIBET  Searching for Shangri-La  From the Himalayas to Hollywood  By Orville Schell  340 pages. Metropolitan Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $26.</p>
        <p>Over the centuries, Tibet has been mythologized in the Western imagination as a magical, utopian realm. For 19th-century explorers trying to scale the daunting peaks of the Himalayas, it was a kind of alluring El Dorado -- one of the great unmapped places of the world, a place whose very isolation endowed it with a frisson of mystery and allure. For spiritualists like Alexandra David-Neel, who journeyed to Lhasa in 1924, it was a fairy tale realm where lamas practiced magic and astral projection. And for readers of James Hilton's 1933 novel ''Lost Horizon,'' Tibet was the inspiration for the never-never land of Shangri-La, a refuge from a desperate world, a paradise where nothing was wanting and no one ever grew old.</p>
        <p>In his highly uneven new book, ''Virtual Tibet,'' Orville Schell, dean of the Graduate School of Journalism at the University of California, Berkeley, and the author of several books on China, attempts to assess the role that Tibet has played in the fantasy life of the West.</p>
        <p>Although his chapters dealing with historical material have been energetically researched and make for engaging reading, the remainder of the book (detailing Hollywood's relationship with Tibet) is flawed by strangely fuzzy thinking. There are inane interviews with such ''Buddhists'' as Oliver Stone, the director of ''Natural Born Killers,'' and the action actor Steven Seagal, who once played ''a C.I.A. agent turned cop with a Buddhist bent.'' There are also long, self-indulgent accounts of Mr. Schell's visits to the movie set of ''Seven Years in Tibet,'' accounts that attempt to draw strained analogies between the fantasies the public projects on movie stars like Brad Pitt (the star of that movie) and the fantasies it has projected on Tibet.</p>
        <p>It is Mr. Schell's thesis that Tibet's isolation and, for many years, its inaccessibility turned it into a blank screen on which Westerners could project their wildest imaginings. In the years before air travel, the very difficulty of getting to the holy city of Lhasa made it a challenge to explorers, while the reluctance of Tibetans to welcome outsiders galvanized the urge of these adventurers ''to transgress forbidden places.''</p>
        <p>As the West grew increasingly industrialized and embarked on two world wars, Tibet also became a magnet for those weary of civilization and its discontents: the country's spectacular Himalayan vistas acquired a kind of religious significance, even as the land came to fill the need of Westerners ''to imagine a peaceful, spiritual, serene country, at once beautiful and removed.''</p>
        <p>Culling through the eclectic writings on Tibet left by explorers, missionaries and spiritual pilgrims, Mr. Schell gives the reader an entertaining account of the disparate Westerners who made their way to Lhasa, or tried. We are introduced to Father Ippolito Desideri, a Jesuit priest who arrived in Lhasa in 1716 after a harrowing trip across the Himalayas and who left the first comprehensive account by a Westerner of life in Tibet; Col. Nikolai Mikhailovich Przhevalsky, a Russian explorer who embarked upon five grueling and unsuccessful expeditions to reach Lhasa and eventually died of typhus on the way; and Mr. and Mrs. St. George Littledale, who set off from India in 1894 with their fox terrier, Tanny, and came within 70 miles of their quest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schell discusses the heroic efforts of such Indian cartographers as Nain Singh and Sarat Chandra Das to map the wilderness of Tibet, and recounts the efforts of eccentric spiritualists like Helena Petrovna von Hahn -- a k a Madame Blavatsky -- to promote Tibet as the epicenter of a new spiritualism. ''The ensuing Western infatuation with Tibet and its form of Buddhism was somewhat reminiscent of the idealization of China by the physiocrats and philosophes during the French Enlightenment,'' Mr. Schell writes. ''Only then, Europeans admired China's practicality and rationality whereas now they admired Tibet's propensity for the irrational and supernatural.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, as Tibetans under Chinese rule have tried to focus world attention on their plight, they have forsaken their once willful isolation. The attention of Hollywood and New Age seekers is welcomed, even cultivated, as is the attention of the press. ''Like a river that has reversed its course,'' Mr. Schell observes, ''Tibetans now desperately turn outward rather than inward.''</p>
        <p>The problem is that such provocative historical analysis is intercut in ''Virtual Tibet'' with long-winded chapters on the making of the movie adaptation of ''Seven Years in Tibet'' that read like outtakes from a hastily written magazine piece.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schell spends an enormous amount of space talking about his negotiations with movie publicists to visit the set in Argentina, where the Andes were used as a stand-in for the Himalayas. Worse, he jokily compares his difficulties in gaining access to the movie set to the hardships suffered by early adventurers trying to make it across the Himalayas to Tibet. Elsewhere, in a discussion of ''Tibet's evolving mythology,'' he callously lumps together the old Western myth of a ''paradisiacal Tibet'' with the current Western view of the land as a spiritual society ''crushed under the jackboot of an aggressive materialist overlord,'' as though both notions were equally projections of ''the popular imagination of the West.''</p>
        <p>In the end, such glibly tossed-off observations distract attention from the more serious aspects of this book, and cast an unnecessary shadow over Mr. Schell's more thoughtful observations.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
