<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bradley Urges His Delegates To Back Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y15BRA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE FORMER RIVAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D6113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bradley Urges His Delegates To Back Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Sen Bill Bradley, in last symbolic act of his failed presidential campaign, releases his 390 delegates to Vice Pres Al Gore, urging them to set aside hard feelings and support Democratic ticket; says Gore will stand up for things they fought for in campaign; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the last symbolic act of his failed presidential campaign, former Senator Bill Bradley released his 390 delegates to Vice President Al Gore today, telling them that ''Al Gore will stand for the things we fought for in our campaign, and he deserves our support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley gave a speech that echoed his stump appearances of the winter, praising the ''goodness of the American people'' and called for universal health care, overhauling the campaign finance system and programs for the poor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the last symbolic act of his failed presidential campaign, former Senator Bill Bradley released his 390 delegates to Vice President Al Gore today, telling them that ''Al Gore will stand for the things we fought for in our campaign, and he deserves our support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley gave a speech that echoed his stump appearances of the winter, praising the ''goodness of the American people'' and called for universal health care, overhauling the campaign finance system and programs for the poor.</p>
        <p>Then, recalling an event last month where he formally endorsed Mr. Gore, Mr. Bradley encouraged his supporters to set aside their hard feelings about the bitterly contested primary and work hard for the Democratic ticket.</p>
        <p>''Winning is a team sport,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''We have to win in the fall. The stakes are large. The Supreme Court. Social Security at a crossroads. And what happens when the budget surplus is up for grabs.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Bradley's remarks, William M. Daley, Mr. Gore's campaign chairman, praised Mr. Bradley as ''a special person'' who had a ''unique understanding of America.''</p>
        <p>''To honor him is to make sure that the sort of things he talked about get implemented,'' Mr. Daley said. ''For that, we need your strong support for Al Gore and Joe Lieberman.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley noted that Mr. Bradley often took ''controversial positions'' that ''may have caused him problems in the short term, but in the long term are the right positions.'' Paradoxically, Mr. Gore attacked Mr. Bradley during the primary campaign for taking positions that did not conform to Democratic orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley is to address the convention on Tuesday night. He will call for ''a new kind of politics'' that is more optimistic, his aides said. But they said he would not shy from criticizing the Republican agenda.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley contends that he pushed Mr. Gore into taking stronger positions on health care, gun control, child poverty and changing the campaign finance system. And many of Mr. Gore's aides acknowledge that Mr. Bradley's challenge made Mr. Gore a better campaigner.</p>
        <p>Many of the delegates said they would work enthusiastically for Mr. Gore, if only out of fear that voting for Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, or not voting at all, would lead to a Bush victory.</p>
        <p>''People don't want Gore to lose,'' said David Loebsack, a professor of political science at Cornell College in Iowa and a Bradley delegate. ''There is a real difference between Gore and the Republican ticket.''</p>
        <p>But Cornel West, a Harvard professor who is close to Mr. Bradley, said there was still wariness among some Bradley supporters toward Mr. Gore and his centrist agenda.</p>
        <p>''Bradley still hasn't had his due,'' Mr. West said. ''It's clear we still don't have two clear choices in this race.''</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE FORMER RIVAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
