<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="15DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2D9113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks Stage Late Rally As Concerns Ease on Rates  Stocks staged a late-day rally as Wall Street bet that the Federal Reserve would keep interest rates steady next week after more than a year of tapping on the brakes to slow dynamic economic growth in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average climbed 148.34 points, or 1.4 percent, to 11,176.14, its highest finish since April 11. The Nasdaq composite index, weighted with technology shares, rose 60.22 points, or 1.6 percent, to 3,849.69, while the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 19.72 points, or 1.3 percent, to 1,491.56. [Page C12.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks Stage Late Rally As Concerns Ease on Rates  Stocks staged a late-day rally as Wall Street bet that the Federal Reserve would keep interest rates steady next week after more than a year of tapping on the brakes to slow dynamic economic growth in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average climbed 148.34 points, or 1.4 percent, to 11,176.14, its highest finish since April 11. The Nasdaq composite index, weighted with technology shares, rose 60.22 points, or 1.6 percent, to 3,849.69, while the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 19.72 points, or 1.3 percent, to 1,491.56. [Page C12.]</p>
        <p>$5.3 Billion Deal for Chris-Craft  The News Corporation confirmed that it had agreed to acquire Chris-Craft Industries, which owns 10 TV stations, for about $85 a share in stock and cash, or $5.3 billion. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Quarterly Loss Widens at Sunbeam  Sunbeam, the maker of small appliances, posted a wider second-quarter loss and said it would sell its Oster barber, beauty and animal-grooming products business. Shares of Sunbeam fell 16 percent. The loss was Sunbeam's 10th consecutive quarterly loss. Shares of Sunbeam fell 43.75 cents, to $2.1875. Sunbeam has $2.4 billion in debt, with $1.5 billion of that owed to banks. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Little Progress in Verizon Strike  Negotiators made little progress on the ninth day of the 12-state strike against Verizon Communications as unions and the company debated the worker impact of the recent merger that made Verizon the nation's largest telecommunications employer. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Creditors Back Hyundai Revamping  South Korean creditors agreed to support a revamping of the Hyundai Group, the country's largest conglomerate, which plans to sell assets and spin off two profitable affiliates. [C4.]</p>
        <p>De Beers to Buy Canadian Company  De Beers Consolidated Mines, the South African giant of the global diamond industry, won control of a promising company in Canada, agreeing to its demands for a higher price after a seven-week takeover struggle. The Canadian company, Winspear, owns a potentially lucrative underwater diamond deposit at Snap Lake in the Northwest Territories. [C4.]</p>
        <p>WPP Group Reports Profit Surge  WPP Group, which will become the world's largest advertising firm with its acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam, reported a surge in profits and revenue and forecast that the boom in advertising spending would last through the end of the year, buoyed by the Olympics and the presidential elections in the United States. Sir Martin Sorrell, WPP's chief executive, sought to counter concerns that an expected slowdown in Internet advertising spending would dent growth prospects. [C4.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Inventories Rose 0.9% in June  The nation's companies, still trying to keep up with robust sales, increased inventories in June by a strong 0.9 percent, government figures showed. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Toy 'R' Us Earnings Fall 75%  Toys ''R'' Us, the largest United States toy chain, said its second-quarter profit fell 75 percent on declining sales in its United States stores and a loss at its Internet division. [C13.]</p>
        <p>A Cafe au Lait and an Advertisement  A French start-up company has begun placing ads on the surface of cafe tables, risking the wrath of a society that takes its cafes very seriously. ''What a horror,'' said a customer, Camille Mouries, a librarian, pointing to a colorful Siemens ad under the glass at her table. Advertising. [C10.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
