<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cranberry Bog Settlement Draws Environmentalists' Fire</title>
    <meta content="15CRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cranberries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demarco, J Garfield</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDA113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cranberry Bog Settlement Draws Environmentalists' Fire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Agreement between NJ State Environmental Protection Department and politically prominent cranberry farmer J Garfield DeMarco is drawing mixed reviews, trumpeted by regulators as 'largest settlement ever' with someone who ran afoul of wetlands protection laws and scorned by environmental groups as 'sellout' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An agreement among state environmental officials and a politically prominent cranberry farmer is drawing mixed reviews, trumpeted by regulators as ''the largest settlement ever'' with someone who ran afoul of wetlands protection laws and scorned by environmental groups as a ''sellout.''</p>
        <p>Announced late last week, the agreement between the State Environmental Protection Department and the cranberry farming concern owned by J. Garfield DeMarco lays to rest charges that the DeMarco operation had illegally and without a permit expanded its cranberry bogs into 22 acres of protected wetlands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An agreement among state environmental officials and a politically prominent cranberry farmer is drawing mixed reviews, trumpeted by regulators as ''the largest settlement ever'' with someone who ran afoul of wetlands protection laws and scorned by environmental groups as a ''sellout.''</p>
        <p>Announced late last week, the agreement between the State Environmental Protection Department and the cranberry farming concern owned by J. Garfield DeMarco lays to rest charges that the DeMarco operation had illegally and without a permit expanded its cranberry bogs into 22 acres of protected wetlands.</p>
        <p>Without admitting any guilt, Mr. DeMarco, the former Republican leader of Burlington County, agreed to donate 74 acres of land to the state and give up all development rights to 591 additional acres that he owns.</p>
        <p>''This settlement amply compensates for any ecological damage done by the unpermitted conversion of the 22 acres to cranberry bogs,'' said Ray Cantor, an official of the department. ''This should make it clear to everyone that protection of wetlands is a serious priority to the department.'' The penalty that could have been levied, $300,000, qualifies the settlement as the largest yet under wetlands law, Mr. Cantor said.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists rejected the settlement as an ''outrageous giveaway'' to Mr. DeMarco. For one thing, said Bill Wolf, policy director of the Sierra Club, state records indicated that DeMarco Enterprises had already been paid $691,000 by another state agency, the Pinelands Development Credit Bank, for agreeing not to develop the same 591 acres that figured in the settlement with the environmental department.</p>
        <p>The environmental protection commissioner, Robert C. Shinn, is on the Pinelands Development Credit Bank board, though it is separate from the agency. Mr. Cantor confirmed that the Pinelands bank had paid Mr. DeMarco's company the money for the development credits, but said the settlement with his agency put more restrictions on what he could do with the 591 acres.</p>
        <p>Under state law, Mr. DeMarco could still have used the land for cranberry and blueberry farming and even allowed the construction of farm buildings. ''But under our settlement, it will stay virtually pristine and he can't use it for agricultural purposes, building a house or even cutting down trees, beyond what is necessary to protect it from fire,'' Mr. Cantor said.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Tittel, a spokesman for the Sierra Club, said Mr. DeMarco ''got away better than free'' in the transactions. ''Not only did he not have to pay a fine for illegally expanding into 22 acres of wetlands, the taxpayers of the state wound up handing him a check for $691,000,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The United States Fish and Wildlife Service criticized other parts of the settlement that would allow Mr. DeMarco to continue producing cranberries on the disputed 22 acres as long as he applies to the state for the permit that was required in the first place. The federal agency, which has long opposed state willingness to expand cranberry acreage, said allowing the farmer to seek a permit now was ''compromising'' the wetlands preservation laws' intent.</p>
        <p>Anthony Drollas, the lawyer for DeMarco Enterprises, said the 74 acres that Mr. DeMarco was donating to the state was land that it would have otherwise bought from him.  And the amount he received from the state not to develop his land was 60 percent of what he could have realized had he sold his credits on the open market to a developer elsewhere in the state.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. DeMarco had business dealings with Mr. Shinn when he ran an agricultural equipment company in Burlington County, Mr. Shinn had recused himself from any role in enforcement actions against DeMarco Enterprises.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
