<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind the Glittery Scene, Much Nothing About a Do</title>
    <meta content="Y15SUR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE NEWS MEDIA -- POLITICAL SURFING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4D6113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind the Glittery Scene, Much Nothing About a Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on coverage of opening night of Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles by news media (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody wanted to go behind the scenes today at the Democratic National Convention, at least during the long hours before President Clinton's address. (Tom Brokaw described it as ''the political equivalent of Elvis's last concert.'')</p>
        <p>Everywhere you looked on television or on the World Wide Web, people were promising to take you backstage, past the security guards, beyond the tall hedges of those Brentwood estates where the glitterati were celebrating their wonderfulness and where, presumably, all the really juicy stuff was going on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everybody wanted to go behind the scenes today at the Democratic National Convention, at least during the long hours before President Clinton's address. (Tom Brokaw described it as ''the political equivalent of Elvis's last concert.'')</p>
        <p>Everywhere you looked on television or on the World Wide Web, people were promising to take you backstage, past the security guards, beyond the tall hedges of those Brentwood estates where the glitterati were celebrating their wonderfulness and where, presumably, all the really juicy stuff was going on.</p>
        <p>But if today's reports were any indication, the convention is a lot like Hollywood, with nothing behind the scenery but plywood, sawdust and a snoozing gaffer.</p>
        <p>The National Journal, on its Web page, followed Rod O'Connor, the convention's chief operating officer and ''a moving target for favor seekers of all sorts.'' Mr. O'Connor's day began at 8 a.m., with a staff meeting at the Staples Center. At 8:45, he and the communications staff discussed the message of the day. At 9:15, there was the first official media briefing, and the whining began.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connor promised to help smooth the ''check-in crush'' of journalists waiting to get into the convention. At 10, he was cornered by a staff member from Speakout.com, which was upset about its placement in the media center. At 11:15, meeting with the hall management staff, Mr. O'Connor had to figure out how to get more local media people onto the podium, at least briefly.</p>
        <p>At a another staff meeting, Mr. O'Connor had to parcel out skyboxes for opening night. ''Let's give B-3 to the mayor,'' he decided. His cell phone rang. A major campaign donor wanted tickets for Thursday. Mr. O'Connor made soothing noises.</p>
        <p>''This is the whole business of the convention here,'' he told The National Journal. ''You try to sift out what people really need as opposed to what they'd like to have.''</p>
        <p>The convention got under way with speeches that were noticeably more partisan than those that characterized the first two days of the recent Republican event. ''We have something we can argue about,'' the Clinton strategist James Carville told MSNBC. ''I think that's fine.''</p>
        <p>The pugnacious theme continued into the evening when Fox News roamed the convention floor to chat with actual delegates. A Michigan teacher was found carrying a cardboard cut-out of Elvis that he hoped to get Mr. Clinton to autograph. ''Elvis is alive and well in Michigan, as is education,'' said the delegate.</p>
        <p>Several Web pages featured their Hollywood party reports, promising to take us into those exclusive enclaves. Long gone, apparently, are the days when starlets jumped nude into the swimming pool while Errol Flynn got into a fistfight at the bar. Yes, the reports were filled with bold-faced names and the sound of Champagne corks popping, but there was a noticeable scarcity of juice.</p>
        <p>MSNBC's Jeannette Walls went to a party at the Playboy mansion and found that some of the well-known names in attendance did not wish to be photographed in such a place. And the Bunnies were off limits, too.</p>
        <p>''These girls are working,'' beefy  guards warned reporters. ''They're not here to be interviewed. They're here to mingle with the guests.''</p>
        <p>Joe Eszterhas, the screenwriter of ''Showgirls'' and author of ''American Rhapsody,'' wrote in Salon.com that Hollywood was of two minds about the nomination of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, a well-known critic of violence and sex in movies, as Vice President Al Gore's running mate. Should they shun him for fear of their livelihoods, or embrace him as better than a Republican?</p>
        <p>''This was a quandary worse than whether to pay Adam Sandler 20 mil for his next picture,'' Mr. Eszterhas explained.</p>
        <p>Stuart Rothenberg of CNN decided that the Democratic convention was structured pretty much like the Republican one, to deflect attention from the party's weak points.</p>
        <p>''Democrats gathering in Los Angeles are being treated to a strong dose of religion, morality and character,'' Mr. Rothenberg wrote. ''Welcome to Bizarro World, where each party addresses its weaknesses and hopes to neutralize its opponents' advantages.''</p>
        <p>So pay no attention to the man behind the curtain. It's just another day in Bizarro World.</p>
        <p>And whatever you do, don't go near the Bunnies.</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS: THE NEWS MEDIA -- POLITICAL SURFING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
