<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Assembly Race, Power of Incumbency Vies With a Household Name</title>
    <meta content="15PRIM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORK PRIMARY -- 68th Assembly District" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denis, Nelson Antonio (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Adam Clayton 4th</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2D7113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Assembly Race, Power of Incumbency Vies With a Household Name</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series on upcoming New York primary contests examines close battle in Manhattan's 68th Assembly district between incumbent Assemblyman Nelson Antonio Denis and former city Councilman Adam Clayton Powell 4th; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of unsuccessful campaigns in the rough-and-tumble politics of East Harlem, usually losing by a hair, Nelson Antonio Denis finally won a seat in the Assembly in 1996. Establishing himself as a reformer and an articulate debater, he coasted easily to re-election two years later.</p>
        <p>While many Manhattan politicians anticipated that Mr. Denis would have another comfortable election this year, the assemblyman is instead facing a formidable race. Over the last month an opponent has emerged in the Democratic primary: former City Councilman Adam Clayton Powell 4th.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years of unsuccessful campaigns in the rough-and-tumble politics of East Harlem, usually losing by a hair, Nelson Antonio Denis finally won a seat in the Assembly in 1996. Establishing himself as a reformer and an articulate debater, he coasted easily to re-election two years later.</p>
        <p>While many Manhattan politicians anticipated that Mr. Denis would have another comfortable election this year, the assemblyman is instead facing a formidable race. Over the last month an opponent has emerged in the Democratic primary: former City Councilman Adam Clayton Powell 4th.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell, 38, the son of the late Harlem congressman, represented much of the same area of Manhattan in the City Council for six years, before leaving that body at the end of 1997. Mr. Powell decided not to seek re-election to the Council, instead taking on an unsuccessful race for Manhattan borough president. He came in third in a field of six candidates in the Democratic primary.</p>
        <p>Despite that loss, Mr. Powell's name is one of the most recognized in Manhattan and this Assembly district is virtually a stone's throw from the prominent Harlem boulevard that bears his famous father's name.</p>
        <p>The primary in the 68th Assembly District is being watched closely by politicians in Manhattan because it will test how firm a grip Mr. Denis has developed on incumbency. Long the political outsider fighting established officials, the 45-year-old assemblyman is now the incumbent who regularly bombards district residents with mailings chock full of news of his stewardship. Mr. Powell is now the outsider as he seeks to regain his political footing.</p>
        <p>The two men agree on a number of issues. Both speak about the need for increased financial support from Albany for New York City's schools.</p>
        <p>The two men agree on a number of issues. Both speak about the need for increased financial support from Albany for New York City's schools. And they speak about the need to provide increased housing for poor and elderly residents of the district, and about the need to get aid from the state to jumpstart the economic health of the district.</p>
        <p>What they disagree on is on the fitness of the other to serve in the Assembly.</p>
        <p>''A lot of the people in the district have been asking me to get back into political leadership,'' Mr. Powell said in an interview. ''They try calling his office and no one even answers the phone. We have someone in Nelson Denis who is missing in action. I can help the people in this area to get decent representation.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Powell's candidacy centers on one basic theme: that Mr. Denis is inattentive to the needs of the district and does a poor job serving his constituents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Denis in turn described Mr. Powell's candidacy as one lacking in rationale. He said that, while Mr. Powell might enjoy great name recognition, he lacked the leadership ability to be effective. He also said that Mr. Powell's 1997 endorsement of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani would not sit well with the voters in this heavily Democratic district.</p>
        <p>''It's an interesting paradox,'' Mr. Denis said. ''You have a very full legacy of one of the most effective legislators in history,'' he said of Mr. Powell's father. ''But then you have the son, who is trading on that. Adam is running on fumes. There is no gas there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Denis, countering Mr. Powell's criticisms, said he has been responsible for increased financial support from Albany to programs in the district ranging from health clinics to cultural organizations. ''We have served the people of this community in housing, in welfare, in sanitation concerns,'' Mr. Denis said. ''My office has set a standard for constituent services.''</p>
        <p>In the years since he left the Council, Mr. Powell has worked most recently with the Federal Emergency Management Agency as a disaster assistance field worker. Immediately after his Council term ended, he turned to political consulting and real estate development in Puerto Rico, where he was born and raised.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Powell might be helped by political legacy, Mr. Denis has roots that are deep in the community, too. A graduate of Harvard University and Yale Law School, Mr. Denis worked as director of strategic planning with the Harlem Community Development Corporation before being elected. On the weekends, he operated a free legal clinic for neighborhood residents. He twice lost attempts to unseat Angelo Del Toro, the East Harlem assemblyman who died in 1995, coming within 160 votes in 1994.</p>
        <p>Mr. Denis and Mr. Powell have had a political relationship characterized by a series of hot and cold phases. Some years ago, they were strong political allies who worked for each other's various campaigns. But, after a series of disagreements, they are now in a decidedly icy phase.</p>
        <p>The 68th Assembly District is anchored in East Harlem, although it includes a small pocket on the Upper West Side. The district is roughly half Hispanic and about 40 percent black, with non-Hispanic white residents making up most of the rest.</p>
        <p>The contest promises to be one not likely to be remembered for civility. Already, Mr. Powell's campaign literature talks about how he has spent the last few years assisting people who were beset by disasters. Now, a campaign flier states, Mr. Powell is back ''to help the people of our community cope with a disaster closer to home'' -- referring to Mr. Denis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Denis said he has already raised $25,000 for the race, about double what he spent two years ago. Mr. Powell said he has raised nearly $20,000. Both men say they might well raise another $10,000 or more.</p>
        <p>There are two other candidates in the primary: Frank Acosta, a local businessman who ran against Mr. Denis two years ago, and Walter Torres, who was once a political ally of Mr. Denis's. In a tight race, the presence of additional candidates could well affect the outcome.</p>
        <p>Still, both Mr. Powell and Mr. Denis say they see themselves as the front-runner.</p>
        <p>''The reality,'' Mr. Powell contends, ''is that I can't see how the other guy wins. I'm not the average insurgent.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Denis says that every race he has undertaken has been difficult, and that he expects this one to be no different.</p>
        <p>''I approach every race as though I am running from behind,'' he said. ''Although, in this one, I'm really in front.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PRIMARY  68th Assembly District</p>
        <p>Articles in this series will examine individual primary contests in Congressional and local districts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
