<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="15OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comet Linear-S4</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brown University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johns Hopkins University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1DF133FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Research on using class of ceramics known as complex oxides to store nuclear wastes noted; Comet Linear observations described; Johns Hopkins and Brown University scientists report finding 'folds' in Jupiter's icy moon Europa (Observatory column) (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Safer Nuclear Waste</p>
        <p>High-level nuclear waste in storage is like an unruly guest in a tidy house. The material that's  used to contain the waste -- be it glass, ceramic or whatever -- owes its strength and stability to its orderly structure, with every atom in its proper place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Safer Nuclear Waste</p>
        <p>High-level nuclear waste in storage is like an unruly guest in a tidy house. The material that's  used to contain the waste -- be it glass, ceramic or whatever -- owes its strength and stability to its orderly structure, with every atom in its proper place.</p>
        <p>Decaying waste, like used fuel from nuclear reactors, upsets the structure: it produces radiation that causes atoms to shift, creating defects that can eventually lead to cracks or other problems that can affect safety. Indeed, most storage containers are designed to last only a century or so.</p>
        <p>Now, scientists from Los Alamos National Laboratory and universities in Britain and Japan say that a class of ceramics known as complex oxides may hold promise for longer-term waste storage. The key, they say, is that this material is not so fastidious: it can tolerate radiation-induced defects.</p>
        <p>The scientists, who reported on their work in the journal Science, first created computer simulations of the effects of radiation on these materials, and then tested them in the laboratory. They found that one kind of complex oxide ceramic, similar in structure to the mineral fluorite, was relatively disordered to begin with. When radiation starts to monkey with it, its atoms can shift to accommodate the defects with relative ease.</p>
        <p>The researchers suggest that similar materials beyond those that they studied may also be radiation resistant. In any case, much more work remains before a satisfactory solution to the problem of long-term storage of waste is achieved.</p>
        <p>Rare View of a Comet</p>
        <p>The celestial soap opera that is Comet Linear continues.</p>
        <p>In our last episode, the comet, after disappointing backyard star gazers, seemed to be fizzling to oblivion. As Linear made its closest approach to the Sun late last month, the heat had caused the comet's nucleus to bubble and blow apart, leaving what astronomers thought was just a cloud of dust.</p>
        <p>But not so fast. While Linear will never be a recurring character like other comets, it's not dead yet. The Hubble Space Telescope and the European Southern Observatory's Very Large Telescope in Chile have observed a group of tiny comets left behind as Linear came apart.</p>
        <p>There are about a dozen of these ''comettes,'' each consisting of a small piece of the original nucleus, perhaps 100 feet or so in diameter, with a tiny tail. While these objects may eventually disintegrate completely, before they do they may provide insight into the comet's original structure. Such a cometary breakup has never been seen in such detail before now.</p>
        <p>Puzzle of a Jupiter Moon</p>
        <p>For the past several decades, scientists have been intrigued by cracks and other signs of stretching on the surface of Jupiter's icy moon Europa. But the scientists have been puzzled by what may be considered a lack of give and take -- that is, stretching in one area of Europa must result in squeezing elsewhere, but no solid evidence of such compression had been discovered.</p>
        <p>But now, scientists from Johns Hopkins and Brown, examining images taken by the Galileo spacecraft, have uncovered what they say are folds in Europa's surface caused by compression, like the ripples in cardboard.</p>
        <p>A high-resolution image of one part of the surface, taken when the Sun was at a low angle, shows subtle shading of a fold's hills and valleys. Other images show cracks on the tops of the hills and small ridges in the valleys, kinds of structures that would be expected in a rippled surface.</p>
        <p>The scientists, writing in Science, suggest that tidal forces within Europa caused the compressional folding, and that the amplitude of the folds was originally much greater -- the hills were higher and the valleys lower. But over time, because of relatively warmer conditions below the surface, the folds relaxed, leaving the faint structures hardly visible today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
