<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Daily Rhythm, a Lifetime Passion</title>
    <meta content="15ARCH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaelogy and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lydian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Silver</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sardis (Turkey)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cornell University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramage, Andrew (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenewalt, Crawford H Jr (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Silver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D7103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Daily Rhythm, a Lifetime Passion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <dateline>SARDIS, Turkey</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Work of archaeologists at Harvard-Cornell Sardis Expedition in western Turkey this summer described; photos of Drs Crawford H Grenewalt Jr and Andrew Ramage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After first light, though not by much, the encampment of archaeologists wakes to the cooing of doves in the pines, the barking of dogs and the early call to prayer from a mosque down the valley.</p>
        <p>Everyone, some 20 professors and students straggling into the dining room, has hot tea, bread and cheese and some fruit. By 7 a.m., they scatter to their pottery shards and marble inscriptions in the laboratory, to the trenches into the scant remains of the city of a famously rich king, Croesus of Lydia, who lived more than 2,500 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After first light, though not by much, the encampment of archaeologists wakes to the cooing of doves in the pines, the barking of dogs and the early call to prayer from a mosque down the valley.</p>
        <p>Everyone, some 20 professors and students straggling into the dining room, has hot tea, bread and cheese and some fruit. By 7 a.m., they scatter to their pottery shards and marble inscriptions in the laboratory, to the trenches into the scant remains of the city of a famously rich king, Croesus of Lydia, who lived more than 2,500 years ago.</p>
        <p>They work in the intense heat till noon. Back at the compound called excavation house, spartan but old-shoe comfortable, they lunch and rest, and it is off again at two o'clock to their tasks. The day's work ends around five, in time for tea and chatter about this or that spadeful of triumph or mystery. A visitor is interrogated about news from home, mostly important things like baseball standings.</p>
        <p>After showers (only cold) and a change into fresh shorts and T-shirts, everyone relaxes, reading or recording notes on the day. Dusk brings a gentle breeze and the cocktail hour, followed by dinner at nine, about an hour or two before bedtime.</p>
        <p>This daily rhythm of a summer's dig by the Harvard-Cornell Sardis Expedition has been repeated with little variation since 1958. Some archaeologists and their students come and go. But the continuity is maintained in part because so many of them, who cut their teeth on archaeology here, keep coming back. It has become a professional home, and the search for Croesus a consuming passion.</p>
        <p>At dinner, Dr. Crawford H. Greenewalt Jr., the expedition's field director, looks down the table like a paterfamilias and sees three generations of the Sardis family -- his own, former students who are now professors themselves and a new crop of aspiring archaeologists. Few archaeology projects last so long.</p>
        <p>Dr. Greenewalt and Dr. Andrew Ramage, the associate director, are the first generation. They were students at Harvard when Dr. George M. A. Hanfmann, a professor there, started the first excavations 42 years ago. Now Dr. Greenewalt, who succeeded Dr. Hanfmann in 1977, is a professor of classical archaeology at the University of California at Berkeley. Dr. Ramage is an archaeologist at Cornell. And students they trained years ago have become senior archaeologists for the expedition.</p>
        <p>Dr. Geenewalt motions toward Dr. Nicholas Cahill of the University of Wisconsin, one of his students who kept coming back and is now in charge of excavations of the Lydian city wall. Another student, Dr. Christopher Ratte of New York University, worked the site for many seasons and has moved on to direct excavations at Aphrodisias, a Greco-Roman site in western Turkey. He paid a visit one afternoon, and it was like a family reunion, the exchange of news and the baby pictures passed around.</p>
        <p>Younger faces at the dinner table belong to the third generation in the Sardis genealogy. Elizabeth Baughan, a doctoral student at Berkeley, is digging through pavements of a Roman road in search of another stretch of the more deeply buried Lydian wall. Christopher Roosevelt, working for his doctorate at Cornell, is excavating the city's eastern wall and developing computer programs for plotting settlement patterns in ancient Lydia beyond Sardis.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ramage says this kind of continuity may be passing from the field.</p>
        <p>''The sort of large-scale projects that run for years are not easily funded,'' he explains. ''It is much less frequent that people come to a site and become so thoroughly immersed. The practice now is to conduct more targeted work with limited objectives.''</p>
        <p>Looming behind the excavation house, some 1,000 feet above the rest of Sardis, is the acropolis, a mountaintop citadel of Croesus and subsequent rulers. Alexander the Great once stood there for a view of the city he had won without a fight.</p>
        <p>Dr. Donald Sullivan, a geographer at the University of Denver, goes there often to survey the valley looking for mounds or subtle changes in vegetation, anything hinting at likely places for new exploration. In particular, he is looking for evidence that the ancient Hermus River once flowed closer to the Lydian capital. He then takes cores in the valley, plots them on a map and finds that, indeed, the river once flowed nearer to the city walls.</p>
        <p>The climb to the acropolis summit is literally and figuratively breathtaking. Amid the crumbling ramparts and limestone terraces, Dr. Sullivan recalls that he has returned to Sardis for 10 seasons, and will be back.</p>
        <p>''A lot of us spent our graduate-school years here,'' he says. ''That's a pretty formative time. It's hard to break the spell, so we keep coming back.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fikret Yegui, a Turkish-born professor of art and architectural history at the University of California at Santa Barbara, has worked at Sardis over the last 36 years. He is preparing a detailed drawing of the beautiful Temple of Artemis, stone by stone, every crack and mason's mark. When drawing is completed, soon, the sheets, fitted together, will be 22 feet long.</p>
        <p>After dinner one evening, some of the archaeologists walked through the temple's marble ruins and stood, transfixed, as a full moon rose over the acropolis and cast its soft light on the temple columns that still stood after 2,300 years.</p>
        <p>The day is complete. The encampment at Sardis falls asleep to a distant dog bark and the last call to prayer from the mosque down the valley.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
