<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jewish Museum Struggles to Be Born; Berlin's Efforts to Honor Lost Millions Are Mired in Dissent</title>
    <meta content="15MUSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Berlin (Germany)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Museum (Berlin)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, W Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorbey, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schoeps, Julius</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Berlin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED7103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jewish Museum Struggles to Be Born; Berlin's Efforts to Honor Lost Millions Are Mired in Dissent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article reviews myriad delays and confusion surrounding Berlin's plans to commemorate Holocaust and Germany's lost Jews; Jewish Museum, with new project director from New Zealand, Ken Gorbey, has still not opened, Topography of Terror site at former SS headquarters has no building, and numbingly debated Holocaust Memorial is still just an embarrassingly vacant lot; photos; map; at stake are big issues of how German should recall cataclysm, and whether projects are for Germans or Jews or both; Julius Schoeps, leading German Jew, charges museum building is 'Holocaust sculpture' that Gorbey may turn into multimedia Disneyland; Gorbey and W Michael Blumenthal, museum's American head, and his former deputy Tom Freudenheim comment; Berlin administration's objections to costs of other two projects also noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The idea seemed simple, pleasing in its balance: bring the German capital back to Berlin 55 years after the fall of Hitler's Reich and mark that return with several major cultural projects commemorating, in different ways, the Holocaust and Germany's lost Jews.</p>
        <p>But almost a year after the government returned, those projects are plagued by delays and confusion. Sitting in a sweltering office in Berlin's still-unopened Jewish Museum, Ken Gorbey, a New Zealander recently appointed its project director, posed just one of the central questions: ''Why on earth should a Kiwi gentile be here?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The idea seemed simple, pleasing in its balance: bring the German capital back to Berlin 55 years after the fall of Hitler's Reich and mark that return with several major cultural projects commemorating, in different ways, the Holocaust and Germany's lost Jews.</p>
        <p>But almost a year after the government returned, those projects are plagued by delays and confusion. Sitting in a sweltering office in Berlin's still-unopened Jewish Museum, Ken Gorbey, a New Zealander recently appointed its project director, posed just one of the central questions: ''Why on earth should a Kiwi gentile be here?''</p>
        <p>He is not the only person pondering that conundrum. Eleven years after its design was approved, three years after Daniel Liebeskind's building was completed, more than a year after the public was allowed a peek into its vertiginous space, one of the emblematic projects of the new Berlin has a new leader from down under even as it struggles to install an air-conditioning system that works.</p>
        <p>A revised opening date has just been set: Sept. 9, 2001, more than a year late. And there are rumblings. Of an unhappy falling-out between W. Michael Blumenthal, the museum's American chief executive, and his former deputy, Tom Freudenheim. Of soaring costs. Of growing unease over Berlin's many Jewish projects. Of a ''Disneyland aesthetic.''</p>
        <p>As things stand, the so-called triangle of major new Jewish projects planned to coincide with the German capital's return to Berlin form a bizarre picture: a building without an exhibition (the Jewish Museum), an exhibition without a building (the Topography of Terror site at the former SS headquarters) and an embarrassingly vacant central lot (the numbingly debated Holocaust Memorial).</p>
        <p>In theory, they form a whole: the museum commemorates Jewish life in Germany; the Topography of Terror focuses on the Nazi perpetrators; and the Holocaust Memorial recalls the six million Jews murdered by the Nazis. But while the theory is tidy, the reality is not.</p>
        <p>Big issues are at stake: how Germany should recall the cataclysm of the Third Reich, whether the projects are for Germans or for Jews or both, and whether the uneasy relationship between Germans and Jews, both marked forever by the death camps, can remain calm even as Holocaust fatigue grows in this country. Irritation is evident.</p>
        <p>''The Jewish Museum building is interesting, but to me it's a Holocaust sculpture, not a museum,'' said Julius Schoeps, the director of the Moses Mendelssohn Center, a Jewish research foundation, and a prominent member of the Berlin Jewish community. ''And now there is an attempt to adorn it in a very American way, to make a museum of experiences with what I have called a Disneyland aesthetic.''</p>
        <p>In a recent interview with the newspaper Die Welt in which he first invoked Disneyland, Mr. Schoeps  also took a swipe at Mr. Gorbey, saying that multimedia installations might work in Washington and ''maybe even New Zealand,'' but that Europeans wanted to see original objects.</p>
        <p>Having developed Te Papa, New Zealand's enormously successful national museum in Wellington, Mr. Gorbey, 58, took up his new post in April. He was drawn to Berlin by what he called ''the incredibly exciting project'' of chronicling the flowering, destruction and partial rebirth of German Jewish life in a building of great power.</p>
        <p>With its towering empty spaces (what Mr. Liebeskind calls voids), its zigzag form and its angular walls and windows, the building induces a sense of loss, sometimes even panic. It has been widely acclaimed.</p>
        <p>But there have been aesthetic concerns -- will the building overwhelm any exhibition it houses? -- and practical problems, not least the discovery last year that the air-conditioning system was inadequate, toilets too scarce and the layout of the entrance liable to create what Mr. Blumenthal called ''a traffic jam of major proportions.''</p>
        <p>The problems are linked partly to the very popularity of Mr. Liebeskind's building, which suggests that crowds will be greater than originally predicted, and to the haphazard way the museum has evolved from a mere adjunct to the Berlin City Museum into a full-fledged national institution. Still, the result was more outlays -- $5 million on top of the $60 million already spent -- and more delays.</p>
        <p>Enter Mr. Gorbey, speaking no German and with no particular knowledge of German or Jewish history. Are these handicaps? ''At times, but perhaps a certain neutrality is a bonus,'' he said. ''I am in the museum industry. This building is a massive capital project, and part of my task is to spend large sums prudently.''</p>
        <p>In other words, Mr. Gorbey is here to get things done, and there is a lot to be done after a period of turmoil. Shaike Weinberg, a former director of the Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington, who had been working closely with Mr. Blumenthal, died early this year; Mr. Freudenheim quit in frustration this summer.</p>
        <p>The institution, not a Holocaust Museum despite its appearance, is to tell the entire 2,000-year history of Jewish life in Germany. It will deploy what the museum's latest manifesto calls ''objects in cases, supported by texts and graphics.'' But it will also engage ''customers'' with ''other experiences provided by object theaters, computer interactives and opportunities for hands-on engagement with subjects.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbey explained his plans.  ''Look,'' he said. ''We're not going to have people saying, 'Let's go and have fun at the Jewish Museum.' No, we will be fronting up to the Holocaust, and so the emotive side will be a little more harrowing. But we hope we will give a balanced view, showing the joy in the Jewish community at times and its sense of achievement.''</p>
        <p>''Schoeps's criticism is a little shallow,'' he continued. ''This museum will be based on scholarship, not whimsy. But we want to appeal to a broad range of people and help them come to terms with history. So we will animate things, bring people and objects to life. If Schoeps thinks that's Disney, he needs to visit a standard object theater in any museum.''</p>
        <p>By ''object theater,'' Mr. Gorbey means the animation of objects through sound, movies, robotics, lighting and other means to add drama and perhaps a message to what is known in the trade as ''the museum experience.'' Wurth &amp; Winderoll, a German company based in Bavaria, has been contracted to work on the design of the exhibits.</p>
        <p>As a possible example of animation, Mr. Gorbey cited the correspondence between two 20th-century German Jewish scientists, Albert Einstein and Fritz Haber.</p>
        <p>Einstein came to scorn Germany -- ''a country of mass murderers'' was his lapidary assessment -- but Haber retained some attachment to a nation he once described as ''bourgeois to its very depths.'' Mr. Gorbey said he found the discussion deeply revealing and could imagine ''doing it in a coffee shop.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumenthal, a 74-year-old former Secretary of the Treasury who was born in Berlin and whose family fled Hitler, said: ''This is not going to be a museum for intellectuals, and so the intellectual snobs don't like it. We hope children will have fun, or at least not be bored. But this will be a serious, talked-about place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumenthal, a tough manager,  has proved extremely adept at cutting through layers of bureaucracy to obtain funds from the city of Berlin and the nation. This drive has culminated with the federal government's taking over the museum from a hugely indebted city and promising to provide most of an annual budget of about $15 million.</p>
        <p>It was for a similar efficiency that Mr. Blumenthal said he chose Mr. Gorbey. ''Our new deadline is going to stretch all of us very far,'' he explained. ''And what I needed was someone very, very good at knowing what it takes to open a museum. He's the best museum manager in the world today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Freudenheim, another old museum hand and an American who  worked for many years at the Smithsonian Institution, departed a few weeks ago after several disagreements with Mr. Blumenthal. ''It's the first time in my life that I've not been respected for doing professional things, and I'm very sad about it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The men clashed over several matters, including whether, as Mr. Freudenheim urged, the museum should have opened much sooner with a partial exhibit, whether a recent show on Berlin Jews at the Jewish Museum in New York should have been brought to the museum and whether the empty building could have been used for theatrical and musical productions.</p>
        <p>The problem, it seems, was that Mr. Blumenthal came to see Mr. Freudenhem as a gifted networker rather than a talented manager, while Mr. Freudenheim came to view his boss as a martinet. The  friction between the two American directors was hardly fruitful.</p>
        <p>The museum's turbulent history  has been matched by difficulties with the other two memorial projects. The Topography of Terror has not evolved beyond a temporary exhibit of photographs. Abutting a solitary remnant of the Berlin Wall, the display chronicles the suffering of people tortured and killed by the SS and the Gestapo. Construction at this site  of a building by the Swiss architect Peter Zumthor, whose plans were approved in 1993, has not even begun.</p>
        <p>The reason is that the Berlin administration has balked at the cost, now estimated at $35 million. ''We were supposed to get a final report from the city building commission in July, but that has been delayed to September,'' said Reinhard Ruerup, the academic director of the Topography of Terror project. ''The fact is, the mayor is not very enthusiastic, but I do not think he will stop it in the end.''</p>
        <p>The mayor, Eberhard Diepgen, is well known for his reservations about both The Topography of Terror and the Holocaust Memorial. But Mr. Ruerup argued that the new German capital could not do without a museum ''located at the spot where the central agencies of terror worked and focusing on the perpetrators.''</p>
        <p>But does Germany want more reminders? Notably, the country has deferred to foreigners in the conception of all three projects: an American architect and chief executive for the museum, a Swiss architect for the Topography of Terror and a New York architect, Peter Eisenman, for the Holocaust Memorial.</p>
        <p>''The Jewish-German question is so delicate and hot that any person who takes on these projects is going to be burned in some way, but perhaps more so a German,'' said Wenzel Jacob, the director of the Federal Museum of Art in Bonn. ''Guilt complicates everything, which is a pity because a lot of Germans are capable of doing these jobs.''</p>
        <p>The most treacherous job of all may be the Holocaust Memorial, a prominent field of columns adjacent to the Brandenburg Gate that could easily become a target for resurgent right-wing groups.</p>
        <p>After a decade of discussion, the final touches to the design are still under review. A planned archive or research center that was to have been above ground has been moved underground, where Joseph Goebbels's former bunker complicates the design. Construction will begin next year at the earliest.</p>
        <p>''You have to give the Germans a lot of credit for doing all this,'' Mr. Blumenthal said. ''But in the minds of many of them, there is the notion that they are doing it for the Jews, not for themselves. And so sometimes they feel we are asking for too much.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps by tying together Jewish and German life over many centuries, and by evoking what Germany lost of itself in the Holocaust, the Jewish Museum may finally have its greatest impact.</p>
        <p>''This museum will also be about what is missing,'' Mr. Gorbey said. ''A pocket handkerchief can tell the story of a whole family.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
