<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skip Instant Replay In New Football Movie</title>
    <meta content="15SAND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Replacements (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6D7113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skip Instant Replay In New Football Movie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports Business column discusses movie Replacements, concerning union-busting football players (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remember scab football? Remember the fun? Those golden moments? The talent? The dignity?</p>
        <p>Of course not. The players who replaced the striking National Football League players in 1987 did not distinguish themselves and faded quickly.</p>
        <p>Union-busting made lousy football and worse television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Remember scab football? Remember the fun? Those golden moments? The talent? The dignity?</p>
        <p>Of course not. The players who replaced the striking National Football League players in 1987 did not distinguish themselves and faded quickly.</p>
        <p>Union-busting made lousy football and worse television.</p>
        <p>But, hey, wash away those dingy old memories and leap into fantasy with the upbeat new film ''The Replacements.'' Here, greedy, boorish union players are replaced during a strike by a lovable, hungry bunch of lugs from Washington, D.C., who bond as a unit while singing ''I Will Survive'' in a jail cell, win the hearts of a grateful metropolis and beat Dallas to make it to the playoffs.</p>
        <p>(Great film idea: the fuzzy, warm side of thugs working for the Ford Motor Company who beat Walter Reuther and other union organizers in 1937.)</p>
        <p>''The Replacements'' is ''Rudy'' and ''Major League'' rolled into one anti-union comedy starring Gene Hackman as the coach, who has now gone from coaching fresh-faced high schoolers in ''Hoosiers'' to leading a team with a convict in some kind of modern correctional reform: a scab football work-release program. ''They have been part of something great,'' Hackman says at the end.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the N.F.L. refused to sanction ''The Replacements.'' Its refusal to grant Warner Brothers a license forced the filmmakers to create team names, like the Washington Sentinels, and to fashion new uniforms.</p>
        <p>''We didn't think it made sense to remind people of our 1987 strike,'' said Greg Aiello, a spokesman for the league. No doubt the league would not have been elated to see a replacement player use a pistol to shoot out the windows of the striking quarterback's expensive foreign car.</p>
        <p>The league's refusal to sanction the film did not keep the Maryland Stadium Authority from seeking the Baltimore Ravens' go-ahead to let the producers use PsiNet Stadium. ''We O.K.'d it because they felt it would be good for the economy of the community,'' said Kevin Byrne, a spokesman for the Ravens.</p>
        <p>(Short historical tidbit: during the 1987 strike, Art Modell, who owned the Cleveland Browns then and owns the Ravens now, said, ''There are no circumstances under which free agency will work.'')</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. Players Association contemplated protesting the making and the opening of the film, but thought better of calling attention to it.</p>
        <p>''The strike was a dark period for players and to make a comedy out of it is unfair to its importance in the lives of our players,'' said Doug Allen, the union's assistant executive director. ''Anyone who cooperated with this movie perpetuates a revisionist and unfair view of history that is denigrating to N.F.L. players who were fighting for the right to choose where they work.''</p>
        <p>In ''The Replacements,'' issues are never discussed. But hiring strippers to be cheerleaders is.</p>
        <p>''The Replacements'' has two familiar faces: Pat Summerall and John Madden. The Fox announcers called N.F.L. replacement games in 1987 when they worked at CBS, and call the film's games.</p>
        <p>Summerall and Madden were contractually bound to call those real-life strike games, but chose to play along with the charade in the film.</p>
        <p>''They looked at it as an entertainment,'' said Sandy Montag, who represents both men. ''They didn't view themselves as an ex-player and an ex-coach, but as announcers.''</p>
        <p>In the film, Summerall seems more himself than Madden, whose hyperactive style of analysis seems half as fast as usual. When they see the film, they may be a smidgen surprised to see some of their game commentary diverted for use as narration for a love scene. Oops!</p>
        <p>At one point in the film, Madden, as Madden, says, ''I never thought I'd say this, but I'm going to miss those replacement games.''</p>
        <p>Frankly, I never thought I'd hear him say that either.</p>
        <p>Dan Dierdorf, a CBS N.F.L. analyst and former St. Louis Cardinals union rep, said he received an early inquiry about being in the film. He said, ''But the N.F.L. wasn't behind it, and I was of the opinion that it would not be a smart thing to do.''</p>
        <p>Lightweight 'Regional'</p>
        <p>Yes, it is possible for a four-minute local sports report by Len Berman or Warner Wolf to be more substantial than Fox Sports Net's new half-hour ''Regional Sports Report.'' A viewing of the first two Sunday editions reveals the program as lightweight and stretched thin; the first Sunday, the anchors Steve Cangialosi and Mike Hill made elementary errors.</p>
        <p>This past Sunday, Cangialosi settled into the role of audience for Hill's subpar imitation of ESPN's Stuart Scott, whose style and personal highlight language are behind his popularity, and Van Earl Wright, a bellowing anchor on FSN's ''National Sports Report.'' Shouting scores and spewing three strained similes a minute is not a sports report -- it's amateur night at the Improv. And yes, anchormen, we've seen those fashionable T-shirts; now it's time to dress up.</p>
        <p>Terrific Olbermann 'News'</p>
        <p>But there are better things from Fox Sports Net: its search for a distinctive show is over: the new Sunday night ''Keith Olbermann Evening News'' is a sophisticated and occasionally silly vacation from ''SportsCenter'' or the ''National Sports Report.'' The program is Olbermann's innovative circus, where he juggles essays, field reports and interviews from his retro perch in what could have been Grantland Rice's office. This past Sunday featured a terrific report on the actors' strike against television commercial production and the decision by Tiger Woods and Kurt Warner to cross picket lines to star in their own ads.</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
