<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 More in Iran Are Detained In Crackdown On the Press</title>
    <meta content="Y15IRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Qoochani, Mohammad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nabavi, Ibrahim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DC113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 More in Iran Are Detained In Crackdown On the Press</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>TEHRAN, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Crackdown on reformers in Iran continues with detention of popular satirist, Ibrahim Nabavi, and newspaper columnist, Mohammad Qoochani; both are interrogated by hard-line court and detained; worked for banned daily (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The crackdown on reformers in Iran continued over the weekend with the detention of two writers. A popular satirist, Ibrahim Nabavi, and a newspaper columnist, Mohammad Qoochani, were interrogated by a hard-line court and detained.</p>
        <p>Both men wrote for a banned daily, Asr-e Azadegan, and won awards from their peers on Saturday in an annual press festival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The crackdown on reformers in Iran continued over the weekend with the detention of two writers. A popular satirist, Ibrahim Nabavi, and a newspaper columnist, Mohammad Qoochani, were interrogated by a hard-line court and detained.</p>
        <p>Both men wrote for a banned daily, Asr-e Azadegan, and won awards from their peers on Saturday in an annual press festival.</p>
        <p>In the last several months, the government has closed the reformist newspapers that supported the moderate president, Mohammad Khatami. Five journalists have been jailed in the last 10 days, and the last major reform newspaper, Bahar, was shut down.</p>
        <p>The newly elected Parliament, which has a preponderance of reformers, suffered a setback last week when Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, the country's supreme leader, ordered it to drop a bill for press reform. The bill was a centerpiece for Parliament, which opened in late May.</p>
        <p>The bill was meant to counter the conservative crackdown on the press, under which almost 25 newspapers have been closed and a dozen journalists jailed.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, a moderate deputy judiciary chief, Hadi Marvi, said today that some of the newspapers might be allowed to publish again because there was disagreement over the closings within the judiciary.</p>
        <p>He said many of the judges believed that the interpretation of existing law under which the newspapers had been shut down ''is not right.''</p>
        <p>The reformist minister of culture and Islamic guidance, Ataollah Mohajerani, a close ally of President Khatami and the official who has issued newspaper licenses for three years, was summoned to court today to answer questions about his ministry's expenses for cultural projects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mohajerani, who is also the government spokesman, escaped a dismissal vote last year by the previous Parliament, which was dominated by conservatives.</p>
        <p>The current crackdown appears to be an attempt to slow the reform movement after its strong showing in the parliamentary elections this year.</p>
        <p>But Hamid Reza Jalaipur, the publisher of five of the banned newspapers, said the cost of closing the papers would be greater for hard-liners than for reformers.</p>
        <p>''This is a new era in which one cannot rule without popular support,'' he said. ''Hard-liners have lost their credibility among the people by these radical measures. The heart of reform is the votes of the people, which cannot be stopped by closing newspapers and jailing journalists.''</p>
        <p>Despite enormous pressure, 161 reformist members of the 290-seat Parliament renewed their pledge to their constituents in a statement read on the floor on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''The honorable people should know that their representatives are faithful to the oath they took to protect their rights and will take all necessary measures to fulfill them,'' the statement said.</p>
        <p>It warned the opponents of reform to ''quit their attempt aimed at disappointing people,'' and be aware that such acts would not affect ''people's decision in pursuing reform.''</p>
        <p>Mohammad-Sadeq Javadihesar, the publisher of the banned daily Tous, said the statement indicated that the reformers ''will not give up because of such obstacles but will only change their approach and strategy.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, he said: ''Reformers and the people should not expect all plans to succeed. What matters is that the reform movement moves forward.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
