<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Negotiators in Telephone Strike Make Little Progress</title>
    <meta content="Y15PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DC113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Negotiators in Telephone Strike Make Little Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Negotiators in Telephone Strike M7</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the ninth day of the 12-state strike against Verizon Communications, negotiators made little progress yesterday as unions and the company debated the effect on workers of the recent merger that made Verizon the nation's largest telecommunications employer.</p>
        <p>And with no easy solutions in sight, both sides were gauging how long a work stoppage each was willing and able to endure. Verizon has begun to consider bringing in managers from other parts of the country to provide relief for the 30,000 managers within the region who are trying to fill in for the 86,000 employees on strike.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the ninth day of the 12-state strike against Verizon Communications, negotiators made little progress yesterday as unions and the company debated the effect on workers of the recent merger that made Verizon the nation's largest telecommunications employer.</p>
        <p>And with no easy solutions in sight, both sides were gauging how long a work stoppage each was willing and able to endure. Verizon has begun to consider bringing in managers from other parts of the country to provide relief for the 30,000 managers within the region who are trying to fill in for the 86,000 employees on strike.</p>
        <p>Some strikers on picket lines, meanwhile, were voicing worry about more days without a paycheck than many had expected when they walked off their jobs on Aug. 6. Having secured a concession late last week allowing them to organize more easily in Verizon's wireless division, the Communications Workers of America and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, have set their sights on other issues.</p>
        <p>The biggest sticking point involves Verizon's ability to shift work from one region to another in an effort to increase the efficiency of operations or reduce labor costs.</p>
        <p>In June, Bell Atlantic, the local telephone company in the region affected by the strike, merged with GTE, a telecommunications company that operates telephone companies in more than a dozen other states around the country. Verizon also includes a venture with Vodafone Airtouch of Britain that has become the largest wireless carrier in the United States. Altogether, Verizon has 260,000 employees.</p>
        <p>Concerned that their jobs might be threatened by movement of some work to other states, striking employees are seeking greater job stability. The strikers are in 12 states from Maine to Virginia and the District of Columbia -- where union membership is generally more widespread and wages higher than in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Given the consolidation in the telecommunications industry in recent years, it is little surprise that Verizon and its unions would lock horns over cost-cutting efforts.</p>
        <p>''This is something we consider essential to the functioning of our company on a competitive level,'' said Eric Rabe, Verizon's spokesman. ''This is about the workings of capitalism.''</p>
        <p>But even as they worry about losing some work, the unions are also protesting at sometimes having too much of it. They are seeking to limit mandatory overtime, which can tack on 15 to 20 extra hours of work each week for some employees. And stress in the workplace from such practices as the monitoring of operators' calls with customers is also an important issue for the unions.</p>
        <p>''This is what it comes down to,'' said Jeff Miller, a spokesman for the communications workers' union. ''We're waiting to see action on these major issues which management seems to consider normal, or even minor.''</p>
        <p>In addition to having managers fill in for striking employees, Verizon said it had brought in nearly 300 retired employees to work as technicians and customer service representatives. If the strike goes on much longer, the company said it was also considering bringing in managers from former GTE regions to perform some work. Most of the managers filling in for the strikers have not had a day off since the strike began, being required to work 12-hour shifts for 13 days before getting a break.</p>
        <p>Verizon is also weighing hiring people from outside the company, although it is not clear when and how this would take place, Mr. Rabe, Verizon's spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>The unions are prepared to dip into their $400 million strike fund to provide members with $200 a week if the strike enters a fifteenth day.</p>
        <p>Mike Stagliano, a striking technician who was part of a group of rain-soaked men shouting ''scab'' at employees entering a Verizon building at 140 West Street in Manhattan yesterday, said he was willing to endure  a few hundred dollars each week instead of his regular weekly income  of $1,110.</p>
        <p>''I equate this to the Pharoah and the slaves. These people will treat you like a slave, if you give in to them,'' Mr. Stagliano said. ''If you say no, they will respect you and think twice before pulling this thing again.''</p>
        <p>But some other striking employees were not so sanguine. Danny Marino, who worked in installation and repairs for six years at Bell Atlantic before it became Verizon, said he never imagined that he would be out on strike.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think that it would come to this, definitely; I thought this would last only two or three days,'' said Mr. Marino, who married last month. ''I have to keep going back to my wife and tell her I don't know what's going to happen. Then she gets worried and asks what am I going to do.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
