<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiries Find Little Abuse By Tax Agents</title>
    <meta content="15IRS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/15/business/15IRS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US) &gt;&gt;&gt; Deleted Term</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roth, William V Jr (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DA113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiries Find Little Abuse By Tax Agents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investigations by Internal Revenue Service and watchdog, Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration, find some of 830 complaints of IRS taxpayer harassment two years ago were bogus, made in effort to derail audits and tax collections; others were either without merit or involved misconduct that fell far short of Congressional definition of harassment; spokesman for Sen William V Roth Jr, who sponsored 1998 IRS Reform and Restructuring Act, says results show that IRS employees are adhering to the law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years ago, Congress, warned in hearings that the Internal Revenue Service was bullying many innocent Americans, passed a law requiring that the agency fire workers who harassed taxpayers.</p>
        <p>But not one of the first 830 complaints of taxpayer harassment filed under the new law has been upheld by the I.R.S. or its new Congressionally designated watchdog, according to new data.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years ago, Congress, warned in hearings that the Internal Revenue Service was bullying many innocent Americans, passed a law requiring that the agency fire workers who harassed taxpayers.</p>
        <p>But not one of the first 830 complaints of taxpayer harassment filed under the new law has been upheld by the I.R.S. or its new Congressionally designated watchdog, according to new data.</p>
        <p>Investigations by the I.R.S. and the watchdog, the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration, found evidence that some of the complaints were bogus -- made in an effort to derail audits and tax collections. Others were either without merit or involved misconduct that fell far short of the Congressional definition of harassment.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Senator William V. Roth Jr., the Delaware Republican who sponsored the 1998 I.R.S. Reform and Restructuring Act, said the results showed that I.R.S. employees ''are adhering to the law.''</p>
        <p>The spokeswoman, Ginny Flynn, added that ''while the vast majority of I.R.S. employees always have adhered to the law, clearly from our hearings some were not adhering to the law all the time and perhaps the restructuring act and its threat of termination has kept them from violating'' the law.</p>
        <p>But others argued that for all the talk of abusive I.R.S. agents, the new law may have gone too far in subjecting employees to extreme scrutiny.</p>
        <p>Representative Lloyd Doggett, a Texas Democrat who sits on the House Ways and Means Committee, said that while he voted for the law because he heard evidence of I.R.S. abuses, he thinks Congress has gone too far in restricting the agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doggett said he now thought the 1998 law was ''another example of the Republican priority of demonizing the I.R.S. and limiting its resources to fulfill its responsibilities, which I believe is all aimed at trying to end income taxation.''</p>
        <p>Most of the crucial testimony in the 1997-98 hearings that preceded the new law, contending abuses by I.R.S. agents, has proved to be unfounded, based on false or misleading testimony or disproved in subsequent court actions.</p>
        <p>One result of the new law has been extreme caution by I.R.S. workers, especially those involved in sensitive audits and collections against those who owe taxes past due, many of whom have become much less aggressive and others of whom say dust gathers on their requests to managers for permission to take enforcement actions.</p>
        <p>Collection has grown so lax that some prominent tax advisers said in interviews last year that they were amazed that the I.R.S. was not trying to collect taxes owed by their clients.</p>
        <p>Congress defined harassment to include deliberate misuse of the law, tax regulations or I.R.S. policies to harass or retaliate against a taxpayer. The new data, which was buried in a routine report issued by the Congressional Joint Committee on Taxation last week, was first disclosed yesterday by Tax Notes, a weekly journal.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. data showed that between July 1998 when the law was enacted and last May, the tax agency fired 4 of its 16,000 auditors for improperly threatening to audit a taxpayer. None of these cases rose to the level of what Congress called harassment because they involved spontaneous outbursts, not the willful misuse of the law, regulations or policies.</p>
        <p>One case involved an auditor arrested for drunken driving off-duty who told a police officer that he would ''find out'' about him and have ''a good time'' with him. The auditor asserted that his judgment was impaired and noted that he never mentioned an audit, but the I.R.S. rejected the claim and fired him.</p>
        <p>The tax agency also dismissed 102 of its 88,000 workers for failing to file tax returns and 2 for not reporting their entire income. In addition, one worker was fired for destroying records to cover up a mistake, an action that the I.R.S. said did not result in any harm to a taxpayer.</p>
        <p>Other data sent to Congress shows that I.R.S. workers are among the most compliant of taxpayers. A separate report from the I.R.S. shows that last year one in 12 taxpayers and one in 20 federal employees and retirees either did not file tax returns or owed back taxes, compared with one in 33 I.R.S. workers. Many of the I.R.S. workers who do not file tax returns are clerks who work only during tax season, but whose taxes are paid because they are withheld from their paychecks.</p>
        <p>The need for the mandatory-firing sections of the law was disputed by Colleen Kelley, president of the National Treasury Employees Union, which represents I.R.S. workers. ''The law is unnecessary and I would like to see it repealed or at least revised,'' she said. ''The law fixes a problem that doesn't exist.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kelley said any organization would have some misconduct in its ranks, but that 4 cases of misconduct among 16,000 auditors was insignificant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Flynn, Senator Roth's spokeswoman, said the data showed that fears among I.R.S. workers that the new law would result in their firing just for doing their jobs were unfounded. ''Clearly there is a very fair process'' of investigating complaints, she said after reviewing the data.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kelley said the law has created an unfair burden on I.R.S. workers ''who must endure sometimes 18 months not knowing if they will be cleared once a complaint is made, all the time fearing they will be fired.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
