<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore and Lieberman Voice Populist Themes</title>
    <meta content="15GORE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATS: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DF1E3FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore and Lieberman Voice Populist Themes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic presidential candidate Vice Pres Al Gore and running mate Sen Joseph Lieberman strike populist themes during campaign appearances in St Louis without mentioning Pres Clinton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without even a nod to President Clinton, who delivered his valedictory speech to Democrats in Los Angeles tonight, Vice President Al Gore struck populist themes today in two appearances and pledged to ''stand up for what's right'' for the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was introduced at a humid open-air rally here tonight within view of the city's landmark Gateway Arch by his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, as a ''decent and honest'' man. But neither referred to the president, whose administration's policies they have both generally supported and want to perpetuate, but whose private behavior they have both criticized.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Without even a nod to President Clinton, who delivered his valedictory speech to Democrats in Los Angeles tonight, Vice President Al Gore struck populist themes today in two appearances and pledged to ''stand up for what's right'' for the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was introduced at a humid open-air rally here tonight within view of the city's landmark Gateway Arch by his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, as a ''decent and honest'' man. But neither referred to the president, whose administration's policies they have both generally supported and want to perpetuate, but whose private behavior they have both criticized.</p>
        <p>After the rally, Mr. Gore relaxed with his wife, Tipper, Mr. Lieberman, and his wife, Hadassah, in a hotel room as he listened to Mr. Clinton's speech.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a great speech,'' he said. ''I appreciate the generous and kind words he said about me.''</p>
        <p>After the speech, he called Mr. Clinton and thanked him, a White House aide said.</p>
        <p>Asked how he reacted to the ''adulation'' heaped on Mr. Clinton, Mr. Gore said, ''Appropriate and what you would think would happen.''</p>
        <p>How could he expect in his own speech on Thursday night to top Mr. Clinton's? Mr. Gore's wife shot reporters an exasperated look as he blew past the question.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Lieberman flew on to Los Angeles tonight, Mr. Gore will meet Mr. Clinton in in Michigan on Tuesday for a symbolic ''passing of the torch,'' a ceremony that Gore aides hope will help shift the attention from Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>At the rally here, Mr. Gore focused on his many pledges -- to improve education, move toward universal health-care coverage, raise the minimum wage and enact anti-hate-crimes legislation. He framed the election as a choice between middle-class families and special interests like drug and insurance companies.</p>
        <p>''It all comes down to this,'' he declared to several hundred people here. ''Which side are you on?''</p>
        <p>''On one side there are working families, middle-class families, and they face a lot of obstacles; and on other side there are a lot of powerful interests who misuse the campaign finance system to wield more influence than they should,'' he declared. ''We need campaign finance reform to give democracy back to you.''</p>
        <p>''It also makes a world of difference who you've got in the White House,'' he said. ''I have never hesitated to take on the powerful, to take on the ones that find ways to make the system work for them, even if it comes as a disadvantage to most people.''</p>
        <p>''I believe that when the big drug companies say that they're opposed to a prescription drug benefit, that shouldn't rule the day in the Congress and in our nation,'' he said. ''We ought to have people who are willing to fight hard enough to overcome that and do what's right for the people of this country. That's what I'm all about; that's what this campaign is all about.''</p>
        <p>In an earlier appearance today in Independence, Mo., Mr. Gore gave a flash preview of his coming convention speech, plunging into details of how he would shore up Medicare and Social Security and suggesting that his Republican opponent, Gov. George W. Bush, was hiding behind generalities on his tax-cut proposal that Mr. Gore argued would cut benefits and hurt other programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is hoping that his detail-laden speech on Thursday, when he accepts the Democratic nomination for president, will accomplish a couple of things: give him a political mandate to follow the course he is proposing, and portray the Republicans as speaking vaguely because their positions are unpopular.</p>
        <p>''To give generalities and not give the specifics -- that's not the best way to elevate our democracy,'' he said today in Independence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers say these detailed discussions, while not exciting, address the concerns of ordinary Americans and play to Mr. Gore's strengths, including his grasp of policy, and at the same time suggest that Mr. Bush is unprepared to grapple with such basic issues.  THE DEMOCRATS: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
