<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Lucas Gets Nod to Pull the Jets Through</title>
    <meta content="15JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucas, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7DA113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Lucas Gets Nod to Pull the Jets Through</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets quarterback Ray Lucas discusses preparations for upcoming season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Quarterback Ray Lucas, the original survivor, went back to leading the Jets today. Just as he did during the second half of last season. Just as he will do Friday night against the Giants. And, if Vinny Testaverde does not recover quickly from an injury, just as he might do in the Jets' season opener against the Packers at Green Bay in three weeks.</p>
        <p>Do not count Testaverde out of the first regular-season game just yet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Quarterback Ray Lucas, the original survivor, went back to leading the Jets today. Just as he did during the second half of last season. Just as he will do Friday night against the Giants. And, if Vinny Testaverde does not recover quickly from an injury, just as he might do in the Jets' season opener against the Packers at Green Bay in three weeks.</p>
        <p>Do not count Testaverde out of the first regular-season game just yet.</p>
        <p>If the Jets played a game in two weeks, Testaverde might have been able to play, Coach Al Groh said today. But after their game against the Giants this weekend, the Jets have a bye week, and then they open the regular season Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>Testaverde sustained a sprained left big toe after being hauled down and fallen on by the 320-pound Sam Adams during the Jets' game Saturday against the Ravens at Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Today, Groh recalled the second half of last season when the Jets went 6-2 with Lucas, a onetime special-teams star, filling in at quarterback for an injured Testaverde.</p>
        <p>''The latter part of the season proved that all along, all along, we had enough talent to win,'' Groh said. ''That should be part of our makeup now.''</p>
        <p>After Testaverde sustained a torn Achilles' tendon in the opening game last season, the Jets went 1-6 with Rick Mirer mainly at quarterback. Then Lucas stepped in and helped the Jets restore some pride.</p>
        <p>Lucas will now start against the Giants on Friday, and he will play into the third quarter with the rest of the first-string players. The game will likely be an emotional and physical test. Last year the Giants were the last team to beat the Jets in the regular season, a 41-28 trouncing, before Lucas led his team to four straight victories in the final games.</p>
        <p>''I know the guys believe in me, and that's all I really care about,'' Lucas said. ''As long as my guys on the front line and the guys standing behind me and the guys on the right or left believe in me, anything is possible.</p>
        <p>''We were definitely one of the best teams in the league at the end of last season, and it's lucky for some of those teams we didn't get in the playoffs because anything could have happened.''</p>
        <p>After his success last season, Lucas had expected to be a Jet for many years to come, maybe even the heir apparent to Testaverde. But long contract negotiations in the off-season were fruitless, and then the Jets drafted quarterback Chad Pennington in the first round.</p>
        <p>Lucas signed a one-year deal for a $385,000. He will be a free agent after next season.</p>
        <p>Despite all that, he is back as the Jets' starter. Pennington sprained a knee against the Ravens and his immediate future is clouded, even though he will not undergo surgery. The only other quarterbacks on the roster are the untested Jim Kubiak and punter Tom Tupa.</p>
        <p>Lucas, however, expects Testaverde to be back for the regular season.</p>
        <p>''I'm telling you right now that if you think he's going to miss any games, you're crazy,'' Lucas said.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on last season's demoralizing defeat to the Giants, Lucas said, ''It was 17-0 before I knew what was going on.''</p>
        <p>So Lucas has some special feelings about Friday's game.</p>
        <p>''Last year our game ended on a sour note; I heard it from Tiki and Sam and Michael,'' Lucas said, referring to the playful ribbing he got from the Giants' Tiki Barber, Sam Garnes and Michael Strahan.</p>
        <p>''I'm not thinking of anything but winning that game and meeting them in the parking lot later and letting them have it.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>JOHN FREE, the first person Weeb Ewbank hired in 1963 after becoming the Jets' coach and general manager, visited camp Monday. Free, who retired as traveling secretary in 1980, recalled that he was reluctant to leave the Colts to join the Jets. The Colts were a powerhouse, a point Free made then to the Jets' new president, Sonny Werblin. ''But Sonny looked me in the eye and said: 'I don't care if you make it in Vienna or Milan or Paris. You don't make it until you make it in New York.' '' Free was responsible for some memorable moments such as spiriting JOE NAMATH safely out of hotels and stadiums and away from screeching fans. . . . JIM PONS, the club's longtime video director who was once a member of the popular rock group the Turtles, has retired. He is devoting his time to The David Center in Baldwin, N.Y., which provides guidance and education to families with autistic children. . . . YATIL GREEN caught three touchdowns in practice against second-string defenders. . . . The Jets waived seven players. Only one of them played in a game for the team: cornerback BUDDY CRUTCHFIELD. The others released were punter ANDY RUSS, the tackles ANTHONY BYRD and MARK BRISTOL, wide receiver CORY PETERSON, safety JONATHAN EATON and linebacker DAX STROHMEYER.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
