<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Rookie Still Confident Despite Muffs</title>
    <meta content="15GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dixon, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DA113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Rookie Still Confident Despite Muffs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of New York Giants rookie Ron Dixon during practice training camp; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just a week ago, there were times Ron Dixon literally skipped back to the Giants' huddle.</p>
        <p>Dixon, the team's 24-year-old third-round draft pick from tiny Lambuth University, was the most popular new player in summer camp. He was the winsome, cheery story of the Giants' preseason, his giddy ebullience for football -- not to mention his speed and smooth moves as a wide receiver and kick returner -- impressed one and all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just a week ago, there were times Ron Dixon literally skipped back to the Giants' huddle.</p>
        <p>Dixon, the team's 24-year-old third-round draft pick from tiny Lambuth University, was the most popular new player in summer camp. He was the winsome, cheery story of the Giants' preseason, his giddy ebullience for football -- not to mention his speed and smooth moves as a wide receiver and kick returner -- impressed one and all.</p>
        <p>Early at practice today, there were other salutations thrown Dixon's way.</p>
        <p>''Get off the field!'' Coach Jim Fassel screamed. ''Get me another kick returner!''</p>
        <p>As Fassel screamed, and cussed, he stalked toward Dixon, the teacher's pet no more. Dixon jogged to the sideline, which was, unfortunately, still close enough for the coach to keep yelling at him.</p>
        <p>Dixon's fantasy-camp itinerary has encountered unscheduled hardships. From a rising star to just another guy with the head coach screeching in his ear, Dixon has, in the span of a few days, been awakened to the authentic life of a rookie in the National Football League.</p>
        <p>''Bad things happen,'' Dixon said, mindful of the two punts he botched in Friday night's preseason loss to the Jaguars and the kicks he kept dropping in today's practice. ''I can't let it get me down.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Dixon's coming-out party was a stellar performance in the team's intrasquad scrimmage. In the Giants' first preseason game, he caught two passes and had a 17-yard run on a double reverse. Fast, agile and seemingly unawed by his new surroundings, he was designated the team's primary kickoff returner and elevated to fourth on the receivers' depth chart, vaulting over Brian Alford, a third-year player. The Giants had plans for him to return punts, too.</p>
        <p>Then came the game at Jacksonville, where Dixon looked and played like someone who suddenly recognized he was no longer at Lambuth.</p>
        <p>The game was at night, with lights positioned on top of a 73,000-seat stadium. At Lambuth, Dixon played before crowds of 200 or 300, and never at night.</p>
        <p>When he told the Giants last week about his inexperience trying to catch kicks at night, some coaches took him out to the lighted game field on the campus of the State University at Albany, where the Giants train.</p>
        <p>''But I told him this wasn't going to be the greatest example of what he'd be seeing in Jacksonville,'' Fassel said of the small-college setting. ''I looked out there that night and wondered if the lights were on.''</p>
        <p>When Dixon made his way into the brilliance of Alltel Stadium in Jacksonville, Fla., he knew he was starting something new, and not necessarily because of the lights. The game was also being televised nationally, all the way to his mother in Wildwood, Fla., and his former college coaches and teammates in Jackson, Tenn.</p>
        <p>''I was nervous, and I don't usually get nervous,'' Dixon said. ''It's everybody's and my worst nightmare to fumble the football on national television. I was kind of baffled.''</p>
        <p>The first punt banged off his chest and bounced upfield, but Dixon scrambled on his hands and knees to recover the fumble. Dixon's second muff was worse. Backpedaling near his own 15-yard line, Dixon did not retreat far enough. He thought about running out from under the ball, but at the last instant decided to try to catch it.</p>
        <p>It is never good to be out of position, especially with a spinning oblong ball descending toward you from the sky. The punt glanced off Dixon's right shoulder as he turned in an attempt to make an over-the-shoulder catch. The football bounded wildly to the Giants' 4-yard line with Dixon in pursuit. Mistake begot mistake as Dixon did not attempt to fall on the fumble. Instead, he tried to pick it up as he ran by.</p>
        <p>Dixon did not make that grab either. The Jaguars recovered the ball and later kicked a short field goal. In a coaches meeting Sunday, the receivers coach Jimmy Robinson was giving his report when he came to Dixon. ''He didn't catch a pass,'' Robinson said.</p>
        <p>''He didn't catch a punt, either,'' Fassel added.</p>
        <p>Then came practice today and Dixon was clearly flummoxed, dropping one kickoff after another. After one bobble was scooped up by a teammate, Dixon stopped on the field. Fassel exploded.</p>
        <p>''Don't stop running, Dixon,'' the coach yelled. ''Did I blow the whistle?''</p>
        <p>Afterward, Dixon did not appear shaken. ''I've been screamed at before,'' he said. ''He's doing a job and I've got a job to do. I just have to do it better.''</p>
        <p>Fassel said he would not hesitate to use Dixon on kick returns again. Until last weekend, Dixon was having a good camp catching the football. ''But I've got to chew him out when he's not catching them,'' Fassel said.</p>
        <p>The Giants' current first-team punt returner, Tiki Barber, recalled that he had trouble catching passes and punts two seasons ago.</p>
        <p>''It's totally mental,'' Barber said. ''It's the same thing Chuck Knoblauch has,'' he added, referring to the throwing problems of the Yankee second baseman.</p>
        <p>Barber said he just kept practicing it until catching the ball became second nature again.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, more veteran Giants observers recalled that David Meggett, as a rookie in 1989, dropped a series of punts in preseason games. Meggett holds the team record for punts returned for a touchdown with six.</p>
        <p>''I guess it came down to a lack of confidence Friday night,'' Dixon said today, a bit more subdued than the day two weeks ago when he declared that football ''is always fun, fun, fun.''</p>
        <p>But this afternoon, in a practice session that was conducted in a steady rain, Dixon caught some punts and made some skillful catches. Afterward, as Dixon walked off the field with his teammates, Fassel rode past in a golf cart.</p>
        <p>''Good work, Ron Dixon,'' the coach barked in passing.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
