<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Corporation to Pay $5.3 Billion for Chris-Craft</title>
    <meta content="Y15RUPE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">News Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chris-Craft Industries</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bhc Communications Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Television Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDC113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Corporation to Pay $5.3 Billion for Chris-Craft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News Corp confirms it has agreed to acquire Chris-Craft Industries, which owns 10 television stations, for about $85 a share in cash and stock; News Corp puts total price at $5.3 billion on complex purchase price, which involves buying Christ-Craft; BHC Communications Inc, company controlled by Christ-Craft; and United Television Inc, which is controlled by BHC; News Corp will own 33 stations after purchase, with two each in five cities, including New York and Los Angeles; says it will sell about $650 million worth of its stations to comply with Federal Communications Commission regulations that prohibit company's stations from reaching more than 35 percent of nation's television market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The News Corporation confirmed yesterday that it had agreed to acquire Chris-Craft Industries, which owns 10 television stations, for about $85 a share in stock and cash.</p>
        <p>News Corporation, which is controlled by Rupert Murdoch and owns the Fox network, put the total price at $5.3 billion on the complex purchase, which involves buying Chris-Craft; BHC Communications Inc., a company controlled by Chris-Craft; and United Television Inc., which is controlled by BHC</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The News Corporation confirmed yesterday that it had agreed to acquire Chris-Craft Industries, which owns 10 television stations, for about $85 a share in stock and cash.</p>
        <p>News Corporation, which is controlled by Rupert Murdoch and owns the Fox network, put the total price at $5.3 billion on the complex purchase, which involves buying Chris-Craft; BHC Communications Inc., a company controlled by Chris-Craft; and United Television Inc., which is controlled by BHC</p>
        <p>News Corporation will own 33 stations after the purchase, with two each in five cities, including New York and Los Angeles, the two biggest markets. But the company said yesterday that it would sell about $650 million worth of its stations to comply with Federal Communications Commission regulations that prohibit a company's stations from reaching more than 35 percent of the nation's television market.</p>
        <p>News Corporation is paying a high premium for Chris-Craft, roughly 18 times estimated 1999 cash flow, several analysts said.</p>
        <p>But the company is promising investors that by selling some stations and improving cash flow at the remaining stations -- particularly in markets where it will have two stations -- it can drastically improve overall cash flow so that shareholders will be paying a far lower multiple, perhaps as little as nine times cash flow. The recent industry average is about 13 times cash flow, according to Chris Dixon, a media analyst at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>Several industry experts questioned the News Corporation figure yesterday, saying that it was unlikely Mr. Murdoch could get such cost savings out of the deal.</p>
        <p>But some analysts agreed that the purchase had value not only because of the power it would give Mr. Murdoch in markets like New York, where he will own two stations -- WWOR and WNYW -- but also because it will assure additional outlets for the reruns of Fox shows like ''X-Files.''</p>
        <p>Viacom had been a bidder for the company but lost to News Corporation, which made its offer only recently. One Chris-Craft shareholder who spoke on the condition of anonymity said he was not particularly happy with the deal because Chris-Craft rejected an offer of $82 a share from Viacom last May, when Viacom shares were trading at $56. Since then, they have risen 28 percent. The outlook for News Corporation, he said, is far less certain.</p>
        <p>The purchase by News Corporation involves several companies. News Corporation is acquiring Chris-Craft and BHC, which owns very-high-frequency and ultra-high-frequency TV stations. BHC in turn controls United Television, a company that owns a number of stations that are part of the Chris-Craft group of 10 stations.</p>
        <p>As part of the deal, News Corporation will receive $1.7 billion in cash that is on the balance sheets of the three companies. News Corporation will keep the cash, using it to pay part of the cash component of the deal. It will give the stations to Fox Entertainment Group, the entertainment company of which it owns 82.76 percent, in exchange for 122.2 million shares in Fox. That will increase its stake in the entertainment company to 85.25 percent.</p>
        <p>Chris-Craft owns 80 percent of the common stock of BHC and 57 percent of UTV's common stock. In each case, News Corporation is offering cash and preferred shares for the outstanding stock. In total, News Corporation said it would pay $2.1 billion in cash and issue about 73 million American depository receipts, each of which represents four News Corporation shares, for a total of 292 million preferred shares.</p>
        <p>There is some flexibility in what investors can accept. Chris-Craft stockholders can choose cash, preferred A.D.R.'s, or a combination of $34 in cash and 1.15 preferred A.D.R.'s.</p>
        <p>The same structure applies for BHC. News Corporation will pay $66 in cash and 2.227 preferred A.D.R.'s for each of the outstanding 4.5 million BHC shares. At United Television, it will pay $60 in cash and 2.02 preferred A.D.R.'s for each of the outstanding 4.2 million shares.</p>
        <p>The total pot that News Corporation is making available is 60 percent cash and 40 percent shares. However, if a shareholder were to choose the all-cash payment, that shareholder would receive cash only to the extent that other shareholders sought payment in stock. Herbert J. Siegel, the chairman of Chris-Craft, who controls about 30 percent of the company, is said to be receiving all stock, which would make it a tax-free transaction.</p>
        <p>Andy Schwarzman, head of the Media Access Project, which represents the public at the F.C.C., opposed the deal because of the danger it poses to media diversity both locally and nationally. He said yesterday that he viewed it as ''an arrogant bet on the outcome of the election.''</p>
        <p>He said it was unlikely that the current F.C.C. would approve the deal but that a Republican-appointed F.C.C. would be more sympathetic. A number of the five positions at the F.C.C. are expected to change hands in the next administration.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
