<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Profits Surge at Big British Advertising Firm</title>
    <meta content="Y15WPP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wpp Group Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">kapner, suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DE113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Profits Surge at Big British Advertising Firm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE KAPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">kapner, suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>WPP Group, which will become world's largest advertising firm with its acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc, reports surge in profit and revenue in first half of year and forecasts that boom in advertising spending will last through end of year; says operating profit grew 22 percent, to 146.5 million pounds ($220 million) compared with 120 million pounds a year earlier; revenue rose 18 percent, to 1.2 billion pounds (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WPP Group, which will become the world's largest advertising firm with its acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc., reported a surge in profits and revenue today and forecast that the boom in advertising spending would last through the end of the year, buoyed by the Olympics and the presidential election in the United States.</p>
        <p>Several analysts, however, said the climate for big advertising firms like WPP is as good as it will get.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WPP Group, which will become the world's largest advertising firm with its acquisition of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc., reported a surge in profits and revenue today and forecast that the boom in advertising spending would last through the end of the year, buoyed by the Olympics and the presidential election in the United States.</p>
        <p>Several analysts, however, said the climate for big advertising firms like WPP is as good as it will get.</p>
        <p>WPP, based in London, said operating profit for the first six months of the year grew 22 percent, to $:146.5 million ($220 million), or 12 pence a diluted share, compared with $:120 million, or 9.8 pence a diluted share, a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Revenue rose 18 percent, to $:1.2 billion, driven by new accounts, like SAP A.G., and increased spending from existing clients like the Ford Motor Company.</p>
        <p>Including Young &amp; Rubicam, which WPP is buying for $4.7 billion in stock, and excluding one-time merger costs, revenue increased 19 percent while operating profit jumped 28 percent.</p>
        <p>Sir Martin Sorrell, WPP's chief executive, said shareholders would vote on the merger in September. Sir Martin sought to counter concerns that an expected slowdown in Internet advertising spending would dent WPP's growth prospects. He said that online spending tripled to $:90 million, or about $135 million, during the first half of the year. What has changed, he said, is who is buying.</p>
        <p>''Big traditional companies are spending more on the new economy, while new economy companies have had difficulties due to stock market falls and are spending less,'' Sir Martin said.</p>
        <p>Going forward, analysts said the currently vibrant conditions for all types of advertising spending were unlikely to continue.</p>
        <p>''Next year, you won't have the presidential elections or the Olympics or anything particularly big,'' said Gareth Thomas, an analyst at Commerzbank. ''Even if the economy stays strong, the top line will slow. And the margin enhancements we've seen to date won't be replicated.''</p>
        <p>WPP has been preparing for an eventual slowdown by paying more employees on a bonus schedule and hiring more staff on contracts. Sir Martin said such flexible costs, which amount to 7 percent of revenue, could be easily cut if need be.</p>
        <p>Shares of WPP, which owns the J. Walter Thompson and Ogilvy &amp; Mather Worldwide advertising agencies along with the public relations firm Hill &amp; Knowlton, rose as much as 2.4 percent on the earnings news, but fell back at the close of London trading to end down 0.11 percent at 907 pence, or about $13.60.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
