<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digging for Satchmo's Roots In the City That Spawned Him</title>
    <meta content="15ARTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000816T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Louis (1900-71)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Tad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D7103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digging for Satchmo's Roots In the City That Spawned Him</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts in America article on Louis Armstrong's roots in New Orleans, where he grew up and got first gig, tooting tin horn on junk wagon; photos; Tad Jones, music writer and fifth-generation New Orleanian, is excavating Armstrong's family history and musical influences; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this not-quite-centennial year of Louis Armstrong, there may not be a better way to see this city than through the eyes of his latest and perhaps most obsessive biographer, Tad Jones, a 48-year-old music writer and fifth-generation New Orleanian. It is a ghostly business, conjuring a legendary life and vanished landmarks from yellowed archives, shuttered ruins and renamed streets, but a labor of love for Mr. Jones, who is deep into the most exhaustive excavation yet of Armstrong's hometown roots and the influences that made him, in the reverent words of Bing Crosby, ''the beginning and the end of music in America.''</p>
        <p>In his dozen years of research and writing so far -- with no publication date set -- Mr. Jones, co-author of an earlier study of New Orleans music, has dug deep into local property archives to trace Armstrong's slave ancestry back to 1818. He has haunted Armstrong's streets, where music once spilled from every saloon, where young Louis once dipped his face in flour and won an amateur contest in whiteface, and where he worked for the Karnofsky family, who gave the future trumpeter his first gig tooting a tin horn on their junk wagon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this not-quite-centennial year of Louis Armstrong, there may not be a better way to see this city than through the eyes of his latest and perhaps most obsessive biographer, Tad Jones, a 48-year-old music writer and fifth-generation New Orleanian. It is a ghostly business, conjuring a legendary life and vanished landmarks from yellowed archives, shuttered ruins and renamed streets, but a labor of love for Mr. Jones, who is deep into the most exhaustive excavation yet of Armstrong's hometown roots and the influences that made him, in the reverent words of Bing Crosby, ''the beginning and the end of music in America.''</p>
        <p>In his dozen years of research and writing so far -- with no publication date set -- Mr. Jones, co-author of an earlier study of New Orleans music, has dug deep into local property archives to trace Armstrong's slave ancestry back to 1818. He has haunted Armstrong's streets, where music once spilled from every saloon, where young Louis once dipped his face in flour and won an amateur contest in whiteface, and where he worked for the Karnofsky family, who gave the future trumpeter his first gig tooting a tin horn on their junk wagon.</p>
        <p>But don't look for any commemorative plaques. There are none to mark these and other landmarks, a lapse that Mr. Jones is trying to remedy with appeals to various officials. Indeed in many cases there is no place to hang a plaque: the sites have vanished.</p>
        <p>Armstrong's very birth was long shrouded in myth, one fostered by Satchmo himself: that he was born on the Fourth of July, 1900. But in a baptismal registry Mr. Jones found proof that Armstrong was born on the more prosaic Aug. 4, 1901, which has stretched out the centennial commemorations being held from here to Corona, Queens, where Armstrong died at home in 1971 when he was 69.</p>
        <p>Just blocks from where young Louis grew up here, in a long since demolished row of red brick rooming houses near today's Loyola Avenue and Perdido Street, Mr. Jones pointed out a boxy green glass office building at 234 Loyola. On this site in the 1870's, Mr. Jones said, his own great-grandfather Jacinto Buno ran a saloon and restaurant. In 1907 his family sold the property to the Colored Knights of Pythias, which put up a 13-story headquarters with offices, theater, dance hall, movie house and roof garden. It was the first such elaborate black enterprise in the South, Mr. Jones said.</p>
        <p>Clearly it captivated young Louis: ''He's seven years old, waiting to go up,'' Mr. Jones said, savoring the imagined scene. In 1913, at age 11, he was remanded to the Colored Waifs' Home for Boys for firing a blank pistol and disturbing the peace. But before his release a year and a half later, Armstrong returned to the Pythias hall as a member of the orphans' orchestra to play a concert. Years later, as an accomplished jazzman in 1921, Armstrong was playing the hall's roof garden.</p>
        <p>One block away toward the Mississippi River, South Rampart Street bears its own Armstrong imprints. It is a street still lined with the frames of old pawnshops and secondhand stores where blacks barred from white Canal Street shopped in Jewish markets and drank in Sicilian bars. Today its parking lots are ghostly markers of the Armstrong legend -- one was once home to the Astoria Hotel, others to the Pelican Saloon and other honky-tonks where Armstrong and Kid Ory on trombone and Joe Oliver on trumpet played.</p>
        <p>It was the melange of musical and cultural influences that fostered Armstrong's humanitarianism, Mr. Jones suggested. For all the deprivation, poverty and discrimination he endured, Armstrong somehow emerged with singular ebullience, although among friends he could be caustic about the evils of segregationist America.</p>
        <p>''With the confluence of all this music, he was taking his genius and synthesizing it, from blues to gospel, ragtime and opera,'' Mr. Jones said.</p>
        <p>He pointed out the easy-to-miss shuttered wood and red brick shell on South Rampart Street, all that remains of the Iroquois Theater, built in 1912. In his memoirs Armstrong told of watching movies there for a nickel and of his triumph in the amateur contest where he performed in whiteface.</p>
        <p>A few doors down, at 427 South Rampart, Mr. Jones stopped at a small building that once housed the secondhand shop of the Karnofsky family, peddlers whose welcoming home and payroll sustained young Louis in hard times. ''You name it, the Karnofskys sold it,'' Mr. Jones said. In 1920 the father, Morris Karnofsky, opened a record shop where the 19-year-old Armstrong and other black musicians were customers.</p>
        <p>Torn down almost 50 years ago for the City Hall complex were the nearby row houses where Armstrong and his sister grew up after their mother, Mayanne, moved the family from squalid Jane Alley in an outlying slum Armstrong called ''Back O' Town.'' A tree marks the spot where their house probably stood, Mr. Jones said, and a nearby grassy rise is all that remains of the music mecca called Kenna's Hall, but that Armstrong and his cronies knew by a cruder nickname. The building of City Hall also wiped out all traces of the Fisk School, the local public school for blacks, which Louis barely attended when he was 6 or 7. ''If he went there for more than two years, I'd be surprised,'' Mr. Jones said. Blacks needed to attend school only for 120 days a year, he said, whites, 180.</p>
        <p>It was in 1988, while doing research for Gary Giddens, the jazz writer, and Toby Byron, a television producer preparing an Armstrong book and documentary, that Mr. Jones began to think that Armstrong had actually been born a year or two later than he said. An overlooked clue had come from Armstrong himself. In the 1940's he told his Belgian biographer, Robert Goffin, that he was baptized at the Sacred Heart of Jesus Church. The church, on Lopez Street, was for whites, but urged on by Mr. Giddens, Mr. Jones discovered that black infants, including Armstrong, had been baptized there as well, and he came up with the new birth date.</p>
        <p>''It was the easiest thing I've ever done,'' said Mr. Jones, dressed in jeans, a maroon golf shirt and sneakers, as he strolled through Armstrongland. ''Do I look like a rocket scientist?''</p>
        <p>He said he gave the news to Richard Allen, a former jazz curator at Tulane University, who passed it on to The New Orleans Times-Picayune, which sent it out on the Newhouse news service ''That was it, 50 newspapers picked up on it,'' Mr. Jones recalled. ''I was getting phone calls like I had discovered the Holy Grail or the cure for cancer.''</p>
        <p>Several years later Mr. Jones landed a book contract with the University of Illinois Press. All told, he said, his advance and grants over his decade of work have barely reached $5,000, although he and his co-authors, Jason Berry and Jonathan Foose, had written the well-received ''Up From the Cradle of Jazz: New Orleans Music Since World War II'' (University of Georgia Press, 1986). A dabbler on the guitar and piano, although he does not play for a living, Mr. Jones has supported himself working as a paralegal and manager of a music publishing group owned by the long-running New Orleans-based rock band the Radiators. (He is also scheduled to lecture on Armstrong's musical influences in a commemorative series at Lincoln Center in New York in October.)</p>
        <p>Retracing some of his archival research in the conveyance office in City Hall, Mr. Jones pulled out heavy quill-penned books that summarized hundreds of thousands of property transfers -- including the sale and purchase of slaves -- from 1827 to 1865. New Orleans was one of the largest slave markets in the South. ''Once you get one sale you can track forward or backward,'' Mr. Jones said.</p>
        <p>And so he traced the roots of Armstrong's family tree. The baptismal certificate with the crucial 1901 date had listed a Catherine Walker as a co-sponsor of the child. ''I initially thought she was a white neighbor whom the Armstrongs might have worked for,'' Mr. Jones said. But the summaries in the conveyance office and the original documents in the city's nearby notarial office told a different story.</p>
        <p>He found the record he was seeking on Page 344 in a thick volume labeled ''Acts, Jan.-July 1818, Marc Lafitte, Notary.'' On May 18, 1818, a slaveowner named Antoine Turcas purchased Daniel Walker, 32, from Richmond for about $600, a substantial price at the time. Walker, a further search of the records showed, had a son, also named Daniel, who married Catherine Washington, born in 1837 and brought with her mother and sister from a plantation in Madison County, Miss., to New Orleans, where they were auctioned off together. Catherine and Daniel Walker had a daughter named Josephine who later married Ephraim Armstrong. They had a son named Willie, the father of Louis Armstrong. Catherine Walker, Louis's great-grandmother, attended the baby's baptism in 1901 as a sponsor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones said he knew he was spending a lot of time on local details but that it was important for the understanding of Armstrong and the myriad influences, musical and otherwise, that shaped him. Some of his predecessors may have been in too much of a hurry, he said, too eager to distance Armstrong from his roots and catapult him to universal fame. ''They race through New Orleans to get to Chicago,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA  Correction:  August 16, 2000, Wednesday  An article yesterday about the retracing of Louis Armstrong's roots in New Orleans by the writer Tad Jones misspelled the surname of a jazz writer and Armstrong biographer for whom Mr. Jones also conducted research. He is Gary Giddins, not Giddens.</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the article also misspelled the surname of Mr. Jones's great-grandfather. He was Jacinto Bunol, not Buno.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 16, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the retracing of Louis Armstrong's roots in New Orleans by the writer Tad Jones misspelled the surname of a jazz writer and Armstrong biographer for whom Mr. Jones also conducted research. He is Gary Giddins, not Giddens.</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the article also misspelled the surname of Mr. Jones's great-grandfather. He was Jacinto Bunol, not Buno.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
