<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Ranger, Ledee Still Misses New York</title>
    <meta content="15PINS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ledee, Ricky</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D6113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Ranger, Ledee Still Misses New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>ARLINGTON, Tex., Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Texas Rangers outfielder Ricky Ledee discusses New York Yankees trading him six weeks ago and how he still misses former teammates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ricky Ledee wept and could not sleep after the Yankees traded him to the Cleveland Indians for David Justice six weeks ago, ending an association with the organization that he had loved since he was 16 years old. Since the fateful night, Ledee was traded a second time, to the Texas Rangers on July 28.</p>
        <p>As Ledee stood in the middle of the Rangers' clubhouse today, wearing a red T-shirt that looked odd on him and speaking as softly as if he were in a library, he admitted within the first minute of an interview that he missed being with the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ricky Ledee wept and could not sleep after the Yankees traded him to the Cleveland Indians for David Justice six weeks ago, ending an association with the organization that he had loved since he was 16 years old. Since the fateful night, Ledee was traded a second time, to the Texas Rangers on July 28.</p>
        <p>As Ledee stood in the middle of the Rangers' clubhouse today, wearing a red T-shirt that looked odd on him and speaking as softly as if he were in a library, he admitted within the first minute of an interview that he missed being with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''When I left, it was tough,'' Ledee said. ''I wish that I was still there. I don't want to keep defeating myself with those thoughts. I'll just talk to them. They are my friends. Even when they got here today, they called me. But you have to keep going.''</p>
        <p>With the Rangers, Ledee is trying to revive his still-promising career, and he talks about how this is a terrific opportunity because he will play more than he would have with the Yankees.</p>
        <p>But Ledee could not disguise his disappointment, no matter how many nervous smiles he offered. He still studies the Yankees and knows every move they have made to try to solve the left-field puzzle created by his inefficiency and Shane Spencer's knee injury, from Justice to Glenallen Hill to Ryan Thompson to Luis Polonia.</p>
        <p>''I was kind of devastated when I left that night in Detroit,'' Ledee said. ''I hardly slept. I cried all night. Not that I had been traded, but that I had gotten such a great opportunity and I didn't do anything with it. I was upset with myself. But I got over it.''</p>
        <p>Always polite, always sensitive, Ledee said he had caused his own demise. He did not blame the pressure of playing in New York or being chastised by the Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, and felt the reason he was traded was that he batted just .241 with 7 homers and 31 runs batted in over 62 games.</p>
        <p>''If I was hitting, I'd probably still be there,'' said Ledee, who belted a grand slam Saturday and is hitting .233 in 15 games with Texas. ''It didn't happen that way. The only one I can blame is myself. I got a great opportunity. I just couldn't put it together there.''</p>
        <p>Yankees Manager Joe Torre recalled having a meeting with Ledee in spring training and trying to get him to relax. But it did not work. Despite going 6 for 10 in the 1998 World Series, the most pressure-filled stage in the majors, Ledee's confidence often wavered if he went hitless, and Torre benched him.</p>
        <p>Torre conceded that Ledee had looked frazzled. ''In his mind,'' Torre said, ''I think he wanted to perform so he wouldn't get traded.''</p>
        <p>Obviously, Ledee did not succeed.</p>
        <p>''It was a baseball move,'' Ledee said. ''Things had to be done.''</p>
        <p>Cone Relaxes a Bit</p>
        <p>A more relaxed David Cone, who is earning $12 million this season, joked that he would like to move from averaging $6 million a victory to $4 million by winning his third game against the Rangers on Tuesday night. It was one sign that Cone, whose mood had turned drearier as he went 15 straight starts without winning, had some of his carefree personality back.</p>
        <p>Cone pitched six solid innings to defeat the Oakland Athletics, 12-6, on Thursday, winning his first game since April 28 and improving to 2-10. Cone said he felt as if he had finally helped the Yankees, who grabbed first place with him doing little in the first four months of the season.</p>
        <p>Torre said: ''I think that first win relieved a lot of pressure, anxiety, all of that stuff. He just seems a lot less fidgety to me. I haven't heard any of the self-analysis or beating himself up. He's feeling better about himself.''</p>
        <p>Canseco's Starting Role</p>
        <p>Jose Canseco, who was 1 for 4 with an R.B.I. in tonight's 7-3 victory over the Rangers, started his fifth straight game at designated hitter because Joe Torre wants to ''play the people who need to play so they can stay sharp.''</p>
        <p>Torre said he thinks that Glenallen Hill and Luis Polonia are more comfortable coming off the bench than Canseco, who has never done that in his career. Since Hill also has a bruised right shoulder and cannot throw yet, David Justice played left field. Torre is leery about overusing Justice and said he would probably use Polonia in left at some point to give Justice a break.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to pick a spot to rest him here and there,'' Torre said. ''I don't have a choice right now.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
