<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skulduggery And Satire On the Good Ship Peking</title>
    <meta content="15NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Street Seaport (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gorilla Repertory Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pirates of Penzance (Operetta)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D7103FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skulduggery And Satire On the Good Ship Peking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber Critic's Notebook review of The Pirates of Penzance, as staged by Gorilla Repertory on three-masted ship docked at South Street Seaport; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a stunning moment, at the end of the Gorilla Repertory Theater's production of  ''The Pirates of Penzance,'' staged outdoors on a three-masted ship docked at the South Street Seaport, when an effigy of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani is pitched summarily overboard.</p>
        <p>The mayor as well as the New York Police Department have already come in for a good deal of abuse throughout this zany adaptation of one of Gilbert and Sullivan's more lovable operettas. None of the gibing is terribly eye-opening or funny (even to the sympathetic ear), but when Mr. Giuliani's surrogate is sent over the gunwale, you guffaw with shock and think, Gee, does the mayor know about this? And that, of course, makes the point of the director and adapter, Michael Scheman: that the mayor's authoritarianism, particularly in regard to the arts, has been a threatening presence in the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a stunning moment, at the end of the Gorilla Repertory Theater's production of  ''The Pirates of Penzance,'' staged outdoors on a three-masted ship docked at the South Street Seaport, when an effigy of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani is pitched summarily overboard.</p>
        <p>The mayor as well as the New York Police Department have already come in for a good deal of abuse throughout this zany adaptation of one of Gilbert and Sullivan's more lovable operettas. None of the gibing is terribly eye-opening or funny (even to the sympathetic ear), but when Mr. Giuliani's surrogate is sent over the gunwale, you guffaw with shock and think, Gee, does the mayor know about this? And that, of course, makes the point of the director and adapter, Michael Scheman: that the mayor's authoritarianism, particularly in regard to the arts, has been a threatening presence in the city.</p>
        <p>Well, it's an ending. In truth, it doesn't feel theatrically pertinent, but you have to admire the gall, and if you can't go with the wacky gumption of this production, then you probably shouldn't climb aboard the Peking and stand on deck with the rest of the audience as the actors perform in front of, around and among you. Indeed, in this enclosed setting, ''The Pirates of Penzance'' (performances are Fridays through Mondays until Aug. 28) asks for an audience's indulgence even more than the Gorilla Rep usually does.</p>
        <p>The company is known for its fourth-wall-less outdoor performances of Shakespeare, and it routinely copes with such random interference as unclued-in passersby, traffic noise and the weather. Its new production of ''As You Like It'' in Washington Square Park (Fridays and Sundays through Sept. 24) was performed in a drizzle on Sunday night. But on the Peking, you're trapped, more or less, unless you jump ship. And the chaos of the production is half the fun. You need to chase the actors around in order to hear them (they're not miked, for some reason), and at the same time hustle to stay out of the way when the scene changes and the company assembles elsewhere. One troublesome loss is that judging from the notes carried on an only intermittently favorable wind, a handful of good voices too often go wafting off over the harbor.</p>
        <p>That's fair warning; give over to it, or be grumpy. And it's certainly true that ''Pirates,'' with its wonderfully goofy story about a mistakenly indentured pirate at the end of his indenture, the pyrotechnical doggerel of W. S. Gilbert and the smile-and-sigh-inducing melodies of Arthur Sullivan, is a show that easily combats a grouch. So when a swaggery actor named Michael Colby Jones, wearing a leather jacket and a bandanna, climbs the Peking's rigging to deliver one of the show's signature songs, it really does seem, for the moment, that ''it is, it is a glorious thing to be a pirate king.''</p>
        <p>This is no more a conventional interpretation of Gilbert and Sullivan than it is a conventional stage. David Joseph, as Frederic, the indentured lad torn by his impending freedom from and loyalty to the incompetent, rascally outlaws who raised him, and Annette Cortes as Mabel, the major general's daughter who steals his heart, play their roles close to straight. But Ruth, the nursemaid who was responsible for Frederic's childhood indenture and who is in love with him now that he's grown, is played in drag by the actor Patrick McCarthy; so are several of the maidens who entrance the pirates, though that doesn't keep them from dressing up as cheerleaders. The Pirate King reads Playboy.</p>
        <p>Much of the score has been rejiggered to reflect a variegated musical style that would have flummoxed, and possibly delighted, Sullivan; Elvis exerts his influence, as do the likes of Dion and the Belmonts, Snoop Doggy Dogg and Andrew Lloyd Webber. And Mr. Scheman's new lyrics, which reference Ivana Trump, Amadou Diallo, President Clinton, Gov. George W. Bush and Charlton Heston, onion rings, the war in Kosovo and the human genome project, are as shamelessly pointed and scattershot as a stand-up comedian's. He makes full use of the famous ditty ''Modern Major General,'' sung here by Gordon Stanley in an aviator jacket. A sample:</p>
        <p>When people know that Lazio would surely drop the ball for us</p>
        <p>When Rudy's forced to realize he's made Times Square a mall for us</p>
        <p>When all the children forced to go to summer school are freed at last</p>
        <p>When Congress gets a clue and starts by legalizing weed at last.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scheman has a nice facility with the tongue-tying rhythms. But for all the hit-and-miss jokery in this production, if there's one thing to be grouchy about, it's his agenda. The idea, evidently, is to take off on the theme of ''Pirates,'' whose subtitle is ''The Slave of Duty,'' and to update the Victorian hypocrisies that Gilbert and Sullivan had fun with more than a century ago. But the show doesn't survive because of its commentary; it survives because it's great fun. The political satire here feels like interference. It's actually more liberal sneering than satire -- the kind that makes even a liberal glaze over -- and it's really all that's standing in the way of a good time.</p>
        <p>Fewer liberties are taken with ''As You Like It'' (which is being presented in repertory with the company's popular rendition of ''A Midsummer Night's Dream''), but the exigencies of outdoor performing paint the proceedings with a loony sheen nonetheless. The acoustics of nature and Greenwich Village being what they are, the actors, directed by Andre-Philippe Mistier, play their roles big and loud, often at top speed and more to the audience than to one another.</p>
        <p>This is, as a result, a production that offers more slapstick than verbal elan, and far more actorly mugging than thought-through character work. As the fool Touchstone, David Blasher gyrates nonstop and shouts himself nearly hoarse, and Adria Lang plays Rosalind, the sublime coquette, as more of a swoony girl than a gender-bending wit. Even in male disguise, she's a bit giggly. Her performance gets stronger as the play goes on, and she delivers the playful epilogue beautifully, with a genuine understanding of Shakespeare's unifying embrace of the players and audience, but it's a disappointingly late arrival of Rosalind's appeal. Men in the audience want to love Rosalind, but here only a passionate lunkhead like Orlando (Reggie Austin) can.</p>
        <p>O.K., these may be the plaints of a critic who spent two hours straining to hear dialogue in a light rain, chasing after the company from scene to scene on the wet grass. Unlike ''Pirates,'' which has a $15 ticket price, this is free theater, a terrific bargain. The whole is performed with great good cheer, a boon in a battle with the elements and more than suitable for what is probably Shakespeare's most good-humored play. The wrestling match in Act I has enough acrobatic faux-violence to be televised for screaming fans.</p>
        <p>Several performers do manage to stay earthbound and textbound even at top volume. (Particularly good are Giselle Jones as Rosalind's cousin Celia and Dale Ho as Oliver, Orlando's evil older brother, who is redeemed and rewarded with Celia's love.) And the end of the play, with its joyously comic untangling of various lovers' confusion, is the production's most accomplished aspect, with the actors at their most relaxed, grinning in the glow of Shakespeare's wit. It's hard not to grin back at this hard-working company.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Mayor? Nothing for you to worry about.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
