<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Would a Few Celebrities Please Move Here?</title>
    <meta content="13GOOD$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD FENCES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Queenan, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFDB1E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Would a Few Celebrities Please Move Here?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE QUEENAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Queenan, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Queenan article discusses impact of celebrity residents on prices of suburban homes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the least examined mysteries of modern suburban life is the impact on a small community when its most famous citizen suddenly ups and leaves. Did residents of Nyack, N.Y., feel they had failed last year when Rosie O'Donnell packed up her three children and moved to Greenwich, Conn.? Will they feel redeemed if she indeed buys a house nearby and returns to the greater Nyack area?</p>
        <p>Do house prices in Bedford, N.Y., go up or down when Mariah Carey leaves town? And would Americans once again start confusing Chappaqua with Pound Ridge should Hillary Clinton lose her senatorial race and grab the next train to a place called Hope? Or for that matter, a place called Chicago?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the least examined mysteries of modern suburban life is the impact on a small community when its most famous citizen suddenly ups and leaves. Did residents of Nyack, N.Y., feel they had failed last year when Rosie O'Donnell packed up her three children and moved to Greenwich, Conn.? Will they feel redeemed if she indeed buys a house nearby and returns to the greater Nyack area?</p>
        <p>Do house prices in Bedford, N.Y., go up or down when Mariah Carey leaves town? And would Americans once again start confusing Chappaqua with Pound Ridge should Hillary Clinton lose her senatorial race and grab the next train to a place called Hope? Or for that matter, a place called Chicago?</p>
        <p>Although I am as concerned about the psychological well-being of Nyackers, Bedfordians and Chappaquii as the next person, it is the impact of celebrity defections on house prices that has consumed my waking hours. As a 17-year resident of historic Tarrytown, an intermittently idyllic but celebrity-deprived Hudson River hamlet, I've spent a lot of time wondering whether luring a Celine Dion or at least one of the Backstreet Boys to our headless-horsemanlike community might not put some juice into house prices.</p>
        <p>At the same time, I have given much thought to whether Tarrytowners could withstand the devastating blow of having a mega-deity -- say, Regis -- briefly alight among us, only to blow town a few months later. But mostly I've been thinking about those house prices.</p>
        <p>As is usually the case when I begin to fantasize about sudden Croesian windfalls, my dreams are cruelly dashed as soon as I subject them to the sober review of seasoned professionals. Real estate agents in Bedford, Chappaqua and Nyack are unanimous in their belief that the peregrinations of celebrities have little or no effect on prices.</p>
        <p>''They might make an impact on the ultra-ultra-top level of the market,'' said Lois Barnett, the owner of Vincent &amp; Whittemore Real Estate in Bedford. But for every Mariah that high-tails it back to Manhattan, 10 more will spring up in her place. As Ms. Barnett noted, ''When Martha Stewart moves in, Michael Crichton and George Soros already live right down the street.''</p>
        <p>Bedford is not the only village that can fall back on its daunting reservoir of equally radiant celebrities. The same is true of Nyack. When I visit this quirky, quasi-Bohemian village that seems to taunt stolid, un-quirky Tarrytown from across the Hudson, it is clear that residents had been cushioned from the blow of Rosie O'Donnell's departure by the presence of celebrities of comparable luminosity, which has long been the case.</p>
        <p>''The first person I ever waited on, 23 years ago, was Helen Hayes,'' said Kenneth Kral, ''assistant everything'' at the Pickwick Bookshop. In fact, it was Hayes's beloved house, Pretty Penny, that Ms. O'Donnell bought for $770,000 in 1996, remodeled for hundreds of thousands of dollars, then abruptly unloaded for close to $2.75 million. Yet, locals did not seem chastened by her departure.</p>
        <p>''Bill Murray was in here last week,'' said a waitress at a pastry shop called the Runcible Spoon, located not far from Edward Hopper's boyhood home.</p>
        <p>''You see William Hurt, Al Pacino and one of the Baldwins all the time,'' a merchant added.</p>
        <p>''This is Hollywood on the Hudson!'' chimed in a second waitress from the Runcible Spoon, located not far from Carson McCullers's house.</p>
        <p>''We had Edward James Olmos sitting right in that very chair,'' a man in a thrift shop observed.</p>
        <p>Obviously, a town frequented by the likes of Edward James Olmos (most famous people sighted in Nyack may actually live somewhere else) does not need a Rosie O'Donnell to bolster its image. Real estate agents in Nyack say she is considering buying  a $2 million house on 25 acres in adjoining Valley Cottage. But even so, for Nyackers, it will only be icing on an already remarkable cake.</p>
        <p>What about an equally charming, much more upscale, yet less overtly cool community like Chappaqua? Does the arrival of the Clintons substantially boost the town's self-esteem? Would that self-esteem evaporate if they vamoosed? And what about those house prices?</p>
        <p>''It's definitely seen as a victory for Chappaqua,'' said Colin Calhoun, the owner of Calhoun's Restaurant. ''People feel validated.''</p>
        <p>But would the locals feel de-validated if Hillary Clinton lost the senatorial election and left? ''No,'' Mr. Calhoun said. ''If she loses, 90 percent of the people would expect her to leave. But the Clintons being here is already a victory for Chappaqua.''</p>
        <p>Margaret Atkinson, a real estate agent at Houlihan Lawrence in Chappaqua, agreed that having the president of the United States and an aspiring United States senator as neighbors has given the Chappaquii some sort of psychological boost. But she doesn't see how that affects house prices. Instead, she mentioned the excellent schools, the easy commute to the city, the guaranteed residents' parking spaces at the train station and other unquantifiable quality-of-life elements.</p>
        <p>''People come to Chappaqua because it's very child-oriented,'' she said. ''It's an easy town. Who wouldn't want to live here?''</p>
        <p>Good question. But here's an even better one. Tarrytown is also an easy town. It is also a child-oriented town. And it is a town that offers an even easier commute to the city than Chappaqua. Moreover, it is not a snooty town, not the sort of town that acts like celebrities are no big deal. Indeed, I would be willing to wager that if an Al Pacino or a Bill Murray or even a Jonathan Demme were willing to ford the Hudson and set down roots in our community, most of the locals would be ready to lay out the red carpet.</p>
        <p>Why then the delay? Is it possible that Tarrytown's well-documented parking problems are all that is keeping celebrities away? Were these parking problems eased, might not Mariah Carey be willing to give Westchester a second chance? And if so, wouldn't that do wonders for house prices? Specifically, mine?</p>
        <p>Predictably, a knowledgeable real estate agent blithely dismisses my dreams of imminent Tarrytownian cultural and economic suzerainty.</p>
        <p>''Celebrities don't raise house prices,'' she said. ''SAT scores raise house prices.''</p>
        <p>Yes, but I still think Madonna could help.</p>
        <p>GOOD FENCES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
