<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Connecticut Post Is Sold Along With 5 Smaller Papers</title>
    <meta content="13POST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000715T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thomson Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Connecticut Post (Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Medianews Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DC1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Connecticut Post Is Sold Along With 5 Smaller Papers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT, Conn., July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomson Corp says it will sell Connecticut Post and five community newspapers in Fairfield County, Conn, to MediaNews Group; MediaNews says it does not plan any staff or management changes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Toronto-based company that owns The Connecticut Post, the state's second-largest daily newspaper, said today that it would sell the paper and five community newspapers in Fairfield County to a chain based in Denver.</p>
        <p>The Post's owner, the Thomson Corporation, did not disclose terms of the sale to the MediaNews Group -- a deal that interested several major newspaper companies. The Post's suburban market is among the wealthiest in the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Toronto-based company that owns The Connecticut Post, the state's second-largest daily newspaper, said today that it would sell the paper and five community newspapers in Fairfield County to a chain based in Denver.</p>
        <p>The Post's owner, the Thomson Corporation, did not disclose terms of the sale to the MediaNews Group -- a deal that interested several major newspaper companies. The Post's suburban market is among the wealthiest in the nation.</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Post, which was called The Bridgeport Post until 1992, has a daily circulation of about 76,000, second in the state to The Hartford Courant, which has a daily circulation of about 216,000. The Courant was also sold this year as part of the Tribune Company's acquisition of the Times Mirror Company.</p>
        <p>MediaNews Group, which owns 130 newspapers in 13 states, including The Denver Post, said it did not plan to make any staff or management changes at the Connecticut newspapers, which include weekly papers in Westport, Fairfield, Norwalk and Darien, and a monthly publication called Inside Fairfield County.</p>
        <p>Last week, MediaNews said it had sold 4 daily newspapers and 40 weekly newspapers in southern New Jersey and Pennsylvania. William Dean Singleton, the president of Media News, said the proceeds would be used to acquire the Connecticut papers in a tax-free exchange.</p>
        <p>''It came down to size and position in the market,'' Mr. Singleton said today. ''The New Jersey newspapers were scattered and were small and were not in dominant positions, and this is one larger daily in a dominant position, and quite frankly in a better market.''</p>
        <p>The sale of the Connecticut publications completes Thomson's divestment of its newspaper holdings in the United States, which had included 49 daily papers. Combined proceeds from all of the sales totaled about $2.4 billion, the company said.</p>
        <p>Thomson announced this year that it would leave the newspaper business, except for publishing The Globe and Mail, its flagship property in Toronto, which circulates throughout Canada. The company is focusing on its fast-growing Internet-based information management businesses.</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Lodovic, a spokesman for MediaNews Group, said that the company had not been actively searching to buy newspapers in Connecticut but that it became interested after Thomson's negotiations with other potential buyers began to stall.</p>
        <p>''It sort of fell into our lap,'' Mr. Lodovic said.</p>
        <p>In March, the Tribune Company became the dominant newspaper company in Connecticut when it reached a deal to buy Times Mirror,  the parent company of The Hartford Courant, The Advocate of Stamford and Greenwich Time. Those papers have a combined weekday circulation of more than 250,000.</p>
        <p>Thomson Newspapers bought The Bridgeport Post and The Telegram, evening and morning sister newspapers, in June 1988 for $210 million from Post Holding, a company controlled by the Pfriem and Flicker families.</p>
        <p>The name of the newspaper was changed in June 1992. Critics said the change was intended to cut ties with  Bridgeport, which was suffering from crime and financial problems.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 15, 2000, Saturday  An article on Thursday about the impending sale of The Connecticut Post, the daily newspaper in Bridgeport, misstated its circulation ranking in the state. The Post is No. 3 -- behind The Hartford Courant as well as The New Haven Register -- not No. 2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 15, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about the impending sale of The Connecticut Post, the daily newspaper in Bridgeport, misstated its circulation ranking in the state. The Post is No. 3 -- behind The Hartford Courant as well as The New Haven Register -- not No. 2.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
