<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On U.S. TV, Mideast's Talking Heads Turn Downright Neighborly</title>
    <meta content="Y13MED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palestinian Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burg, Avraham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ashrawi, Hanan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crossfire (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DA1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On U.S. TV, Mideast's Talking Heads Turn Downright Neighborly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>FREDERICK, Md., July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Avraham Burg, Israeli Parliament speaker, and Hanan Ashrawi, a Palestinian legislator, set lighthearted and friendly tone as they debate peace issues on CNN's Crossfire; television appearance, amid news coverage of Camp David summit, exposes a reality that ordinary Israelis and Palestinians do not get to see at home: the real familiarity that has grown during seven-year conversation between elite strata of the two sides; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To American television viewers, it was probably unremarkable to see Avraham Burg, the Israeli Parliament speaker, and Hanan Ashrawi, a Palestinian legislator, bantering, teasing each other and debating peace issues on CNN's ''Crossfire'' on Tuesday night. That's what guests with opposing points of view do on such shows: they furiously argue in a stagey way that makes it absolutely clear that they are sparring intellectually, not personally.</p>
        <p>''Let me finish, Avrum!'' Dr. Ashrawi said, using his nickname, as she lightheartedly chided Mr. Burg, who bowed his yarmulke-covered head, apologized profusely and smilingly bit his lip, in perfect debate-show mode.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To American television viewers, it was probably unremarkable to see Avraham Burg, the Israeli Parliament speaker, and Hanan Ashrawi, a Palestinian legislator, bantering, teasing each other and debating peace issues on CNN's ''Crossfire'' on Tuesday night. That's what guests with opposing points of view do on such shows: they furiously argue in a stagey way that makes it absolutely clear that they are sparring intellectually, not personally.</p>
        <p>''Let me finish, Avrum!'' Dr. Ashrawi said, using his nickname, as she lightheartedly chided Mr. Burg, who bowed his yarmulke-covered head, apologized profusely and smilingly bit his lip, in perfect debate-show mode.</p>
        <p>But in the Middle East, Israeli and Palestinian officials do not do this.</p>
        <p>The issues, bone-deep and highly personal, do not lend themselves and the forums do not exist. Palestinian officials do not traipse onto Israeli television shows and play bang-bang, kiss-kiss. They do not appear at all.</p>
        <p>There do exist close bonds between Israeli and Palestinian officials that have developed since the first peace agreement was signed in 1993. But these relationships are behind closed doors; official Israeli-Palestinian camaraderie is rarely publicly spied.</p>
        <p>So it was an absolutely startling sight for Middle Easterners and Middle East hands here, not far from Camp David, to watch the exchange on ''Crossfire,'' and a similar one between Dr. Ashrawi and Yuli Tamir, the Israeli immigration minister, on PBS's ''NewsHour With Jim Lehrer.''</p>
        <p>In the course of covering the Camp David summit meeting, American television was unwittingly exposing a reality that ordinary Israelis and Palestinians do not get to see: the real familiarity that is the fruit of a seven-year conversation between elite strata of the two sides.</p>
        <p>The shows somehow made the conflict seem so manageable, as if it were just a disagreement over, say, defense funding between American politicians. It made it seem as if it could, after all, be resolved by talk, by human contact between people who do live right down the road from each other. It made it seem easier than it really is, of course, but it pointed up just what makes this summit meeting at Camp David different from previous negotiations: the Israelis and the Palestinians, unlike the Israelis and the Syrians or the two sides before 1993, now know each other.</p>
        <p>''Here, you saw a transition from what goes on behind the scenes to national television,'' said David Makovsky, a senior fellow at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy. ''On the one hand, it's remarkable. On the other, it's not such a big leap. To me, it illustrates the best hope for why a meeting like this could succeed. Because each side knows the other, and knows the parameters of the possible.''</p>
        <p>A clear illustration of how far things have come in a decade is the first attempt by the American news media to place Israelis and Palestinians together on television.</p>
        <p>In the late 1980's, Ted Koppel, the host of ABC's ''Nightline,'' went to Jerusalem and tried to engineer a conversation between the two sides at the Jerusalem Theater. He succeeded but only after agreeing to erect a kind of fence between them on the stage, so that as Dr. Ashrawi then insisted, the occupier could be separated from the occupied and it would be clear that the conversation was neither routine nor normal.</p>
        <p>This week, the fences have truly come down.</p>
        <p>''For me, to see myself and Hanan Ashrawi, at the same studio,'' Mr. Burg said, shaking his head. ''We've been in the crossfire at home, literally speaking, a couple of years ago.''</p>
        <p>Bill Press, the host, tried to understand. ''A Palestinian Crossfire?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Mr. Burg said, ''It was ---- '' Dr. Ashrawi finished his sentence, ''Real live.'' Mr. Burg continued, ''It was real live crossfire in Ramallah. Both of us at her place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burg, who is a religious Jew and a dove, went on, effectively, to recognize the Palestinian state. ''If it walks like a duck and it talks like a duck and it sounds like a duck, it's a Palestinian state,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Again, Dr. Ashrawi interjected: ''A lame duck.''</p>
        <p>A gregarious, ambitious Labor Party politician who got his start as an antiwar activist following the Israeli invasion of Lebanon, Mr. Burg said he was explicitly trying to ''create a kind of covenant'' with Dr. Ashrawi, ''us against the extremists of both sides, not to enable them to veto the peace process.''</p>
        <p>The show conveniently ended before Dr. Ashrawi, a seasoned media expert who can speak cogently and passionately about the Palestinian cause at the drop of a microphone, had a chance to join or reject the covenant. Since she has been expressing a very nuanced critique of the peace effort in her role as Palestinian spokeswoman this week, it would probably not have been easy for her to embrace Mr. Burg's enthusiasm as wholly as he would have liked.</p>
        <p>In her appearance with Dr. Tamir, a political philosopher and a long-time peace advocate, Dr. Ashrawi talked with great familiarity. ''It was like a reunion of two girlfriends,'' Gadi Baltiansky, Prime Minister Ehud Barak's spokesman, said. But the two women diverged strongly in their outlook, and their ideological differences served to underscore how unusual their social ease with each other was.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ashrawi talked about breaking down the psychological legacy of the occupation that still colors the Israeli-Palestinian relationship. She talked about how Israelis are approaching the peace table in what she sees as a patronizing fashion, describing themselves as ready to grant the Palestinians a generous deal, ''take it or leave it.''</p>
        <p>''I have a problem with this kind of mentality and I'm sorry, Yuli, I know you very well and I have tremendous respect for you as a friend and a woman,'' Dr. Ashrawi said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tamir, in turn, said, ''I am surprised that Hanan -- if I may call you Hanan, because we are good friends -- talks about unilateral attempts to sort of impose a solution. We are here in a summit talking together. I mean, Prime Minister Barak and Yasir Arafat are sitting together and trying to find the most suitable compromise for all of us in the region.''</p>
        <p>Their ideological differences served to underscore the effortlessness of their rapport. The dynamic, so newly displayed on American television far from home, suggested both how far Israelis and Palestinians have come and how far they have to go.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
