<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Slain In Robbery At a Home In Queens</title>
    <meta content="13SLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, John W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFDD1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Slain In Robbery At a Home In Queens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, John W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Woman is slashed to death in her Queens apartment by three men who also nail hands of her boyfriend, Todd Taylor, to wooden post and take thousands of dollars from safe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 24-year-old woman was slashed to death inside her Queens apartment yesterday by three men who also nailed the hands of her live-in boyfriend to a two-by-four and took thousands of dollars from a safe, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police did not release the name of the woman, pending notification of her family. They said she worked as a topless dancer at Ten's, a cabaret in Manhattan, and was thought to have been from Canada. They found her with her throat slashed early yesterday in her apartment on 135th Street in the Briarwood neighborhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 24-year-old woman was slashed to death inside her Queens apartment yesterday by three men who also nailed the hands of her live-in boyfriend to a two-by-four and took thousands of dollars from a safe, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police did not release the name of the woman, pending notification of her family. They said she worked as a topless dancer at Ten's, a cabaret in Manhattan, and was thought to have been from Canada. They found her with her throat slashed early yesterday in her apartment on 135th Street in the Briarwood neighborhood.</p>
        <p>The man described by the police as her boyfriend, Todd Taylor, 34, was taken to Mary Immaculate Hospital, treated for injuries to his hands and released about 10 a.m., said Daphne Lawrence, a hospital spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor's hands had been nailed behind his back to a wooden post with two nails apiece, said Lt. Stephen Biegel, a police spokesman. Mr. Taylor called 911 at 4:24 a.m., but it was not clear how, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor told investigators that he awoke early yesterday to find three men, clad in stocking masks and gloves, inside the apartment.</p>
        <p>Further details about the victims and the crime, including the amount of money taken, were sketchy yesterday.</p>
        <p>Outside the three-story red-brick house in a quiet neighborhood of tree-lined streets, a steady flow of police investigators streamed in and out. They collected evidence throughout the day. A driveway at the apartment building was marked off with four bright orange cones and red tape. Neighbors watched as the police removed a body bag from the apartment building just after 1:30 p.m. Few seemed to know anything about the couple.</p>
        <p>Anthony Sorensen, 21, who lives in a building across the street, said he had occasionally seen the woman coming and going, but did not know her name. Mr. Sorensen, who was walking his two pit bulls yesterday, said that earlier the police had asked him whether he had heard anything unusual the night before. He told them that he had not and that his dogs, who usually bark if they hear a disturbance in the neighborhood, were quiet Tuesday night, he said.</p>
        <p>Like other residents, he was surprised by the crime. ''Nothing really happens here, maybe a stolen car occasionally,'' he said. ''But we don't hear about stuff like this happening. It's kind of scary.''</p>
        <p>A woman who answered the telephone yesterday at Ten's, at 35 East 21st Street, said the club had not been contacted by police investigators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
