<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ISRAEL DROPS PLAN TO SELL AIR RADAR TO CHINA MILITARY</title>
    <meta content="13MIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Sales Abroad</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DA1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ISRAEL DROPS PLAN TO SELL AIR RADAR TO CHINA MILITARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>THURMONT, Md., July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel announces that it has canceled its sale of a sophisticated $250 million airborne radar system to China, a decision timed for second day of Camp David summit meeting and aimed at improving mood in Congress, where heated opposition to deal has threatened aid to Israelis; move is carefully calibrated by Isreali officials so that they would be better poised to receive increased assistance if any peace accord is reached with Palestinians; Pres Clinton welcomes decision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel announced today that it had canceled its sale of a sophisticated $250 million airborne radar system to China, a decision timed for the second day of the Camp David summit meeting and aimed at improving the mood in Congress, where heated opposition to the deal had threatened aid to the Israelis.</p>
        <p>The move was carefully calibrated by Israeli officials so that they would be better poised to receive increased American military assistance if any peace accord is reached between the Palestinians and Israelis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israel announced today that it had canceled its sale of a sophisticated $250 million airborne radar system to China, a decision timed for the second day of the Camp David summit meeting and aimed at improving the mood in Congress, where heated opposition to the deal had threatened aid to the Israelis.</p>
        <p>The move was carefully calibrated by Israeli officials so that they would be better poised to receive increased American military assistance if any peace accord is reached between the Palestinians and Israelis.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel informed Mr. Clinton of the decision Tuesday night when the two leaders met about six miles from here at Camp David, a spokesman for Mr. Barak said.</p>
        <p>An Israeli statement said the deal, which had been under way for five years, was canceled ''with consideration of the need for a continued intimate relationship with the United States administration and Congress.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who said recently that he had spoken more than once to Mr. Barak about the administration's concern over Israel giving military help to the Chinese, welcomed the decision. His spokesman, Joe Lockhart, said: ''Israel has made a decision here; they took into account our security concerns. We appreciate that.''</p>
        <p>The cancellation was unlikely to have any direct effect on the workings of the summit meeting, where talks continued in what was described as an informal atmosphere of casual dress and simple gatherings at mealtime between Israeli and Palestinian negotiators. Despite the carefree atmosphere, Mr. Lockhart said that reaching a positive outcome was still going to be a struggle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton spent his second day with Mr. Barak and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, but was scheduled to take a break for a speech on Thursday before an N.A.A.C.P. meeting in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Pressure on Israel to cancel the Phalcon airborne radar had been building for weeks as senior members of Congress, including some considered sympathetic to Israel, publicly criticized the deal. The planned sale of military technology to China was particularly irritating, they said, given the strong military relationship between Israel and the United States.</p>
        <p>Israel's assurances that it was not providing American technology to the Chinese did not mollify critics.</p>
        <p>In announcing the cancellation, the Israelis avoided what could have been an embarrassing debate on the floor of the House of Representatives today, where the chairman of the Appropriations Subcommittee on Foreign Operations, Representative Sonny Callahan, Republican of Alabama, was preparing to bring up an amendment holding back $250 million in assistance to Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callahan said he was glad that ''for the sake of United States national security interests and, in fact, in the national security interests of all our allies, such as Israel'' that the sale had been canceled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callahan's proposal to hold back the money had already failed in his subcommittee. And the amendment was not expected to pass the House either. But each airing of the legislation provoked negative remarks against Israel at a time when the Barak government has been seeking more assistance.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Barak's objectives at Camp David is that Israel should come away with an upgraded military relationship with the United States as compensation for any risks it might encounter in compromising with the Palestinians. If a full peace accord is reached at Camp David, Israel expects to get a significant increase in its defense capabilities from the United States, including radar to detect missiles from Iran and Iraq. This year, of a $2.8 billion aid package to Israel, $1.98 billion was for military assistance.</p>
        <p>Until quite recently, the Israeli government had tried to modify the sale with the Chinese to calm the increasing opposition in Congress. Israel has earned billions of dollars in arms sales to China in recent years, according to arms experts, and was reluctant to cut off the relationship.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the Chinese president, Jiang Zemin, laying out the cancellation, Mr. Barak expressed the hope that there might be room for future cooperation, an Israeli official said today.</p>
        <p>The letter was delivered on Monday in Beijing by the director general of the Ministry of Defense, Amos Yaron.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon began protesting to the Israeli government late last year after a subsidiary of Israel Aircraft Industries mounted the radar system on a Russian-made cargo plane destined for the Chinese Air Force. The subsidiary, known as Elta, designed the Phalcon system for the Israeli Air Force. A Chinese-owned Ilyushin-76 outfitted with the radar has been parked at Ben-Gurion International Airport.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration said it was most concerned because the system would significantly increase the capabilities of the Chinese to track warplanes in and around the Taiwan Strait.</p>
        <p>The Israeli argument that a closer relationship with the Chinese military would allow Israel to dissuade Beijing from supplying weaponry to Iran and Iraq did not win many converts in the United States.</p>
        <p>In Congress today, there was wide support for the cancellation, but still caution. ''This is not a note of victory,'' said Fred Downey, a legislative aide to Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut. ''It's the Israelis coming to the right decision so we can discuss the upgraded security arrangement'' that would come with a successful summit meeting.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress were informed of the decision this morning by the Israeli ambassador to Washington, David Ivri, a former Israeli Air Force commander and a main architect of Israel's weapons sales to China since the mid-1990's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
