<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Co-op City's Operators Face Race Discrimination Lawsuit</title>
    <meta content="13COOP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Co-Op City (Bronx, NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Riverbay Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scott, Marion, Real Estate Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Marion</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DA1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Co-op City's Operators Face Race Discrimination Lawsuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fifty employees and tenants of Co-Op City apartment complex, Bronx, most of them either black or Hispanic, sue Riverbay Corp, complex's owner, Marion Scott Real Estate Co, which manages development, and sales manager Steve Gold, charging racial discrimination in workplace and in sales office; charge workers face crude racial harassment by white co-workers and were denied promotions based on race; charge prospective black residents are steered into less desirable buildings, with preference given to whites; Marion Scott, who is black, denies charges, noting two-thirds of workers and 70 percent of residents are black or Hispanic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The operators of Co-op City, the sprawling apartment development in the Bronx that is home to 60,000 mostly black and Hispanic residents, are being sued by 50 employees and residents who say they faced racial discrimination in the workplace and in the sales office of the complex.</p>
        <p>In the suit, which the plaintiffs plan to file this morning in State Supreme Court in the Bronx, the employees charge that they faced crude racial harassment at the hands of white co-workers and were denied promotions based on their race. The workers and tenants, all but one of whom are black or Hispanic, also say prospective black residents were steered into less desirable buildings, with preference given to whites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The operators of Co-op City, the sprawling apartment development in the Bronx that is home to 60,000 mostly black and Hispanic residents, are being sued by 50 employees and residents who say they faced racial discrimination in the workplace and in the sales office of the complex.</p>
        <p>In the suit, which the plaintiffs plan to file this morning in State Supreme Court in the Bronx, the employees charge that they faced crude racial harassment at the hands of white co-workers and were denied promotions based on their race. The workers and tenants, all but one of whom are black or Hispanic, also say prospective black residents were steered into less desirable buildings, with preference given to whites.</p>
        <p>The suit names as defendants the Riverbay Corporation, Co-op City's owner; Marion Scott Real Estate Company, the development's private manager; and Steve Gold, the sales manager. Parts of the suit were provided yesterday to The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey K. Brown, the lawyer for the plaintiffs, said the development's owners had ''systematically repressed minorities.''</p>
        <p>''They've done it through various mechanisms,'' he said. ''One is denial of advancements. Two is disparate treatment and three is a racially hostile and intimidating environment, where people are called the 'N' word, where people have feces smeared on their vehicles, where people are told not to place African-Americans and minorities in certain housing sections.''</p>
        <p>The accusations were aggressively denounced by Marion Scott, president of Marion Scott Real Estate, which last year became the first private company to run Co-op City since the 1968 construction of its 35 towers, schools and retail centers in the northeast Bronx.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott, who is African-American, called the claims ludicrous given that two-thirds of Co-op City's 925 employees and more than 70 percent of residents are black or Hispanic. He said he was incensed at charges  that prospective black residents were steered toward ''black'' buildings or that their applications were shredded. He said state oversight of Co-op City prevents such bias.</p>
        <p>He also said creating hurdles for prospective minority residents would have been economically foolhardy, especially because the development had about 700 vacancies during the time that the plaintiffs are alleging the wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>''We have outside bouncers throwing people in here, not throwing people out,'' he said. ''We were looking for anyone who had the money and the qualifications to apply.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott also accused the Long Island law firm filing the suit, Leeds, Morelli &amp; Brown, of being ''stick-up artists.'' He said the firm was trying to extort money from Co-op City with a frivolous case.</p>
        <p>Last week, Riverbay's lawyers  filed a complaint with the New York State Grievance Committee of the 10th Judicial District, accusing Leeds, Morelli &amp; Brown of trying to force Riverbay to pay $7.5 million in fees to pay for mediation to resolve the complaints and forgo litigation.</p>
        <p>Several plaintiffs remained adamant about their charges yesterday. Jaime Paredes, 57, said he kept running into obstacles when he tried to buy a two-bedroom apartment in a desirable area. He was rejected last September, he said.</p>
        <p>''They're looking to put a white family in that apartment, not a Hispanic, and I'm a Hispanic,'' Mr. Paredes said.</p>
        <p>Brenda Brown, 48, a former Riverbay office worker and resident of Co-op City who is black, said she put up with racial taunts and watched white office workers make it difficult for blacks to move into Co-op City. Ms. Brown also said she was passed up for promotions.</p>
        <p>''It's hostile,'' she said, ''when your face is black and you see injustices done.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Scott said Ms. Brown was fired in June 1999 after she was caught on videotape punching the time cards of fellow workers hours after the workers had finished their shift. As for Mr. Paredes's claims, Mr. Scott said people who are rejected often complain to regulators, though most claims are unfounded.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the demographics of the young people who've rented, they're mostly black and Hispanics,'' Mr. Scott said. ''He might have been turned down for other reasons.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
