<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strong Gains Return Nasdaq to Positive Ground for Year</title>
    <meta content="Y13STO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DE1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strong Gains Return Nasdaq to Positive Ground for Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composit indes gains 143.17 points, or 3.6 percent, to close at 4,099.59, best finish since start of slump April 10; Dow Jones industrial average gains 56.57 points to close at 10,783.76; graph (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Internet and other computer-related stocks surged yesterday, propelling the Nasdaq market to its biggest gain in more than five weeks and back into positive territory for the year.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index rose 143.17 points, or 3.6 percent, to 4,099.59 -- its best finish since April 10, the beginning of a disastrous week when the index fell 25.3 percent over five consecutive days. Analysts and strategists attributed yesterday's sharp rise to fading concern about higher interest rates and a better-than-expected earnings report from Yahoo issued after the exchanges closed on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Internet and other computer-related stocks surged yesterday, propelling the Nasdaq market to its biggest gain in more than five weeks and back into positive territory for the year.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index rose 143.17 points, or 3.6 percent, to 4,099.59 -- its best finish since April 10, the beginning of a disastrous week when the index fell 25.3 percent over five consecutive days. Analysts and strategists attributed yesterday's sharp rise to fading concern about higher interest rates and a better-than-expected earnings report from Yahoo issued after the exchanges closed on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''Yahoo helped set the stage,'' said Andrew Brooks, chief trader at T. Rowe Price Associates, as revived strength in high-technology shoved cyclical stocks, which briefly rallied earlier in the week, into the background once again.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average still managed to post its fourth consecutive gain, rising 56.57, or 0.5 percent, to 10,783.76. J. P. Morgan, up 4 5/8, to 122 9/16, accounted for more than half the advance. Brokerage stocks, benefiting from the announced takeover of PaineWebber by UBS of Switzerland, joined high-technology as the session's best-performing group. PaineWebber soared 161 5/16, to 66 7/8.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gained 12.04, or 0.8 percent, to 1,492.92, lifting its gain so far this year to 1.61 percent.</p>
        <p>''The real concern is earnings, not interest rates,'' said Charles J. Pradilla, strategist at SG Cowen Securities. ''And there's a growing conviction that you're looking either at the last or the penultimate tightening'' by the Federal Reserve.</p>
        <p>Applied Micro Circuits, up 11 11/16, to 125 7/16, reported after the close that revenue more than doubled and profits, after allowing for merger costs, beat expectations. Bestfoods, to be acquired by Unilever, matched Wall Street profit estimates. Motorola said after the markets closed yesterday that its earnings met expectations.</p>
        <p>''Yahoo clearly led the market and convinced people that the fundamentals of Internet stocks, which have been acting sickly lately, remain vibrant,'' said Thomas M. Galvin, chief investment officer at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Having erased the steep spring losses, the Nasdaq is now ahead for the year, by a scant 0.74 percent, after an 85.6 percent leap in 1999.</p>
        <p>The Dow narrowed its loss so far this year to 6.2 percent. After Morgan, the biggest positive contributors were Intel and I.B.M., each up more than 2.</p>
        <p>Drug stocks were weak as the Senate considered adding prescription benefits for Medicare recipients, raising concerns among investors about possible price controls that could more than offset the benefit of greater sales.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Notes Are Down</p>
        <p>(By Bloomberg News) -- Treasury notes fell yesterday, as  $15 billion of new higher-yielding nongovernment debt lured investors.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of corporate sales that offer value'' compared with Treasuries, said Gary Zeltzer, who may buy some of the new corporate debt for the $10 billion he invests at J &amp; W Seligman &amp; Company. He bought notes of the utility company Dominion Resources that sold on Monday with five-year yields at about 7 3/4 percent.</p>
        <p>The 10-year Treasury note fell 6/32, to a price of 103 3/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 6.07 percent from 6.04 percent on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond rose 1/32, to 105 6/32. The bond's yield was unchanged at 5.88 percent.</p>
        <p>Results of yesterday's Treasury auction of 10-year inflation notes:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>High Price: 103.539  High Yield: 4.030%  Low Yield: 3.880%  Median Yield: 3.997%  Accepted at low price: 52%  Total applied for: $11,741,020  Accepted: $5,001,620  Noncompetitive: $47,639  Interest set at: 4 1/4</p>
        <p>The 10-year inflation notes mature Jan. 15, 2010.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
