<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Who Fled Austria in Terror Return in Triumph</title>
    <meta content="13ARTS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Museum (Vienna)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porges, Paul Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porges, Lucie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willis, Mary Pleshette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DD1E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Who Fled Austria in Terror Return in Triumph</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Pleshette Willis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Willis, Mary Pleshette</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts Abroad column on retrospective at Jewish Museum in Vienna honoring life and work of illustrators Paul Peter Porges and wife Lucie; both were persecuted there during Nazi era; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What really gets you is the red sweater with three white P's across the breast, the same hand-knit sweater a 12-year-old boy named Paul Peter Porges wore as he boarded a Kindertransport from Vienna to France on a wet, nasty night in March 1939, one step ahead of the Nazis. That this particular sweater has survived and is part of a retrospective honoring his life and work, along with that of his wife, Lucie, who also barely got out of Vienna alive, perhaps symbolizes what makes this exhibition compelling: the everyday details of life.</p>
        <p>''Lucie and Paul Peter Porges: Style and Humor'' opened at the Jewish Museum of Vienna on May 31 and runs through mid-September. But it almost did not open. The Porgeses seriously considered canceling the show when Jorg Haider's right-wing Freedom Party became part of Austria's coalition government. Both lost grandparents, aunts, uncles and cousins in Nazi camps -- Mauthausen is only 80 miles away -- and Mr. Porges's parents spent two years in Theresienstadt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What really gets you is the red sweater with three white P's across the breast, the same hand-knit sweater a 12-year-old boy named Paul Peter Porges wore as he boarded a Kindertransport from Vienna to France on a wet, nasty night in March 1939, one step ahead of the Nazis. That this particular sweater has survived and is part of a retrospective honoring his life and work, along with that of his wife, Lucie, who also barely got out of Vienna alive, perhaps symbolizes what makes this exhibition compelling: the everyday details of life.</p>
        <p>''Lucie and Paul Peter Porges: Style and Humor'' opened at the Jewish Museum of Vienna on May 31 and runs through mid-September. But it almost did not open. The Porgeses seriously considered canceling the show when Jorg Haider's right-wing Freedom Party became part of Austria's coalition government. Both lost grandparents, aunts, uncles and cousins in Nazi camps -- Mauthausen is only 80 miles away -- and Mr. Porges's parents spent two years in Theresienstadt.</p>
        <p>Sixty years after they were persecuted here, Peter Marboe, Vienna's cultural affairs counselor, presented the Porgeses with a medal honoring them. Werner Hanak, 31, the curator of the show, said: ''I wanted the city to honor them not as an excuse for what happened but as a thank you for their astonishing generosity. They are first and foremost fine artists, amazingly upbeat people who have provided a positive link between Vienna and New York.''</p>
        <p>Lucie Eisenstab and Paul Peter Porges were born at the same maternity clinic in Vienna in 1926, when the city had a thriving community of almost 200,000 Jews; today there are only about 8,000. After different but equally dramatic escapes to Switzerland from the Nazi occupiers in France, they met and fell in love at art school in Geneva and eventually emigrated to New York, where they were married, raised two daughters and still live.</p>
        <p>In an interview at the museum, Mr. Porges said: ''Why should I feel any more animosity toward the Austrians than the French? They were just as bad. There was a cop in France who caught me at the Swiss border, took me home and handcuffed me to the window while he sat down with his family to eat dinner.''</p>
        <p>Today people forget that Engelbert Dollfuss, Austria's 1930's chancellor, was a dictator, he said. ''He was meek compared to Hitler, but he was a fascist'' too, he said. ''Next to them Haider is a ninny.''</p>
        <p>The early drawings in the exhibition were done when Mr. Porges was living at La Guette, a school outside Paris sponsored by Baron Eduard Rothschild to protect and educate Jewish children from Austria and Germany. The drawings tell the story of a child who was ripped away from his parents and plunked down in a country where he neither spoke the language nor knew a soul.</p>
        <p>''Aunty Ella Making Schnitzel and Pauly Eating Artichokes'' is a poignant drawing of a child longing for home. His self-portrait in his red sweater with the caption ''I'm doing fine'' is a sweet assurance to his parents (and himself) that he is alive. The other early drawings depict a world of violence: knives, hammers, hypodermic needles (''The Vaccination''), blood-spurting wounds and Hitler gobbling up Europe.</p>
        <p>In 1940, eight months after he arrived at La Guette, the Germans invaded France, and Mr. Porges began three years of wandering through Vichy France until he was captured trying to cross into Spain and sent to an internment camp near Perpignan. Once again he escaped and was smuggled with 15 other teenagers into Switzerland.</p>
        <p>''I was the only one who wasn't turned back,'' he said. ''The Swiss didn't like the Jews any better than anybody else. But because I wasn't yet 16, they had to keep me.''</p>
        <p>His first work in America was a comic strip, ''Pvt. Adam Apple,'' which he drew for the United States Army after he was drafted in 1950. Eventually his cartoons became decidedly American, depicting ordinary people doing things like watering their lawns, playing with their dogs, getting their eyes examined.</p>
        <p>He became one of the most published cartoonists in The Saturday Evening Post and a member of the gang at Mad magazine. But it was the more subtle cartoons of the 1960's and 70's in The New Yorker and Playboy that captured his American style: a typical suburbanite who watches his Calder mobile shed leaves as the tree does outside his large picture window, or an assembly line of angst-ridden patients whose therapist is suspended above them on a chair attached to a pulley.  As the exhibition shows, Mr. Porges's drawing style looked as if it had emanated from a person who had grown up in the United States.</p>
        <p>Lucie Porges, on the other hand, despite a successful career in fashion design in Manhattan, never lost her distinctively European flair. After World War II, which she survived without once being separated from her younger sister and parents, she went to Paris to become a fashion illustrator and would have happily remained to design clothes had the Army not prevented her husband from joining her in France. After arriving alone in New York, she took her portfolio to the designer Pauline Trigere. She was hired the following week and remained for 43 years.</p>
        <p>The actual clothes she designed -- made of the most luxurious thick satins and brightly colored silks, soft woolen tweeds and furs -- are not part of the exhibition. Instead they are represented by large paper-doll cutouts that attest to her talent as a designer but do not show how the garments feel or how they fall. More touching are the early sketches she did in Paris, a series of watercolors of herself in her little room that breathe with the aspiration of a young woman setting out on her own after the war.</p>
        <p>She said she had wanted to cancel the Vienna show more than her husband did, but that in the end she agreed it was important to go forward.</p>
        <p>''At first I thought I can't go back and be honored by the city that chased me out and killed my grandparents,'' she said. ''But then I thought about all the young friends we have made here, none of whom want Haider. And I thought, 'Why let him ruin it for the rest of us?' I feel this show is like rounding out the circle. A way of showing them we won.''</p>
        <p>At the museum, addressing the audience of friends and family, press and politicians in English, Mr. Porges said: ''This is more than just a show. It's a happening. And without my friends it would mean nothing.''</p>
        <p>Then, lapsing into German, he added: ''The night I left Vienna my father and I walked past the park where I had played until the Jews were no longer allowed. It was early morning, and no one was around. 'Do you want to go in and look around?' he said. But I was too scared. Then he took my face in his hands and said, 'One day you will come back, and you will be honored as a Jew.' ''</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
