<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travel Boom Pulls Japan and South Korea Closer</title>
    <meta content="Y13JAP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japan-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fukuoka (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Fukuoka</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED61E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travel Boom Pulls Japan and South Korea Closer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>FUKUOKA, Japan</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Warming relations between South Korea and Japan after years of mistrust and disdain are reflected by explosion in tourism between the two countries; Fukuoka, which is close to Korean peninsula, has become favored jumping-off point for Japanese travelers; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As he waited to board a flight back to his native South Korea, Kim Tae Won still could not believe the reception his 40-person theater troupe had received all week from standing-room-only audiences in this provincial capital in southern Japan.</p>
        <p>After years of hearing stories about Japan tinged in mistrust and disdain, Mr. Kim, whose troupe was performing a historical play about a Mongol invasion of Japan via Korea, pronounced what amounted to a burying of the hatchet between two of Asia's most closely related, yet persistently contentious, neighbors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As he waited to board a flight back to his native South Korea, Kim Tae Won still could not believe the reception his 40-person theater troupe had received all week from standing-room-only audiences in this provincial capital in southern Japan.</p>
        <p>After years of hearing stories about Japan tinged in mistrust and disdain, Mr. Kim, whose troupe was performing a historical play about a Mongol invasion of Japan via Korea, pronounced what amounted to a burying of the hatchet between two of Asia's most closely related, yet persistently contentious, neighbors.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the old feelings of hatred toward Japan like we used to anymore,'' he said. ''And I guess our stay here shows that the Japanese have finally learned to respect us, too.''</p>
        <p>The burgeoning detente between South Korea and Japan can be seen in many ways, from their agreeing to be co-hosts of the World Cup soccer tournament in 2002, to the increasingly frequent trips back and forth between leaders of the two countries, to South Korea's pending invitation of the Japanese emperor to Seoul, which, given Japan's bitterly resented imperial rule of Korea early this century, would have been unthinkable even just a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim visited during Korea Week in Fukuoka, where Korean master potters displayed their works and lectured Japanese audiences about ceramics, brought to this country from Korea centuries ago. And Korean flower arrangers showed off their innovations in an art largely inspired by ancient Japanese traditions.</p>
        <p>But the best reflection of the spreading warmth between the countries is the way travel between them -- not just by business people and officials, but by homemakers, students and ordinary tourists -- has exploded in the last few years, making South Korea the preferred destination of Japanese last year, replacing the longtime favorite, Hawaii.</p>
        <p>Travel between the countries is booming at a time of historic shifts in relationships throughout the region. Japan and South Korea are enjoying  rare warmth in what had long been lucrative but frosty economic ties.</p>
        <p>For the first time in years, starting with a historic summit meeting of their leaders in June, North and South Korea have been making major progress toward ending the state of war between them. The thaw between North and South Korea, meanwhile, has encouraged the government in Pyongyang, North Korea, to moderate its often shrill rhetoric against Tokyo, and even begin hinting at a reconciliation with Japan, which North Korea usually depicts as the source of evil and corruption in Northeast Asia.</p>
        <p>The softer tone may reflect a recognition that capital from Japan -- which has the world's second largest economy -- will be indispensable for the reconstruction of a North Korea on the verge of collapse.</p>
        <p>It would be hard to find a sea boundary in Asia whose history has been more tumultuous or of deeper impact than the Korea Strait, a 100-mile-wide stretch of ocean separating Fukuoka from Pusan, in southern South Korea. Although the subject remains shrouded in mystery and is taboo here, Japan's imperial family is believed by many historians to have arrived from across these seas some 2,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>The Mongols, who ruled Korea, invaded twice and were defeated the second time only by a typhoon, the original kamikaze, or holy wind, which wrecked their armada of 3,500 ships in 1281.</p>
        <p>Three centuries later, feudal Japan launched two invasions of its own, involving 150,000 or so troops each time, but was undone by help from Chinese allies and Korea's invention of the world's first armored sea craft, the Turtle Ship.</p>
        <p>These days, the invasions are different but still aggressive: weekend shopping expeditions and culinary raids for spicy Korean kimchi or delicate Japanese specialties, or school trips, amusement park visits and health spa ''cures.'' Private visits between the two countries are taking place at a rate of more than two million a year, and because of its proximity to the Korean peninsula, Fukuoka, once the favored jumping-off point for conquerors, has become the leading springboard for travelers.</p>
        <p>Where diplomacy has often come up short in the past, growing contacts like these between South Korea and Japan seem to be changing the ways -- often deeply stereotyped -- the two peoples think about each other. Japanese people visit South Korea and discover a country far more orderly and developed than they had been led to believe.</p>
        <p>''I had heard a lot about Korea before I went, but my impressions of the place were much better than the image I used to have,'' said Kyoko Fukuda, a Japanese beautician whose flight from Seoul, where she went to attend a conference, had just landed. ''We have always heard that the living standard is very low there, but in fact the difference was not so terribly great.''</p>
        <p>South Koreans, meanwhile, are noting a greater willingness among Japanese to acknowledge them as peers rather than subjects and to acknowledge that Japanese culture has borrowed heavily from its western neighbor -- which is important given South Koreans' deep sense of national pride.</p>
        <p>In June, as a result, South Korea lifted restrictions on imports of Japanese films and most television programming. The measure follows a more timid relaxation of controls on ''cultural imports'' from Japan that began in 1988.</p>
        <p>''The Japanese were deeply influenced by Korea,'' said Lee Kang Hyo, a South Korean ceramics artist who lectured recently in Fukuoka, where Korean masterpieces were on display at a municipal exhibition hall, along with historical correspondence from Hideyoshi, the Japanese shogun who twice invaded the country. ''But you have to come to Japan to see the best of our classical tradition preserved.''</p>
        <p>That fact has much to do, Mr. Lee hastened to add, with Japan's 35-year colonization of Korea, which ended in 1945, and its previous conquest of the country, when Korean masterpieces were carted off to Japan in large quantities. But he said he was also surprised to learn during his first visit to Fukuoka, last month,  that there was still a deep sense of prestige attached to the classical Korean style here.</p>
        <p>Japanese academics, meanwhile, say that they have begun to work closely together with their Korean counterparts to piece together the shared history of the two peoples, overcoming a legacy of mutual contempt. ''It is safe to say that Japan had a feeling of superiority over Korea,'' said Koji Saeki, a professor of history at Kyushu University, in Fukuoka. ''But the exchanges between Japanese and Korean scholars are very active now, and they are strengthening all the time.''</p>
        <p>It is in the area of the painful history that has long divided the two peoples that the most distance has been traveled.</p>
        <p>Only in fits and starts has the Japanese government shown a willingness to address the question of Japanese imperial rule over the Korean peninsula, apologizing officially to the Korean government, but devoting relatively little attention in officially sanctioned textbooks to Japanese brutality, like the use of Korean women as sex slaves for the imperial army.</p>
        <p>Prominent Japanese politicians, meanwhile, periodically continue to make provocative statements about Koreans in Japan, blaming them for crime, for example.</p>
        <p>Individual Japanese who have traveled to South Korea, however, say that their experience of the country has brought them to reflect deeply about their own country's expansionist past. Often they express a kind of remorse whose sincerity rings far truer than any official declaration.</p>
        <p>South Korean tour guides play a subtle but important role, deliberately bringing Japanese visitors to sites that commemorate the sacking of their country and attempted destruction of their culture by several generations of Japanese invaders.</p>
        <p>''We learned almost nothing about this in school,'' said Makiko Nakatsukuma, a 27-year-old homemaker, who had just traveled with her best friend to Pusan by high-speed ferry for a weekend of shopping. ''In Korea it was explained to us how Japan had forced Koreans to learn our language, and to abandon their names in favor of Japanese names. Many Koreans were brought to Japan by force, too, and had to work as virtual slaves.</p>
        <p>''The whole time I was there, I just felt like apologizing to the Korean people. It is very hard to explain, but even though I am from the postwar generations, I felt so bad about all of this. You want to say you are sorry, but who do you say it to?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
