<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y13BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DB1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: EUROPEAN PANEL PICKED -- The European Court of Human Rights appointed three men to a panel that will study Austria's human rights record and the political nature of Jorg Haider's far-right Freedom Party, a step that seems to be ending Austria's political isolation. They are diplomats from Finland and Spain and a professor from Germany. France then indicated it was inviting Austria's envoys to its Bastille Day celebrations, on Friday, and Belgium said it was making a similar invitation for its national day.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: SPEAKER TO QUIT -- Betty Boothroyd, the first woman to be Speaker of the House of Commons, whose cries of ''Order! Order!'' are familiar to television viewers in Britain and abroad, announced that she will retire this fall. Ms. Boothroyd, 70, a Labor Party lawmaker since 1973 and Speaker since 1992, said ''Be happy for me!'' in response to groans of disappointment. She received a round of applause, rarely heard in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: EUROPEAN PANEL PICKED -- The European Court of Human Rights appointed three men to a panel that will study Austria's human rights record and the political nature of Jorg Haider's far-right Freedom Party, a step that seems to be ending Austria's political isolation. They are diplomats from Finland and Spain and a professor from Germany. France then indicated it was inviting Austria's envoys to its Bastille Day celebrations, on Friday, and Belgium said it was making a similar invitation for its national day.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: SPEAKER TO QUIT -- Betty Boothroyd, the first woman to be Speaker of the House of Commons, whose cries of ''Order! Order!'' are familiar to television viewers in Britain and abroad, announced that she will retire this fall. Ms. Boothroyd, 70, a Labor Party lawmaker since 1973 and Speaker since 1992, said ''Be happy for me!'' in response to groans of disappointment. She received a round of applause, rarely heard in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: PROTESTANT ADMISSION -- The Protestant church admitted it used forced laborers in World War II and said it would pay $4.9 million to a $4.9 billion compensation fund for Nazi-era victims. The acknowledgment came after disclosures that from 1943 to 1945, 26 Protestant and 2 Catholic parishes in Berlin ran a camp for about 100 forced laborers from eastern Europe and Russia for work in graveyards. A Catholic spokesman said the church had no plans to contribute to the fund.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>GREECE: GERMAN PROTEST -- Germany lodged a protest with Greece as bailiffs, guarded by the police, moved to assess the value of German property in Athens to be seized and sold in compensation for the massacre of 218 Greek villagers by Nazi forces in 1944. The properties include the Goethe Institute. The Supreme Court sanctioned the move in an April ruling awarding $30 million to the victims' families.</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
        <p>GREECE: ANTITERROR MESSAGE -- Greek television broadcast a message against terrorism at noon as lawmakers and civil servants held a minute's silence in tribute to terrorist victims. The message, reading ''Terrorism is an insult to Greeks, and a threat to Greece,'' comes a month after the assassination of Brig. Stephen Saunders, Britain's top military envoy to Athens.</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: BOMB WOUNDS 9 -- Suspected Basque rebels set off a car bomb in central Madrid, wounding nine people. Callers saying they were from the Basque separatist group E.T.A. warned authorities the bomb was to go off in 30 minutes, but it exploded after 15 minutes, leading officials to believe the police officers clearing the area were the intended target.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: ABORTION ALERT -- The police have warned abortion providers to be on alert after a man entered the office of a Vancouver gynecologist who performs abortions and stabbed him in the back. Dr. Garson Romalis was hospitalized after he was attacked by a young man in his 20's whose face was obscured by a black sweatshirt hood. In 1994 a sniper shot and wounded Dr. Romalis at his home.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: GUERRILLAS STAY JAILED -- A Tel Aviv court ruled two Lebanese guerrillas abducted and held for years as bargaining chips for a missing Israeli airman should remain in jail for three more months, until the case is decided. The court accepted government arguments that Sheik Abdel Karim Obeid of Hezbollah and Mustafa Dirani of the Amal movement were a security threat. The state raised the security issue after the Supreme Court ruled prisoners could not be held as bargaining chips.</p>
        <p>Joel Greenberg (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: POLITICAL MERGING -- A month after the two leading white political parties announced plans to merge, officials from the Inkatha Freedom Party, the country's second largest black political party, said they would consider merging with the governing party, the African National Congress. No formal decisions have been made yet. But the suggested merger comes as parties position themselves for local elections, scheduled for November.</p>
        <p>Rachel L. Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS</p>
        <p>U.S. PAYS DUES -- The United States paid some of its back dues to peacekeeping operations, including $40 million for Kosovo and $53 million for East Timor. By international agreement, Washington is billed 31 percent for every peacekeeping mission, but Congress has ruled that 25 percent is the limit, and arrears continue to build. United Nations accounts show the United States debt totals $1.65 billion.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>CHINA: COHEN VISITS -- Defense Secretary William S. Cohen met China's vice president, defense minister and senior military leaders in the first of three days of talks. Mr. Cohen had a friendly reception, reflecting China's desire to patch up relations with the United States, though it expressed vehement opposition to Washington's proposed national missile defense.</p>
        <p>Erik Eckholm (NYT)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: EUROPEAN PLEA -- Three European foreign ministers will press the government in person to secure the release of hostages held by Muslim rebels, Foreign Minister Hubert Vedrine of France said. Mr. Vedrine said he and Joschka Fischer of Germany would team up today in Manila with Erkki Tuomioja of Finland for meetings with officials and hostage negotiators. France, Germany and Finland are the three European Union countries with citizens held captive on the southern island of Jolo.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
