<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Building Peace in Ulster</title>
    <meta content="13THU2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Ulster Constabulary</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D61E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Building Peace in Ulster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says recent disturbances between Catholics and Protestants during summer marching season in Northern Ireland have been overshadowed by common desire by both sides to strengthen still-fragile peace; urges Britain to help reinforce peace by reforming Royal Ulster Constabulary, Northern Ireland's police force, which is 93 percent Protestant and viewed by many Catholics as alien body (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summer parade season in Northern Ireland is always a time of volatility, and this year is no different. But even the recent disturbances have been overshadowed by a common desire among Protestants and Catholics to strengthen a still-fragile peace. This year's marchers, who commemorate Protestant victories long ago, are fewer in number and less violent than in the past. They are also more marginalized, criticized even by their traditional allies for their intransigence.</p>
        <p>There are other signs of progress. Last month the Irish Republican Army allowed two international envoys to visit a weapons dump and certify that the contents could be monitored -- a measure that should be followed by real I.R.A. disarmament later. Home rule has been revived and is working well. The ministers in Northern Ireland's cabinet belong to parties ranging from Sinn Fein, the political wing of the I.R.A., to the Democratic Unionists, who reject the entire peace process. They are proving to be effective and surprisingly collegial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summer parade season in Northern Ireland is always a time of volatility, and this year is no different. But even the recent disturbances have been overshadowed by a common desire among Protestants and Catholics to strengthen a still-fragile peace. This year's marchers, who commemorate Protestant victories long ago, are fewer in number and less violent than in the past. They are also more marginalized, criticized even by their traditional allies for their intransigence.</p>
        <p>There are other signs of progress. Last month the Irish Republican Army allowed two international envoys to visit a weapons dump and certify that the contents could be monitored -- a measure that should be followed by real I.R.A. disarmament later. Home rule has been revived and is working well. The ministers in Northern Ireland's cabinet belong to parties ranging from Sinn Fein, the political wing of the I.R.A., to the Democratic Unionists, who reject the entire peace process. They are proving to be effective and surprisingly collegial.</p>
        <p>Britain can help reinforce the peace by reforming the Royal Ulster Constabulary, Northern Ireland's police force. The R.U.C., which is 93 percent Protestant, is viewed by many Catholics as an alien body. The composition, law enforcement practices and even the name of the force should be changed so that it can fairly serve the interests of all citizens.</p>
        <p>The British government has recently revised an earlier reform plan that fell well short of the changes that are needed. The version voted out of the House of Commons on Tuesday improves efforts to recruit Catholics into the police and strengthens the powers of a new civilian oversight board. But serious flaws remain that must be remedied. The bill gives too much power to the British secretary for Northern Ireland to impede or block investigations of police misconduct by the civilian board. A new ombudsman would be barred from looking at past events except under extraordinary circumstances.</p>
        <p>But the most controversial provision is the name. Under the bill, the police force would be called the Police Service of Northern Ireland for all operational purposes. But the group's formal documents would use ''Royal Ulster Constabulary'' in its name as well.</p>
        <p>Even symbolic continuity with the R.U.C. may persuade Catholics to continue rejecting the police, which undermines the inclusiveness that is crucial to peace. It could also give the I.R.A. an excuse to stall on disarmament. Northern Ireland's moderate Catholic party also worries that reforms will be watered down when the legislation is instituted. The British government should amend the bill, which now goes to the House of Lords. Northern Ireland cannot have a lasting peace if the police -- in appearance or in fact -- remain a divisive force.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
