<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Writer Rebuilds A Home Called Childhood</title>
    <meta content="13TONY$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT HOME WITH/TONY EARLEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Earley, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, William L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jim the Boy (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDD1E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Writer Rebuilds A Home Called Childhood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, William L</byline>
      <dateline>NASHVILLE, July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William L Hamilton interviews Tony Earley, whose first novel, Jim the Boy, has been hailed in Times as a pitch-perfect parable of childhood; hotos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Earley and his wife, Sarah Bell Earley, were standing in their mustard-yellow kitchen, opening mail. ''French's Mustard yellow,'' Ms. Earley said. ''If you hold the jar up to the wall, it's almost identical.'' The Earleys had been on the road for six weeks, promoting Mr. Earley's first novel, ''Jim the Boy,'' published by Little, Brown last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley read a congratulatory postcard from a college acquaintance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony Earley and his wife, Sarah Bell Earley, were standing in their mustard-yellow kitchen, opening mail. ''French's Mustard yellow,'' Ms. Earley said. ''If you hold the jar up to the wall, it's almost identical.'' The Earleys had been on the road for six weeks, promoting Mr. Earley's first novel, ''Jim the Boy,'' published by Little, Brown last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley read a congratulatory postcard from a college acquaintance.</p>
        <p>''He stole my girl in 1984,'' Mr. Earley said, with some humor and some pique. ''And now he's writing me a postcard. I suppose he thinks I forgot.''</p>
        <p>Things worked out, as stories involving writers often do. The Earleys, from the same town in North Carolina, Rutherfordton, married in 1993.</p>
        <p>''I grew up in a very tiny country Baptist church,'' Mr. Earley said, sitting in the vestibule of their five-room Victorian house in a gentrifying neighborhood of English-cottage gardens and late-model Saabs and chainlink fenced front yards with plastic doghouses and mongrel dogs.</p>
        <p>''I started going to the Episcopal church in our hometown just to impress another woman I was dating at the time, and developed a crush on this girl who sang in the choir. Sitting in church I felt like just a complete heel, because I was there with my girlfriend, but I was longing for this girl in the choir.</p>
        <p>''I married the girl in the choir.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley's first book, ''Here We Are in Paradise,'' short stories, was published in 1994. He was chosen by Granta in 1996 as one of the 20 best young American writers, and in 1999 by The New Yorker as one of ''20 writers for the 21st century.'' Mr. Earley, 39, has taught writing at Vanderbilt University since 1997.</p>
        <p>''Jim the Boy'' is the crystalline story of a year in the life of Jim Glass, a 10-year-old boy growing up in rural North Carolina during the Depression. Mr. Earley said that he wrote the book in the style of children's classics like ''Charlotte's Web'' and ''The Yearling,'' as ''a children's book for adults.'' Janet Maslin reviewing it in The New York Times, called the novel a ''radiant, knowing, pitch-perfect parable of childhood.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley's own childhood and adulthood have been darker. He battles depression: the bright scars of his most recent bout grace the walls as colorful folk paintings he made when he couldn't write.</p>
        <p>''After 'Here We Are in Paradise' came out, I got sick, and stayed sick for a couple of years,'' said Mr. Earley, who speaks quietly and carefully, and with the occasional running jump of an enthusiastic boy. ''I was on the suicide watch for a while. I didn't know if I'd ever write again.'' He started painting on a stack of discarded storm windows, then slowly writing, too.</p>
        <p>''I bought a bunch of cheap paint at Wal-Mart and I started making big words on them,'' he said. ''That's how I started coming out of it: one big word at a time.'' Mr. Earley discounted any therapeutic interpretation of his new book, but said of the nearly clairvoyant simplicity of Jim's impressions, ''On some level that I didn't understand, I wrote the book that I needed to read.''</p>
        <p>Without bearings, in unfamiliar country at the end of the book, Jim asks, ''Which way is home?'' By the author's implication, it is a child's question that most adults spend their lives answering.</p>
        <p>''I was way too sensitive for life on planet Earth,'' Mr. Earley said of himself when he was Jim's age. ''Noises were too long and lights were too bright and my feelings were always hurt. It was just because, I think, I was so incredibly thin-skinned.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley's father was a welder; his mother worked in a department store. His sister was killed in an automobile accident when he was a freshman at Warren Wilson College in Asheville.</p>
        <p>''We grew up in a suburb of a town with 3,000 people in it,'' he said. Mr. Earley's parents' marriage was troubled until he returned from college as an adult, a tension he said dispossessed his happiness in the house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley liked his maternal grandmother's house, ''a big old folk Victorian'' with a parlor and Sunday furniture as he called it, where the preacher sat when he visited.</p>
        <p>In his book, Mr. Earley has turned a child's sensitivities into writerly strengths; domestic events have an extraordinary witness.</p>
        <p>Jim's father dies without warning the week before he is born; at 10, he is as old as his mother's unending grief. By his 11th birthday, he has stepped into the world, wading into its strong waters on a trip to the Atlantic Ocean. At midnight, he has watched Aliceville, his upland county town, visited like a disturbing Bible vision by electric light. On the porch of a moonshiner's shack, he has pressed his nose to a rusted screen, scratched it with his finger and seen his young father rise like river mist in the breath of the dying man inside.</p>
        <p>And at the center of his family circle, Jim's childhood has the buoyant weight of love.</p>
        <p>North Carolina country is Jim's natural sense of place and the haunt of his understanding of the importance of home. It is the other large character in the book.</p>
        <p>''I think it's just a family thing,'' said Mr. Earley, whose family, ''both sides,'' have lived for generations within a five-mile radius in a corner of western North Carolina. ''When every one of your ancestors has been looking at the same landscape for 200 years, it becomes rooted like family, passed on, maybe even genetic.''</p>
        <p>That kind of orientation -- which closes the book as Jim sights Aliceville from the top of a mountain, and realizes that only home has the power to hold the great world's center -- is being lost, Mr. Earley fears.</p>
        <p>''I notice it in the accents of students,'' he said, ''particularly female students. They have the same accent, no matter what part of the country they're from -- a sort of a Valley Girl, television accent. They sound alike.''</p>
        <p>Now, he has his own branch of the family, living in Nashville with Ms. Earley, a former seminary student, and their two Jack Russell terriers, Jubal and Rastus.</p>
        <p>''She's the C.E.O. of the family,'' Mr. Earley said of his wife as he stood in her office. ''I'm production and she's management.'' On the mantel was a map of North Carolina. Behind a rocking chair hung three quilts, made by his grandmothers.</p>
        <p>''Not fancy quilts,'' he said. ''Just everyday quilts.''</p>
        <p>The house is furnished with modest, friendly-looking pieces from a previous era, which the Earleys bought cheaply as a young married couple for their first home.</p>
        <p>''We were just broke,'' he said. ''We lived in a depressed little steel town outside of Pittsburgh. Because it was so depressed, we managed to buy and renovate a house. All of our furniture we bought at used furniture stores in the Ohio River Valley in these other little depressed steel towns strung out along the river. I had a route I drove every Saturday looking for nice furniture that was cheap. Because we got it with smoke and mirrors, I'm attached to it.''</p>
        <p>As a storyteller, Mr. Earley also has a sympathy with the sincerity and drollness of folk art.</p>
        <p>''I have a slight weakness for folk art,'' he said. ''Sarah manages to keep it under control. I'd have paintings on plywood all over the house if it were left up to me.''</p>
        <p>In the kitchen is a copy of a Cezanne still life.</p>
        <p>''It's by a guy we found in Florida who was so excited we were interested in his pictures he gave us three,'' Mr. Earley said. ''His pictures were hanging in a filling station. They'd been there four years and nobody had ever even asked about them.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Earley pointed out that the back line of a table in the picture is untrue, shifting planes behind the globes of fruit. ''I thought that was just his mistake, but in the Cezanne, it's not even across, either,'' she said. ''It's an accurate copy -- the colors are just completely different.''</p>
        <p>On a bookcase in the vestibule is a wood Madonna nursing a child, carved with a chain saw by a sculptor in Mr. Earley's home county.</p>
        <p>''Baptists wandered up into the yard and gave him hard time about a nursing Madonna,'' Mr. Earley recalled. '' 'Well, Jesus had to eat didn't he?' he said to them.''</p>
        <p>In the Earleys' bedroom is a hand-lettered sign set on the lintel of a closet. The sign is naive but not art. ''EVERY DAY I WRITE THE BOOK,'' it says.</p>
        <p>Below it is a pad of large papers with fierce red numbers drawn on them, tacked to the doorjamb like the marks a child makes to measure his height. They are the numbers of the chapters in ''Jim the Boy'' -- a lottery that Mr. Earley fought not to lose for six years.</p>
        <p>''The better I get, the more I feel like I have to lose,'' he said. ''I don't want to give any ground back. I haven't always been where I am now. I don't want to go back to where I was. I don't want to have to climb this hill again.''</p>
        <p>As with the terrain of ''Jim the Boy,'' familiarity can vanish with each new view.</p>
        <p>''It's too big,'' says Jim, seeing his world from the mountain, faltering briefly as an adult.</p>
        <p>Mr. Earley, who says he wishes to write ''The Complete Jim Glass,'' intends to let him grow into it.</p>
        <p>AT HOME WITH/TONY EARLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
