<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grant to Give New York a Look</title>
    <meta content="13KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Portland Trail Blazers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gundy, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Layden, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Portland Trail Blazers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DB1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grant to Give New York a Look</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portland Trail Blazers player Brian Grant visits New York for meeting with New York Knickerbockers coach Jeff Van Gundy and general manager Scott Layden, who are anxious to recruit him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy and General Manager Scott Layden stood nervously by the window at Gate 92 in Newark Airport, talking on cell phones and watching for the flight from Portland, Ore., to arrive. When the plane pulled up to the gate and Brian Grant disembarked, it marked the start of the Knicks' biggest recruiting opportunity and a chance to again alter their aging team.</p>
        <p>With Larry Johnson's body wearing down, the Knicks can offer the 6-foot-9-inch Grant a starting job at power forward and the money that he seeks if he were to commit to New York and force a sign-and-trade deal with the Portland Trail Blazers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy and General Manager Scott Layden stood nervously by the window at Gate 92 in Newark Airport, talking on cell phones and watching for the flight from Portland, Ore., to arrive. When the plane pulled up to the gate and Brian Grant disembarked, it marked the start of the Knicks' biggest recruiting opportunity and a chance to again alter their aging team.</p>
        <p>With Larry Johnson's body wearing down, the Knicks can offer the 6-foot-9-inch Grant a starting job at power forward and the money that he seeks if he were to commit to New York and force a sign-and-trade deal with the Portland Trail Blazers.</p>
        <p>But as he joined Van Gundy and Layden in a limousine this afternoon, the purpose of the trip was to convince Grant and his wife, Gina, that New York can fit the lifestyle that he seeks, something that they could not prod either Grant Hill or Tim Duncan to even take the trip to consider. ''Everybody knows about the New York City nightlife,'' Grant said. ''But you don't really hear a lot about where players live, feedback like how people like the commute. Things like that are going to be important to me and my wife.</p>
        <p>''My main concern is not too much about me altogether, but more so my family. That's what we're really going to look into when we come out here, how this would affect our family, our kids.''</p>
        <p>Grant, who grew up in Georgetown, Ohio, starred at Xavier University and spent three seasons in Sacramento and then the last three in Portland. While the Knicks usually sell the allure of New York City and the opportunities present for a star athlete, Grant already has all the acclaim he seeks. He heads up the Brian Grant Foundation and his charitable efforts have earned him the National Basketball Association's J. Walter Kennedy Citizenship Award for the 1998-99 season. And he has endorsement deals with McDonald's, AT&amp;T and Sega, among other companies. Fans can go to his Web site and purchase an array of souvenirs that feature his dreadlocks and the ''Rasta Monster'' logo.</p>
        <p>What caused Grant to opt out of his contract with the Blazers, which would have paid him more than $40 million over the next four seasons, was his desire to find a more suitable role on the court. The Knicks can certainly offer that after finishing last in the N.B.A. in offensive rebounding last season, with Johnson doing his best to contend against players six inches taller.</p>
        <p>Grant found his playing time reduced to just 21 minutes per game last season on the deep Portland bench. . After undergoing surgery in the off-season, he missed the first eight games last year and was never able to pry his minutes back from Rasheed Wallace. Grant played just eight minutes in the decisive Game 7 loss to the Lakers in the Western Conference finals.</p>
        <p>''I think anything can happen,'' Grant said. ''I am with a great team. I had a very little role in one of the biggest seasons the Blazers had in a long time. We've still got every piece there. It's nothing that you can fault the Blazers for or fault me for. We've just got a lot of players in my position.</p>
        <p>''I've kind of got to weigh out, maybe being in one place and possibly winning a championship and having somewhat of a minor role in it, or to be able to go somewhere where you are already in the playoffs and contending and you have a major role in it.'' Grant, 28, was traveling with his wife, but a major concern was his three sons, the oldest just 4 years old, and how they would adjust to life in New York.</p>
        <p>After pulling out of his contract with the Blazers, he has made it clear that returning to Portland is not out of the question. Without Portland agreeing to a sign-and-trade agreement, the most the cap-restricted Knicks could offer Grant is $2.25 million next year.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks began rookie camp at Fairfield University in Connecticut Wednesday, and FREDERICK WEIS, last year's first-round draft pick, was still absent with no word of when he would arrive. FRANK CATAPANO, who represents Weis in the United States, said he had been unable to contact the center, who is remaining in France to be with his ill father.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
