<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Meditations and Bird Song, Messiaen Has Arrived. Or Has He?</title>
    <meta content="13PHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS: MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival 2000</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vonk, Hans</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oestreich, James R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messiaen, Olivier (Eugene Prosper Charles) (1908-92)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA1E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Meditations and Bird Song, Messiaen Has Arrived. Or Has He?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oestreich, James R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James R Oestreich reviews performance of music of Olivier Messiaen by New York Philharmonic under Hans Vonk, at Lincoln Center Festival 2000 at Alice Tully Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Has Olivier Messiaen's time come? And if so, what does that arrival say about this time?</p>
        <p>Such questions are raised by Lincoln Center Festival 2000, with its central focus on the music of Messiaen, including three of his grandest statements. ''Eclairs sur l'Au-Dela'' was part of the festival's opening night on Tuesday, performed by the New York Philharmonic at Avery Fisher Hall. The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center gives a reprise of an acclaimed performance of ''Des Canyons aux Etoiles'' next Tuesday at Alice Tully Hall, and the Philharmonic follows three days later with the ''Turangalila'' Symphony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Has Olivier Messiaen's time come? And if so, what does that arrival say about this time?</p>
        <p>Such questions are raised by Lincoln Center Festival 2000, with its central focus on the music of Messiaen, including three of his grandest statements. ''Eclairs sur l'Au-Dela'' was part of the festival's opening night on Tuesday, performed by the New York Philharmonic at Avery Fisher Hall. The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center gives a reprise of an acclaimed performance of ''Des Canyons aux Etoiles'' next Tuesday at Alice Tully Hall, and the Philharmonic follows three days later with the ''Turangalila'' Symphony.</p>
        <p>Works of Messiaen are also featured in the festival's Electronic Evolution series, with ''Le Merle Noir'' being presented tonight at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, near Lincoln Center. With the composer's organ music having received expert surveys in each of the last two seasons in New York, all that is missing, it seems, is Messiaen's huge opera, ''St. Francois d'Assise,'' which the festival has been eyeing for years without result.</p>
        <p>Messiaen would probably never have presumed to declare, as Mahler did, that his time would come. Accumulating evidence, including those dozen organ recitals, suggests that it may have, yet it remains to be seen whether the wave is still merely forming or near its crest.</p>
        <p>That Messiaen's time should come sooner -- now, just eight years after his death -- rather than later is not surprising in this fast-paced blur of an age. But as with his mystical counterparts in Eastern Europe, the current attention must also owe much to the awe (not to say sheer weirdness) greeting the millennium.</p>
        <p>For Messiaen's music is deeply imbued with his Roman Catholic faith. Like the music of those Eastern Europeans and unlike Mahler's, it represents withdrawal from this world, nowhere more than in ''Eclairs sur l'Au-Dela'' (''Illuminations of the Beyond'') from 1991. This was Messiaen's last major work, given its premiere by the Philharmonic after his death.</p>
        <p>In 11 movements, Messiaen offers meditations on quotations from the Revelation of St. John the Divine and elsewhere. This 65-minute symphony is a deft summation of his spiritual concerns and musical style.</p>
        <p>And ''meditations'' is the word, for by this time Messiaen had perfected his ability to make music stand still. For the most part, progress is hardly an issue. Chords are shaped and polished to preserve their individual integrity rather than lead from one to another. Phrases open out in all directions rather than simply rise or fall. Interruptions and abrupt changes are everywhere. The music is what it is so long as it is, and then, suddenly, it is something else.</p>
        <p>All the better to help the listener savor these contemplations of God, often represented by nature, especially birds. It is hard to imagine Messiaen ever using birds or animals to comic effect, as Mahler did. But Mahler was rooted in the earth and nature, where he seemed to find whatever gods he needed. Messiaen is rooted in the Christian deity, with all of nature its mere reflection.</p>
        <p>The ninth movement of ''Eclairs'' (better translated, as a program note suggests, as ''Lightning Bolts'') is quintessential, casting Christ as the tree of life. ''The elect will gather the fruits of this wonderful tree,'' Dom. J. de Monleon's text runs, ''and they will sing like birds in its branches.''</p>
        <p>The music is glorious: 18 woodwinds playing songs of 25 birds. The movement is also typical in the way it uses an expanded orchestra: often piecemeal, a section or two at a time.</p>
        <p>The performance, conducted by Hans Vonk, was excellent. Although the vast assemblage sported many unfamiliar faces, and although some important familiar ones were missing, Mr. Vonk pulled the group into a convincing and sonorous whole.</p>
        <p>All well and good, but if Messiaen's time is truly to come, it will have to carry audiences in tow, and the meager turnout here was unpromising. However edifying the occasion, however fine the performance, it is hard to feel entirely festive sitting amid swaths of empty seats.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS: MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
