<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Millions Offered for 2 Manuscripts Show High-Stake Gambles in Publishing</title>
    <meta content="13BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000725T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Random House</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harpercollins Publishers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warner Books</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John F Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1DA1E38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Millions Offered for 2 Manuscripts Show High-Stake Gambles in Publishing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's Making Books column examines $3.3 million offer by Random House for memoir of former Treasury Secretary Robert Rubin and $7.7 million offer to General Electric chairman John F Welch by HarperCollins and Warner Books; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's bemusing that within the last few days two books that promise to deliver the wisdom of two men celebrated for their economic and business prescience and perspicacity received bids so large that many are questioning the fiscal prescience and perspicacity of the publishers who offered the money.</p>
        <p>On Friday Random House agreed to pay Robert Rubin, former secretary of the treasury, $3.3 million for his memoir. Almost a beggarly sum, it turned out to be, compared with the record $7 million advance that was put on the tabzaple Wednesday by two publishers before John F. Welch Jr., chairman and chief executive of General Electric, for his chronicle of success. The publishers who each made this colossal commitment were HarperCollins and Warner Books, and both apparently spent yesterday scurrying about showing Mr. Welch and his agent, Mark Reiter, their distinct marketing plans in hopes of closing the deal. Fiscal lunacy on their part? Perhaps. But in a business that is essentially risk-driven, it's really not as nutty as it sounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's bemusing that within the last few days two books that promise to deliver the wisdom of two men celebrated for their economic and business prescience and perspicacity received bids so large that many are questioning the fiscal prescience and perspicacity of the publishers who offered the money.</p>
        <p>On Friday Random House agreed to pay Robert Rubin, former secretary of the treasury, $3.3 million for his memoir. Almost a beggarly sum, it turned out to be, compared with the record $7 million advance that was put on the tabzaple Wednesday by two publishers before John F. Welch Jr., chairman and chief executive of General Electric, for his chronicle of success. The publishers who each made this colossal commitment were HarperCollins and Warner Books, and both apparently spent yesterday scurrying about showing Mr. Welch and his agent, Mark Reiter, their distinct marketing plans in hopes of closing the deal. Fiscal lunacy on their part? Perhaps. But in a business that is essentially risk-driven, it's really not as nutty as it sounds.</p>
        <p>What kinds of sales are needed for these two deals to be successful, if not brilliant? One publisher who underbid on the Welch book estimated that with a cover price of $30, there would have to be a net sale --  called ''clean sales,'' or the actual number of books sold to readers -- of about 1.6 million copies to make a profit. The Rubin book would have to have a net of about 750,000. These are rough figures, since each publisher calculates differently. Still, however one does the math, it comes down to selling a deluge of books, numbers seldom achieved in nonfiction.</p>
        <p>Of course, many disdain the deals as mad, and say they don't think it's possible for Mr. Rubin's book to be profitable at his price, let alone Mr. Welch's. But as Stuart Applebaum, the spokesman for Random House,  noted: ''The favorite pastime in book publishing is second-guessing the competition's big-money acquisitions.'' Mr. Applebaum was one of the three Bantam Books executives who persuaded Lee A. Iacocca, the chairman of Chrysler, to write his autobiography with William Novak in 1982. (He and Mr. Iacocca went to the same Manhattan hair stylist, and it was the barber who arranged for the executive to meet with the Bantam group.) The book went on to sell more than than seven million copies in North America after its publication in 1984, and is sort of the obelisk of business books, cited often by those who bid for Mr. Welch's project. (Mr. Iacocca, one recalls, was appearing about a thousand times a week on television in Chrysler ads, and was almost a pop figure. His advance was in the six figures. Imagine what it would be now!)</p>
        <p>Publishing books is always about speculation, whether a publisher or an editor is taking a plunge with a $15,000 advance for a first novel or a $100,000 advance for nonfiction. What is the psychology of the very high-price dice roll, in seven figures? Publishers will bid high not just for economic reasons, but often to make a statement, to announce that they are serious players for a particular kind of book, as, for instance, when a paperback house moves into hardcover publishing as well. (Bantam Books did just that in 1982 by publishing Jimmy Carter's White House memoirs.)</p>
        <p>Or, as Morton L. Janklow, Mr. Rubin's agent, said: ''There's all kinds of reasons to publish a big book, and it's not only measured by royalties. There's list leadership, there's prestige; there are many reasons for doing books and many ways define profits.''</p>
        <p>And, of course, big-money advances generate big headlines, which will generate big awareness among potential readers, which (it is then hoped) will generate big sales.</p>
        <p>To take a $7 million or even $3.3 million leap takes the courage of one's convictions. To a person not in book publishing, Mr. Rubin's 16-page proposal and outline (written with his co-author, Jacob Weisberg) is dry reading indeed. But to Ann Godoff, the publisher of Random House, who will edit the book, it was as exciting as, well, standing at the craps table with the dice on her fingers. She said that Mr. Rubin ''is the architect of one of the biggest bull markets in history, certainly in this century, and a lot of people are going to want to look at his experience and learn from it.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''He was rather an oracle; the book will be a front-row seminar to advance thinking on economics and will explain the very practical decision-making tools that he uses. People want to be around that kind of thinking.''</p>
        <p>How government and business connect; how the markets work; his predictions for the global economy. There is for this sort of book ''a first constituency, a big hardcover market of people who read books about finance and the economy,'' Ms. Godoff said. That's the mantra. And Random House has the paperback rights as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin will deliver the manuscript in two years. Will potential readers still care? That's part of the gamble. People are still reading Mr. Iacocca. Ms. Godoff said that ''if we construct the book properly it will have an enormous backlist potential; we will have created a classic title that can be reissued and updated for a really long time.''</p>
        <p>If the Rubin book is grandly perceived by its creators as the economic primer for the new century, Mr. Welch's memoir (to be written with John A. Byrne) will be, at least in part, a how-to book by the man who is arguably the most successful corporate executive in the world. Certainly his name is invoked daily in M.B.A. classes as embodying a sort of business divinity, and the two publishers left of the eight who bid find the project irresistible because they believe it, too, will have a big sale up front and a long backlist life. Businessmen, like movie stars, seem to be catnip to book publishers and, besides Mr. Iaocca's, the last decade or so has seen books from, among others, Thomas J. Watson Jr. (I.B.M.), which succeeded, and three from Donald J. Trump, one of which was a huge best seller; the other two did less well. Michael Eisner's (Disney) failed. And, of course, there's William H. Gates, America's best-known chief executive, whose two books had combined hardcover sales of fewer than one million copies.</p>
        <p>It's easy for a publisher when the bidding shoots sky high to roll his eyes and say, ''Not for me,'' for the numbers alone will almost always say, ''No go.'' So about these two books? For my 2 cents, the publishers might just pull it off. To paraphrase Mark Twain's remark about Wagner's music -- ''It is better than it sounds'' -- the deals could well turn out better than they appear.</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS  Correction:  July 25, 2000, Tuesday  The Making Books column on July 13 and an article in Business Day on July 14 about the $7.1 million book advance reportedly being paid to John F. Welch Jr., the chairman of the General Electric Company, referred to the precedents incompletely. (Similar references appeared in an Op-Ed page column on July 16, in the Media Talk column of Business Day on July 17 and in an editorial on July 20.) While the advance is apparently a single-book record for North American nonfiction rights, higher amounts have been paid for worldwide English rights. Pope John Paul II reportedly received an $8.5 million advance in 1994 for his book about Roman Catholicism in the modern era. The sale of Mr. Welch's worldwide English rights is expected to add millions to his North American advance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 25, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Making Books column on July 13 and an article in Business Day on July 14 about the $7.1 million book advance reportedly being paid to John F. Welch Jr., the chairman of the General Electric Company, referred to the precedents incompletely. (Similar references appeared in an Op-Ed page column on July 16, in the Media Talk column of Business Day on July 17 and in an editorial on July 20.) While the advance is apparently a single-book record for North American nonfiction rights, higher amounts have been paid for worldwide English rights. Pope John Paul II reportedly received an $8.5 million advance in 1994 for his book about Roman Catholicism in the modern era. The sale of Mr. Welch's worldwide English rights is expected to add millions to his North American advance.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
