<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Hunting Down The 'Perfect' Outfit</title>
    <meta content="13SHOP$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sombasa Media</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">StyleSpeak (E-Mail Newsletter)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D61138F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Hunting Down The 'Perfect' Outfit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Online Shopper column on buying clothes through the e-mail newsletter called StyleSpeak by Sombasa Media, which provides fashion advice and links to Web sites of the merchants selling recommended items; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FASHION guru I consulted last week told me that if I wanted to look ''daring,'' I should shop online for a certain outfit that consists of a peacock blue camisole and matching skirt, then accessorize with a turquoise necklace and wedge-heeled sandals to avoid concealing any toe ring I might happen to be wearing.</p>
        <p>This outfit, not including toe ring, would cost me $597, but the consultant assured me that it would be worth it if I wanted to ''stand out'' while attending a social event like, say, a friend's wedding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FASHION guru I consulted last week told me that if I wanted to look ''daring,'' I should shop online for a certain outfit that consists of a peacock blue camisole and matching skirt, then accessorize with a turquoise necklace and wedge-heeled sandals to avoid concealing any toe ring I might happen to be wearing.</p>
        <p>This outfit, not including toe ring, would cost me $597, but the consultant assured me that it would be worth it if I wanted to ''stand out'' while attending a social event like, say, a friend's wedding.</p>
        <p>It was tempting, if only because I didn't have to do all the hard work.  The service was free from an e-mail newsletter called StyleSpeak by Sombasa Media, whose parent company is About.com. Inspired by the success of its BargainDog newsletter, which sends e-mail updates to more than a million subscribers looking for online discounts, Sombasa Media began offering StyleSpeak last month. I subscribed to the weekly newsletter (www.stylespeak .com), which offers two editions, one for women's clothing and one for men's.</p>
        <p>My online mentor then hunted down accessories and chose colors that work well together, then rounded up thumbnail photos of all the items so I could scrutinize them online. All I had to do to look put together really well was click on the links beneath the photos to go directly to the Web sites of the merchants selling the various pieces of my outfit.</p>
        <p>In the past, the only people who have consistently displayed that level of concern over my personal appearance have been my mother, whose interest waned about 30 years ago after I announced that I would no longer wear appliqued pinafores, and my husband, who hopes in vain that I'll stop blaming him for letting me buy that ghastly brown skirt at the mall.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to create a type of online catalog that would show people what goes together,'' said David Beisel, a Sombasa spokesman, ''which wristwatch you should wear with which pants, how to put together a whole style and look, and then buy it easily online.''</p>
        <p>But StyleSpeak is not a typical catalog, I decided after reading the first two editions. What sets it apart is personality.</p>
        <p>With a friendly orange background, a clean layout and outfits that revolve around weekly themes like ''Still Single?'' and ''Summer Lovin','' StyleSpeak offers sturdy opinions without sounding like a know-it-all. It provides context and a catchy description for each article of clothing. And most important, it assigns a specific theme to almost any item you might want to buy, whether it's a bathing suit or shoes. Want to look ''sporty'' at the beach? StyleSpeak says: ''Sporty girls love that surfer-chick style. Just add a pair of cute beaded flip-flops, rubproof sun block and a colorful tote to throw it all in.'' If you're a guy who wants to look ''urban'' at a social event? ''You can't go wrong with this stylish three-button suit from Brooks Brothers. Add a subtle, soft gray shirt with a bold DKNY tie.''</p>
        <p>Those sorts of self-assured judgments were almost enough to make me believe, momentarily, that I was chatting with a trusted friend. Perhaps I should buy the camisole outfit?</p>
        <p>Then a small, inner voice piped up. It asked, ''Peacock blue?'' This is a color, after all, that makes my complexion look sallow. And couldn't a toe ring cut off circulation?</p>
        <p>Troubled, I phoned Linda Price, a marketing professor at the University of Nebraska who has studied how and why shoppers seek guidance in deciding what to buy. ''Things like StyleSpeak are an important break from the past because they are more personal and more customized than if you were flipping through Cosmopolitan magazine to see what they recommend in makeup,'' Professor Price said. ''What's at the heart of this Internet stuff is this question: What kind of relationship do we have with a company, like StyleSpeak, and is it the same kind of relationship we would have with a person, like a friend, who is giving us advice?''</p>
        <p>If I had gotten advice from my mother or a friend, Professor Price pointed out, I would have known ''that person is working for you.''</p>
        <p>''But StyleSpeak is working for StyleSpeak,'' she said. ''It's not interested in helping you. It's interested in getting you to buy things.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Beisel said, StyleSpeak earns money by taking a percentage of the sales it generates by referring people to its several dozen merchant partners, which include such online retailers as Gap, Lands' End, Spiegel and Shoebuy.com.</p>
        <p>If StyleSpeak really understood me, it would have nudged me toward outfits that fit in with the themes in my existing wardrobe. ''Urban'' and ''sporty'' are too generic. For social events, for instance, I favor a look called ''too young to have children.'' Waiting impatiently to be seated in a crowded restaurant, I like my clothes to say ''possible celebrity.'' And on days when I have to attend school events, my daughters like me to dress in a style I can describe only as ''cute mom with a ponytail.''</p>
        <p>Helpfully, I phoned StyleSpeak's merchandising manager, Anya Kyong, to suggest those themes.</p>
        <p>''I can picture 'cute mom in a ponytail' in some Gap capris, something like that,'' she agreed. ''That would be our classic look.''</p>
        <p>We were getting along pretty well, and I was starting to really trust Ms. Kyong. In fact, after I heard that she is the person responsible for handpicking the newsletter's recommendations and that she favors ''real-life dressing, like wearing the cute flower dress with the flip-flops you picked up on sale at the drugstore,'' I started to think that her advice would be helpful to me.</p>
        <p>But when I confided that what I was really looking for this summer was a youthful theme -- ''you know, an outfit that screams 'Card me, please!' '' -- she paused.</p>
        <p>''Hmm,'' she said. ''You're probably a little older than I am. I'm just one year out of school. Maybe what you want would be the 'daring' look.''</p>
        <p>I hung up the phone and logged off. No peacock blue camisole for me.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
