<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official Says Test Implicates Inmate Given Stay by Bush</title>
    <meta content="13DEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcginn, Ricky Nolen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFDC1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official Says Test Implicates Inmate Given Stay by Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials say DNA test has failed to exonerate Texas death row inmate Ricky Nolen McGinn, whose case took on political significance last month when Gov George W Bush interrupted his presidential campaign to grant a stay of execution (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DNA test has failed to exonerate a Texas death row inmate whose case took on political significance last month when Gov. George W. Bush interrupted his presidential campaign to grant the man a stay of execution, say officials knowledgeable about  the results.</p>
        <p>The case of Ricky Nolen McGinn, 43, who was convicted of raping and murdering his 12-year-old stepdaughter, attracted national attention when his lawyers urged that new DNA tests be conducted to address doubts about his conviction. Mr. Bush, who has presided over 137 executions since taking office in 1995, granted Mr. McGinn a reprieve -- the first time the governor had done so -- to allow the DNA tests to take place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DNA test has failed to exonerate a Texas death row inmate whose case took on political significance last month when Gov. George W. Bush interrupted his presidential campaign to grant the man a stay of execution, say officials knowledgeable about  the results.</p>
        <p>The case of Ricky Nolen McGinn, 43, who was convicted of raping and murdering his 12-year-old stepdaughter, attracted national attention when his lawyers urged that new DNA tests be conducted to address doubts about his conviction. Mr. Bush, who has presided over 137 executions since taking office in 1995, granted Mr. McGinn a reprieve -- the first time the governor had done so -- to allow the DNA tests to take place.</p>
        <p>Now, one of a series of DNA tests being conducted in response to Mr. Bush's reprieve has confirmed a match with Mr. McGinn, a law enforcement official and a high-ranking Texas Republican said. The match was also confirmed by a federal law enforcement official.</p>
        <p>In June, after the reprieve, Judge Stephen Ellis in Brown County, ordered tests on pubic hairs and semen collected from the victim's body. Under the judge's order, the Federal Bureau of Investigation is testing the hair, while the Texas Department of Public Safety is testing the semen. DNA experts hired by Mr. McGinn's lawyers also are conducting tests. The law enforcement official did not say which test had confirmed the match.</p>
        <p>The complete battery of tests are expected to be completed by Aug. 15 when a hearing is scheduled and when Judge Ellis could rule and set a new execution date. USA Today reported today that the test conducted by the F.B.I. showed that the hair belonged to either Mr. McGinn or a maternal relative, which officials see as an unlikely alternative because none of his relatives were implicated in the case.</p>
        <p>The test findings could provide some political ammunition for Mr. Bush, who has come under scrutiny and criticism for the capital punishment system in Texas. Michael Jones, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, said the governor's office had not yet been notified of any DNA results and noted that the additional testing could take several more weeks.</p>
        <p>At a news conference outside the governor's mansion, Mr. Bush said: ''All the evidence is under a gag order. All parties are not supposed to talk about it, and I'm going to honor that gag order.'' Later, he said of the case, ''at some point in time we'll find out the truth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McGinn had been scheduled to die by lethal injection on June 1, and the state Board of Pardons and Paroles had voted against recommending a reprieve for DNA testing. But Mr. Bush, who under state law can override the board in such a case and grant a 30-day stay, decided to do that. In doing so, he said Mr. McGinn could ''have his full day in court.''</p>
        <p>The issue of DNA testing arose at Mr. McGinn's initial trial five years ago. But DNA tests conducted at the time were inconclusive. But because of advances in testing technology, Mr. McGinn's lawyers had argued that new tests would now yield conclusive results. Mr. McGinn's lawyers professed his innocence and argued in particular that DNA testing could at the very least exonerate him of the rape. It was the conviction that crime that when added to the murder conviction, created the aggravated circumstances that qualified Mr. McGinn for the death penalty.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor in the case, Lee Haney, did not return telephone calls seeking comment. Lawyers for Mr. McGinn, citing a gag order in the case, declined to discuss the DNA test. But speaking in broad terms, one lawyer, Maurie Levin, said a test result from any single case should not serve as an endorsement of the state's death penalty system.</p>
        <p>''To me, Governor Bush's reprieve acknowledged problems in the system,'' said Ms. Levin, who as the head of Texas Defender Service regularly handles death row appeals.</p>
        <p>In June, State Senator Rodney Ellis, a Democrat from Houston, announced that he would introduce a bill the legislative session next year that would allow convicted felons under certain circumstances to request DNA testing if such testing could definitively prove their guilt or innocence. Currently, only New York and Illinois have such a law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
