<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Generic-Drug Maker Agrees to Settlement In Price-Fixing Case</title>
    <meta content="13GENE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lorazepam (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ativan (Tranquilizer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clorazepate (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Traxene (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anxiety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mylan Laboratories Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anxiety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Sedatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DB1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Generic-Drug Maker Agrees to Settlement In Price-Fixing Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Generic drugmaker Mylan Laboratories tentatively agrees to pay $147 million to settle accusations that it improperly cornered market on raw materials for two widely prescribed drugs and then raised price of those drugs, in some instances more than 3,000 percent; if approved, settlement would be largest ever reached by Federal Trade Commission in an anticompetition case and would settle lawsuits filed by the commission, 33 states and variety of other drug purchasers, from large health maintenance organizations to groups of patients; would also break new legal ground by using most of money to reimburse consumers; settlement is also seen as important step in efforts by government to control rapidly rising medical costs; case concerns antianxiety drugs lorazepam, generic version of Ativan, and clorazepate, generic version of Traxene (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the world's largest makers of generic drugs tentatively agreed today to pay $147 million to settle accusations that it improperly cornered the market on raw materials for two widely prescribed drugs and then raised the price of those drugs, in some instances more than 3,000 percent.</p>
        <p>If approved by the government and a judge, the settlement with Mylan Laboratories would be the largest ever reached by the Federal Trade Commission in an anticompetition case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the world's largest makers of generic drugs tentatively agreed today to pay $147 million to settle accusations that it improperly cornered the market on raw materials for two widely prescribed drugs and then raised the price of those drugs, in some instances more than 3,000 percent.</p>
        <p>If approved by the government and a judge, the settlement with Mylan Laboratories would be the largest ever reached by the Federal Trade Commission in an anticompetition case.</p>
        <p>It would resolve lawsuits filed almost two years ago by the commission, 33 states and a variety of other drug purchasers, from the largest health maintenance organizations to groups of insured and uninsured patients. They had accused Mylan of monopolizing the market and conspiring to restrain trade.</p>
        <p>The tentative settlement, which was confirmed by government officials, also proposes to plow new legal ground by using most of the money to reimburse consumers. In the great majority of antitrust cases, the F.T.C. has sought injunctions to halt illegal conduct. It is rare for the commission to force a company to surrender what it regards as ill-gotten gains.</p>
        <p>The settlement is also an important step in efforts by the government to control rapidly rising medical costs. Generic drugs have traditionally been more attractive to consumers, particularly those on fixed incomes and the elderly, because  they are less expensive than brand names.</p>
        <p>But a few years ago the prices of many popular generic drugs began to rise drastically, far outpacing increases in brand-name drugs, and some analysts said Mylan was the most aggressive of the price raisers.</p>
        <p>The cases concerned two widely prescribed antianxiety drugs, which shot up in price in 1998. Doctors write  more than 21 million prescriptions each year for the drugs, lorazepam, the generic version of Ativan, and clorazepate, the generic version of Tranxene.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Mylan raised the price of a bottle of 500 tablets of clorazepate to $377 from $11.36. A similar bottle of lorazepam was raised to $190 from $7.</p>
        <p>The government said the price increases were a result of exclusive license agreements Mylan had reached with its supplier for certain ingredients in the drugs. The government said the agreements prevented Mylan's rivals from obtaining sufficient supplies and enabled the company to gouge patients on the prices it charged for the drugs.</p>
        <p>Officials said today that they had vigorously pursued Mylan because they thought the company's conduct was particularly egregious and had hurt society's most vulnerable members.</p>
        <p>''This illegal conduct has cost consumers millions of dollars over the past two years,'' said Betty D. Montgomery, the attorney general of Ohio. ''What makes this behavior even more unconscionable is that these drugs, especially lorazepam, are antianxiety mediations frequently prescribed for nursing home and hospice patients, including those suffering from long-term debilitating conditions such as Alzheimer's disease.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''The bulk of the restitution will go back into the pockets of the affected seniors, where it belongs.''</p>
        <p>As they have since 1998, Mylan executives said today that they had never violated any antitrust laws. But they said that they had decided to settle because of the continuing costs and uncertainties associated with the lawsuits. Mylan officials estimated that the lawsuits had already cost the company more than $20 million and that recently it had been spending about $6 million every quarter on the litigation.</p>
        <p>Company executives also said they were willing to settle the cases for more than the federal government had sought because they feared that the government might try to expand the lawsuit, include broader accusations and seek larger damages. The federal government had sought $120 million, and the amount being sought by the private plaintiffs has not been disclosed.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time in Mylan's 39-year history that any government agency has accused us of improper conduct,'' said Milan Puskar, chairman and chief executive of the company, which is based in Pittsburgh. ''We continue to believe we acted properly.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The board and I view these settlements to be in the best interest of our company's shareholders, customers and employees. By putting a significant portion of this case behind us, we can now look forward to devoting our full resources to the business of this company.''</p>
        <p>While many details of the tentative settlement are still to be worked out over the next month, the plan is to distribute $100 million to all the states, which will then determine which purchasers should be reimbursed.</p>
        <p>More than a dozen states have their own drug assistance programs to help low-income patients, and they may be among the larger beneficiaries of today's agreement.</p>
        <p>An additional $35 million is earmarked to settle private lawsuits brought by some large institutional buyers. The remaining $12 million will be paid to the government and private lawyers to cover legal costs.</p>
        <p>But the tentative settlement does not end all of the legal disputes. Mylan executives said the agreement did not settle 11 lawsuits brought by some institutional buyers, like wholesalers. The company said it would continue to defend against those cases and that it was confident it would prevail.</p>
        <p>Three other companies that were accused of conspiring with Mylan to corner the market on raw ingredients also settled, but because they are indemnified by Mylan, they will not have to pay any damages. The three are Cambrex, a chemical supplier based in East Rutherford, N.J.; Profarmaco, an Italian drug supplier owned by Cambrex; and Gyma Laboratories of America, which is based in Westbury, N.Y., and is Profarmaco's American distributor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
