<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stricter Sentences for Livery-Cab Crimes</title>
    <meta content="13CABB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000715T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime Victims, Compensation of</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Limousines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, John W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Roy M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Espaillat, Adriano (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DD1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stricter Sentences for Livery-Cab Crimes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, John W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George E Pataki signs bill directing New York judges to add three to five years to minimum sentences of anyone convicted of certain violent crimes against on-duty livery-cab, yellow-cab and limousine drivers; bill also provides for expedited funds from Crime Victims Board for livery-cab drivers and their families who are victims of violent crimes while on duty; Sen Roy M Goodman and Assemblyman Adriano Espaillat sponsored bill; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tougher sentencing laws have long been used to deter violent crimes against minority groups or those in dangerous public jobs, like police officers. But yesterday, Gov. George E. Pataki signed into law a bill meant to deter violence against a private occupation: livery-cab drivers.</p>
        <p>The measure was in response to the killings of 10 livery-cab drivers this year. Mr. Pataki signed it at the offices of Seaman Radio Dispatch, a livery company in Washington Heights, where he was joined by the families of slain drivers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tougher sentencing laws have long been used to deter violent crimes against minority groups or those in dangerous public jobs, like police officers. But yesterday, Gov. George E. Pataki signed into law a bill meant to deter violence against a private occupation: livery-cab drivers.</p>
        <p>The measure was in response to the killings of 10 livery-cab drivers this year. Mr. Pataki signed it at the offices of Seaman Radio Dispatch, a livery company in Washington Heights, where he was joined by the families of slain drivers.</p>
        <p>''It is in a sense a sad day,'' the Republican governor said, ''because when I look out in the front row I see the widows of people, immigrants that came to this country with a dream.''</p>
        <p>The measure directs judges to add three to five years to the minimum sentence of anyone convicted of committing certain violent crimes against on-duty livery-cab drivers, as well as yellow-cab drivers and drivers with black car limousine services. The covered crimes include assault, manslaughter, attempted murder and robbery. The sentencing changes take effect Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>It also provides for expedited funds from the New York State Crime Victims Board for both livery-cab drivers and the families of drivers who are victims of violent crimes while on duty. Up to $20,000 in $500 weekly payments may be awarded for loss of earnings to a livery-cab driver who suffers a serious physical injury in a violent crime, or to the family of a slain driver, said Jill Konviser, an aide to the governor who wrote the legislation. The award may include an additional $10,000 in certain cases, she said.</p>
        <p>Yellow-cab drivers who are crime victims will not receive these payments, she said, because they are eligible for workers' compensation. The compensation program is retroactive to Jan. 1, which means previous victims may seek benefits.</p>
        <p>The law also creates a task force to study the availability of insurance coverage for livery-cab drivers, a vehicle safety program that will be in place next January, and a 20-member panel that will examine ways to help improve livery-cab safety.</p>
        <p>It is unusual for legislators to single out a private occupation for protection, said Burt Newborne, a professor at New York University School of Law. Laws of this sort have  typically been adopted for classes of people considered vulnerable to violence, like members of ethnic groups or gays, who are protected by hate-crime laws, he said, or government officials like tax collectors, police officers and prison guards.</p>
        <p>''There is a tradition in criminal law of identifying vulnerable groups, particularly classes of people, for these types of protections, in the hope that they will increase the deterrent, but it's rare,'' Mr. Newborne said. ''It's extremely rare that it is done by profession.''</p>
        <p>The governor was joined yesterday by Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver and the legislation's sponsors, Senator Roy M. Goodman and Assemblyman Adriano Espaillat.</p>
        <p>The measure is the latest attempt by public officials to help New York City's estimated 41,000 livery-cab drivers, who work in poor, high-crime neighborhoods where yellow cabs seldom venture. They ''perform an enormously important service,'' Mr. Pataki said.</p>
        <p>Officials in the livery-cab business praised the law. ''I believe that certain industries that are vulnerable should have this type of protection, and I believe that livery-cab drivers are the most vulnerable,'' said Fernando A. Mateo, president of the New York State Federation of Taxi Drivers, which represents 15,000 livery drivers. ''It's not only right, it's fair. When you kill a livery-cab diver, or assault them or rob them, now you know you are going to pay dearly.''</p>
        <p>''These widows need money, and this is a boost for an industry,'' Mr. Mateo said.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, several of the widows, surrounded by their children, broke down in tears. ''I want justice,'' said Maria Lopez, whose husband, Cesar Lopez, 42, was killed in Brooklyn in April. ''They have to make people pay for what they did.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 15, 2000, Saturday  An article on Thursday about Gov. George E. Pataki's signing of a law intended to deter crimes against cabdrivers misspelled the surname of a law professor at New York University who explained its significance. He is Burt Neuborne, not Newborne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 15, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about Gov. George E. Pataki's signing of a law intended to deter crimes against cabdrivers misspelled the surname of a law professor at New York University who explained its significance. He is Burt Neuborne, not Newborne.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
