<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Flux, Gooden Explores His Options and Stays Upbeat</title>
    <meta content="13BASE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gooden, Dwight</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neagle, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDD1F38F930A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Flux, Gooden Explores His Options and Stays Upbeat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Curry column on fate of pitcher Dwight Gooden in light of New York Yankees trade for Denny Neagle; holds Gooden should savor chance to stay with team, even in long relief (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ella Gooden received so many congratulatory phone calls about her son's return to the Yankees that she felt as if Dwight had pitched another no-hitter. Gooden had so many people plant their palms on his back after his five innings against the Mets last Saturday that he wondered if it was a dream. Had he ever left the Yankees? Could his comeback be this smooth?</p>
        <p>The answers came rushing forward before lunch yesterday when Gooden found out that the Yankees had acquired Denny Neagle from the Cincinnati Reds for four minor leaguers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ella Gooden received so many congratulatory phone calls about her son's return to the Yankees that she felt as if Dwight had pitched another no-hitter. Gooden had so many people plant their palms on his back after his five innings against the Mets last Saturday that he wondered if it was a dream. Had he ever left the Yankees? Could his comeback be this smooth?</p>
        <p>The answers came rushing forward before lunch yesterday when Gooden found out that the Yankees had acquired Denny Neagle from the Cincinnati Reds for four minor leaguers.</p>
        <p>Neagle's arrival surely signals that Gooden will be removed from the rotation, his improbable and inspirational story fading after five days.</p>
        <p>Five measly days. Gooden defeated his former team at Shea Stadium and gave the Yankees a surprising jolt, but he was given a jolt of another sort yesterday as his role drastically changed and his next start vanished.</p>
        <p>But Gooden refused to view it as a demotion. He is more humble after being discarded by two other teams this season, which is a smart strategy if he wants to continue surviving. ''I think it was a good move,'' Gooden said of the deal for Neagle. ''He's shown that he's still a good pitcher since he came back from that injury. When you can bring in another left-hander, you do it.''</p>
        <p>Then Gooden laughed into the phone and said, ''What that means for me, I have no idea.''</p>
        <p>Gooden's laugh was a curious laugh, not a nervous laugh. Less than a week from that splendid day in Flushing, his old playground, Gooden knows that he is a 35-year-old pitcher with question marks who is trying to hang on as desperately as any of the tribe members trying to win $1 million on ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>If Gooden criticizes Manager Joe Torre, gets into a scuffle with a cab driver or has a horrendous outing, all things he has done, George Steinbrenner, the only person whose vote matters on the Yankees' island, can squash Gooden's career as quickly as he rekindled it.</p>
        <p>So Gooden should be shrewder now, not bitter. It is the best way for him to act.</p>
        <p>It seemed unlikely that he would ever get another shot with the Yankees so he must savor it and seize it, even if he winds up as a long reliever behind the unsteady David Cone or as an insurance policy. It appears that Gooden will remain in the majors, but the Yankees have the option of returning him to the minor leagues. Before being promoted to pitch against the Mets on Saturday, he agreed contractually to accept a return to the minors.</p>
        <p>So the bullpen is better than demotion, or retirement.</p>
        <p>''Three or four years ago, I would have said: 'I only want to start. I'm out of here and I'm going home,' '' Gooden said. ''But maybe it's time for me to make the change. I feel comfortable starting or relieving. Maybe the bullpen is the thing for me now.''</p>
        <p>Gooden is serious. He has appeared in 413 major league games and has relieved only 7 times, but Gooden realizes the bullpen is the way to prolong his 16-year career. Mel Stottlemyre, the Yanks' pitching coach, was very intrigued when he heard Gooden express interest in relieving because Gooden had never uttered something like that to him. But even baseball survivalists must make concessions.</p>
        <p>The prospect of being a reliever is one reason Gooden is so enamored of the arm manipulation exercises that he does on a robotic machine a few times a week with Al Meilus, a trainer. Meilus said the exercises lengthen the muscles in Gooden's right arm, increase his range of motion and enable him to throw harder and freer.</p>
        <p>Gooden has already seen results since it takes him 10 minutes to warm up, a reduction from 20 minutes and an important development for a reliever.</p>
        <p>Two days before Gooden started against the Mets, Meilus said his fastball barely reached 87 miles an hour. But, after an intense session on the robotic machine, Gooden hit 89 and matched Al Leiter's fastball from one day earlier. Gooden claimed his fastball has been as robust as 92. ''My goal,'' Meilus said, ''is to get him to 95.''</p>
        <p>It is a bold goal, but the Yankees do not need Gooden to throw 95 m.p.h. bullets. They simply need him to be reliable. The Yankees scrambled so much in June that they started rookies three times in one week. With the stellar Neagle, a possibly rejuvenated Gooden and a healthy Ramiro Mendoza, the Yankees should finally have some depth.</p>
        <p>Gooden actually referred to 1997 as evidence for why he can thrive in an uncertain role, another interesting sign since he had one relief outing in 20 games and maligned Torre for using him inconsistently. Now Gooden is embracing this insecure position because it is the only one available.</p>
        <p>Five days. Gooden had five days where he was back in the rotation with the Yankees and in a spot that he never envisioned five weeks ago. Now that Neagle's presence has altered the rotation for the better, Gooden must adjust again if he hopes to survive.</p>
        <p>''I want to be a utility pitcher, just like we have utility players,'' Gooden said. ''I'll spot-start; I'll relieve. I'll do anything they want.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
