<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="08DIGE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D81238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Royal KPN Reopens Talks On Mobile Phone Venture  Royal KPN returned to the bargaining table with another potential partner, NTT DoCoMo of Japan, just days after KPN called off merger talks with Telefonica of Spain.</p>
        <p>Royal KPN, the largest telephone operator in the Netherlands, and DoCoMo, the mobile operations of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone, have been negotiating in fits and starts for over a month now. They are hoping to reach an agreement that could include an alliance between the two companies' mobile telephone operations. [Page C12.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Royal KPN Reopens Talks On Mobile Phone Venture  Royal KPN returned to the bargaining table with another potential partner, NTT DoCoMo of Japan, just days after KPN called off merger talks with Telefonica of Spain.</p>
        <p>Royal KPN, the largest telephone operator in the Netherlands, and DoCoMo, the mobile operations of Nippon Telegraph and Telephone, have been negotiating in fits and starts for over a month now. They are hoping to reach an agreement that could include an alliance between the two companies' mobile telephone operations. [Page C12.]</p>
        <p>Israeli Cabinet Passes Tax Measure  Israel's cabinet voted to overhaul the country's tax system for the first time in a quarter century, backing a finance ministry proposal for lower income tax rates balanced by new levies on inheritances, foreign earnings and capital gains. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Hyundai Announces 'World Car' Deal  Hyundai Motor said it had agreed to take part in an alliance with Mitsubishi Motors and DaimlerChrysler to build a one-liter ''world car'' with commercial production set for 2002. But DaimlerChrysler denied that it had agreed to take part in the venture. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Time Warner's Big Gamble  Time Warner's decision to block the ABC television network in 3.5 million homes last Monday will surely be a prominent chapter in public relations history. In just 39 hours -- the time it took for it to restore the ABC signal -- Time Warner managed to anger many of its customers, rile local and national politicians, , draw the ire of the Federal Communications Commission, and upset what had looked like smooth sailing on the way to approval of its merger with America Online. [C20.]</p>
        <p>Cisco's Younger, Smaller Rivals  Cisco is the undisputed leader in Internet communications equipment and the No. 1 company in market value. But in the new economy, few titans remain astride their industry for long, and several newer communications equipment companies have Cisco in their sights. [C4.]</p>
        <p>'Millionaire' Enters 'E.R.' Zone  With a week of celebrity contestants, ABC had already found a new way to use ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' to hammer its competitors in a sweeps month. But last Thursday the network managed to pile on some additional torment for NBC: ABC quietly let the Thursday edition of ''Millionaire'' run eight minutes long, just enough to blunt the start of NBC's strongest series, ''E.R.'' ABC beat ''E.R.'' in its first half-hour, something no regularly scheduled ABC show had done in the seven-year run of the hit medical drama. [C20.]</p>
        <p>A Top Inspired by Buckminster Fuller  Kurt Przybilla's childhood jungle gym inspired a lifelong fascination with Buckminster Fuller, the architect and futuristic thinker who invented the geodesic dome, and that led to Mr. Przybilla's newly patented invention, which he describes as an omnidirectional top. He says that his tops can help children develop an intuitive understanding of physics or chemistry in much the same way that an understanding of geometry can grow out of playing with blocks. Patents. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Unilever's Shampoo Campaign  Unilever -- a company known for its household and personal care products -- is planning a multimillion-dollar advertising extravaganza for a shampoo line. The British-Dutch conglomerate is staking millions in production costs and more than $40 million in media buys to promote the two-year-old ThermaSilk shampoo, conditioner and hair care line. The campaign goes on the air on network television today. Advertising. [C18.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
