<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Out Of Our Wits</title>
    <meta content="08SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gridiron Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DF1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Out Of Our Wits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire Op-Ed column on recent Gridiron dinner and White House Correspondents Association dinner in Washington at which members of political establishment, notably Pres Clinton and Vice Pres Gore, were roasted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One great cultural divide in our nation's capital is between the ostensibly off-the-record white-tie Gridiron dinner, which has been roasting presidents for 115 years, and the star-studded, made-for-TV affair of the White House Correspondents Association.</p>
        <p>The Gridiron, run by 60 of the Washington newspaper elite, is steeped in a bipartisan tradition of good-humored satire; it ''singes but never burns.'' The much larger W.H.C.A. affair, which properly includes electronic media, has been known to get out of hand, not only in oratorical taste but in the hot-tickety competition of its follow-up parties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One great cultural divide in our nation's capital is between the ostensibly off-the-record white-tie Gridiron dinner, which has been roasting presidents for 115 years, and the star-studded, made-for-TV affair of the White House Correspondents Association.</p>
        <p>The Gridiron, run by 60 of the Washington newspaper elite, is steeped in a bipartisan tradition of good-humored satire; it ''singes but never burns.'' The much larger W.H.C.A. affair, which properly includes electronic media, has been known to get out of hand, not only in oratorical taste but in the hot-tickety competition of its follow-up parties.</p>
        <p>Though a few singers are pros, the pencil fogies of the Gridiron dress in outrageous costumes and put on an amateur-theatrical set of skits and songs. (In this, my rookie year as a member, I appeared in a bunny suit, grimly determined to demonstrate good-sportsmanship.) The W.H.C.A. features instead a performance by a celebrated emcee. At both dinners, the highlight is the response of the main satiric target, who is frequently the president or vice president.</p>
        <p>Here is where a difference in the cultural style of Washington audiences illustrates the difference between political wit and political humor.</p>
        <p>In olden times, roasted pols responded with witty speeches replete with self-deprecating ''in'' jokes, often written by Liz Carpenter or Paul Keyes, a Gridiron tradition continued this year as Democrat Bob Strauss showed how political wit could sting without overstepping. Sometimes an unexpected performance substituted for wit: Nixon and Agnew plonked out a duet on the piano, or Nancy Reagan stole the show with a song. This year, a quintet of women cabinet members, starring Janet Reno, stopped the show with ''Thank Heaven for Grown-Up Girls.''</p>
        <p>Inside-the-establishment stuff works because of the intimacy of a live performance directly in front of a usually adversarial audience. But broadcasting does not lend itself to inside-the-brainwaves wit; as the physicist Werner Heisenberg uncertainly theorized, the wide observation of the comic performance changes the stimulus to laughter.</p>
        <p>Consider the performances this year of Clinton and Gore. If you watched TV last week -- from interviews with emcee Jay Leno to televised excerpts released by the White House on news programs everywhere -- you saw highlights of the undeniably boffo show put on at the W.H.C.A. dinner by the president.</p>
        <p>Clinton stimulated sympathy for his pangs of departure with well-produced outside stuff. His production culminated in a filmed scene of an abandoned Clinton running after the campaigning first lady's car, holding up a bag and shouting ''You forgot your lunch!'' Thus did the White House effectively use the forum provided by the convulsed press to show the general public that the Clintons were adept at poking fun at themselves. The humor was broad and professional, in the sure-fire style of Lucy and Desi.</p>
        <p>By contrast (and both are Democrats, so this is a nonpartisan analysis), Gore at the Gridiron emulated a style perfected two generations ago by John Kennedy at a memorable Al Smith memorial dinner in New York. Hard to believe, but Gore, like J.F.K., played to the people in the room with an unexpectedly light touch, using lines attuned to his politically sensitive audience.</p>
        <p>Everyone present knew that Gore's greatest campaign vulnerability is his denial of prior knowledge about illegal fund-raising. Many in the audience were aware he had claimed to have been out of the room when his aides were discussing this; he had even suggested he may have been off to the john after drinking a lot of iced tea. Few accept this.</p>
        <p>So Gore reportedly stepped to the lectern and asked for a glass of iced tea. Small laugh. He took the glass and slowly drained it all the way to the bottom, as the tittering grew. Then he carefully returned the glass to the waiter and delivered the punch line: ''I can't stay long.''</p>
        <p>That went over as nicely suggestive but clean, topically pointed and disarmingly self-directed. Just as Clinton's ''You forgot your lunch!'' was designed to elicit a belly laugh from a national audience, Gore's ''I can't stay long'' was intended to induce a grudgingly appreciative chuckle from an opinion-molding audience.</p>
        <p>One was broadcast humor, the other political wit. That's the difference in responses at two press dinners that seem cultural worlds apart.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
