<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe's Migrant Fears Rend a Spanish Town</title>
    <meta content="08SPAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">El Ejido (Spain)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morocco</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7DD1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2198" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe's Migrant Fears Rend a Spanish Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>EL EJIDO, Spain</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three-day rampage against Moroccan immigrants in El Ejido, Spain, which was sparked by killing of Spanish woman, is worst recent case of racial violence in Europe, which is increasingly uneasy about immigrants; across continent, young laborers are being lured from poorer places to perform menial jobs, only to meet resistance from countries afraid that national identities will be diluted or generous welfare systems overwhelmed; problems in El Ejido, which became rich through production of winter fruits, picked by large influx of Moroccans, have parallels in Austria, Germany, France and Britain; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The newly planted orange trees on the quaint Plaza de la Colonizacion suggest a certain civic pride in this southern Spanish town, but the rubble and charred remains of Afrolatino Communication demonstrate how civility has gone up in smoke.</p>
        <p>The 20 telephone cabins in the burned establishment were used by immigrants, mainly Moroccans, to call home. That was until the place was set alight on the night of April 20, two days after the newspaper kiosk of a Moroccan immigrant in nearby Almeria was burned down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The newly planted orange trees on the quaint Plaza de la Colonizacion suggest a certain civic pride in this southern Spanish town, but the rubble and charred remains of Afrolatino Communication demonstrate how civility has gone up in smoke.</p>
        <p>The 20 telephone cabins in the burned establishment were used by immigrants, mainly Moroccans, to call home. That was until the place was set alight on the night of April 20, two days after the newspaper kiosk of a Moroccan immigrant in nearby Almeria was burned down.</p>
        <p>''This is pure racism -- $12,000 of investment up in smoke because some Spaniards can't stand Africans,'' said Armon Elia Mejia, the owner, who is an immigrant from the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>Those incidents are the latest spasms in anti-immigrant violence in this region of southern Spain. After a Spanish woman was killed in a local market by a Moroccan in early February, there was a three-day rampage directed against the tens of thousands of North African laborers here.</p>
        <p>The outburst, known simply as ''la guerra,'' or ''the war,'' was the worst recent case of racial violence in a Europe increasingly uneasy about immigrants. ''When a people rises up, it is because they are tired,'' said Alejandro Fernandez, whose fiancee was the woman killed. ''I tell you, this place is a time bomb.''</p>
        <p>In some senses, that bomb is of purely local manufacture. A lot happened suddenly to El Ejido, creating a rootless culture in which sparks flare easily. It became rich through the production of winter fruits; it became mixed through a huge influx of Moroccans to pick them; it became angry because its identity was suddenly unclear.</p>
        <p>But in other ways, the quandary of El Ejido is that of all of Europe. Spain, like many of its partners in the European Union, is a rich country with a fast-aging population, a low birthrate, a growing aversion to menial jobs and an uneasy proximity to lands of poverty. It needs immigrants from poorer places even as its national psyche resists them.</p>
        <p>Across the Continent, young laborers are being lured from poorer places, whether in Africa or Eastern Europe, only to meet resistance from countries afraid that their national identities will be diluted or generous welfare systems overwhelmed.</p>
        <p>In Austria, the party of Jorg Haider rails against ''overforeignerization.'' In Germany, conservatives urge people to have more children rather than accept immigrants. In France, riots erupt after an Algerian is shot by the police. In Britain, drastic laws are introduced to curb the growing number of asylum-seekers.</p>
        <p>''Europe requires immigrants today because of simple demographics,'' said Kirsty Hughes, a senior European Union official. ''But try telling that to people. The political atmosphere is one of fortress Europe, even if immigrants are doing the jobs nobody else wants to do and are needed to ensure that we don't end up as a continent of old people.''</p>
        <p>Spain is growing older fast. Without an influx of young immigrants, or a radical change in the birthrate of 1.2 children per woman, it will have the world's highest percentage of old people by 2050, United Nations projections show. People over 65 will account for 37 percent of the population, compared with 17 percent now.</p>
        <p>Somebody will have to support those people under Europe's taxpayer-financed pension schemes, just as somebody on the Costa del Sol today has to be ready to do the hot, back-breaking work of picking the cherry tomatoes and basil that the baby boomers of Hamburg and Helsinki now want on their tables year-round.</p>
        <p>But suggest that immigration from Africa or Romania is one answer, and Western Europe tends to rebel. Unlike the United States, these old nations do not readily see themselves as ''lands of immigration,'' nor do they readily indulge the idea that newcomers may be catalysts to innovation rather than threats to jobs. In Spain, long a poor country that sent emigrants abroad, the cultural leap required to invert that self-image is huge.</p>
        <p>''We never thought of ourselves as racist -- until the invasion of the 1990's,'' said Tomas Calvo Buezas, a sociologist. ''Even today, we deny it publicly, and a successful anti-immigrant politician like Austria's Haider or France's Le Pen is unthinkable. But look at our language. We call the rich 'Arabs'; we deride poor North Africans as 'Moors.' ''</p>
        <p>One of the many North Africans eking out an existence in the vast sea of plastic-covered hothouses that surrounds El Ejido is Ilhami Elhoussin, 24. In 1998, he paid $500 for an illegal passage in a small boat from his native Morocco across the narrow strait to Spain. The other 19 passengers were caught on arrival; he ran and slipped through.</p>
        <p>Two years later, his immigrant's dream consists of this: a hovel without water or electricity, roofed with sheets of plastic anchored by rocks, set in the middle of an arid field where garbage skitters in the enervating wind out of Africa. A cousin shares the tiny shanty; 50 other Moroccan laborers live in abutting structures on the outskirts of El Ejido.</p>
        <p>Some have done slightly better. Eljabiry Salah, 29, has electricity and running water in his shack. But his bed is a foam mattress perched on the plastic crates that serve by day to collect fruit and vegetables.</p>
        <p>''Mine is a home for animals, not for humans,'' Mr. Elhoussin said. But he would not return to Africa. Here he can earn $25 a day picking produce. In Morocco, he said, there is no work for young people, unless a man wants to go into the army for $6 a day.</p>
        <p>So most days, carrying his knife and pliers, this young African in Europe sets out to work ''under the plastic,'' where temperatures can reach 113 degrees in the spring and summer.</p>
        <p>Human ingenuity has not yet conceived a machine to pick tomatoes. So today Mr. Elhoussin picks them, filling buckets at a rate of more than 28 pounds an hour. Tomorrow, the plump fruit will be in Perpignan, France, or Rotterdam, the Netherlands, ready to adorn the Insalata Caprese at lunch.</p>
        <p>Such exports, which have risen to over 1.5 million tons annually, from 100,000 tons in the early 1980's, have turned a dirt-poor corner of Spain into a boom town. The sun, pouring into 75,000 acres of plastic-covered hothouses, has proved as valuable as oil.</p>
        <p>Construction is ubiquitous in El Ejido, whose population has almost doubled since 1981, to 55,000 from 29,000. Modern shopping malls are the rage. But this ''New Spain,'' chic and confident, remains utterly foreign to Mr. Elhoussin and the North Africans whose labor helped transform the region.</p>
        <p>One of eight children from a village near Casablanca -- the birthrate in Morocco is two and a half times that in Spain -- he sends about $350 a month to his father to help him raise the family (his youngest sister is 10). With the remaining $150, he lives simply, seldom going out, especially since ''la guerra.''</p>
        <p>''A lot of the bars don't want us Moroccans at night,'' he said. ''We came here in the same way as Spaniards once went overseas to work. Young Moroccans today want a house, a car, and the money is better here. But the majority in El Ejido is racist. They don't want us to rent their property, they don't want us to look at their girls, they don't want us to build mosques.''</p>
        <p>Still, the violence in February, in which more than 500 North Africans lost homes, astonished this young Moroccan. As shanties and cars burned, and a marauding mob wielded clubs, Mr. Elhoussin fled in terror to the snow-capped mountains behind El Ejido, where he and a group of fellow Moroccans survived for four days without food.</p>
        <p>At last he returned -- but to a changed place where unstated grievances had become open wounds. The uneasy truce that has followed is partial, marked by the averted gazes of divided communities, and punctuated by violence.</p>
        <p>In every war, there are two realities, seemingly unbridgeable. People talk past each other, entrenched in their opposing worlds.</p>
        <p>To hear Spanish officials and businessmen tell it, the Moroccans largely brought the cataclysm on themselves. There was the death of Encarnacion Lopez, the woman who was killed in the market, but also two other slayings by Moroccans in the 10 days before that. ''There are more than 4,000 North Africans here with no fixed work,'' said Antonio Martin, the official in charge of regional security. ''If they don't work, they can't eat. So they rob, they deal drugs, they cause trouble.''</p>
        <p>The complaints go beyond crime. If the Moroccans live in shanties, it is because they do not want to pay rent, the Spaniards say. If they do not want to pay rent, it is because they want to send all their money home. If ever they do rent, they want to put 20 people in a room, and who in Europe can accept that?</p>
        <p>Spaniards, the arguments continue, went to Argentina or Germany to find work when the country was poor, but were culturally compatible, unlike these ''Moors'' who expect to be presented with everything their own government will not give them even as they refuse to invest a dime.</p>
        <p>''The reality is we need their labor, so we are going to have to learn to live together,'' said Antonio Escobar, the director of an exporter called Agroponiente. ''Our mental attitude must improve. But they must also learn to assimilate. Why is it that we have to adapt to their Ramadan?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fernandez, 25, the bereaved hotelier who had planned to wed Miss Lopez, 26, before her slaying set off the violence, still wears a gold engagement ring, and his blue eyes still glisten with tears when he speaks of his beloved.</p>
        <p>''She was humble, she was hard-working, she was loving -- she was right for me,'' he said, fingering a gold crucifix nestling on his chest. ''But a woman is worth nothing to a Moroccan. He'd exchange her for a goat or a sheep.''</p>
        <p>As in all such situations, truth hovers somewhere between the two sides. The Moors were the eighth-century Arab and Berber conquerors of Spain who remained until 1492, so history imbues the tensions with a particular charge. Papers in Morocco have been denouncing Spain's ''new anti-Islamic Crusades.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, after a period of heady expansion, the produce industry here has entered a period of consolidation. Jobs are more scarce. The pay of pickers, around $500 a month, does not attract Spaniards, who expect at least double that, even with unemployment at more than 15 percent.</p>
        <p>Estimates of the number of North Africans in the region vary wildly: 45,000, says Ali Blidan, the leader of an immigrant rights group; less than half that, according to the police. Most came in the last decade, and the squares of El Ejido are full of idle young Moroccans.</p>
        <p>On the square in the San Agustin district where Afrolatino Communication was burned down, there are two bars -- one frequented by Spaniards, the other by Moroccans. The two groups even sit on separate benches, eyeing each other suspiciously.</p>
        <p>In the adjacent police headquarters, Paco Ruiz, the local chief, offered a different explanation of the recent violence -- which, he ventured, was caused by rivalry between Moroccans and Algerians ''who cannot stand each other.'' Because they were not allowed to drink in their own countries, ''they are out of control when they drink here,'' Mr. Ruiz opined.</p>
        <p>He looked a visitor in the eye and continued: ''The fire may be out here, but the embers are still burning. This place is going to explode again.''</p>
        <p>In an attempt to ensure that it does not, Spanish authorities have brought in several hundred extra police officers since February. The government has also introduced legislation allowing illegal immigrants to regularize their situation if they arrived before June 1, 1999.</p>
        <p>But Ilhami Elhoussin is not interested. As soon as he can save enough money, he said, he wants to head north to a ''more civilized place like France,'' where he hopes to work in a restaurant.</p>
        <p>The reception there may not be much warmer. The mood of ''fortress Europe'' tends to vary little from country to country.</p>
        <p>''The march from the south to the north is inevitable,'' said Jean-Claude Chesnais, a French demographer. ''Africa's population is growing by 20 million a year, while ours declines rapidly. The problem is we are afraid of the immigration we need.''</p>
        <p>The grieving Mr. Fernandez sees every reason for such fear. The stabbing of his fiancee was an aberration, the work of one man. But emotion is irrational, and Mr. Fernandez insists on drawing a general conclusion.</p>
        <p>''Who,'' he asked, ''wants to risk living with a neighbor who is a complete stranger?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
