<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out-of-State PAC's Continue to Aid Pataki</title>
    <meta content="08PATA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Action Committees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hu, Winnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5DB1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out-of-State PAC's Continue to Aid Pataki</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hu, Winnie</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George E Pataki continues to raise money through two political action committees that he set up outside New York to enhance his national profile; stated purpose of those committees, which bear name 21st Century Freedom, is to help Republican candidates throughout country who share his views; campaign records show, however, that most of total of $892,573 raised so far has been used to benefit Pataki by building new political alliances and subsidizing increasingly expensive political apparatus that helped him win two terms as Governor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, hoping to keep his political choices open, has continued to raise money through two political action committees that he set up outside New York to enhance his national profile.</p>
        <p>The stated purpose of those committees, which bear the name ''21st Century Freedom,'' is to help Republican candidates around the country who share his views. But campaign records show that most of the total of $892,573 raised so far has been used to benefit Mr. Pataki by building new political alliances and subsidizing an increasingly expensive political apparatus that helped him win two terms as governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, hoping to keep his political choices open, has continued to raise money through two political action committees that he set up outside New York to enhance his national profile.</p>
        <p>The stated purpose of those committees, which bear the name ''21st Century Freedom,'' is to help Republican candidates around the country who share his views. But campaign records show that most of the total of $892,573 raised so far has been used to benefit Mr. Pataki by building new political alliances and subsidizing an increasingly expensive political apparatus that helped him win two terms as governor.</p>
        <p>The out-of-state PAC's -- one was formed under federal law, and the other in Virginia, where there are no limits on contribution amounts -- have channeled $67,433 to state and federal races outside New York. Yet they have paid at least $126,944 to Mr. Pataki's longtime pollster, Arthur Finkelstein; $118,046 to his political consultants, Kieran Mahoney and Adam Stoll; and $190,653 to a half-dozen campaign aides who are or have been on his payroll for years.</p>
        <p>Other money has been used to hire prominent Republican consultants who could help Mr. Pataki in a future run for national office. For instance, Benjamin L. Ginsberg, an elections specialist at the Washington law firm of Patton Boggs, whose clients include Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, billed $7,264 in legal fees as recently as March. Stephen Moore, an economist with the Cato Institute in Washington, received $27,500 for fine-tuning Mr. Pataki's fiscal proposals, while Peggy Noonan, a speechwriter for Presidents George Bush and Ronald Reagan, was paid $10,000 to polish his words.</p>
        <p>The money figures are the latest the committees had available. In the case of the Virginia PAC, they cover all of calendar 1999; the federal PAC's figures cover the period from January 1999 to March 31, 2000.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Pataki has not revealed his political plans, it is clear that he commands substantial resources that could be mobilized on short notice. In the last week, politicians and lobbyists have speculated that Mr. Pataki may do just that to run for the Senate against Hillary Rodham Clinton if the probable Republican candidate, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, is forced to drop out because of his prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, the most successful political fund-raiser in the state's history, has brought in a total of more than $3.2 million in contributions since January 1999, including $2.4 million through his main campaign fund, Friends of Pataki, which is based in New York.</p>
        <p>He has already spent more than two-thirds of that money -- mainly on political consultants, salaries for his full-time campaign staff members, travel and fund-raising expenses -- even though he does not face re-election until 2002.</p>
        <p>''It's a complete change in culture,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Democrat from Westchester County who has criticized Mr. Pataki and Republican leaders for their aggressive fund-raising practices. ''There is no election cycle anymore; it's flat-out fund-raising from the inauguration to the next election.''</p>
        <p>Zenia Mucha, chief political adviser to Mr. Pataki, said money from all three committees had enabled the governor to travel around the country and build support for the party. ''The governor feels very strongly about promoting the Republican agenda of smaller, more effective and efficient government, lower taxes, individual freedom and other issues that are part of it,'' she said. ''We have and will continue to use these PAC's to disseminate and promote that message.''</p>
        <p>Many lobbyists and other regular contributors complain that they are paying heavily for Mr. Pataki's growing political activities. They say privately that Mr. Pataki's campaign aides have aggressively encouraged them to send donations to the Virginia or federal PAC's as a way to skirt New York's contribution limits.</p>
        <p>''Now they call and ask us to make out two or three checks instead of one,'' said a lobbyist who had given several thousand dollars to Mr. Pataki's committees but spoke on condition of anonymity because the issue had become so sensitive.</p>
        <p>Under New York election law, a corporation's contributions to all candidates and committees is limited to $5,000 a year. The law also limits an individual's donation to a governor's general election campaign to $30,700 over the four years of his term. But several corporations and individual donors would have exceeded those limits if their donations to all the committees were tallied up.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic, one of the state's largest employers, contributed $50,000 to the Virginia committee -- 10 times the corporate limit in New York -- in addition to $50,500 in largely unregulated soft money to the Republican Party's housekeeping committee. Although Mr. Pataki's PAC is separate from the Republican committees, they often transfer money back and forth.</p>
        <p>A real estate developer, Peter S. Kalikow, contributed $25,000 to the Virginia PAC and $12,500 to Friends of Pataki, a total of $37,500, which is more than the state's limit for individual donors. He also directed $12,500 to the Republican state committee, and his company, H. J. Kalikow, gave $5,000 to the state committee.</p>
        <p>The Virginia PAC collected $291,400, or more than half its total contributions, from New York businesses, residents and other political committees. The federal PAC, which is barred from accepting corporate donations and limits individuals to $5,000, still raised $356,073 including $138,375 from New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Blair Horner, legislative director for the New York Public Interest Research Group, said Mr. Pataki's multiple committees had made a sham of the state's campaign finance laws. ''It essentially means there are no campaign contribution limits for governor,'' he said. ''Those who are seeking to curry favor can give as much as they want.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mucha rejected such criticism. ''This gives us the ability under the law -- which, the last time I looked, both parties were doing -- to go out to other states and other arenas and talk about the governor's successful record in New York and the principles of the Republican Party,'' she said.</p>
        <p>To some extent, Mr. Pataki's out-of-state committees have helped finance Republican aspirations in other parts of the country. The Virginia PAC contributed $28,000 to 12 Republican candidates running for the State Legislature in New Jersey, and $28,100 to 8 Republican candidates in Virginia. The federal PAC contributed $11,333 to 11 Republicans from Vermont to Arizona who are running for federal office.</p>
        <p>But campaign records show that most of the money has been used to further Mr. Pataki's own political interests. There was little real difference in how the money was spent from the three committees -- indeed, the same political consultants drew regular payments from each one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
