<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Absence at Auction Time; Former Sotheby's Official Is in Limbo Instead of in the Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="08BROO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Diana D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5D81238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Absence at Auction Time; Former Sotheby's Official Is in Limbo Instead of in the Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL and RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol; Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diana D Brooks, who resigned as Sotheby's chief executive amid antitrust probe, is missing from customary pre-auction spotlight as Sotheby's and Christie's prepare for spring auctions of Impressionist and modern art; friends, family and associates say she fears possible financial ruin or prison; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In other times, this would have been Diana D. Brooks's moment.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the multimillion-dollar spring auctions of Impressionist and modern art at Sotheby's in New York, it was always Ms. Brooks's striking presence and booming voice that predominated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In other times, this would have been Diana D. Brooks's moment.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the multimillion-dollar spring auctions of Impressionist and modern art at Sotheby's in New York, it was always Ms. Brooks's striking presence and booming voice that predominated.</p>
        <p>As the auction house's president and chief executive, she cropped up on ''Charlie Rose'' or ''Today,'' talking up the forthcoming sales. She greeted the thousands of visitors who thronged Sotheby's York Avenue galleries to view the art coming up for auction. Ms. Brooks, six feet tall with distinctive curly blond hair, presided over cocktail parties, dinners and brunches in the United States and abroad for Sotheby's big-money collectors. When the selling began, sometimes she even wielded the auction gavel herself.</p>
        <p>But as experts finish preparing for the two weeks of auctions at Sotheby's and Christie's that begin tonight -- hundreds of millions of dollars' worth of art will change hands -- there is an uncomfortable silence on York Avenue. Ms. Brooks, who had become something of a celebrity in the 13 years since Sotheby's made her the first woman to head an auction house, resigned under fire on Feb. 21, along with A. Alfred Taubman, the company's chairman and its biggest shareholder, in connection with a federal antitrust investigation. Allegations center on whether the two colluded with their counterparts at Christie's, Sotheby's archrival, in setting the commissions charged to buyers and sellers. Between them Sotheby's and Christie's dominate the multibillion-dollar auction market.</p>
        <p>The prospect of financial ruin or even prison has taken a toll on Ms. Brooks and her family, friends and associates say. ''She is extraordinarily upset and terrified about the consequences,'' one friend said, speaking on condition of anonymity. She recently cut her hair short and straightened it to be less recognizable. But the friend also described her as resilient and physically fit, still devoted to morning runs of several miles.</p>
        <p>Except for one visit to Sotheby's since her resignation -- several hours that employees described as painful in their awkwardness -- Ms. Brooks, 49, has kept to herself, spending considerable time at her mother's house in Hobe Sound, Fla., but returning periodically to a luxury apartment on the East Side of Manhattan and a Connecticut home.</p>
        <p>She and her husband, Michael C. Brooks, a venture capitalist, recently bought a house in Jupiter, Fla.; Florida protects homes from seizure in bankruptcy proceedings. The week she resigned from Sotheby's, the couple put their 7,262-square-foot Colonial house in Greenwich, Conn., on the market for $4 million, along with an additional two-acre plot for $1.5 million. They also own a residence in Lawrence, on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brooks turned away numerous requests for interviews, made through one of her lawyers, Stephen E. Kaufman, and Sotheby's chief spokeswoman, Diana Phillips.</p>
        <p>Ms. Phillips, a longtime confidante of Ms. Brooks, said that they had spoken from time to time since Ms. Brooks's resignation and that ''she sounded fine.''</p>
        <p>As Ms. Brooks's lawyers maneuver to negotiate a settlement with the Justice Department, her life is in limbo. If charged and found guilty, she could be heavily fined and sentenced to up to three years in prison. But the Justice Department could still determine that the evidence is insufficient to warrant prosecution, or it might offer her lenience or even immunity in exchange for her testimony.</p>
        <p>People close to the case said she was prepared to testify that Mr. Taubman had directed her to meet with her counterpart at Christie's, Christopher M. Davidge, to discuss price-fixing arrangements. But they said she would give such testimony only in exchange for favorable treatment from prosecutors. Such a statement would support one made by Mr. Davidge, who has told the government that a former chairman of Christie's, Sir Anthony Tennant, devised the price-fixing scheme in meetings with Mr. Taubman and then instructed Mr. Davidge to carry it out on behalf of Christie's.</p>
        <p>Christie's turned over documentation from Mr. Davidge to the government and has received immunity dependent on its continued cooperation.</p>
        <p>Through their lawyers Mr. Taubman and Sir Anthony have disputed the accounts and denied any wrongdoing. The chief Justice Department antitrust prosecutor in New York, John J. Greene, has consistently declined to discuss the case.</p>
        <p>Life at Sotheby's is not going on entirely without Ms. Brooks. Although she is no longer a company officer -- she and Mr. Taubman are now listed only as board members in Sotheby's catalogs, and even those references will soon disappear as neither is standing for re-election -- she remains on her full salary of $600,000, people close to her said.</p>
        <p>William F. Ruprecht, Sotheby's new chief executive, who joined the company in 1980, confirmed only that she was still getting paid for helping with what he called the transition. Art dealers say that she has been calling their clients, hoping to win business for Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>So big was her role at Sotheby's that it was impossible for her simply to walk away, officials at the company say. It was Ms. Brooks who shaped relationships with the company's most important clients, often pre-empting other Sotheby's specialists. It was Ms. Brooks who brokered every important deal, whether for a highly valuable Picasso or for a giant canary diamond. ''She's a very smart, innovative thinker,'' said George Goldner, chairman of the department of prints and drawings at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, who negotiated complicated deals with Sotheby's while curator of paintings and drawings at the J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles. ''She was not restricted by the boring ways most people buy and sell art.''</p>
        <p>Collectors and dealers say they do not believe the Justice Department investigation will hamper a serious collector who covets a Monet or a Matisse. But in an auction world governed by the ''three D's'' -- death, divorce and debt -- the robust economy is such that collectors who don't have to part with their artworks are holding on to them. Since no big collectors died this past winter, experts at both Sotheby's and Christie's were left to scramble for property. Ms. Brooks was Sotheby's most powerful business getter.</p>
        <p>The first daughter of a family of six children, Ms. Brooks was brought up comfortably on the North Shore of Long Island. She once said she remembered her father, Martin, telling her she could do anything her two older brothers did.</p>
        <p>''I believed him,'' she said years ago. ''When I was 8, I announced I wanted to go to Yale.'' She graduated from Yale in 1972.</p>
        <p>The man she would marry, Mr. Brooks, was also a Yale graduate. Their eldest child, a daughter, graduated from Yale last year.</p>
        <p>Her father controlled the only private water company covering a part of New York City, the Jamaica Water Company. After he died in 1977, Ms. Brooks's brother, Andrew, took over the company, then called Jamaica Water Properties, and through rapid acquisitions built it into the nation's largest computer reseller, a multibillion-dollar public company renamed JWP Inc.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brooks later joined the board of JWP but left before December 1993, when the company collapsed in bankruptcy and litigation charging fraud in bookkeeping. JWP later re-emerged as the Emcor Group. A lawsuit by insurance companies seeking to recover $148 million from Ernst &amp; Young, JWP's accounting firm, was recently reinstated by the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit in New York. Ms. Brooks was not a defendant in the actions.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brooks got to Sotheby's by accident. In 1979, while taking a leave from Citibank, where she was a lending officer, to spend more time with her infant daughter, she was told by a friend that Sotheby's was looking for a business person. She was hired part time as director of financial planning and soon assumed the job full time.</p>
        <p>For four years Ms. Brooks, who is known to her friends and colleagues as Dede (pronounced DEE-Dee), concentrated on the business side of the company. Then she moved into a more administrative position. That was in 1982, when the company's profits were down and its staff bloated. Through buyouts and pink slips, Ms. Brooks reduced the staff by 90. The move earned her praise from some outside financial analysts, but some inside the company called her ''the hatchet woman.''</p>
        <p>As a boss Ms. Brooks was known for putting a premium on the company's profitability and seeking out new business opportunities, for instance, using the Internet and offering clients insurance. She stressed that the company's future depended on reaching beyond the traditional deep-pocketed buyer.</p>
        <p>But her management style lacked subtlety and got mixed reviews. ''Dede is an extremely smart person, effective in putting teams together in every imaginable project and creative in bringing people together, often outside their regular expertise,'' her successor, Mr. Ruprecht, said. ''We had a full and frank relationship with each other, and 'warm' needs to get added to that.''</p>
        <p>But some colleagues and former Sotheby's employees, who signed confidentiality agreements in exchange for lucrative financial settlements but who agreed to speak on condition of anonymity, said she displayed a temper and willfulness, sometimes directed even at Mr. Taubman, the chairman, who himself is strong willed.</p>
        <p>''Nothing happened without her knowledge or say-so,'' said one former employee. ''She micromanaged everything.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ruprecht made light of such accounts, saying, ''She deconstructed some things and put them back together.'' He called her ''a conciliator and provocateur, as any boss needs to be,'' adding, ''We worked all the time in concert -- not all the time.''</p>
        <p>From the beginning, despite occasional frictions, Ms. Brooks won the support and respect of Mr. Taubman. ''I think they worked closely with each other for a long period of time,'' Mr. Ruprecht said.</p>
        <p>In 1990 she was elected to the board of the Yale Corporation, on which she still serves. She and her husband have contributed generously to the university.</p>
        <p>She was asked to leave another board, however, that of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, after she resigned at Sotheby's.</p>
        <p>She supports various charities, including a juvenile outreach program in Baltimore that she and two friends started after Ms. Brooks's godson, a 19-year-old high school student, committed suicide two years ago. A sportswoman who runs nearly every day and was known to have whipped male employees on company golf outings, Ms. Brooks frequently spends vacations tackling challenging pursuits like helicopter skiing.</p>
        <p>Her competitive side was just as visible in the office. When the company arranged with Amazon.com last year to create a new Web site called Sothebys.Amazon.com, which sells collectibles online, Ms. Brooks was all over the airwaves once more. The company has poured tens of millions of dollars into that site and a sister one, and once more Ms. Brooks was not only Sotheby's champion, but also its personification. Promotions for the Amazon venture featured a picture of Jeff Bezos, chairman and founder of Amazon, and Ms. Brooks posed together in a gilt frame.</p>
        <p>That was only last summer, but in many ways it was a long time ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
