<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Recollections of a Prelate in Touch With the People</title>
    <meta content="08DAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE MOURNING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7DC1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Recollections of a Prelate in Touch With the People</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tributes to late Cardinal John O'Connor continue at St Patrick's Cathedral; two public masses, one devoted to those who worked with cardinal in his previous pastoral affiliations in Scranton, Pa, Philadelpha and military, and other primarily for members of religious orders and employees of Archdiocese of New York, are followed by evening vigil; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the pulpit and the pew, those who knew Cardinal John O'Connor both closely and fleetingly yesterday offered more intimate, personal remembrances of a man who they said retained a personal touch despite his lofty status as the archbishop of New York.</p>
        <p>The tributes came in two public Masses that were followed by an evening vigil -- the third day of rites leading up to today's invitation-only funeral in St. Patrick's Cathedral that is expected to attract far more than its 2,500-seat capacity. An afternoon Mass was devoted to those who worked with the cardinal in his previous pastoral affiliations in Scranton, Pa., Philadelphia and the military, and the other primarily for members of religious orders and employees of the Archdiocese of New York, which encompasses 2.4 million Catholics in 10 counties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the pulpit and the pew, those who knew Cardinal John O'Connor both closely and fleetingly yesterday offered more intimate, personal remembrances of a man who they said retained a personal touch despite his lofty status as the archbishop of New York.</p>
        <p>The tributes came in two public Masses that were followed by an evening vigil -- the third day of rites leading up to today's invitation-only funeral in St. Patrick's Cathedral that is expected to attract far more than its 2,500-seat capacity. An afternoon Mass was devoted to those who worked with the cardinal in his previous pastoral affiliations in Scranton, Pa., Philadelphia and the military, and the other primarily for members of religious orders and employees of the Archdiocese of New York, which encompasses 2.4 million Catholics in 10 counties.</p>
        <p>Bishop Edward M. Egan of the Diocese of Bridgeport, Conn., who is said to be the most likely successor to Cardinal O'Connor, attended the second Mass, which was said by Cardinal Bernard Law of Boston, a close friend of Cardinal O'Connor, who died on Wednesday of complications related to brain cancer.</p>
        <p>Bishop Egan sat at the altar, in the first row of several bishops. He did not speak but was one of a number of bishops to offer Holy Communion. An announcement from the Vatican on the next archbishop for New York was not expected until tomorrow at the earliest.</p>
        <p>While thousands waited long hours  in yesterday's heat to get into the cathedral -- halfway through both Masses ushers were still trying to find seats for those left standing -- homilists and parishioners offered a glimpse of the workaday cardinal as well as his lesser-known life before his appointment in 1984.</p>
        <p>Bishop Robert A. Brucato, apostolic administrator of the archdiocese, said during the evening Mass that the cardinal lived dual lives, that of a ''world figure who could talk to presidents and kings'' and made a conscious effort, despite the potential for criticism, to reach out to the news media to deliver his message. But then, he said, there was also ''the John Cardinal O'Connor more familiar to the people of New York, the John Cardinal O'Connor who touched people. There will be less of a paper trail of that John Cardinal O'Connor.''</p>
        <p>''He started so many works, especially for those in need,'' Bishop Brucato said, mentioning the cardinal's efforts to reach out to AIDS patients, schoolchildren and the disabled. ''And then he personally ministered in those programs.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, archdiocese workers and members of religious orders reflected on the theme and recalled their own contact with the cardinal, whether it was his riding the elevator like any other employee at the archdiocese's East Side headquarters or checking up on pet projects.</p>
        <p>Patricia Francis, an executive with the church-sponsored Catholic Health Care System, said she recalled the cardinal's driving by a nursing home undergoing renovation and then phoning employees the next day with a suggestion to add shades to the windows of the cafeteria.</p>
        <p>''He was always a big supporter of us,'' she said. ''There were many times he would sit with AIDS patients and personally bathe them and pray with them.''</p>
        <p>Jeanne-Marie Neilson, a psychiatric social worker who works for the archdiocese, said the cardinal fostered a family-like atmosphere among workers at the Catholic Center, the archdiocese offices at 1011 First Avenue. Her closest contact with the cardinal came when she shared an elevator ride with him one morning and exchanged morning greetings. ''He was waiting for the elevator and riding up just like the rest of us,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, in a similar vein, congregants offered similar folksy views of the cardinal.</p>
        <p>''When my mother died in January he called the same day and asked to come to the funeral,'' said the Rev. Jerry Deponai, one of three priests assigned to the United States Military Academy at West Point, who occasionally visited the cardinal and shared his concern about the shortage of priests in the military. ''As you know, he did not say things unless he meant it.''</p>
        <p>At the earlier Mass, with the United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, looking on, Edwin F. O'Brian, the archbishop of the Archdiocese for the Military Services, noted the cardinal's 27 years as a Navy chaplain; he retired with the rank of rear admiral.</p>
        <p>''We are not Red Cross volunteers or scoutmasters,'' Archbishop O'Brian said of the attitude the cardinal impressed on military officers. ''Chaplains are distinct professionals, pastors whose uniforms belonged to the corps but whose heart and soul were possessed by God.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''One newspaper the other day said he was an obscure military chaplain. There was never a day when John O'Connor was obscure.''</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE MOURNING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
