<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Orioles Learn to Take a Cue From Yanks on Coming Back</title>
    <meta content="Y08BASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DE1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Orioles Learn to Take a Cue From Yanks on Coming Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses Baltimore Orioles comeback victory over New York Yankees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees were obviously teasing the Orioles. All nine batters in their lineup went down in their first swings against Sidney Ponson, the Baltimore starting pitcher, then they left the bases loaded in the sixth inning and squandered a leadoff double in the fifth and a leadoff triple in the seventh. When the Yankees took their turn at bat in the eighth inning, they had the Orioles where they wanted them. The Orioles were winning, 4-2.</p>
        <p>They had been there before. Only two days earlier the Orioles led the Yankees by 8-5 after six innings, and by 10-8 after eight. But they lost, 12-10. Bernie Williams hit a game-tying three-run home run in the seventh inning; Jorge Posada cracked a game-winning three-run home run in the ninth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees were obviously teasing the Orioles. All nine batters in their lineup went down in their first swings against Sidney Ponson, the Baltimore starting pitcher, then they left the bases loaded in the sixth inning and squandered a leadoff double in the fifth and a leadoff triple in the seventh. When the Yankees took their turn at bat in the eighth inning, they had the Orioles where they wanted them. The Orioles were winning, 4-2.</p>
        <p>They had been there before. Only two days earlier the Orioles led the Yankees by 8-5 after six innings, and by 10-8 after eight. But they lost, 12-10. Bernie Williams hit a game-tying three-run home run in the seventh inning; Jorge Posada cracked a game-winning three-run home run in the ninth.</p>
        <p>So when Scott Brosius unleashed a grand slam in the eighth inning yesterday, the Orioles knew the feeling.</p>
        <p>''You're almost sick to your stomach,'' said Mike Hargrove, the Orioles' manager, who had endured similar experiences as manager of the Cleveland Indians. ''But it's not despair. It's a little bit of anger that it's happened. You've got to have something to give you a little bit of an edge, and usually anger will do it for you.''</p>
        <p>Even though the Yankees have made a habit of winning close games in the late innings, members of other teams try not to sit around when they have a lead, wondering when it will happen this time.</p>
        <p>''You don't think about it until it starts happening to you,'' Hargrove said. ''Then you get a little shellshocked. Somebody claps their hands and you jump four inches. You understand they've been doing that. The Indians dropped a couple of fly balls to allow them to win games, stuff like that. You're certainly aware of it.''</p>
        <p>And there's no mistaking it when an opposing player or manager sees it happening. ''You sure do get the feeling,'' Hargrove said. ''If I'm chewing gum, I just spit it out because I know I'm going to bite my tongue or the side of my mouth because I'll chew it too hard.''</p>
        <p>After the Brosius blast against Mike Trombley gave the Yankees a 6-4 lead, the Baltimore outfielders gathered while the team was making yet another pitching change.</p>
        <p>''We just commented on how amazing it is they come up with such clutch home runs,'' Brady Anderson said. ''It is amazing. You think of Bernie's home run the other day, and Posada hit a home run when we have the wheel play on, thinking he's going to bunt, and he hits the ball 400 feet. They have an amazing team. They've proven that.''</p>
        <p>And the Orioles talked, too, about how Mariano Rivera makes the Yankees even more amazing, how after the Yankees snatch the late-inning lead Rivera comes in and closes out the game, putting another notch in the victory column.</p>
        <p>Charles Johnson, the Baltimore catcher, acknowledges that Rivera has made it unlikely that teams will come back against him. ''He's tough,'' Johnson said. ''He's probably the best closer in the game. He showed over the years that once he gets the lead, he pretty much comes in and shuts the door.''</p>
        <p>But Hargrove refused to ascribe supernatural qualities to Rivera. ''You realize he isn't Superman, that he is vulnerable like anybody else,'' the manager said. Sure enough, Rivera arrived at the mound for the ninth inning wearing a pinstriped uniform, not red-and-blue tights cum cape.</p>
        <p>Hargrove, however, was also realistic. ''I don't think you ever think today is the day you're going to get to him,'' he said. ''You just take it an at-bat at a time and try to build something. Catch a break along the way.''</p>
        <p>Johnson laid the foundation with a leadoff single to center field. Mike Bordick hit a fly ball to deep center, but then came the break Hargrove talked about. Anderson, as so many batters do against Rivera, broke his bat -- ''in 12 pieces,'' he said -- but hit the ball just out of Derek Jeter's reach for a single on which Johnson scooted to third.</p>
        <p>Delino DeShields followed with another single that drove in Johnson, and after B. J. Surhoff moved the runners to second and third with a groundout, Albert Belle rapped a single that brought both home for a 7-6 lead and an eventual improbable victory.</p>
        <p>''That's the first time I've seen that happen to Rivera since Cleveland did it to him in the '97 playoffs,'' said Hargrove, who managed the Indians to a division series victory over the Yankees after Sandy Alomar Jr. turned the series around with a home run against Rivera.</p>
        <p>The Orioles, in the flush of victory, thought they could have won two games in the series, if not all three. They were happy to leave Yankee Stadium with one.</p>
        <p>''They have a very good club,'' Hargrove said. ''It's always interesting and fun to play them.'' Everything about it is fun? ''The whole experience,'' he said, ''from the ride from the hotel to the ride to the airport and everything in between. It's a great city.''</p>
        <p>Maybe Hargrove could return at the end of next month, when the Atlanta Braves are in town, and take John Rocker on a tour of the city he finds so much fun.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
