<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two sturdy companies -- Juniper and Sycamore -- are setting their sights on Cisco.</title>
    <meta content="08NECO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Juniper Networks Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sycamore Networks Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cisco Systems Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DA1238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two sturdy companies -- Juniper and Sycamore -- are setting their sights on Cisco.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Seth Schiesel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profiles of Juniper Networks and Sycamore Networks, which are among young companies seeking to succeed Cisco Systems as powerhouse of Internet communications equipment; Juniper leads in field of ultrahigh-capacity Internet switches; Sycamore leads in next generation of optical networking; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RIGHT now, Cisco Systems  seems as close to perfect as a technology company can be.</p>
        <p>The biggest maker of Internet communications equipment, Cisco is also the second-most valuable company in the nation, after General Electric. It has succeeded in elevating its chief executive, John Chambers, to near-deity status in some quarters, and has even managed to stay in the government's good graces, in contrast to Microsoft, among others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RIGHT now, Cisco Systems  seems as close to perfect as a technology company can be.</p>
        <p>The biggest maker of Internet communications equipment, Cisco is also the second-most valuable company in the nation, after General Electric. It has succeeded in elevating its chief executive, John Chambers, to near-deity status in some quarters, and has even managed to stay in the government's good graces, in contrast to Microsoft, among others.</p>
        <p>Which all means that this is probably an excellent time to think about which companies have a legitimate shot at eating Cisco's lunch. After all, one of the canons of the technology business the last two decades has been that it is at a company's moment of maximum optimism that the seeds of trouble are most likely germinating. (Think I.B.M. Or for that matter, Microsoft.)</p>
        <p>Actually, the companies that appear best positioned to be the next powerhouses in communications equipment do not want to eat Cisco's lunch at all. Rather, moving in new economy time, they are planning financial and technical smorgasbords of their own for the next generation of digital networks.</p>
        <p>In an arboreal coincidence, the two leading candidates among the many young companies vying to be the ''next Cisco'' are called Juniper Networks and Sycamore Networks. Though they do very different things, the two companies are remarkably similar in many ways. They have innovative technologies, Juniper in high-capacity Internet routers and Sycamore in optical networking. They are both narrowly focused but forward-looking. They have the financial resources to position themselves for growth. And perhaps most important, each is led by an executive who has been there before.</p>
        <p>''What's interesting about Juniper and Sycamore is that what you have is that this is not just a category-killer but in many cases a category-definer,'' said Steven D. Levy, a Lehman Brothers communications equipment analyst. ''They're both hypergrowth companies, and they have managements that have seen at least one or two wars.''</p>
        <p>Cisco, Juniper and Sycamore are spoiling to sell equipment to both established and upstart communications carriers for the next generation of high-speed networks. Those networks will be necessary to meet the growing demand for Internet and other data communications services.</p>
        <p>Even though it barely generated $100 million in revenue last year, Juniper has already established its leadership in a sector that Cisco wants to own: ultrahigh-capacity Internet switches. Put simply, Juniper's systems can route more billions of digital bits each second more reliably than anyone else's.</p>
        <p>With its almost ludicrously impressive financial strength, Cisco is never to be discounted. But there are good reasons to believe that Juniper will be able to go toe-to-toe with Cisco  the next few years.</p>
        <p>First, Juniper is focused on high-end Internet routers for big communications carriers. Cisco had its start selling relatively low-capacity routers for use in corporate networks,  and analysts say it still derives two-thirds of its revenue from corporate customers, though it is selling more to communications carriers.</p>
        <p>Second, as strong as Cisco may be in developing new technologies, the company is best known for acquiring and integrating other companies. But there are not many companies that Cisco could acquire to help in its battle against Juniper. Nexabit Networks, one company in the same sector, has been acquired by Lucent Technologies, while Avici Systems, another high-end routing company, has not yet announced big commercial customers.</p>
        <p>In a bit of backhand diplomacy, Scott Kriens, Juniper's chief executive, said: ''Our success doesn't mean that the other will go away. Cisco is certainly not going to go away, just like I.B.M. did not go away. But they are not any more likely to dominate networking in the future than I.B.M. dominated computers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kriens himself is well positioned to compete against Cisco. Cisco's carrier-sales group essentially did not exist until Cisco acquired Mr. Kriens' previous company, Stratacom, for about $4 billion in 1996.</p>
        <p>In that sense, Mr. Kriens is quite similar to Daniel Smith, Sycamore's chief executive.</p>
        <p>Sycamore is at the forefront of the next generation of optical networking, which is set to allow communications carriers to route digital information from one point to another using lightwaves. Cisco has tried to add optical networking gear to its offerings with its acquisitions the last year of the Cerent Corporation, Monterey Networks and a unit of Pirelli of Italy, but it remains a minor player in that market. Sycamore's main competition in optical networking is not Cisco but the giants of the communications industry, including Lucent, Nortel Networks of Canada and  Fujitsu of Japan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith's previous company, Cascade Communications, was a competitor of Stratacom for much of the 1990's and is now deep inside Lucent (by way of its sale in 1997 to Ascend Communications, which was subsequently acquired by Lucent).</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Kriens, Mr. Smith is betting that his company's focus on a specific and potentially lucrative  niche will allow it to outmaneuver titans like Lucent and Cisco that are trying to span a variety of communications sectors. And like any good entrepreneur, Mr. Smith tempers his confidence with caution.</p>
        <p>''I truly do respect Cisco,'' he said. ''They're very aggressive, in every way. But I sure don't fear them. I know that when I'm on the field with them I better have my chinstrap buckled and be ready to hit. And I think they know that about me.''</p>
        <p>NEW ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
