<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Women's League Is Playing as Another Is Planning</title>
    <meta content="08SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">W-League (Women's Soccer League)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5DC1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Women's League Is Playing as Another Is Planning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women's soccer league, W-League, begins 8th season; several teams profiled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best women's soccer league that few people have ever heard of -- the W-League -- began its eighth season Saturday. That was when the Long Island Lady Riders, one of the league's original eight teams, traveled to Upper Manhattan and defeated the New York Magic, 4-0, at Baker Field on the campus of Columbia University. It was a cozy gathering of players, family and friends.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the recent announcement that next spring a top-flight league -- the Women's United Soccer Association -- will begin play has in some minds relegated the W-League to the scrap heap of soccer leagues in the United States. Perhaps not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The best women's soccer league that few people have ever heard of -- the W-League -- began its eighth season Saturday. That was when the Long Island Lady Riders, one of the league's original eight teams, traveled to Upper Manhattan and defeated the New York Magic, 4-0, at Baker Field on the campus of Columbia University. It was a cozy gathering of players, family and friends.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the recent announcement that next spring a top-flight league -- the Women's United Soccer Association -- will begin play has in some minds relegated the W-League to the scrap heap of soccer leagues in the United States. Perhaps not.</p>
        <p>''First of all, our posture is that nothing bad happens to us because I believe that we become more valuable,'' said Francisco Marcos, the founder of United Soccer Leagues, the umbrella organization that includes the W-League. ''I believe that our model works and has worked for women's soccer in this country, but no one wants to listen. To say that one event, the World Cup -- two if you include the Olympics -- have helped the women's game make that quantum leap from crayons to perfume possible, I beg to differ.''</p>
        <p>The W-League is a semiprofessional open league, which includes current and former college players, amateurs and professionals with 36 teams in the United States and Canada. Eight members of the United States women's national team that won the World Cup last summer have played in the W-League, including Michelle Akers; the captain, Carla Overbeck; and Sara Whalen. In all, the United Soccer Leagues has more than 100 minor league teams, male and female, in five leagues around the country. In men's soccer, the A-League (first division) is affiliated with Major League Soccer (premier league). Will the same relationship apply to W.U.S.A. and the W-League? No one is sure.</p>
        <p>W.U.S.A., with eight teams owned by large media companies (Time Warner has the rights to the New York franchise), has signed 20 members of the World Cup-winning United States national team, but 20 players are clearly not enough for an entire league.</p>
        <p>W.U.S.A., led by its chairman, John Hendricks (head of the Discovery Channel), and its new commissioner, Tony DiCicco (the former women's national team coach), has applied to the United States Soccer Federation for its sanction to run the top-level women's league. The M.L.S. has also applied for the sanction. A decision is expected to be announced in July.</p>
        <p>W.U.S.A. has already announced an ambitious television package with CNN/SI and TBS (both are owned by Time Warner) that will offer viewers programming on weekend afternoons. According to people familiar with its business plan, W.U.S.A. has raised $40 million to cover the first five years of operations, which means a commitment to losing between $8 million and $10 million a year, provided the league can draw 6,500 fans to each of the 80 games during its inaugural 2001 season. Like the M.L.S. and the Women's National Basketball Association, W.U.S.A. will operate under a single-entity system where the league owns all player contracts.</p>
        <p>Predictions about who will operate the top women's league and what effect it will have on the W-League are speculative at best. The owner of the Lady Riders, Chuck Jacob, and the president of the Magic, Lyndelle T. Phillips, are trying to focus on their three-month, 16-game 2000 season while planning warily for the future.</p>
        <p>''My concern is not that it's too soon for women's soccer; we've been doing it on Long Island for seven years,'' Jacob said. ''But experience teaches us that approaching spectator soccer in this country based on a big budget that is dependent on high attendance is very risky. There is a big difference between having a year to promote a big event like the World Cup, undeniably a world-class event, and the week-in, week-out job of promoting a team in a community. I think that the W-League will always be in the position of developing talent.''</p>
        <p>The Lady Riders averaged fewer than 1,000 spectators a game last season while playing at Michael J. Tully Jr. Park in New Hyde Park, N.Y. In 2001, the club plans to move to the soccer complex at Mitchel Field Athletic Center in Uniondale, N.Y., which can accommodate up to 8,000 spectators.</p>
        <p>W.U.S.A. plans call for stadiums with a minimum capacity of 6,500, and while Mitchel Field might seem like a good site for Time Warner's franchise, Long Island is the territory of Cablevision Systems. Cable politics could come into play, but perhaps not as starkly as last week's imbroglio between Time Warner and Disney over WABC-TV. Still, a franchise that intends to play in New York City will be hard pressed to find an attractive locale that seats between 6,500 and 10,000 fans.</p>
        <p>''The W-League doesn't have the desire to be what the W.U.S.A. wants to be -- a multimillion-dollar operation,'' the Magic's Phillips said. ''Right now, we are the only soccer team playing in New York City. We've got national team players from other countries. But right now, we are holding our breath. Our league has been a feeder system for the national team; we could still do that. It would be nice to have some kind of partnership, but I don't know at this point.''</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
