<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Notebook; Bush Runs, With a Lexicon of His Own</title>
    <meta content="Y08NOT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DF1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Notebook; Bush Runs, With a Lexicon of His Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., May 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush is slowly developing political dictionary all his own to thwart reporters' demands that he say what he really means; flashes a supermarket tabloid headline stating that he has endorsement of an extraterrestrial; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush has never been considered much of a wordsmith. But bit by bit, he is developing a political dictionary all his own.</p>
        <p>For example, when Vice President Al Gore distorts the Texas governor's record and proposals, at least as Mr. Bush sees it, Mr. Gore is not ''lying,'' two syllables that never escape Mr. Bush's lips. Rather, Mr. Gore is behaving in a manner that is ''disappointing,'' four syllables that the governor much prefers and has begun to use ad nauseam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush has never been considered much of a wordsmith. But bit by bit, he is developing a political dictionary all his own.</p>
        <p>For example, when Vice President Al Gore distorts the Texas governor's record and proposals, at least as Mr. Bush sees it, Mr. Gore is not ''lying,'' two syllables that never escape Mr. Bush's lips. Rather, Mr. Gore is behaving in a manner that is ''disappointing,'' four syllables that the governor much prefers and has begun to use ad nauseam.</p>
        <p>And while Mr. Bush, the de facto Republican presidential nominee, says that he will soon identify numerous ways in which the government can save money, none of these plans will be ''cuts,'' a four-letter word that the candidate avoids. They will be ''savings'' that make the government more ''efficient'' -- kinder, gentler terms.</p>
        <p>It is a name game all the more interesting for the fact that Mr. Bush, with little smiles and wiggles of his eyebrows, wholly acknowledges that he is playing it. And this unspoken but unmistakable admission has precipitated endless rounds of semantic jousting between Mr. Bush and reporters, who are constantly trying to get him to say what he clearly means.</p>
        <p>On his campaign plane on Wednesday, as he flew from Austin to Palm Springs, Calif., he said the vice president was demonstrating a predilection to ''stretch the truth.''</p>
        <p>Was that not the same as lying?</p>
        <p>''I'm just disappointed,'' Mr. Bush said, with a ''nice-try'' twinkle and grin. ''I think that's the word I'd like to use. It's a disappointing thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, a savvy enough candidate, understands that in politics, diction establishes tone, and tone is everything. And he turns to euphemisms to resolve inherent tensions in his campaign, like his pledge to run a positive race and his simultaneous resolve to wage an aggressive fight that exposes what he believes to be Mr. Gore's shortcomings.</p>
        <p>He did the same thing in the primaries, watering down the nouns and verbs he used to describe and disparage his principal opponent, Senator John McCain of Arizona. Mr. Bush's mantra at the time was that Mr. McCain ''says one thing and does another.''</p>
        <p>Did that not make the Arizona senator a ''hypocrite''?</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush flinched at the mere suggestion. No, he said, it made the senator a man practiced in the ways of ''Washington,'' a word that was perhaps dirtier but much less explicitly mean-spirited.</p>
        <p>Support From Far Away</p>
        <p>Throughout the Republican primaries, the Bush campaign trumpeted seemingly any and every endorsement, whether it came from the governor of a large state or the secretary of a small sewing circle.</p>
        <p>But last week, the Bush campaign took that tendency to the outer limits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush showed reporters in the back of his campaign plane a recent copy of Weekly World News, a supermarket tabloid, with a cover story on the extraterrestrial support he was receiving. The front page featured a photograph of the governor standing beside an oblong, hairless, vaguely reptilian space alien.</p>
        <p>This was not to be taken lightly. As the newspaper noted, the same intergalactic kingmaker had backed Bill Clinton when he was first elected president in 1992.</p>
        <p>And as Mr. Bush noted, his alien encounter was further proof of his commitment to expanding the Republican Party's appeal.</p>
        <p>''New faces, new voices,'' he said as he held the front page high. ''It goes to show I'm willing to reach across certain demographic lines.''</p>
        <p>Earthier Exchanges</p>
        <p>The exchange also went to show what a prankster and funnyman Mr. Bush fancies himself, a persona on vivid display last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was hurling accusations and put-downs in the governor's direction, and Mr. Bush was laughing, establishing a contrast that may not have been accidental in the least.</p>
        <p>His humor was broad. Asked by reporters during an airborne news conference one afternoon if he would be giving a lengthy stump speech at the airport in Palm Springs, he blanched.</p>
        <p>''Not outdoors!'' he gasped, alluding to the desert heat and one of its less attractive effects on the human body. He tugged at the portion of his dress shirt covering his underarms.  ''Pit city,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He recalled his exodus from Washington the week before, after several campaign stops there, and how one local man reacted to the passing of yet another motorcade by pulling down his pants.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush said the man was really ''mooning authority.''</p>
        <p>The governor seemed a bit less sanguine when the topic turned to a profile, in a major magazine, of the campaign's chief strategist, Karl Rove. Mr. Bush has a thing about advisers eclipsing the candidates they serve.</p>
        <p>And he jokingly wondered what he should expect next: a Playgirl magazine pictorial of his campaign manager, Joe Allbaugh? Mr. Allbaugh is older and burlier than a typical centerfold, but Mr. Bush had a vision.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to have him wear a bikini bathing suit,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
