<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Arena, Different Result for the Knicks in Miami</title>
    <meta content="08KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DC1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Arena, Different Result for the Knicks in Miami</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Miami Heat defeat New York Knickerbockers, 87-83, in first game of National Basketball Association's Eastern Conference semifinal playoff series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deep in the pit of a prized new building that is decorated in the happy color scheme of a Lifesavers roll, a fretful Pat Riley was as helpless a sight this afternoon as he was a year ago in the dank and gloomy air of the old Miami Arena.</p>
        <p>Once again, an anxious Riley was planted on the sideline, waiting to see if Allan Houston would begin to summon the kind of mental focus that can bend spoons, move pencils and throw his Heat into a trance. Houston had done that before. So, Riley, his team and the screaming masses inside American Airlines Arena seemed to be bracing themselves for the moment when the serene shooter would make another playoff game go ''poof.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deep in the pit of a prized new building that is decorated in the happy color scheme of a Lifesavers roll, a fretful Pat Riley was as helpless a sight this afternoon as he was a year ago in the dank and gloomy air of the old Miami Arena.</p>
        <p>Once again, an anxious Riley was planted on the sideline, waiting to see if Allan Houston would begin to summon the kind of mental focus that can bend spoons, move pencils and throw his Heat into a trance. Houston had done that before. So, Riley, his team and the screaming masses inside American Airlines Arena seemed to be bracing themselves for the moment when the serene shooter would make another playoff game go ''poof.''</p>
        <p>But there was an apparent malfunction in Houston's spell, a missing ingredient in his potion. Instead of undoing the Heat, Houston fell apart in the final five minutes of Game 1 today. Instead of calm, Houston exhibited uncharacteristic jitters as he botched an open 3-pointer and turned the ball over three times in the Knicks' 87-83 loss. Instead of deflating the Heat's hope of growing from its past pains, he opened the way for Miami to take a 1-0 lead in this four-of-seven-game second-round playoff series. Game 2 will be played here Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Houston's final misstep of the game came when Dan Majerle -- the 34-year-old guard who was patrolling him the day he eliminated the Heat last year with his destined runner -- stuck his jalopy-shaped body on Houston at the top of the arc with five seconds left in the game. As Houston moved to shoot, Majerle stripped the ball in mid-dribble with 1.7 seconds left on the clock. Any chance for a miracle was over.</p>
        <p>''If I'm going to be the guy with the ball in his hands at the end of the game, I've got to get a shot up or make something happen,'' said Houston, who finished with a team-high 21 points but was 8 for 18 from the field. ''In the past, I've usually done that. I didn't do either today, and that's what's so disappointing. We didn't do what we had to at the end to get this win.''</p>
        <p>Alonzo Mourning did exactly what his team needed. He did not take pity on his mentor, Patrick Ewing. He did not think twice about how Ewing spent his idle moments on the bench today wrapped in a heating pad for his tight back. He did not freeze at the moment he had a late-game encounter with his boyhood hero.</p>
        <p>Mourning slipped to a spot outside the paint. And with Ewing laboring to reach him 17 feet from the basket, Mourning rose off the floor and sent up a soft jumper that was nestled by the net with 5.6 seconds on the clock to pad the Heat's lead and close out the scoring.</p>
        <p>With 41.8 seconds left, Mourning had broken an 83-83 tie when he got the ball deep in the post and put in a layup past Ewing.</p>
        <p>''You have to admire Patrick's attitude and his determination,'' said Mourning, who led the Heat with 26 points and helped hold the ailing but able Ewing to 17. ''That's one of the things I've admired about him over the years, from watching him play at the age of 12. A lot of him has rubbed off on me. He's the reason I approach the game the way I do.''</p>
        <p>The Heat approached this game with desperation. The Knicks arrived with an air of arrogance that did not wear very well. It is as if they thought the game would simply come to them in the end -- because it has so often. When it did not, they grew impatient.</p>
        <p>During a fourth quarter filled with too many jump shots and not enough drives, the entire team failed to keep its composure. In the final five minutes of the game, the Knicks were 0 for 5 and committed four turnovers. And not one of the Knicks who had haunted the Heat in the past could avoid a trap door.</p>
        <p>A harried Chris Childs failed to crush the Heat by missing two 3-pointers in the final four minutes; a wide-open Larry Johnson wavered just enough when he unleashed a 3-pointer with 1 minute 11 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>''I saw him out there by himself,'' said Tim Hardaway, who limped on his injured foot, left the game briefly to get retaped, and finished with 6 points and 7 assists. ''If he had hit that one, we would have seen him doing his L. J. thing up and down our court.''</p>
        <p>With his team down by 2 points, Johnson missed the go-ahead shot. But in some ways, the Heat created Johnson's miss by playing aggressive defense most of the game. It was the kind of hovering effort that left the Knicks to shoot only 42.3 percent from the field, the kind that left Johnson shocked at how alone he was at that point in the game.</p>
        <p>''All day long, they were rotating to me,'' he said. ''So, I was a little surprised to see myself that wide open. Once I saw that, I thought I rushed it. Got too excited. I've got to hit that. I really do.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Knicks managed to tie the game with 55.6 seconds left when Jamal Mashburn mindlessly fouled Latrell Sprewell. Finally, Sprewell had a chance to make an impact. For most of the day, he had been banged and bumped off his game by the bulky Mashburn. This was not the more compact, less experienced Vince Carter. This was harder. Without double-teams to help him, Sprewell gave up 21 points to a steady Mashburn. Without a way to score around his size, Sprewell ended up with 11 points.</p>
        <p>But his last two were critical. Sprewell made his free throws, tied the game at 83-83, but watched Houston commit two turnovers in the span of 30 seconds. With his logic on the blink, Houston tried to zip a pass to Ewing in the post, right beneath the chin of P. J. Brown, who made the steal with 28.3 seconds on the clock.</p>
        <p>''It was just one of those passes where I would have really had to thread a needle,'' Houston said. ''That's probably the single play I wish I could have back. I don't care if Patrick was Jerry Rice, that would have been a tough one to catch. As soon as I threw it, I wish I had it back.''</p>
        <p>There were a lot of those moments during the game. The Knicks wished the first quarter had not happened. They failed to match the Heat's intensity, and went on an 0-for-12 stretch over a seven-minute period. They wished they had not fallen behind by 8 points twice in a third quarter that was revived only on the solo intensity Charlie Ward showed as he drove to the hoop and dived on the floor. On one move, he left Hardaway in pain as the Heat guard planted his bad foot to stop Ward's drive. On another, Ward crashed into Mourning's right temple in a scramble for a loose ball.</p>
        <p>''The Heisman Trophy winner had some flashbacks,'' Mourning said. ''He went headfirst into me. That's the way both coaches teach. The football player he is, he shook it off. I had to gather myself and get back into it.''</p>
        <p>The Heat did that all day. If the Knicks made a run, the Heat regrouped. If the Knicks came up with a big play, the Heat returned it with two. While the Knicks melted down in the fourth quarter with five turnovers, the Heat did not turn it over once.</p>
        <p>''They kept their composure,'' Houston said. ''That's something we usually pride ourselves on doing.''</p>
        <p>Usually, they do it right here, right in the pit of Riley's turf.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
