<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In 'Sweeney,' Words Drive Art Forms</title>
    <meta content="08TODD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Choral Artists</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sondheim, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Price, Lonny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litton, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gershon, Grant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lupone, Patti</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hearn, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sweeney Todd: the Demon Barber of Fleet Street (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DA1238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In 'Sweeney,' Words Drive Art Forms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews New York Philharmonic's concert version of Stephen Sondheim's Sweeney Todd, directed by Lonny Price and conducted by Andrew Litton; Grant Gershon directs New York Choral Artists; Patti LuPone and George Hearn star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question is boring, but one is obliged to ask it. Is ''Sweeney Todd'' an opera? Here are three definitive answers: 1) I don't care. 2) It doesn't matter. 3) No.</p>
        <p>No, at least as applied to Friday night's splendid performance at Avery Fisher Hall. Maybe we are wrong to look for the label in the garment. Maybe the name of the thing is in the eye of the beholder: different onlooker, different measurements. (Einstein, take note). Stephen Sondheim's grimly funny blood bath of a show, which opened on Broadway in 1979 and has been much in our thoughts ever since, is opera for those who expect it to be. But it was certainly American musical theater for the wildly enthusiastic audience that came to this, the second of the New York Philharmonic's three performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question is boring, but one is obliged to ask it. Is ''Sweeney Todd'' an opera? Here are three definitive answers: 1) I don't care. 2) It doesn't matter. 3) No.</p>
        <p>No, at least as applied to Friday night's splendid performance at Avery Fisher Hall. Maybe we are wrong to look for the label in the garment. Maybe the name of the thing is in the eye of the beholder: different onlooker, different measurements. (Einstein, take note). Stephen Sondheim's grimly funny blood bath of a show, which opened on Broadway in 1979 and has been much in our thoughts ever since, is opera for those who expect it to be. But it was certainly American musical theater for the wildly enthusiastic audience that came to this, the second of the New York Philharmonic's three performances.</p>
        <p>Describe Friday's event as ''semi-staged'' or an ''oratorio with movement,'' a crisply managed version, directed by Lonny Price and conducted by Andrew Litton. It was in the end a hybrid that drew its elements from the place it was in and the materials with which it was presented. The customary threat to operas-in-concert is an orchestra not recessed in a theater pit but onstage, where its members can cheerfully douse all but the mightiest singers in a high tide of sound. Confronted by voice amplification, the mighty Philharmonic offered only docile background to Mr. Sondheim's intricate wordplay.</p>
        <p>To innocent ears this quasi-public-address system sounded ghastly, but Broadway has found such electric tools useful in combatting the challenged attention spans and hearing-impaired spirits of the theater's new audiences. Amplification serves words, and what separates Mr. Sondheim's art from grand opera is its literacy. In ''Sweeney Todd'' words drive music. In Puccini music smothers language, helpfully rescuing us from a lot of execrable melodrama. Why else those printed librettos, supertitles and back-of-the-seat television screens, bearing messages that in the end we wish we had never read. (Ignorance can be bliss.)</p>
        <p>The Philharmonic's cast was evenly split between two art forms: George Hearn, Patti LuPone, Audra McDonald, Davis Gaines and Neil Patrick Harris drifting in and out of operatic voice but mainly articulating texts as Broadway has taught them to do; Heidi Grant Murphy, Paul Plishka, John Aler and Stanford Olsen working very hard to make their big voices serve words.</p>
        <p>The New York Choral Artists, more accustomed to delivering Verdi and Beethoven from a standing position, were prodded admirably by their guest conductor, Grant Gershon, to march, writhe and generally turn themselves into actors. They also sang very well.</p>
        <p>Broadway or opera? Again, the audience made that decision. Ms. Murphy and Mr. Plishka, both first rate, received polite enthusiasm, while Mr. Hearn and Ms. LuPone were engulfed in delirious ovations.</p>
        <p>Just as opera has its cults of the voice, musical theater enthusiasts like those in Fisher Hall have their icons, too. Mr. Hearn in the title role was splendid: self-possessed, clear of speech and manipulating a cavernous voice to good effect. Ms. LuPone's Mrs. Lovett exuded energetic charm but made this set of ears work very hard to distinguish everything she said and sang.</p>
        <p>Ms. McDonald's Beggar Woman was flat-out, concentrated emotion. Mr. Harris's patter sounded admirably distinct. Mr. Gaines's throbbing sentimentality bordered on overkill but was bearable in small doses.</p>
        <p>At the end the original question comes back, and in reflection it may not be so boring after all. Naming things -- opera, musical, oratorio, symphony concert -- is after all how we make sense of the world. One person walks through a forest or a flowerbed and sees masses of green, yellow, purple and white. Another identifies spruce, oak, peonies and azaleas. The names are like eyeglasses; they turn the vague into the specific; they sort out experience for the senses.</p>
        <p>All this, I think, is true, but it still doesn't help me in naming ''Sweeney Todd.'' I know that Mr. Sondheim has created powerful and lasting theater, but that is about all I know.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
