<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gliding in Center Field But Slinking in the Dark</title>
    <meta content="08WERT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Experience, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Joe DiMaggio: The Hero's Life (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D91238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gliding in Center Field But Slinking in the Dark</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews television program Joe DiMaggio: The Hero's Life, presented as part of PBS series The American Experience; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consider the life of Joe DiMaggio, who was such a graceful success on the baseball field and such a miserable failure off it, and you may wonder if he sold his soul for that 56-game hitting streak. But after viewing the fascinating biography tonight on PBS's ''American Experience'' series, you might conclude that DiMaggio had no soul to sell.</p>
        <p>Mark Zwonitzer's film ''Joe DiMaggio: The Hero's Life'' paints a damning portrait of a man who was inarticulate, proud, vain and cheap; a man who cheated at cards, took gifts from crooks and failed miserably as a husband (twice) and father (once). But he was most of all a thrilling performer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consider the life of Joe DiMaggio, who was such a graceful success on the baseball field and such a miserable failure off it, and you may wonder if he sold his soul for that 56-game hitting streak. But after viewing the fascinating biography tonight on PBS's ''American Experience'' series, you might conclude that DiMaggio had no soul to sell.</p>
        <p>Mark Zwonitzer's film ''Joe DiMaggio: The Hero's Life'' paints a damning portrait of a man who was inarticulate, proud, vain and cheap; a man who cheated at cards, took gifts from crooks and failed miserably as a husband (twice) and father (once). But he was most of all a thrilling performer.</p>
        <p>''We strove for more than 60 years to give Joe DiMaggio the hero's life,'' says the narrator, Richard Ben Cramer, who wrote the film with Mr. Zwonitzer. ''From his debut at Yankee Stadium in 1936 until his death in 1999, DiMaggio was, at every turn, one man we could look at who made us feel good.''</p>
        <p>The documentary may make you feel bad. But you'll be glad you watched it, or rather, listened to it. With its newsreel clips, file photos and talking heads, this film looks no different from the historical fare offered nightly on a half-dozen cable channels.</p>
        <p>But pay attention to the words, chiefly those spoken by Mr. Cramer and the veteran sportswriter and DiMaggio biographer Maury Allen, and you'll be touched by an American tragedy.</p>
        <p>''It seemed he was walking on air,'' Mr. Allen says of DiMaggio. ''He would glide through a stadium. He would glide through a restaurant.'' But despite appearances, he slinked darkly through much of his life.</p>
        <p>DiMaggio, son of a San Francisco fisherman, found baseball by a process of elimination. He didn't want to follow his father onto the boat. An indifferent student, he dropped out of school at 15. From semipro ball he progressed to the minor league San Francisco Seals. He was making money. This was worth an effort.</p>
        <p>''Joe bent his life to the game,'' Mr. Cramer says. ''He'd never had any coaching, but now he learned like Mozart learned the piano: all at once and instantly.''</p>
        <p>He tore up the Pacific Coast League; and the Yankees, at sea since the departure of Babe Ruth, pinned their hopes on this prospect. New York and DiMaggio took to each other. He became a regular at Toots Shor's. And while the team never paid him what he thought he was worth, he quickly learned that ''there was money in just being Joe.'' He piled up endorsement fees and accepted favors, including a Cadillac just for showing up at a Newark banquet.</p>
        <p>His first marriage, to the movie starlet Dorothy Arnold, brought the couple pain and Joe DiMaggio Jr.  Father and son would never have any kind of relationship. But in the summer of 1941, while Americans shuddered over news of a war that was soon to envelop them, the public was happily diverted by DiMaggio's record-setting hitting streak. ''The entire country seemed to be emotionally involved,'' Mr. Allen says.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, though, war trumped baseball. DiMaggio became a reluctant volunteer and spent the duration safely playing ball for an Army team. Back with the Yankees in '46 he was beginning to feel his age. In 1951 he saw history repeated as a kid named Mickey Mantle showed up to claim the spotlight.</p>
        <p>His teammate Jerry Coleman recalls DiMaggio's pain at ''watching this halo around his shoulders sort of slip away.'' He retired and embarked on 48 years of living on his past glories.</p>
        <p>His second brief and tragic marriage, to Marilyn Monroe, almost cost DiMaggio his standing with the public. He could not bear living in her shadow, and when she left him, she had bruises on her face.</p>
        <p>DiMaggio retreated, appearing now and then to sign autographs or pitch products. He had no real friends and was estranged from his family. But somehow his legend flourished in that vacuum. ''The more he retreated, the more our hunger for him grew,'' Mr. Cramer says. ''His blankness allowed us to make him perfect in our eyes.''</p>
        <p>Joltin' Joe is rendered most imperfect by this cold-eyed documentary. But his tale is worth your attention. Despite his flaws, he is still revered. To understand why, do two things. First watch this film. Then talk to someone who remembers the summer of '41.</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAN EXPERIENCE  Joe DiMaggio: The Hero's Life  PBS, tonight  (Channels 13 and 49, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>A production by Lennon Documentary Group for ''The American Experience.'' Mark Zwonitzer, producer and director; Richard Ben Cramer and Mr. Zwonitzer, writers; Bruce Shaw, editor. The American Experience is a production of WGBH Boston. Margaret Drain, executive producer; Mark Samels, senior producer; David McCullough, series host.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
