<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; 'Good Friend,' A Marriage, And Voters</title>
    <meta content="08MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nathan, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DF1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; 'Good Friend,' A Marriage, And Voters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column questions Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's plea for privacy following disclosure that he is 'very good friends' with a woman; contends Giuliani, who as candidate for Senate wants to pronounce his behavior to be nobody's business and suffer no ill political consequences, is asking for leeway that he has rarely granted others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TREAT him is if he were Everyman, says Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. Public officials have problems, too.</p>
        <p>Will the public accommodate him, as one recent poll suggested? That would mean a married candidate -- if Mr. Giuliani remains a Senate candidate -- can acknowledge a relationship with ''a very good friend,'' pronounce his behavior to be nobody's business, and suffer no ill political consequences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TREAT him is if he were Everyman, says Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. Public officials have problems, too.</p>
        <p>Will the public accommodate him, as one recent poll suggested? That would mean a married candidate -- if Mr. Giuliani remains a Senate candidate -- can acknowledge a relationship with ''a very good friend,'' pronounce his behavior to be nobody's business, and suffer no ill political consequences.</p>
        <p>All this from a Catholic school alumnus who has labored to rid his city of sleaze, tried to punish a museum that exhibited art he considered immoral, and wants the Ten Commandments posted in public schools.</p>
        <p>Talk about your Nixon-to-China syndrome.</p>
        <p>We don't know if the mayor will pursue his Senate campaign, given his bout with cancer. We do know that he is asking a lot of tolerance from New Yorkers -- and from his wife, Donna Hanover, who now refers obliquely to the need for ''decisions.''</p>
        <p>''This is a very unusual thing,'' said Michael Beschloss, a historian of the presidency. ''You can wrack your brain and not find a precedent in recent history that foreshadows this.'' Not, Mr. Beschloss noted, that it comes out of nowhere. A half-century ago, a divorce spelled the death knell of presidential aspirations; by 1980, Ronald Reagan, a divorced man, was elected. Bill Clinton won the presidency in 1992 despite Gennifer Flowers and survived Monica Lewinsky, and impeachment, with his popularity intact.</p>
        <p>Gary Hart's presidential candidacy collapsed primarily because of revelations of an affair, but only after he boasted of a solid marriage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani and Ms. Hanover long ago acknowledged leading separate lives, so the mayor's problem is not hypocrisy. But can a man not known for his empathies ask the public to understand that public officials also live the lives ''that other human beings do''?</p>
        <p>The mayor has worked a lifetime creating the impression that he is unlike the rest of us: the tough, unyielding prosecutor; the high-minded, uncompromising mayor. He routinely berates those who ask him questions he doesn't like and roughly faces down all critics.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC matters, not private, Mr. Giuliani would say. But distinctions blur. In the long run, what is likely to matter most is what people think of the Giuliani they know, not of his new relationship.</p>
        <p>''I think the rule in politics is if you have a general reservoir of good will among your constituents, you can get away with it,'' suggested Robert Ellis Smith, publisher of the newsletter Privacy Journal. ''People have come to know Giuliani over several years. Everyone pretty much has made up his mind about him as a public figure. Associating with someone not his wife isn't going to change people's minds.''</p>
        <p>New Yorkers do, indeed, know Mr. Giuliani; few are undecided between him and Hillary Rodham Clinton. Even his conduct in addressing this friendship was in character. The mayor, who loves to manipulate the media, all but announced the relationship himself.</p>
        <p>The story broke last week in the tabloids after the mayor brought Judith Nathan to several public events, including (tweak, tweak) the Inner Circle, a reporters' dinner and show held March 11. Rumors flew, and finally the couple were seen together so frequently that the story broke, first in The Daily News, then The New York Post. They said she was a divorced nurse, a mother of a 15-year-old girl, who works for a pharmaceutical company and has been seeing the mayor for months.</p>
        <p>The mayor confirmed his friendship,  perhaps, because the timing was good -- he was drawing sympathy for his diagnosis of prostate cancer. Besides, he knew that two books about him were in the works and that Gail Sheehy had written an article about the Senate race in the new Vanity Fair. Getting potentially damaging news out yourself is good politics.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers may not care much about inside baseball. What they know is that the mayor has a failing marriage, that Mr. Giuliani is open about pursuing midlife happiness, that Ms. Hanover is upset, that two children are caught in the middle. There are consequences, as there are for millions of people in troubled marriages.</p>
        <p>The mayor will not lie about it, to his credit, but asks the public to allow him a degree of latitude that he has rarely granted others. It seems logical that the voters' willingness to separate his personal and political identities will depend not on any theories about what is private in public lives, but on the reputation Mr. Giuliani long ago created for himself -- and on Ms. Hanover's ''decisions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
