<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Summer Days in May As Only DeHaven Qualifies</title>
    <meta content="Y08MAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeHaven, Rod</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DF1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Summer Days in May As Only DeHaven Qualifies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rod DeHaven wins United States Olympic Marathon trials event, Pittsburgh; will be lone American representative in men's Marathon at Sydney Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the brutal heat and humidity, legs cramped and blisters bled through shoes and some of the runners left the finish line on stretchers instead of on their feet. Rod DeHaven reached the tape first today after 26.2 miles at an Olympic trials that became more about survival than about speed. It also left American marathoning in a state of utter depletion.</p>
        <p>DeHaven's winning time was  2 hours 15 minutes 30 seconds, respectable for a day in which the temperature on a hilly course hit 77 degrees by midmorning with 57 percent humidity. But because he did not achieve the Olympic ''A'' qualifying standard of 2:14, DeHaven will be the lone American representative in the men's marathon at the Summer Games for the first time since 1896.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the brutal heat and humidity, legs cramped and blisters bled through shoes and some of the runners left the finish line on stretchers instead of on their feet. Rod DeHaven reached the tape first today after 26.2 miles at an Olympic trials that became more about survival than about speed. It also left American marathoning in a state of utter depletion.</p>
        <p>DeHaven's winning time was  2 hours 15 minutes 30 seconds, respectable for a day in which the temperature on a hilly course hit 77 degrees by midmorning with 57 percent humidity. But because he did not achieve the Olympic ''A'' qualifying standard of 2:14, DeHaven will be the lone American representative in the men's marathon at the Summer Games for the first time since 1896.</p>
        <p>Christine Clark, who won the women's trials in February, will be the lone American in the women's marathon at the Olympics in Sydney, Australia, in September. In the past, when stringent time requirements were not imposed, the United States sent three male and three female marathoners to the Games. But the situation has grown dire as the rest of the world has gotten faster and Olympic officials have restricted the number of athletes competing in the ever-growing Summer Games.</p>
        <p>Today's race left even the winner curiously downcast and left track and field officials to contemplate significant changes in the way the marathon trials are conducted, as well as the way American marathoners are trained.</p>
        <p>''The win is pretty significant,'' said DeHaven, a 33-year-old computer programmer from Madison, Wis., who earned $75,000 for his victory. ''But being the only one going doesn't leave me with the best taste in my mouth. Maybe this is the low point for marathoning in the country. Maybe we can go up from here.''</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh was awarded the 2000 trials in the spring of 1998 when it was the only city to offer to pay air fare, per diem and prize money to the elite marathoners. Organizers could not have known that the weather would be this awful. To prevent a recurrence of unexpected heat, slow times and minimal representation in the Olympics, officials and runners have suggested putting future marathon trials on cooler, flatter courses.</p>
        <p>Also, officials said, ways must be found to make American runners faster. The methods may include programs that identify potential marathoners at an early age, group training camps and financial support in the years between the end of college and the late 20's, when many distance careers begin to blossom. Such an assistance effort would cost $1 million a year, said Craig Masback, the chief executive of USA Track and Field, the sport's national governing body.</p>
        <p>''We've never been able to raise that money,'' Masback said.</p>
        <p>But something has to change if the Americans are to regain their international competitiveness.</p>
        <p>''I think it's safe to say we will never again have an Olympic trials that will be this hot or this slow,'' said Danny Grimes, chairman of USA Track and Field's long-distance-running committee.</p>
        <p>DeHaven's winning time was the slowest at the American Olympic trials since 1972. Peter De La Cerda, who had been the pacemaker the past two years at the Pittsburgh Marathon, took the lead between Miles 12 and 13 and held it until the patient DeHaven took the lead after 22 1/2 miles. On a slight downhill, DeHaven ran Mile 24 in 4:56 and put the race out of touch. De La Cerda finished second in 2:16:18, and Mark Coogan, a 1996 Olympian, took third in 2:17:04.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to say I had a grand plan, but it was totally a race of attrition,'' DeHaven said.</p>
        <p>Only 9 of the 99 starters ran under 2:20. Another 21 runners dropped out during the race. David Morris, the American record-holder in 2:09:32, began suffering from abdominal cramps at Mile 2 and briefly stopped in the 15th mile. He finished 38th in 2:29:26. Morris said he had become anxious over the 2:14 qualifying standard and the uncertainty about whether Khalid Khannouchi, the Moroccan-born world record-holder who got his American citizenship last Wednesday, would compete. He did not because of injuries.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't sleep at all this week,'' Morris said.</p>
        <p>DeHaven, who was able to train more efficiently after reducing his work in the computer business to part-time, said the heat and humidity were not as bad as he had expected. The conditions were worse at the 1999 world championships, held last August in Seville, Spain, where DeHaven was the top American finisher in 24th place.</p>
        <p>''In a couple areas, the cigarette smoke was so thick I could hardly breathe,'' he said.</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
