<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reconstructing the Genesis of a Blunder</title>
    <meta content="08TIME$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDA1238F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reconstructing the Genesis of a Blunder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time Warner officials now say decision to block Disney's ABC television network was based on legal miscalculation and mistaken conviction that Disney would back down; poisonous atmosphere at talks over how much cable company should pay Disney for use of three of its cable channels and over whether Disney would renew Time Warner's right to carry ABC apparently clouded their judgments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What, exactly, was Time Warner thinking?</p>
        <p>When the next history of public relations is written, the company's decision to block the ABC television network in 3.5 million homes last Monday will surely be a prominent chapter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What, exactly, was Time Warner thinking?</p>
        <p>When the next history of public relations is written, the company's decision to block the ABC television network in 3.5 million homes last Monday will surely be a prominent chapter.</p>
        <p>In just 39 hours -- the time it took to restore the ABC signal -- Time Warner managed to anger many of its customers, rile local and national politicians, provoke a tough editorial in The New York Times, draw the ire of the Federal Communications Commission, give its satellite competitors a rare opening to grab customers and upset what had looked like smooth sailing on the way to approval of its merger with America Online.</p>
        <p>And it made ABC's parent, Walt Disney, no media midget itself, look, in many eyes, like a helpless victim.</p>
        <p>Time Warner executives now acknowledge that they erred. This came about, they say, through a legal miscalculation and a conviction that Disney would back down. It is also clear that judgments may have been clouded by emotion. For months, tension had been building as negotiators tried to resolve how much Time Warner should pay Disney for the use of three of its cable channels and whether Disney would renew Time Warner's right to carry the ABC network.</p>
        <p>Everyone agrees that the atmosphere of the bargaining was poisonous. Five months of negotiating had gone nowhere. Deadlines were extended seven times. Time Warner accused Disney of blackmail for threatening to pull its ABC signal if Time Warner did not meet its demands. Disney accused Time Warner of shortchanging it on its valuable ABC programming.</p>
        <p>At one point, two Disney executives were asked to leave the Time Warner offices, and by late April face-to-face talks had ceased.</p>
        <p>Then came Wednesday, April 26, five days before the latest negotiating deadline, when Time Warner's rights to carry the ABC network were to expire. ABC faxed a terse letter to Time Warner notifying it that Disney expected Time Warner to continue carrying the ABC signal through May 24 after the end of the sweeps period, when stations measure audiences to determine what to charge advertisers. Time Warner had been insisting on an eight-month extension.</p>
        <p>The tone of the fax set off the tempers of some Time Warner executives, who felt ABC was negotiating by fiat. Previously, before the other deadlines, ABC had faxed polite requests for signatures on proposed extension agreements.</p>
        <p>''In this case, they were saying, 'We give you the right to carry our signal,' '' said Mike Luftman, spokesman for Time Warner Cable. ''We felt that clearly things had changed.''</p>
        <p>Time Warner executives began to prepare for the worst. They ordered an advertising agency to create a blaring message to replace the ABC signal, the dramatic sentence ''Disney has taken ABC away from you.''</p>
        <p>But still, they expected no Armageddon. For one thing, they thought ABC would never allow its programming to be pulled during a sweeps month, especially because it would jeopardize its chance to finish the season as the No. 1 network for the first time in five years.</p>
        <p>At that point, both sides were interpreting the law differently. ABC maintained that an F.C.C. regulation stipulated that its signal could not be pulled in a sweeps month. Time Warner's lawyers argued that, barring mutual agreement on an extension, it had to do just that.</p>
        <p>Within Time Warner, executives debated what to do if Disney stood its ground. Some saw blocking the network signal as a real risk. A cable company -- an institution about as popular as a parking violations bureau and often the target of accusations of monopolistic practices -- was more likely to take the blame than a network, these people argued.</p>
        <p>But others saw advantages. Assuming the law was on Time Warner's side, ABC would potentially face big advertising revenue losses -- up to $3 million a day, according to some estimates. And perhaps Disney, a huge conglomerate, would take just as much blame, if not more, if Time Warner put its message out effectively. And then there was also the resentment at play.</p>
        <p>''At some point you have to put your foot down and be a man and stand up and say 'Look,' '' Fred Dressler, Time Warner's senior vice president for programming,  later told a reporter.</p>
        <p>Sunday, April 30, came, and still no agreement had been reached. More terse faxes went back and forth that afternoon. Neither side budged. By around 8:30 p.m., Disney executives began to sense that Time Warner's threat to pull the ABC signal was real, though they still found it hard to believe.</p>
        <p>Was Disney playing the bullfighter taunting the bull? There is no evidence that this was the corporate plan, though pulling the signal clearly played into Disney's strategy of painting Time Warner as a monopolist that would become even bigger should its merger with America Online win approval.</p>
        <p>Time Warner executives were convinced, meanwhile, that they had Disney cornered.</p>
        <p>''It's clear they didn't think we would drop, and we didn't think they would let us drop,'' said Mr. Dressler, who led the Time Warner negotiating team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Luftman, the Time Warner Cable spokesman, said, ''Right up until the last minute, we were hoping to get something acceptable on the table.''</p>
        <p>But Preston R. Padden, the Washington lobbyist for Disney, who had become increasingly involved in the negotiations, said: ''All we could do was sit in front of the TV and wait until midnight to see what they were going to do. I didn't think they were going to do it.''</p>
        <p>With no compromise offer from Disney, Time Warner executives felt there was no turning back. Not long before midnight, Time Warner Cable's president, Joseph J. Collins, alerted Gerald M. Levin, the Time Warner chairman, that he was about to order his engineers to block the ABC signal. Mr. Levin supported the decision. Executives said Stephen M. Case, the America Online chairman, was also apprised of the situation.</p>
        <p>At 12:01 a.m., the ABC screen went briefly to static before the accusation against Disney appeared on a blue screen in bright yellow letters. Mr. Padden was in his room at the Four Seasons Hotel in Manhattan. ''I had a very sick feeling in the pit of my stomach,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Where things stood for Time Warner were pretty clear within 24 hours. In New York, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani attacked Time Warner as a predatory monopoly. ''This is an example of what happens when you let a monopoly get too big,'' Mr. Giuliani said.</p>
        <p>Disney dispatched its lawyers to the Washington offices of the F.C.C., where they requested that the commission force Time Warner to transmit its signals based on the sweeps regulation.</p>
        <p>In the same building, Time Warner representatives made their case. They thought they were getting positive signals. But later in the day, during a meeting with the commission's cable bureau, Time Warner had a different feeling.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, The New York Times published an editorial that said the threat to Disney by a combined America Online and Time Warner was real.</p>
        <p>At about 10 a.m. that day, Mr. Dressler said, Time Warner executives decided it was time to try a resolution. It was becoming rapidly clear that Time Warner was badly losing the public relations war, though both sides were suffering to some degree. ''We certainly knew at that point that our customers weren't happy,'' Mr. Dressler said. ''We thought it was in our interest, certainly in theirs as well, to extend the olive branch.''</p>
        <p>At a hastily called news conference, Mr. Collins announced that he had offered Disney an extension of the negotiations until October. During the news conference, Robert A. Iger, the Disney president, sent a fax to Time Warner officials proposing July 15 as the next deadline. Mr. Collins accepted immediately.</p>
        <p>The next day, the F.C.C. ruled that Time Warner had indeed violated the law by blocking ABC from its systems during a sweeps month. The company received a strong rebuke from the F.C.C. chairman, William E. Kennard, who declared, ''No company should use consumers in a private contract dispute.''</p>
        <p>The question now is how much the dispute will hurt Time Warner as it tries to conclude its merger with America Online.</p>
        <p>''Why did we decide to take a stand now?'' Mr. Dressler said. ''We thought it was the right time. They were just pushing us and pushing us.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
