<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of Sight at Cathedral, Playing the Hymns and Cleaning the Crypt</title>
    <meta content="MB231637" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marsellus, John D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DB1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of Sight at Cathedral, Playing the Hymns and Cleaning the Crypt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John D Marsellus of Marsellus Casket Company comments on the coffin made for Cardinal John O'Connor of New York (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The official farewell to Cardinal John O'Connor culminates this afternoon in his funeral Mass, an intricately choreographed service that reflects the work of hundreds of people, many of them volunteers, most of them little noticed.</p>
        <p>The Coffin Maker</p>
        <p>When thousands of mourners arrive at the funeral today, they will view on the sanctuary steps a red African mahogany wood coffin, lined in velvet, made hundreds of miles away in the Syracuse, N.Y., company of John D. Marsellus, 61.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The official farewell to Cardinal John O'Connor culminates this afternoon in his funeral Mass, an intricately choreographed service that reflects the work of hundreds of people, many of them volunteers, most of them little noticed.</p>
        <p>The Coffin Maker</p>
        <p>When thousands of mourners arrive at the funeral today, they will view on the sanctuary steps a red African mahogany wood coffin, lined in velvet, made hundreds of miles away in the Syracuse, N.Y., company of John D. Marsellus, 61.</p>
        <p>Nearly 130 years ago, Mr. Marsellus's great-grandfather left New York City at age 26 for the banks of the Erie Canal, to start his own coffin making business. That company now employs about 360 people.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday after flying back from New York City, where he was viewing the casket at St. Patrick's, Mr. Marsellus, the chairman of Marsellus Casket Company, said that he ''felt proud today.''</p>
        <p>''I got to St. Patrick's Cathedral, and to hear people talk about how beautiful the setting was, how meaningful it was for seeing him at peace, I guess I kind of said to myself, 'My family has done the right thing by dedicating 128 years to making caskets.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marsellus did not want to discuss the price of the coffin or how long it took to make, but he noted that it was made of wood shipped in from the Ivory Coast, in West Africa.</p>
        <p>From there, he said, the coffin was shipped to Syracuse, where it was dried, seasoned and shaped. Seamstresses worked to weave the velvet lace that now lines the structure.</p>
        <p>''These are all folks whose skills and talents are special, Mr. Marsellus said. ''He was not just a cardinal for New York City, but he was a cardinal for many people, and our employees felt touched to be able to serve for this type of tribute.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marsellus has no plans to attend the memorial service today, but flew in yesterday for other services.</p>
        <p>After hearing his reactions from priests and Cardinal O'Connor's family members, Mr. Marsellus said, ''I'm feeling a little bit proud and feeling a sense of dedication and reaffirmation in of our industry, which has had some criticism at times.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''This will be in the heads and hearts of many people, and it will be happy. I guess I kind of felt we were fulfilling our mission today.''</p>
        <p>JAYSON BLAIR</p>
        <p>DEATH OF A CARDINAL: THE PEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
