<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 Are Killed and One is Hurt by Carbon Monoxide In House</title>
    <meta content="08FAMI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asphyxiation and Suffocation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Furnaces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Roslyn Heights (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kranz, Andrei (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDB1338F93BA35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 Are Killed and One is Hurt by Carbon Monoxide In House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carbon monoxide fumes from defective furnace are suspected to have killed six people at house in Roslyn Heights in Nassau County, NY; Dr Andrei Kranz is in critical condition after entering the house and trying to rouse the victims (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carbon monoxide fumes from a defective furnace are suspected to have killed six people at a house in Nassau County either late Saturday night or early yesterday morning and left another victim hospitalized in critical condition, police officials said.</p>
        <p>The hospitalized man, Dr. Andrei Kranz, 46, returned home to 27 Parkway Drive in Roslyn Heights yesterday morning after working an overnight shift at Nassau County Medical Center to find his parents, his 2-year-old daughter, a nanny and two house guests unconscious, police officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carbon monoxide fumes from a defective furnace are suspected to have killed six people at a house in Nassau County either late Saturday night or early yesterday morning and left another victim hospitalized in critical condition, police officials said.</p>
        <p>The hospitalized man, Dr. Andrei Kranz, 46, returned home to 27 Parkway Drive in Roslyn Heights yesterday morning after working an overnight shift at Nassau County Medical Center to find his parents, his 2-year-old daughter, a nanny and two house guests unconscious, police officials said.</p>
        <p>They were apparently the victims of carbon monoxide poisoning, said Officer Bob Jones, a spokesman for the Nassau County Police Department.</p>
        <p>Police officials said that those killed were Dr. Kranz's 2-year-old daughter, Simina; the family's live-in nanny, Emelia Dumtru, 58; Dr. Kranz's parents, Victoria Kranz, 74, and Marcus Kranz, 85, who live at another home in Roslyn Heights; and two house guests from Romania, Maria Mihaela Campeanu, 68, and Ioan Campeanu, 75.</p>
        <p>Officer Jones said that the deaths were still under investigation pending autopsies by the Nassau County Medical Examiner's office. But he added that ''it appears to be carbon monoxide poisoning.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kranz called 911 at 9:38 a.m. yesterday to report that he had found everyone in his house unconscious, the police said.</p>
        <p>Police officials said that Dr. Kranz was found lying in the driveway of his home, trying to resuscitate Simina, who was lying in his lap, dressed in her pink pajamas. Officials said that it appeared as if Dr. Kranz went into the house and tried to wake the victims before calling 911.</p>
        <p>He was in critical but stable condition last night at Nassau County Medical Center, said Shelly Lotenberg, a spokeswoman for the hospital.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kranz, a second-year radiology resident at the hospital, was being treated for carbon monoxide exposure and was in the intensive care unit, on the same floor where he works.</p>
        <p>The police said that Dr. Kranz's wife, Anca, 45, also a doctor, and the couple's 17-year-old daughter were not home at the time of the incident and had been told of the deaths, the police said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that the pair were visiting family members in Romania.</p>
        <p>Autopsies on the victims were  scheduled for yesterday and today, officials said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that the family had lived on the block for about one year. Before that, the family had lived on and off in Nassau and Suffolk Counties since 1983, records show.</p>
        <p>Detectives are looking into whether an air-conditioning unit and furnace caused carbon monoxide to start wafting through the house overnight, one official said.</p>
        <p>Investigators were looking into a theory last night that the central air conditioning system sucked in carbon monoxide from a faulty furnace, and then distributed it throughout the house.</p>
        <p>But the official cautioned that the deaths were still being investigated.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that the Kranz family were among the few on the block who used gas heat.</p>
        <p>The deaths shocked the community. Meredith Landau, 23, a neighbor, said she could not stop thinking about how ''the little girl and the nanny used to walk up and down the streets, and she used to ride on the bike. Things like this really haven't happened around here.''</p>
        <p>In the last few months, several people in the region have been killed in carbon monoxide-related incidents.</p>
        <p>In December, a kitchen worker was killed and five workers were overcome by fumes from a defective heating system in a popular club near Times Square.</p>
        <p>Candy Bassen, who lived on the same street as the Kranz family, described them as a quiet family who kept to themselves.</p>
        <p>''It was very upsetting, from what I understand he was outside in his driveway with his little girl'' in his arms, Ms. Bassen said of Mr. Kranz. ''It is a terrible tragedy and it is something every homeowner needs to understand -- the mechanics of a house, something like this doesn't need to happen. It could happen to anyone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
