<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Softbank Deal for Nippon Credit as Deadline Passes</title>
    <meta content="Y01BAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Softbank Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nippon Credit Bank Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED8153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Softbank Deal for Nippon Credit as Deadline Passes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Softbank Corp is dealt setback in efforts to acquire Japan's Nippon Credit Bank, large insolvent bank nationalized by government, which says it will seek other possible buyers; investment group led by Softbank had won exclusive right to negotiate purchase of bank three months ago; deadline for reaching agreement expires with little progress made on terms (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Softbank Corporation, Japan's leading Internet company, was dealt a setback today in efforts to acquire a large insolvent bank nationalized by the government, which said it would seek other possible buyers.</p>
        <p>An investment group led by Softbank had won the exclusive right to negotiate the purchase of the Nippon Credit Bank three months ago, in what was described at the time as a deal with far-reaching implications for Japan's banking and Internet industries. But the deadline for reaching an agreement, which had already been extended once, expired today with little progress made on the terms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Softbank Corporation, Japan's leading Internet company, was dealt a setback today in efforts to acquire a large insolvent bank nationalized by the government, which said it would seek other possible buyers.</p>
        <p>An investment group led by Softbank had won the exclusive right to negotiate the purchase of the Nippon Credit Bank three months ago, in what was described at the time as a deal with far-reaching implications for Japan's banking and Internet industries. But the deadline for reaching an agreement, which had already been extended once, expired today with little progress made on the terms.</p>
        <p>The Financial Reconstruction Commission, the regulatory agency overseeing the overhaul of Japan's troubled financial sector, said it intended to keep talking to the Softbank-led group, which includes the Orix Corporation, one of Japan's largest leasing companies, and the Tokio Marine and Fire Insurance Company. But the agency said it would also talk to other potential bidders.</p>
        <p>Regulators said they could not agree with the Softbank group on the scope of Nippon Credit Bank's bad- loan problem and the value of the collateral backing those and other loans. ''Those three each had an opinion over how to estimate and deal with bad loans,'' said Shoji Mori, a senior commission official. ''The situation at the final meeting was that we were far from reaching an agreement.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, the Softbank-led group, which had tentatively offered 100 billion yen, or about $938 million at current exchange rates, for the bank, said it would continue the pursuit of Nippon Credit.</p>
        <p>Some financial analysts were betting that the Softbank group would win the bank, one of two big banks nationalized during Japan's financial crisis in 1998.</p>
        <p>''They have a credible business plan, and they want the bank,'' said Dean Perry, an analyst who tracks nonbank financial companies at ING Barings.</p>
        <p>Government officials, speaking privately, said the failure to meet today's deadline reflected political concerns arising over how much responsibility the government would be forced to accept for loans that sour after the sale.</p>
        <p>The commission has recently been criticized by politicians over the terms of its deal to sell the Long-Term Credit Bank, the other nationalized bank, to an investment group led by Ripplewood Holdings L.L.C., an American investment fund.</p>
        <p>Long-Term Credit Bank has emerged as the largest creditor of several firms that have recently gone bankrupt or asked their creditors for substantial debt forgiveness. Under the terms of Ripplewood's agreement, the government must take responsibility for bad loans that arise from such circumstances, reducing Ripplewood's risk.</p>
        <p>Political concerns about the sale of these banks have come as the country prepares for contentious parliamentary elections that could weaken the power of the dominant Liberal Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Approval ratings for the cabinet led by Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori plunged to a record postwar low this week, according to a poll done by the Asahi Shimbun.</p>
        <p>Despite the setback to Softbank, some analysts welcomed the possibility that it might not be acquiring Nippon Credit.</p>
        <p>''We thought this was a very expensive way to buy a banking license that came with too much legacy management,'' said Thomas Rodes, who follows Japan's Internet industry at Nikko Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>The failure to reach a deal by today's deadline did not come as a complete surprise. Japan's Internet business community has buzzed with rumors that Softbank's ardor for the deal was cooling.</p>
        <p>Yoshitaka Kitao, the president and chief executive of the Softbank Finance Corporation, Softbank's financing subsidiary, has been debating the wisdom of buying into Nippon Credit Bank openly with Masayoshi Son, the Softbank founder and chief executive, who wants to use the bank to finance the fledgling companies that have historically lacked access to bank financing here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kitao has questioned whether Softbank can assume the risk of a bank that has a sizable portfolio of bad loans, particularly at a time when Softbank's own financial structure is considered shaky. The company has a speculative credit rating, its stock has fallen more than 73 percent since February, and earnings plunged 77 percent in the fiscal year that ended March 31.</p>
        <p>Mr. Son has dismissed such concerns, saying Softbank has more cash on hand than the total of its debts due for the next eight years.</p>
        <p>''We have enough reserves to repay all debts at once if we want,'' he said at a news conference last week.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
