<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Says New York City May Have to Spend $6 Billion on Filtration</title>
    <meta content="01WATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservoirs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hu, Winnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DB123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Says New York City May Have to Spend $6 Billion on Filtration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hu, Winnie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal environmental officials say that New York City might be forced to bear huge cost of building $6 billion water filtration plant because it has fallen far behind in efforts to assure quality of drinking water from its upstate reservoirs; Environmental Protection Agency accuses city of failing to upgrade 34 sewage plants discharging treated waste water into city's biggest reservoirs and of failing to buy enough undeveloped land around Kensico Reservoir in Westchester County (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal environmental officials said yesterday that New York City might be forced to bear the huge cost of building a $6 billion water filtration plant because it had fallen far behind in efforts to assure the quality of drinking water from its upstate reservoirs.</p>
        <p>In its bluntest words yet, the Environmental Protection Agency accused the city of failing to upgrade the 34 sewage plants discharging treated waste water into the city's biggest reservoirs, and of failing to buy enough undeveloped land around one crucial reservoir just north of White Plains in Westchester County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal environmental officials said yesterday that New York City might be forced to bear the huge cost of building a $6 billion water filtration plant because it had fallen far behind in efforts to assure the quality of drinking water from its upstate reservoirs.</p>
        <p>In its bluntest words yet, the Environmental Protection Agency accused the city of failing to upgrade the 34 sewage plants discharging treated waste water into the city's biggest reservoirs, and of failing to buy enough undeveloped land around one crucial reservoir just north of White Plains in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>The report is the first comprehensive review by the E.P.A. since it allowed the city to avoid filtering its drinking water as part of a 1997 agreement in which the city pledged to take several major actions to safeguard the quality of its water supply. If the city does not follow through, the agency will require it to filter its water beginning in May 2002.</p>
        <p>''The city has done well in a number of areas, but in others they are falling far behind,'' said Jeanne M. Fox, regional administrator for the agency. ''They must turn things around or risk being required to filter.''</p>
        <p>Under the 1997 agreement, New York City and communities around its 19 reservoirs pledged to protect the city's water supply by installing new equipment in sewage plants, buying land around the reservoirs to prevent future development that could lead to more chemical runoff into the water, and undertaking several other improvements. In return, the E.P.A. granted the city a conditional waiver from filtering its water for five years.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the city's efforts to avoid building the filtration plant have become increasingly jeopardized by delays and unforeseen complications. James M. Tierney, an assistant state attorney general charged by Gov. George E. Pataki with tracking the cleanup, said last month that the city's plan to modernize the sewage plants had not progressed beyond preliminary planning and would be nearly impossible to finish by the deadline.</p>
        <p>New York City maintains the largest unfiltered water supply in the country. Its reservoirs in the Catskills provide 90 percent of the city's drinking water. City officials have committed to build a $600 million filtration plant for its second system of reservoirs, east of the Hudson River, a result of an earlier court settlement with the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>City officials said yesterday that they were aware of the latest criticisms by the federal government and that they had redoubled their efforts in the problem areas. They said they expected to complete most, if not all, of the required improvements to the watershed within the next two years.</p>
        <p>''We welcome the E.P.A.'s midterm report,'' said Geoffrey Ryan, a spokesman for the city's Department of Environmental Protection. ''The D.E.P. will continue its aggressive efforts to protect the watershed and achieve compliance.''</p>
        <p>But several environmentalists said the agency's report should serve as a danger signal to city officials and to residents, who would almost certainly face substantial rate increases in their water and sewer rates if the city was forced to build a costly new filtration plant.</p>
        <p>''It's a long-term hurricane forecast,'' said Eric A. Goldstein, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, an advocacy group in New York City that monitors water quality issues. ''What this report is saying is, if things don't change in the next two years, New York will face the prospect of building a $6 billion filtration plant.''</p>
        <p>But the agency's report also says that city officials have made some improvements, like upgrading six city-owned sewage plants that produce 40 percent of the total discharge into the Catskill reservoirs. A new educational program has also encouraged most farmers along the watershed to reduce or control runoff from pesticides and other contaminants, the report says.</p>
        <p>''This is not the end of the road yet,'' said Mary Mears, a spokeswoman for the E.P.A. in New York City. ''We're halfway through the process, and this is a way for us to tell them what to focus on.''</p>
        <p>The city has bought 20,000 acres around city reservoirs to prevent future development, including 5,400 acres around the West Branch Reservoir, one of two crucial reservoirs in the Catskill system. But it has acquired only 17 acres -- out of 1,000 acres identified by federal environmental officials -- around the Kensico Reservoir, which is in a fast-developing area north of White Plains.</p>
        <p>City officials said that property owners around the reservoir had been contacted, but that some were unwilling to part with their land, at least for the prices that the city was offering. The 1997 agreement prohibits city officials from forcing owners to sell their land, or from buying land that has a commercial or residential building on it.</p>
        <p>''They call that land available -- it's not available if the owner won't sell,'' said Mr. Ryan, who added that the city remained in discussion with those owners.</p>
        <p>But the environmentalists said that city officials had not done enough to persuade property owners there. ''The development pressure around there is intense,'' said Mr. Goldstein of the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''Kensico is a big trouble spot and one area where further attention is needed.''</p>
        <p>A State Supreme Court decision last week may greatly curtail some of that potential development, however. The court ruled that New York City could not let developers install septic systems on steeply sloping hills around the city's upstate reservoirs.</p>
        <p>The federal report also accused city officials of moving too slowly to modernize 34 sewage plants that discharge water into the Catskill reservoirs. Mr. Ryan said that those plants were in various stages of improvement. ''Some are being designed now, some have conceptual designs,'' he said. ''But they have all achieved some level of progress toward the goal.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
