<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On a Shoe Quest From Clicks to Mortar</title>
    <meta content="01SHOP$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DF153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On a Shoe Quest From Clicks to Mortar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla (Online Shopper) article on shopping for shoes on the Internet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I AM not going to waste anyone's time here with a long theoretical discussion about the relationship of new shoes to self-esteem. I think we can agree that the right pair will really improve your life, at least for a day or two. That is why I got so excited a few weeks ago in Bloomingdale's, where I saw these really adorable Tommy Hilfiger blue plaid sneakers.</p>
        <p>I believe that the industry term for this style of shoe, which resembles a bedroom slipper because it has no back, is ''mule.'' (Am I kidding? I know very well the technical term for this and every other style of shoe ever invented, and I would be happy, if called upon, to talk extemporaneously for a couple of hours about the subtle differences among mules and slides and thongs.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I AM not going to waste anyone's time here with a long theoretical discussion about the relationship of new shoes to self-esteem. I think we can agree that the right pair will really improve your life, at least for a day or two. That is why I got so excited a few weeks ago in Bloomingdale's, where I saw these really adorable Tommy Hilfiger blue plaid sneakers.</p>
        <p>I believe that the industry term for this style of shoe, which resembles a bedroom slipper because it has no back, is ''mule.'' (Am I kidding? I know very well the technical term for this and every other style of shoe ever invented, and I would be happy, if called upon, to talk extemporaneously for a couple of hours about the subtle differences among mules and slides and thongs.)</p>
        <p>Picture these plaid sneakers with denim capri pants. I did, as I caressed one -- I mean, tested the quality of its stitching. Then I tried to flag down one of the 50 million salesclerks stampeding through the shoe department as though they were all late for a Bruce Springsteen concert in another state.</p>
        <p>Years of shopping for shoes in Bloomingdale's have trained me to persevere. Sure enough, after about 10 minutes, a clerk reluctantly met my gaze. No matter what he may say later under oath, I did not, to the best of my recollection, tap him forcefully on the shoulder with the display sneaker to get his attention. I admit, however, that I may have used an ''urgent'' tone to persuade him to help me.</p>
        <p>In the end, it didn't matter: my size was sold out. In the past I would have accepted that bleak verdict, and after a period of mourning I  would have tried to forget the feelings I had for the sneakers.</p>
        <p>But I knew that somewhere in the world was a pair of those blue plaid sneakers in my size. A complicating factor was that I have long counted myself among the majority of Internet shoppers who say they are reluctant to buy clothing online because they cannot see or touch or try it on first. But in the tug-of-war between the sneakers and my long-held shopping convictions, the sneakers won.</p>
        <p>So I went right to Nordstrom.com, which claims that its collection of 20 million pairs is the ''largest selection of shoes on earth.'' (That may well be true, but if there isn't one pair among the 20 million that is the right one for you, who cares?)</p>
        <p>A search for ''Tommy Hilfiger'' yielded a red sneaker-mule hybrid that looked familiar. I clicked on it, and learned that it came in many colors, including ''multi.'' A quick call to the toll-free customer service line at Nordstrom.com confirmed that multi meant blue plaid. So I ordered the shoes, which cost an amount that my husband, if he is reading this, need not bother to look up online.</p>
        <p>Would they fit? With the sweet rush of a highly successful shopping experience coursing through my veins, I decided that it didn't matter.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, I visit online retailers that I know, retailers with real stores where I can return unwanted items. I ordered six T-shirts (on sale) from Gap.com and a pair of denim capri pants from Jcrew.com.</p>
        <p>Within days, packages started arriving. The plaid sneakers fit (we are inseparable). Ditto the capri pants. The T-shirts I returned to a Gap store three minutes away.</p>
        <p>The convenience reminded me of something I hadn't thought of since childhood: Ruby's Department Store. In the Midwestern town where I grew up, a van from Ruby's would pull into the driveway every autumn. Inside was a selection of potential ''school clothes'' for me and my three brothers. My mother, who was too smart to take four small children into a real store, kept whatever fit and sent back the rest.</p>
        <p>That level of personal service did not seem unusual back in the 1960's, a decade when dry cleaners and butchers and fruit sellers stopped weekly at the homes in our middle-class neighborhood. But in the inflationary years that followed, such deliveries became a luxury. Most vendors gravitated in one of two different directions, either providing a high level of customer service or low prices.</p>
        <p>But now the Internet makes it possible to get both. For one thing, you can quickly compare prices online.  ''But at the same time it is a customized medium,'' said Joseph B. Pine, co-author of ''The Experience Economy'' (Harvard Business School Press, 1999). ''Anything you can digitize, you can customize how a product is presented. You can even customize the product itself.''</p>
        <p>I'm not naive enough to think that I will shop for all my clothes online in the future. Kathryn Olson, executive vice president of marketing at Nordstrom.com, predicted that it would depend on my mood. Some Nordstrom customers, she said, browse first in a store, then go home and order several sizes of an item online. They try the clothes on at home at their leisure, then return unwanted apparel to the store.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you may shop online for convenience,'' Ms. Olson said. ''Other times you may want the in-store environment.''</p>
        <p>Last week, I got both. I considered a pair of pale green silk shantung ballet flats at Talbots.com. My size was sold out, but the Web site offered 10 percent off another style. Instead, I used the online chat function to pester the site -- I mean, ask nicely -- to find out if I could have the discount if I ordered the ballet flats in a slightly larger size. Yes, a customer service representative wrote back.</p>
        <p>Knowing that it would break my heart if they did not fit, I jumped up and drove five minutes to a nearby Talbots store, tried on the flats (the only color in the store was a less attractive beige) and found that the larger ones in fact fit better. So I drove home and ordered them online.</p>
        <p>The flats are back-ordered and will not be shipped before June 9, luckily. By then I may be ready to betray the sneakers.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
