<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hoofing, Stripping, Collaborating</title>
    <meta content="01SOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dance Theater of Harlem</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DC153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hoofing, Stripping, Collaborating</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews New York City Ballet and Dance Theater of Harlem performing together at New York State Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Ballet and Dance Theater of Harlem happily joined forces once again Saturday night at the New York State Theater. Members of the two troupes, conducted by Andrea Quinn, appeared in repeat performances of ''Tributary,'' collaboratively choreographed by Robert Garland and Robert La Fosse, and George Balanchine's ''Agon'' and ''Slaughter on Tenth Avenue.''</p>
        <p>''Slaughter'' was of special interest because a new pair of dancers took over the leading roles of the Strip Tease Girl and the Hoofer. When she did her barroom routine as the stripper, Kellye A. Saunders, of Dance Theater of Harlem, looked appropriately sexy. At the same time she managed to seem oddly detached and even innocent, as if indicating that her gyrations were only a show-business act.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Ballet and Dance Theater of Harlem happily joined forces once again Saturday night at the New York State Theater. Members of the two troupes, conducted by Andrea Quinn, appeared in repeat performances of ''Tributary,'' collaboratively choreographed by Robert Garland and Robert La Fosse, and George Balanchine's ''Agon'' and ''Slaughter on Tenth Avenue.''</p>
        <p>''Slaughter'' was of special interest because a new pair of dancers took over the leading roles of the Strip Tease Girl and the Hoofer. When she did her barroom routine as the stripper, Kellye A. Saunders, of Dance Theater of Harlem, looked appropriately sexy. At the same time she managed to seem oddly detached and even innocent, as if indicating that her gyrations were only a show-business act.</p>
        <p>But when she encountered the Hoofer of Philip Neal, of the City Ballet, her dancing grew passionate, for the feelings she felt for this character were genuine. Mr. Neal was impetuous, and when the Strip Tease Girl was shot by a gangster, he danced himself into a frenzy.</p>
        <p>City Ballet also offered some sensitive characterizations on Saturday afternoon, when Hugo Fiorato conducted. Yvonne Borree and Damian Woetzel managed to make stiffness appear virtuosic and oddly touching when they portrayed the doll and the toy soldier in Balanchine's ''Steadfast Tin Soldier.'' As toys, both were appropriately creaky. Yet Mr. Woetzel's courtship of Ms. Borree had tenderness as well as deadpan humor, and his leaps and turns were militarily precise.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Millepied, Tom Gold and Arch Higgins were boisterous sailors in Jerome Robbins's ''Fancy Free.'' But they took care to make their pranks never become merely oafish. And Deanna McBrearty, Jenifer Ringer and Melissa Walter played strong-willed young women who might well enjoy flirting with sailors but would not put up with nonsense from anyone.</p>
        <p>The guest performances of Robert Tewsley, of the Stuttgart Ballet, have been among this season's highlights. He was a gallant cavalier in Balanchine's ''Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto No. 2.'' The sense of ease that made him satisfying to watch was curiously absent on this occasion from the interpretations of Wendy Whelan and Michele Gifford in the two ballerina roles. Although they often moved brilliantly, they seldom suggested that creating brilliance could be a pleasure as well as a duty. Cameron Grant was the piano soloist.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
