<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Days of Sales and Roses</title>
    <meta content="01CAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CALENDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDE153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Days of Sales and Roses</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Decorative Arts at the Armory  Seventh Regiment Armory, 643 Park Avenue (66th Street); (212) 472-0590.</p>
        <p>''Sculpture, Objects and Functional Art,'' a sale of contemporary furniture and decorative works by 54 dealers, will be held today through Saturday, from 11 a.m. to 8 p.m., and on Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Admission is $12; a four-day pass is $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Decorative Arts at the Armory  Seventh Regiment Armory, 643 Park Avenue (66th Street); (212) 472-0590.</p>
        <p>''Sculpture, Objects and Functional Art,'' a sale of contemporary furniture and decorative works by 54 dealers, will be held today through Saturday, from 11 a.m. to 8 p.m., and on Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Admission is $12; a four-day pass is $20.</p>
        <p>Other organizations will offer programs to coincide with the show. The American Craft Museum will sponsor a daylong seminar on lighting for artworks, tomorrow from 8:45 a.m. to 5 p.m., at the Donnell Library Center of the New York Public Library, 20 West 53rd Street. Speakers will include the architect Richard Meier, and David Clinard, a lighting designer for the American Museum of Natural History. Tickets are $100, including lunch; students, $50. Information: (212) 956-3535.</p>
        <p>A second event, on Saturday at 10:45 a.m. in East Hampton, N.Y., will be a guided tour of LongHouse Reserve, led by the house's owner, the textile designer Jack Lenor Larsen. Participants will also visit the Pollack-Krasner House, the former home of the artists Jackson Pollack and Lee Krasner. Reservations are required: (631) 329-3568. Tickets, including lunch, $135.</p>
        <p>Roses, Center Stage  New York Botanical Garden, 200th Street and Southern Boulevard, the Bronx; (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>As part of Rose Week, guided tours will be offered in the Peggy Rockefeller Rose Garden on Wednesday, Thursday and Friday of next week at 1 p.m. Experts will also be available to answers visitors' questions this Saturday and Sunday, and again on June 10 and 11.</p>
        <p>Other events will include a talk by Clair G. Martin about his book ''100 Old Roses for the American Garden,'' on Saturday at 2:30 p.m. On Sunday at 11:30 a.m. and 1 p.m., storytelling by Regina Ress.</p>
        <p>Admission to the grounds, conservatory and children's garden is $10; students, those 65 and older, $7.50, children 2 to 12, $4.50. Grounds admission only, $3; students and the elderly, $2; children, $1; no charge all day Wednesday and on Saturday from 10 a.m. to noon.</p>
        <p>Architecture as Theory  Urban Center Galleries of the Municipal Art Society, 457 Madison Avenue (51st Street); (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>''Anyone for Architecture,'' an exhibition of film excerpts from nine annual conferences exploring ideas and theories, starts Monday and runs through July 29. Participants have included Frank O. Gehry, Peter Eisenman, Zaha Hadid, Rem Koolhaas, Bernard Tschumi and Jacques Herzog. The 10th conference, which takes place today through Saturday, is sold out. Open 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., except Sundays and Thursdays. Free.</p>
        <p>Bauhaus Influences  Jewish Museum, Fifth Avenue at 92nd Street; (212) 423-3224.</p>
        <p>A screening of ''Bauhaus in America,'' a 1995 documentary by Judith Pearlman, will be given on Sunday at 4 p.m. The film includes comments by the architects Philip Johnson, I. M. Pei and James Ingo Freed, as well as by Anni Albers, whose textiles and designs are featured in a retrospective at the museum through Aug. 20. The film will be followed by a discussion with Ms. Pearlman and the curator of the Albers exhibition, Nicholas Fox Weber. Tickets, including museum admission, $8; students and those 65 and older, $7; members, $6.</p>
        <p>CALENDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
