<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pacers Bounce Knicks Off Seesaw</title>
    <meta content="01KNIC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED8123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pacers Bounce Knicks Off Seesaw</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indiana Pacers defeat New York Knickerbockers, 88-79, to take 3-2 lead in NBA Eastern Conference championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was just under four minutes left when a cruel punctuation to Patrick Ewing's return to the Knicks was about to unfold. With his aching joints creaking like old floorboards, with his bones as heavy as lead pipes, Ewing lumbered out too slow and too late to reach Sam Perkins as he settled in to the left corner of the floor.</p>
        <p>The Pacers' braided old-timer had enough light to line up a 3-pointer that took the air out of the Knicks' plans to right their miserable second-quarter collapse with a late comeback. As Perkins's 3-pointer was swallowed by the net, the Pacers' 6-point lead grew to 9, and the Knicks' resilience finally snapped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was just under four minutes left when a cruel punctuation to Patrick Ewing's return to the Knicks was about to unfold. With his aching joints creaking like old floorboards, with his bones as heavy as lead pipes, Ewing lumbered out too slow and too late to reach Sam Perkins as he settled in to the left corner of the floor.</p>
        <p>The Pacers' braided old-timer had enough light to line up a 3-pointer that took the air out of the Knicks' plans to right their miserable second-quarter collapse with a late comeback. As Perkins's 3-pointer was swallowed by the net, the Pacers' 6-point lead grew to 9, and the Knicks' resilience finally snapped.</p>
        <p>The Pacers went on to win Game 5 of the Eastern Conference finals, 88-79, tonight at Conseco Fieldhouse. They also pushed the Knicks to the brink of elimination by taking a lead of three games to two in this four-of-seven-game series. Game 6 will be played on Friday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the Knicks' performance only fed the illusion that they are a better team without Ewing. At first glance, it will look as if Latrell Sprewell (4 for 14) and Larry Johnson (2 for 8), the heroes of Games 3 and 4 without Ewing, were stifled by their center's presence. It will look as if the perimeter-bound Allan Houston (25 points) was the only one who could function with Ewing on the floor.</p>
        <p>''Everyone will say we're 5-1 without Ewing,'' said Sprewell, citing the Knicks' record against the Pacers over the last two years when Ewing has been injured. ''That's not a fair thing to say about Patrick. We hate to see it. It is what it is. But the bottom line, he'll probably be playing in the next game, and we have to get a win with him on the floor.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks started off in the right direction. It was Ewing's dream return at first. He made his first three shots and sent the Knicks off to an 18-point lead early in the second period only to watch the team unravel during the rest of the nightmarish quarter.</p>
        <p>The Knicks scored just 8 points, went 1 for 15 during the last 10 minutes and 42 seconds of the quarter and trailed by 42-40 after the Pacers' 23-3 run. It was a horrendous stretch filled with lost loose balls and a lack of composure.</p>
        <p>''They made their run,'' said Ewing, who finished 5 for 10 from the field with 13 points and 7 rebounds during 29 minutes of playing time. ''We didn't regroup. You have to stay positive. You have to keep on believing.''</p>
        <p>Could it be that the many Knicks injuries -- Sprewell's foot, Johnson's back, Ewing's foot -- are just too much for one team to overcome?</p>
        <p>''Ask me that after the season,'' Ewing said. ''Ask me that after we win the championship.''</p>
        <p>Ewing maintained his stubborn faith even after a second quarter that rattled the Knicks and left them irreparably damaged -- if only for a night. Instead of containing the Pacers, Chris Childs and Charlie Ward let Travis Best (24 points) beat them off the dribble and Mark Jackson (11 points, 7 assists) bludgeon them in the post. Instead of closing off Reggie Miller (16 points), Houston gave him open looks and let him slip by him on the baseline. Instead of blocking out their man, the Ewing-anchored Knicks were outrebounded, 45-43.</p>
        <p>''We were outworked, out-hustled,'' Sprewell said. ''We didn't have that extra something Indiana did.''</p>
        <p>In that fateful second quarter, the Pacers' effort showed on the boards. With Marcus Camby (0 for 3, 4 rebounds) getting beaten to the boards by players like Austin Croshere, Best and Derrick McKey, the Knicks were outrebounded in the second quarter, 16-8. On one play, Best hit a 3-pointer on a third chance after two misses by Miller. The 3-point opportunities haunted the Knicks. They gave up 4 for 9 from 3-point range in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>''We played an outstanding 12 to 14 minutes,'' Van Gundy said. ''After that, we didn't play like we're capable of playing. You can characterize it by saying it was a little of good defense by them and some bad offense by us. Being up 18, and then losing that lead, you are still only behind by 2 points at the half.''</p>
        <p>But the damage had been done to the Knicks' psyche. They never recovered the lead from there. Only Houston was able to make any dents in the Pacers' ever-increasing lead. Almost each time Houston came up with a jumper, there would be a breakdown on the other end.</p>
        <p>''We didn't keep our intensity up,'' Sprewell said. ''We just started going away from all the things that worked early.''</p>
        <p>For almost a week, Ewing watched his team win two playoff games without him while listening to his critics argue how the Knicks were better when he was seated on the bench. That was enough motivation for Ewing tonight. But if he needed one more incentive to push him through the pain during Game 5, he received it from Jeff Van Gundy this morning.</p>
        <p>A blissfully unaware Rik Smits ambled into a hallway today only to find that an indignant Van Gundy had turned his honest replies about playing against Ewing into a gauntlet for the Knicks' aging and injured center. On Tuesday, Smits said he preferred to play against Ewing because he felt the 37-year-old center was easier to score on. Ewing played him from behind, while Chris Dudley and Kurt Thomas fronted him and denied him the ball.</p>
        <p>''If I was Rik Smits, personally, I would not have said that,'' Van Gundy said before his team's shoot-around at Conseco Fieldhouse. ''I've never heard anybody ask to play against Patrick. This is a first for me. Not many guys ask to play against a Hall of Famer at his position.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how Patrick will respond. I know one thing: he's not usually motivated by external forces, but I've never seen someone basically call him out.''</p>
        <p>Ewing responded by humiliating Smits in the opening quarter, and leading the Knicks to a 32-17 first-quarter lead. Then the Pacers, with Smits on the bench and Travis Best guiding their way, responded by embarrassing the Knicks right back. In one surreal second quarter, the Pacers unleashed a frenzied rebounding effort, pressured the Knicks into a four turnovers and made up an 18-point deficit. With an overpowering 23-3 run, the Pacers grabbed an amazing 42-40 halftime lead.</p>
        <p>The Knicks stayed in the game, but came up short. ''It didn't matter if Patrick was in or out of the game,'' Ward said. ''He was there when we got a big lead. It's only one game. They're up, 3-2. We can't let this zap our intensity or our emotions.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Knicks' 8 points in the second quarter set a franchise record for fewest points in a quarter. On April 19, 1983, they scored 9 points in the third quarter against Philadelphia. . . . Another ailment was added to the Knicks' mounting injury list. At the end of Game 4, LARRY JOHNSON felt discomfort in his right foot and took himself out with 4.1 seconds left. On Wednesday, the injury was diagnosed as plantar fasciitis.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
