<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Feels Like '88, Good News (Maybe) for Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y01ELEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDF123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Feels Like '88, Good News (Maybe) for Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats backing Vice Pres Al Gore recall his rival's father, then-Vice Pres George Bush, trailed in polls in May 1988, only to prevail in Nov; they and some leading scholars hold vice presidents seeking election in own right do not take their place in public's mind as party leader until convention; veterans of 1988 campaign cite key differences between two elections; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ghost of the 1988 election is a comforting spirit to many Democrats, who like to remember another sitting vice president, George Bush, who was trailing in the polls in May only to prevail, handily, in November.</p>
        <p>In the eyes of these Democrats and some leading scholars, the message of 1988 is clear. Vice presidents seeking election in their own right take time to emerge; not until the convention do they truly take their place in the public's mind as the leader of their party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ghost of the 1988 election is a comforting spirit to many Democrats, who like to remember another sitting vice president, George Bush, who was trailing in the polls in May only to prevail, handily, in November.</p>
        <p>In the eyes of these Democrats and some leading scholars, the message of 1988 is clear. Vice presidents seeking election in their own right take time to emerge; not until the convention do they truly take their place in the public's mind as the leader of their party.</p>
        <p>And when voters finally pay attention to the race, broader issues become most important: How good is the economy, how stable is the world and, essentially, do they want a third term of the party in power?</p>
        <p>If the '88 paradigm holds, Vice President Gore is stronger than he looks, and his present difficulties in the polls are much exaggerated -- particularly given the stronger economy of 2000. Citing both the extraordinary economy and President Clinton's approval ratings, Thomas E. Mann, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, a research group, said, ''It will be a first in modern American history if an incumbent administration is deposed from office under these conditions.''</p>
        <p>But veterans of the 1988 campaigns of Vice President Bush, the Republican, and Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts, the Democrat, say there are also important differences between the two elections -- from the background of the challengers to the tenor of the times.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Mann and other analysts agree that there is a complicated variable that may be masked by this administration's high approval ratings: How will the long ordeal of scandal and impeachment affect the voters' desire to stay the course?</p>
        <p>Bob Teeter, a pollster and top strategist for Vice President Bush's 1988 campaign, argued: ''Even in a good economy, Gore is vice president of an administration that people don't like very well. They like its performance and its policies, but they don't like what's been dragged before them.''</p>
        <p>For all of that, the parallels with 1988 are striking. Then, and now, the incumbent vice president was struggling to emerge from the shadow of a two-term president presiding over a peaceful, prosperous nation. Then, and now, the vice president secured his party's nomination only to lag, persistently, in the polls behind a fresh-faced governor declaring it was time for a change. Then, and now, the vice president's campaign tried methodically to redefine that governor as untested and risky.</p>
        <p>The New York Times/CBS News poll ratings for May 1988 and May 2000 are eerily similar for the candidates. Vice President Bush, 12 years ago, was viewed favorably by 33 percent, unfavorably by 35 percent. Vice President Gore, earlier this month, was viewed favorably by 34 percent, unfavorably by 36 percent. Mr. Dukakis was -- at least by this measure -- in better shape than Gov. George W. Bush is today. Thirty-eight percent viewed him favorably, 14 percent unfavorably; earlier this month, 40 percent viewed Governor Bush favorably, 28 percent unfavorably.</p>
        <p>But the Dukakis support proved exceedingly soft. In May 1988, in a moment that lives on in campaign folklore, the Bush campaign team took some of the most controversial elements of the Dukakis record in Massachusetts and tested them with a focus group of voters in Paramus, N.J. They emerged with the makings of a devastating attack.</p>
        <p>A Gore adviser said of the Bush  strategists of 1988: ''One of the critical insights they had, when they dissected Dukakis in '88, was that it was no one single issue that proved decisive. When they did those focus groups in Paramus, N.J., it was the accumulation of negatives'' that ultimately swayed the voters.</p>
        <p>But veterans of that campaign say that Governor Bush will be harder to redefine, by virtue of his family name and history. 'I don't think you can make a Wasp governor from Texas as much of a stranger to the American public as a Greek-American liberal'' from Massachusetts,  said Jack Corrigan, director of operations for the Dukakis campaign.</p>
        <p>Moreover, some campaign veterans say, the younger Bush and his strategists have clearly learned lessons from 1988, and have quickly moved to advance Mr. Bush's biography, themes and policy proposals for the fall campaign; he will not be the tabula rasa Mr. Dukakis was.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis ''didn't have a clue as to how wedge issues play out in a general election campaign,'' said Richard Bond, the national political director for the elder Bush's 1988 campaign. As a result, Mr. Bond added, Mr. Dukakis underestimated the power of issues like the Massachusetts prison program that gave furloughs to convicted murderers like Willie Horton, which was used against the Democrats to extraordinary effect. ''Who thinks that Gore will ever be able to do that to Bush Jr.?'' Mr. Bond asked.</p>
        <p>Others see it as less far-fetched. Geoffrey Garin, a Democratic pollster, said, ''When Governor Bush has come under scrutiny in the primary period, he has not stood up very well.  And its clear that the Gore campaign will do its best to take a page out of Vice President Bush's treatment of Dukakis.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the Gore campaign has been using a set of potential wedge issues against Mr. Bush, including his support for laws allowing licensed Texans to carry concealed weapons, even in church.</p>
        <p>Another line of attack in 1988 was Vice President Bush's success in presenting himself as the only credible commander in chief -- aided and abetted by Mr. Dukakis's uncomfortable outing in a tank, an image used repeatedly in Republican advertising. But during the cold war, voters were much more sensitive to a candidate's qualifications to be commander in chief, particularly governors with no foreign policy experience.  Today, such factors are much further down the voters' agenda, Mr. Teeter said -- and thus less of a hurdle for Governor Bush.</p>
        <p>Still, there are deeper similarities to 1988, some analysts say, notably what is sometimes called the shadow theory: How hard a vice president's  transition is from helpmate to leader in his own right.</p>
        <p>''Vice Presidents in the modern American political context have either won the election, like George Bush Sr., or they came amazingly close,'' like Richard M. Nixon in 1960,  , said George Sirgiovanni, professor of history at the College of St. Elizabeth in Morristown, N.J.</p>
        <p>For a vice president to prevail in November, there is an artful process of baton-passing that needs to occur, strategists say, in which vice presidents both separate from the departing president and benefit from his legacy.</p>
        <p>President Ronald Reagan was, in spring 1988, still recovering from the Iran-contra scandal. His approval rating in May was not a match for Mr. Clinton's today, which has remained above 55 percent throughout his second term. But as Mr. Reagan's final year played out, his ratings climbed, as did the general good feelings about the times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush both benefited from Mr. Reagan's aura and, at the Republican convention, memorably asked  and answered the question of who should replace the president, saying,  ''I am that man.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis, who watched his 10-point lead in May 1988 melt away, reflected: ''I think it takes a while for a vice president to come into his own. That certainly happened with Bush, and I think it's going to happen with Gore.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
