<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day After a Record Gain, the Nasdaq Declines 1.7%</title>
    <meta content="Y01STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DE123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day After a Record Gain, the Nasdaq Declines 1.7%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composite index drops 58.57 points, or 1.7 percent, to 3,400.91; Dow Jones industrial average edges down 4.80 points, to 10,522.33, while Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index eases 1.85 points, or 0.13 percent, to 1,420.60; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After adding modestly to Tuesday's record percentage gain, Nasdaq stock prices fell in the final hour yesterday to finish with a 1.7 percent loss as investors digested further evidence of a slowing economy and girded themselves for a crucial employment report tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index ended 58.57 points lower at 3,400.91. Other major gauges traded in a relatively narrow range and ended nearly unchanged. The blue-chip Dow Jones industrial average edged down 4.80 points, to 10,522.33, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index eased 1.85 points, or 0.13 percent, to 1,420.60.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After adding modestly to Tuesday's record percentage gain, Nasdaq stock prices fell in the final hour yesterday to finish with a 1.7 percent loss as investors digested further evidence of a slowing economy and girded themselves for a crucial employment report tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index ended 58.57 points lower at 3,400.91. Other major gauges traded in a relatively narrow range and ended nearly unchanged. The blue-chip Dow Jones industrial average edged down 4.80 points, to 10,522.33, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index eased 1.85 points, or 0.13 percent, to 1,420.60.</p>
        <p>''The positive note is that we did not give back a lot'' of the post-holiday rally, said Michael Strauss, a managing director of Commonfund, an investment pool for college endowments. On the other hand, he added, the market was pleased with reports of lower home sales and less industrial inflation in the Midwest, ''but couldn't do anything with it.''</p>
        <p>Stock prices mostly moved sideways -- and with little obvious pattern -- except that investors seemed to welcome the opportunity to lighten positions in high-technology concerns, while bidding up shares of household names, like Wal-Mart Stores, which leaped 5, to 58, the biggest positive contributor to the Dow and the S.&amp; P. 500.</p>
        <p>''If the economy is going to downshift to a lower gear, you don't want to own a whole load of technology stocks,'' said Ned Riley Jr., chief strategist at State Street Global Advisors. Mr. Riley examined trading blocks of at least 5,000 shares, and calculated that retail investors accounted for 70 percent of the activity in the top 10 Nasdaq stocks yesterday, even though they held only 57 percent of the shares.</p>
        <p>Utilities and brokerage firms were among yesterday's leaders. Timothy M. Stevenson, a senior portfolio manager at the First Capital Group, said the performance of brokerage firms was ''a vote of confidence'' in the market outlook. Merrill Lynch gained 4 1/4, to 98 7/8, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter 4 3/8, to 71 3/8, and Dain Rauscher 2 5/8, to 59 5/8.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stevenson was also upbeat about market breadth, with 1,719 issues advancing on the New York Stock Exchange compared with 1,287 that declined. Among the S.&amp; P. 500, however, losers outnumbered winners by 268 to 213, the biggest drags on the index being Cisco Systems, down 2 15/16, to 56 15/16, and Qualcomm, down 10, to 66 3/8. Hewlett-Packard, which skidded 4 3/8, to 120 1/8, was the biggest drag on the Dow.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasury Prices Rally</p>
        <p>By Reuters</p>
        <p>Treasury bond prices rallied yesterday after a series of weaker-than-expected economic reports raised hopes that the Federal Reserve would not have to increase interest rates as aggressively as once feared.</p>
        <p>The government's report that sales of new homes fell 5.8 percent in April offered evidence that six Fed interest rate increases since June were starting to crimp the housing market.</p>
        <p>The Conference Board reported, meanwhile, that the index of leading indicators slipped 0.1 percent in April, instead of rising 0.1 percent, as forecast.</p>
        <p>The market was also pleased by a Chicago Purchasing Managers report that manufacturing growth in the Chicago area slowed in April while the group's ''prices paid'' index dropped to 64.4, nearly 10 points below its March high.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond rose 16/32, to 103 13/32. The bond's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 6 percent from 6.09 percent.</p>
        <p>The price of the 10-year note rose 24/32, to 101 22/32. The yield fell to 6.26 percent from 6.37 percent.</p>
        <p>Results of yesterday's Treasury auction of one-year bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures</p>
        <p>Price: 93.933  High Rate: 6.00%  Coupon Yield: 6.37%  Low Rate: 5.85%  Median Rate: 5.98%  Total applied for: $30,672,383  Accepted: $13,617,655  Noncompetitive: $672,569</p>
        <p>The one-year bills mature May 31, 2001.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
