<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ING and Aetna Renew Talks; Partial Sale Is Considered</title>
    <meta content="Y01INSU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aetna Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ing Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DE123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ING and Aetna Renew Talks; Partial Sale Is Considered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aetna Inc and ING Group are discussing new offer from ING to buy Aetna's financial and international divisions; Aetna declines to discuss price under negotiation, but some Wall Street traders speculate on offer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aetna Inc. and the ING Group, the Dutch financial services company, said yesterday that they were discussing a new offer from ING to buy Aetna's financial and international divisions. Aetna declined to discuss the price under negotiation, but some Wall Street traders estimated it could be as high as $9 billion, only slightly less than the roughly $10 billion ING had offered for all of Aetna earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Aetna shares rose $5 at midday after CNBC reported the ING offer, and closed up $4.0625 at $66.75 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aetna Inc. and the ING Group, the Dutch financial services company, said yesterday that they were discussing a new offer from ING to buy Aetna's financial and international divisions. Aetna declined to discuss the price under negotiation, but some Wall Street traders estimated it could be as high as $9 billion, only slightly less than the roughly $10 billion ING had offered for all of Aetna earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Aetna shares rose $5 at midday after CNBC reported the ING offer, and closed up $4.0625 at $66.75 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>William H. Donaldson, chief executive of Aetna, said his company was ''working with ING on their new proposal concerning our financial services and international businesses.'' He added that Aetna was still committed to improving its Aetna U.S. Healthcare unit, the nation's largest health insurer. ING said in a statement that Aetna's ''domestic U.S. health care operations are not part of these negotiations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Donaldson said there were ''no assurances'' that the ING deal would close or what the terms would be.</p>
        <p>And he said Aetna was still ready to split the company into two separate health and ''wealth'' divisions and spin them to shareholders as independent publicly traded companies as it vowed to do when it rejected ING's $9.9 billion takeover offer in March.</p>
        <p>Wall Street traders welcomed word of the talks, which they said cleared the way for a bidding war over Aetna's attractive financial services business.</p>
        <p>''This opens up the situation,'' said Herbert Denton, president of Providence Capital Inc., which has Aetna holdings. ''Aetna has abandoned its split-up plan, and it is basically in play.''</p>
        <p>''It is very difficult to put the genie back in the bottle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Securities analysts said $9 billion would be a high-end price.</p>
        <p>It would value Aetna's financial, pensions and overseas units at 20 times this year's projected earnings of about $470 million, said Kenneth S. Abramowitz, a Sanford C. Bernstein analyst. He said financial services companies had typically sold for 15 times earnings.</p>
        <p>But ING has made no secret of its ambition to become one of the biggest players in the North American insurance market. ING said yesterday that the talks with Aetna were consistent with its goal of joining the top 10 companies in overall insurance in the United States as well as expanding significantly in Latin America and Asia.</p>
        <p>ING recently agreed to pay $5.1 billion for ReliaStar, a Midwestern insurer, and assumed $1 billion of ReliaStar debt.</p>
        <p>Big European insurance companies are eager to buy American insurance companies because the growth potential for pensions and annuities is much stronger than in Europe, said Arun Kumar, a bond analyst at Chase Securities. ''There is more money being spent on retirement in the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Other European companies that have been prospecting for acquisitions in the United States include Aegon, another Netherlands-based insurer, AXA of France and Allianz of Germany.</p>
        <p>But analysts said a sale to ING could also create problems for Aetna shareholders. Although Aetna could spin off the financial services and health units to shareholders without any tax implications, a sale to ING would cause a big capital gains tax liability for investors. Todd Richter, a Banc of America Securities analyst, said the tax could be as high as $2 billion to $3 billion.</p>
        <p>''We need to know how they will deal with the tax liability,'' Mr. Richter said. Another ''pivotal question,'' he said, ''is the value of the health care business on a stand-alone basis.''</p>
        <p>Investors have been clamoring for asset sales that would result in big stock buybacks that would bolster Aetna's share price. But Mr. Abramowitz pointed out that Aetna also had $5 billion of debt. At least some of that would probably have to be paid off as part of a sale.</p>
        <p>Lee Cooperman, head of Omega Advisers, a hedge fund manager, said Aetna would rather split up and avoid the tax liability, ''but perhaps they have been offered a price they couldn't refuse; I'm happy they are open-minded and flexible.''</p>
        <p>Aetna shares have bounced back to the mid-$60's over the last two weeks, after sliding into the high $50's when Aetna's board rejected the earlier offer from ING on March 12. ING then had a plan to resell the big health unit to Wellpoint Health Networks, based in California. Wellpoint said it knew nothing about ING's latest overture to Aetna.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
