<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton Pledges a Race Based on 'Issues, Not Insults'</title>
    <meta content="01HILL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D8123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton Pledges a Race Based on 'Issues, Not Insults'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton criticizes her Republican opponent for Senate Representative Rick A Lazio for operating what she says is campaign based on insults; asserts that her positions better reflect views of mainstream New Yorkers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With her Republican opponent now confirmed, Hillary Rodham Clinton took an aggressively combative tone yesterday, criticizing Representative Rick A. Lazio for operating what she said was a campaign based on insults and asserting that her positions better reflected the views of mainstream New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''While my opponent tells you where he's from, I'm going to tell you what I'm for,'' Mrs. Clinton, the Democratic candidate for the United States Senate, told about 300 cheering supporters at a noon rally at the Lower Manhattan headquarters of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. ''This is not about who's from New York. This is about who will fight the right fights for all New Yorkers.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With her Republican opponent now confirmed, Hillary Rodham Clinton took an aggressively combative tone yesterday, criticizing Representative Rick A. Lazio for operating what she said was a campaign based on insults and asserting that her positions better reflected the views of mainstream New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''While my opponent tells you where he's from, I'm going to tell you what I'm for,'' Mrs. Clinton, the Democratic candidate for the United States Senate, told about 300 cheering supporters at a noon rally at the Lower Manhattan headquarters of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. ''This is not about who's from New York. This is about who will fight the right fights for all New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>The rally was held one day after the Republican Party officially nominated Mr. Lazio at its convention in Buffalo, where several speakers harshly criticized Mrs. Clinton's decision to move to New York and to run for the Senate seat being vacated by Daniel Patrick Moynihan.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Republicans extolled Mr. Lazio as a born-and-bred product of the state and a candidate with moderate positions on issues. Indeed, the Republican candidate himself suggested in his acceptance speech that Mrs. Clinton was at a disadvantage in the race because she was not a native New Yorker.</p>
        <p>''My opponent may be new,'' Mrs. Clinton told those at yesterday's rally. ''But the issues that New Yorkers care about remain the same. And the issues I care about remain the same. I pledge to run a campaign based on issues, not insults, and about the real differences between us.</p>
        <p>''For 30 years, I have fought for children and families, for women and workers,'' Mrs. Clinton told the audience of union workers and political activists. ''And in this campaign, I've stood up for New Yorkers who needed a voice. I'm not afraid of the tough fights.''</p>
        <p>She then discussed a number of the issues that have become common themes in her campaign speeches: her support for mandatory handgun registration and for targeted tax cuts, like tax deductions for college tuition, and the need to modernize New York's school buildings.</p>
        <p>As she has since Mr. Lazio emerged as the likely Republican candidate in place of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, Mrs. Clinton highlighted her support of handgun registration, a position on which she differs with Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''Every teenager who wants to drive a car has to get a license and register their car,'' she said. ''I think it's time we license every handgun owner and register every new handgun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's aides said that the congressman favors many forms of gun control, but not registration.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's aides said that, with Mr. Lazio now nominated, the first lady would become far more assertive in stressing the differences between the two candidates on a host of issues. And her campaign has sought to portray the Republican candidate as having more conservative positions and a more negative campaign style.</p>
        <p>Following the rally, Mrs. Clinton flew to Buffalo, the city where Mr. Lazio was nominated just 24 hours earlier, to visit a school and to emphasize her support for a bill in Congress to defray the interest on school construction bonds.</p>
        <p>It was a trip, her aides suggested, that was designed both to highlight her position on school modernization and to steal some of the limelight that Mr. Lazio might have gained in that region.</p>
        <p>''I'm not taking anything in this election for granted,'' Mrs. Clinton said yesterday in Buffalo, when asked about her return to the city.  ''That means you'll be seeing a lot of me here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
