<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corporate-News Proposal Criticized by Dow Jones</title>
    <meta content="Y01SCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bloomberg Lp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levitt, Arthur Jr (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1DE123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corporate-News Proposal Criticized by Dow Jones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Co, owner of The Wall Street Journal, Barron's and Dow Jones Newswires, complains to Securities and Exchange Commission that proposed rule intended to prevent companies from giving information to hand-picked group of investors would result in 'less informative, less objective and less timely reporting'; SEC proposed rule in December, after issue had been publicly championed for months by commission's chairman Arthur Levitt; Journal's opposition highlights increasing scrutiny given to how, and to whom, companies provide information in era when new technologies and hair-trigger markets have made information more valuable and sensitive commodity; Bloomberg News, financial service that is competitor of Dow Jones, questions Dow Jones's criticism (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company has complained to the Securities and Exchange Commission that a proposed rule intended to prevent companies from giving information to a hand-picked group of investors would result in ''less informative, less objective and less timely reporting.''</p>
        <p>Unless the proposal is amended, wrote Peter G. Skinner, executive vice president and general counsel of the company that owns The Wall Street Journal, Barron's and Dow Jones Newswires, it could increase timidity among corporate executives afraid of running afoul of the rule, and end up ''choking the flow'' of information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company has complained to the Securities and Exchange Commission that a proposed rule intended to prevent companies from giving information to a hand-picked group of investors would result in ''less informative, less objective and less timely reporting.''</p>
        <p>Unless the proposal is amended, wrote Peter G. Skinner, executive vice president and general counsel of the company that owns The Wall Street Journal, Barron's and Dow Jones Newswires, it could increase timidity among corporate executives afraid of running afoul of the rule, and end up ''choking the flow'' of information.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. proposed the rule in December, after the issue had been publicly championed for months by the commission's chairman, Arthur Levitt. In a speech in October, Mr. Levitt said: ''The behind-the-scenes feeding of material nonpublic information from companies to analysts is a stain on our markets. In a time when instantaneous and free-flowing information is the norm, these sort of whispers are an insult to fair and public disclosure.''</p>
        <p>The Journal's opposition highlights the increasing scrutiny given to how, and to whom, companies provide information in an era when new technologies and hair-trigger markets have made information a more valuable and sensitive commodity.</p>
        <p>The view that the proposed rule could have the unintended consequence of restricting the flow of financial information, however, is hardly universal. While critical comments were filed by Dow Jones and some members of the Society of American Business Editors and Writers, other news organizations largely remained silent.</p>
        <p>Bloomberg News, a financial service that is a competitor of Dow Jones, published a news report yesterday highlighting its rival's decision to criticize the proposed rule. Dow Jones, Bloomberg reported, was arguing that the proposal ''could dry up scoops at its flagship Wall Street Journal newspaper.''</p>
        <p>Matt Winkler, Bloomberg's editor in chief, said in an interview yesterday: ''There isn't a great story that has come from a handout. Ever.'' He added: ''The best stories come from good old-fashioned enterprise. I say that as a former Wall Street Journal reporter. I don't understand what the fuss is about.''</p>
        <p>Dow Jones's critical comments, filed as the designated period for reaction was ending last month, sought to make the proposed rule inapplicable to information released ''to bona fide news organizations.''</p>
        <p>Financial journalists are not the only group split on the proposal, which is in general disfavor with most analysts but appears quite popular among small investors, whose numbers have expanded exponentially in recent years.</p>
        <p>Daniel J. Kramer, a partner at the law firm of Schulte Roth &amp; Zabel, says he believes that the key question in analyzing the new rules is ''whether they will result in an information brownout, and result in less information being available to the public rather than more.''</p>
        <p>The high profile given to the practice of selective disclosure, however, has had some impact. A 1998 study by the National Investors Relations Institute, cited by Mr. Kramer, found that while the majority of the 163 companies surveyed preferred to discuss new information with analysts on conference calls, 29 percent invited individual shareholders, and 14 percent invited the media.</p>
        <p>Three months ago, a report from the investor relations' group showed that 82 percent of companies let individual investors in on their conference calls and 74 percent let journalists participate.</p>
        <p>First Amendment lawyers were divided on the likelihood that the rule would crimp journalists' ability to report corporate developments. James C. Goodale, a lawyer with the New York firm of Debevoise &amp; Plimpton, said, ''the government already has rules'' forbidding its employees to release classified information, ''but those rules don't apply to the press and don't stop the press from getting classified information.''</p>
        <p>''Therefore, these rules aren't going to keep the press from getting insider information,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Bruce W. Sanford, a lawyer with the Washington offices of Baker &amp; Hostetler, said, ''My concern is that the rules and all the baggage that goes with the rules would tend to have the effect of corporate executives having fewer meetings with investors and everyone else, including the news media.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
