<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Counting Life Without Parole as a Victory</title>
    <meta content="01PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Law</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Kevin M. Doyle's</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Doyle, Kevin M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0DF123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Counting Life Without Parole as a Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of Kevin M Doyle, director of New York State's Capital Defender Office; he discusses responsibility for assuring that any defendant who faces execution gets qualified lawyer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Kevin M. Doyle'sKevin M. Doyle's radio alarm clock went off last Thursday, he woke up hearing about the shooting of the Wendy's workers. Like so many others, his first thought was: ''Sweet Jesus! This is a horrible loss of life!''</p>
        <p>Then, his thoughts diverged from ours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Kevin M. Doyle'sKevin M. Doyle's radio alarm clock went off last Thursday, he woke up hearing about the shooting of the Wendy's workers. Like so many others, his first thought was: ''Sweet Jesus! This is a horrible loss of life!''</p>
        <p>Then, his thoughts diverged from ours.</p>
        <p>Premeditated murder plus robbery equals potential death penalty case, his thoughts continued. Ipso uh-oh: soon, a new client.</p>
        <p>As New York State's capital defender, responsible for assuring that any defendant who might face execution gets a qualified lawyer, Mr. Doyle, the son of a police officer, goes to work thinking about how to do right by suspects reviled by the public, politicians and victims' families, whose crimes he finds as repugnant as the death penalty itself.</p>
        <p>To spend an afternoon with Mr. Doyle, 44, at his memorabilia-filled Manhattan office -- a gallon of stage blood, anyone? Good for recreating  spatter patterns at murder scenes and for pranks played by staffers' children -- is to sojourn in the sovereign state of counterintuition, where deathspeak and Doyle-isms are the lingua franca, where ''life without parole'' is music to the ears.</p>
        <p>''Of course the heinousness of a crime strikes me,'' says Mr. Doyle, a long-legged, antsy fellow with a punchy Bronx patois. ''I call it 'the garnish' -- an element of the case that is food for the tabloids. It has no legal weight, but enough inflammatory weight to push a district attorney to go death on us.''</p>
        <p>''Do you know what my biggest frustration is?'' says Mr. Doyle, whose office represents John B. Taylor, charged with murdering the five Wendy's employees. ''The tremendous self-destructiveness of our clients who refuse to plea. I tell lawyers, if you can bring yourself to care about the client or in some way love them, you can overcome that cowboy instinct of theirs which says, 'O.K., walk me or fry me!' '' -- acquittal or an execution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doyle and his 25 trial and appellate lawyers have handled most of the 41 cases in which prosecutors have sought the death penalty since New York's revised first-degree murder law took effect on Sept. 1, 1995. His Capital Defender Office is regarded as among the best in the country: there are only five men on the state's death row, and just one was represented by the C.D.O.</p>
        <p>''C'mon,'' moans Mr. Doyle, who prevented the imposition of the death sentence in 11 trials during his teeth-cutting years in Alabama. ''Don't make it sound like I'm Babe Ruth! Just say we use copious amounts of vinegar and honey to get our pleas for life without parole. I've been lucky, and I've also been willing to schmooze and to grovel.''</p>
        <p>FOR though Mr. Doyle certainly has his high-octane side -- he has called decisions by New York judges ''unconscionable'' and ''dead wrong''; and his office has been accused of zealotry by a Queens prosecutor -- he can also be fastidiously cautious in his public remarks, mindful that his office and, by extension, his clients, live and die at the behest of legislators and elected officials.</p>
        <p>At two-minute intervals, he says that although he opposes the death penalty, the mission of the office is simply to represent clients. And despite his high-jinks nature, Mr. Doyle wears a tie and urges staff members to dress conservatively. ''Like the Justice Department,'' he says with a smirk, ''only we want to be better lawyers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doyle got his calling while doing pro bono death penalty work as an associate at a Wall Street firm. Representing clients who were poor and almost always black or Hispanic was the right fit for a lawyer whose parents gave him the middle name Martin after Martin de Porres, a biracial Peruvian saint who ministered to the poor; he in turn named a son Aedan Martin King Doyle, after his boyhood hero.</p>
        <p>''That's right,'' read the birth announcement from Mr. Doyle and Mary Sullivan, his wife, a nurse practitioner. ''We're skipping the Luther because we're papist and we're loyal.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Doyle is deeply engaged with his Roman Catholicism: he attends Mass at least once a week, opposes the death penalty, abortion and the ban on the ordination of women, and will debate church history with elan.</p>
        <p>''If I believed death was truly the end of the line, the stakes in death penalty work would be too much to handle,'' he says. ''My faith brought me to the work, but in a good way, the work has rubbed my nose in my religious faith.''</p>
        <p>Law and order and religious order vied with each other during Mr. Doyle's childhood. ''My father used to think the death penalty should be abolished for everyone except killers of police officers,'' he says. ''He thought that was how society should acknowledge the value of cops.''</p>
        <p>Thus Mr. Doyle comes to a border crossing at the sovereign state of counterintuition: it's March 17, 1996, and the new capital defender has brought his children to their first St. Patrick's Day parade since returning from Alabama. ''I'm a cop's son, awash in bagpipe music,'' recounts Mr. Doyle. ''It's a big deal.''</p>
        <p>The air is full of pride and sorrow. Kevin Gillespie, a Bronx police officer, had been shot to death, a capital offense. There is Mr. Doyle, one hand waving at the marchers, cell phone in the other, arranging for the suspect to get a good lawyer.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
