<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ESPN Stumbles in Knight Interview</title>
    <meta content="01SAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Espn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DC123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ESPN Stumbles in Knight Interview</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV Sports column discusses ESPN's interview with Indiana basketball coach Bob Knight; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you were to interview Richard Nixon about his vice presidential years, surely you would watch his Checkers speech. If you were to chat with President Clinton about his impeachment, surely you would watch his taped deposition.</p>
        <p>And if you were chosen to interview Indiana Coach Bob Knight about his anger management problems, you would obviously watch the 1997 tape of him applying a one-handed choke hold to the throat of Neil Reed, a former player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you were to interview Richard Nixon about his vice presidential years, surely you would watch his Checkers speech. If you were to chat with President Clinton about his impeachment, surely you would watch his taped deposition.</p>
        <p>And if you were chosen to interview Indiana Coach Bob Knight about his anger management problems, you would obviously watch the 1997 tape of him applying a one-handed choke hold to the throat of Neil Reed, a former player.</p>
        <p>But Roy Firestone of ESPN accepted the job of interviewing Knight by avoiding the tape. How any sports journalist could have avoided seeing the choking tape since CNN/SI first showed it on April 13, even by accident, is mystifying.</p>
        <p>But to purposely not watch it during preparation is reckless.</p>
        <p>''That was a surprise,'' said Steve Anderson, an ESPN executive vice president. ''Roy should have watched the tape.''</p>
        <p>Firestone said he wanted to view the tape with fresh eyes with Knight during the on-campus interview. ''It was my mistake as a journalist, one that I shouldn't have made,'' Firestone said yesterday. ''But I was so sure we would show it on the air.''</p>
        <p>By not previewing the tape, Firestone risked letting Knight commandeer the agenda.</p>
        <p>Firestone's risk turned to embarrassment minutes before the 6:30 p.m. Eastern air time. Firestone was rehearsing how he would show the tape and ask Knight questions when Christopher Simpson, an Indiana University spokesman, saw a frozen frame of the tape on an ESPN monitor. ''I asked Roy if he was going to use it and he said, 'Yes, we want his reaction,' '' Simpson said. ''I told him that he had never suggested he would use it. It seemed unfair to put it in the coach's face without advance warning.''</p>
        <p>At no time since Simpson called ESPN to set up the interview last Saturday did the issue of using the tape arise. How could anyone not assume ESPN would, de rigueur, show Knight the tape?</p>
        <p>''I just assumed it was fair game,'' Firestone said.</p>
        <p>''But the clock was ticking, and we didn't know if Knight would walk off,'' said Norby Williamson, the program's producer.</p>
        <p>Firestone said, ''When Simpson saw the tape, he freaked out and realized he had to protect Knight.''</p>
        <p>Simpson's insistence persuaded ESPN to purge the tape.</p>
        <p>''This was my call, not the coach's,'' Simpson said.</p>
        <p>Having surrendered use of the tape, ESPN meekly surrendered some of its credibility. ESPN wanted to prove it had bagged Knight and didn't want to risk losing him. Had Knight stalked off, leaving considerable dead air, he would have confirmed his lack of self-control and jump-started the lottery he snidely proposed to raise money when he erupted. Knowing his ability to manage his anger is being analyzed as if he were truly important, Knight would most likely have sat and ignored the tape.</p>
        <p>Firestone's candor then did him in. Before the program, he told Knight he had not seen the tape. When he raised the Reed incident early in the show, Firestone asked Knight if he had watched the tape. Knight, now armed, shot back by asking if Firestone had.</p>
        <p>No, Firestone said, he had not. By not seeing any more than freeze frames of the tape, Firestone had compromised himself on the issue.  He couldn't counter Knight's responses that Reed's accusations were more serious than the tape proved and that the two Indiana trustees who investigated Knight's misbehavior did not think he looked mad when he choked Reed.</p>
        <p>''I could have been a little more direct if I'd seen the tape,'' Firestone said. ''I was dying inside that I couldn't get the tape on.'' Firestone worries that the value of the hour -- done with Digger Phelps, a friend of Knight's -- will be damaged by the choking tape flap. Firestone asked some tough questions -- and did not lack for some good follow-ups. But one can only wonder how much better the program would have been had Firestone done all his homework and ESPN had stood up to the university.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
