<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Grit of Daily Life Meets Spiritual Epiphany</title>
    <meta content="01MASL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banks, Russell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Angel on the Roof, The: The Stories of Russell Banks (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDA153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Grit of Daily Life Meets Spiritual Epiphany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews The Angel on the Roof: The Stories of Russell Banks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ANGEL ON THE ROOF  The Stories of Russell Banks  By Russell Banks  506 pages. HarperCollins. $27.50.</p>
        <p>''You! You're not mad at me like that, are you?'' asks a character in Russell Banks's story ''Firewood.''  ''For leaving your mother and all?'' Only a few pages later, in the next of the 31 stories in this beautifully lucid, frequently wrenching collection, another father is asking his disaffected child essentially the same thing. ''Was I wrong, to divorce your mother? To leave you?'' a man asks in ''Quality Time,'' only to be spurned by an adult daughter not interested in giving him a second chance. ''Now you've lost us both,'' she says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ANGEL ON THE ROOF  The Stories of Russell Banks  By Russell Banks  506 pages. HarperCollins. $27.50.</p>
        <p>''You! You're not mad at me like that, are you?'' asks a character in Russell Banks's story ''Firewood.''  ''For leaving your mother and all?'' Only a few pages later, in the next of the 31 stories in this beautifully lucid, frequently wrenching collection, another father is asking his disaffected child essentially the same thing. ''Was I wrong, to divorce your mother? To leave you?'' a man asks in ''Quality Time,'' only to be spurned by an adult daughter not interested in giving him a second chance. ''Now you've lost us both,'' she says.</p>
        <p>At his shattering best -- that is, in stories less easily schematic than ''Quality Time'' turns out to be -- Mr. Banks offers answers that are tough, honest and inevitable without being simple. He returns again and again to the caldron of domestic life, in which hard drinking, deep-seated strife and often the prospect of a bleak New Hampshire winter make the walls close in. ''In those days, women and me not finding out about them are what connected everything in that man's life,'' one woman tells her son about his father in ''Assisted Living.'' In ''Success Story,'' the narrator observes that ''in some ways, my family was a civic reclamation project -- the bright and pretty children and pathetic wife of a brute who, nearly a decade ago, had disappeared into the northern woods with a woman from the post office, never to be heard from again.''</p>
        <p>In ''Firewood,'' Mr. Banks describes a man who has had his third drink of the day by 8 a.m. as part of a familiar pattern (''and before he knows how it happens, it has happened again, and there he is, being pulled off some guy and hustled out the door or picked up off the floor and aimed by strangers toward his car'') and winds up alone in the snow, finding it easier to stack wood than to make sense of his life. In ''Plains of Abraham,'' as in many of the stories here, a character registers real regret about the wreckage in his past.  ''Family life had slipped from his grasp without his having noticed, as if, closing his eyes to drink from a spring, he'd lost a handful of clear water and was unable afterwards to imagine a way to regain it. The spring must have dried up. A man can't blame his hands, can he?''</p>
        <p>As this book reveals, with stories dating back to his 1975 ''Searching for Survivors'' and nine previously uncollected stores from Esquire, Ploughshares and other sources, the contrasts here between quotidian reality and spiritual epiphany have been as central to Mr. Banks's short fiction as they have to his novels. Anyone who first became familiar with his work through the transcendent film adaptations of ''The Sweet Hereafter'' and especially ''Affliction,'' which is closer in eloquent, unflinching tone to the author's writing, will find nearly as much to discover here as in the best of his longer fiction (those novels and the magnificent ''Continental Drift'').</p>
        <p>What elevates these stories far above their tacitly heartbreaking events are the vast reserves of compassion and wisdom that Mr. Banks brings to framing tragedy. One of the most eloquent stories in the book is ''The Child Screams and Looks Back at You,'' in which a woman witnesses the death of her son.</p>
        <p>But ''The Angel on the Roof'' so knowingly and movingly explores this kind of intimacy that its efforts to reveal a larger range cast an unflattering light on some of its more marginal material. Although this book collects work from four previously published short story collections, almost all of the best entries come from the 1981 ''Trailerpark,'' which features interwoven accounts of the Granite State Trailerpark and its community of residents. Shuffling the order of these pieces (so that ''The Fisherman'' is the first to appear here, though it provided an ending to ''Trailerpark'' and is best read after all its characters are already familiar) is perhaps meant to show them off in a new perspective. But they still stand out starkly amid more awkward conceits, like the stories ''The Caul'' and ''Indisposed,'' narrated respectively by Edgar Allan Poe and Jane Hogarth, wife of the renowned portrait painter. Within these stories are the seeds of ''Cloudsplitter,'' the voluminous historical novel in which Mr. Banks reconstructed John Brown's raid on Harper's Ferry. But far more successful and less manipulative are the more direct, down-to-earth accounts of ordinary lives as glimpsed by an extraordinarily wise observer.</p>
        <p>As a book that is not to be missed but is best read selectively, ''The Angel on the Roof'' is especially impressive for stories like ''The Guinea Pig Lady,'' a trailer park novella that builds to a harrowing finale for its eccentric heroine, and ''Queen for a Day,'' a stunning account of how a young boy tries helping his mother to redefine their family. ''Lobster Night,'' previously uncollected, begins its first paragraph this way:  ''Stacy didn't mean to tell Noonan that when she was 17 she was struck by lightning.'' And its second paragraph starts this way: ''The night Stacy told Noonan about the lightning was also the night she shot and killed him.'' Among Mr. Banks's extraordinary skills, the technical prowess and storytelling grace that hook a reader so seemingly easily should not be overlooked.</p>
        <p>The story that best encapsulates Mr. Banks's cyclical sense of domestic strife is ''The Visit,'' in which a man returns to the scene and the memories of his father's bullying. ''It's as if violence were a gift worth any price. Beyond the light and the heat, it's a gift that engenders gorgeous dreams of retribution, and they last for tens of generations of fathers and children, husbands and wives -- it's a gift that shapes and drives fantasies of becoming huge as a glacier and hard as iron, fast as light, and sudden, like a volcano.'' Or of being able to articulate and confront it as mightily as this.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
