<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Calvin Klein Battles Maker of Its Jeans</title>
    <meta content="Y01PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jeans (Apparel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Underwear</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin, Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warnaco Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wachner, Linda J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E7DD123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Calvin Klein Battles Maker of Its Jeans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Calvin Klein Inc files suit to break licensing pact with Warnaco Group Inc, which makes its underwear and jeans brands, in what many industry insiders say is act of vegeance against Warnaco chief executive Linda J Wachner; suit seeks to terminate Warnaco's long-term license to make Calvin Klein jeans on ground that company has breached its fiduciary duty by 'diluting' quality of Klein's image; among specific infractions cited is selling new products through unauthorized mass marketers; whatever the merits of suit, timing could not be more devastating to Wachner, who is already target of irate Warnaco shareholders; photos (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calvin Klein Inc. has filed suit to break a licensing pact with the Warnaco Group Inc., which makes its underwear and jeans brands, in what many industry insiders consider an act of vengeance against the flint-tough chief executive of Warnaco, Linda J. Wachner.</p>
        <p>Last October, Mr. Klein and his long-time partner Barry Schwartz engaged the investment firm of Lazard Freres to find a buyer for their private company. Tommy Hilfiger Inc., Liz Claiborne and Warnaco were among the companies that expressed interest. But none were willing to bite at Mr. Klein's asking price, said to be $1 billion. Part of the problem was that the brand was already highly exposed -- the Klein name appears on everything from sunglasses to bed linens -- and therefore did not offer prospective buyers an obvious path for dynamic future growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Calvin Klein Inc. has filed suit to break a licensing pact with the Warnaco Group Inc., which makes its underwear and jeans brands, in what many industry insiders consider an act of vengeance against the flint-tough chief executive of Warnaco, Linda J. Wachner.</p>
        <p>Last October, Mr. Klein and his long-time partner Barry Schwartz engaged the investment firm of Lazard Freres to find a buyer for their private company. Tommy Hilfiger Inc., Liz Claiborne and Warnaco were among the companies that expressed interest. But none were willing to bite at Mr. Klein's asking price, said to be $1 billion. Part of the problem was that the brand was already highly exposed -- the Klein name appears on everything from sunglasses to bed linens -- and therefore did not offer prospective buyers an obvious path for dynamic future growth.</p>
        <p>But Klein's long-term licensing deal with Warnaco complicated the picture as well. Warnaco accounted for about $1 billion of the $2.5 billion in Calvin Klein products sold wholesale in 1999, and Ms. Wachner has pressed for more control of design and distribution. While Mr. Klein insists that he could have sold the company if he wanted to and that the new lawsuit is unrelated, he says that Ms. Wachner scared off prospective partners. ''People have told us that they were hesitant to have a relationship with Linda Wachner,'' he said in an interview last night.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner said Mr. Klein's lawsuit, filed in United States District Court for the Southern District of New York on Tuesday, was a complete surprise and that she first learned of it that night by phone while in a design meeting at Calvin Klein Inc. ''One must wonder why having tried and failed to sell their business that they have adopted this tack now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>David Wolfe, creative director of the Doneger Group, a retail consulting firm, and one of the many people in New York's Garment District enjoying the fight, put it bluntly: ''This is about Calvin's failure to cut a deal. He is kicking her while she is on the defensive. He grew up in the Bronx. He is a streetwise kid. It will really be fascinating to watch it play out.''</p>
        <p>The lawsuit seeks to terminate Warnaco's long-term license to make Calvin Klein jeans on the ground that the company has breached its fiduciary duty by ''diluting'' the quality of Klein's image. Among the specific infractions cited was selling new products through unauthorized mass-marketers like Costco and B. J.'s Wholesale Club and affixing the Klein name to products made by other designers or products designed by Klein but altered without his consent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein and Mr. Schwartz said  the suit was an instrument of last resort, after years of complaints through letters, personal meetings and lawyers. Mr. Schwartz said the issue reached a turning point in March when Warnaco handed over a list of its retail clients, and the top six, which accounted for over $200 million in sales in 1999, were unauthorized off-price outlets. ''It was clear to us then that this was a premeditated strategy to destroy the trademark,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner says she is baffled by Mr. Klein's allegations. ''I am not going to respond to a lawsuit I have not yet seen,'' Ms. Wachner said, ''but it is without merit.'' She added that all Warnaco's licensing and royalty agreements have been clearly known to the Klein partners since last fall, when they requested the information to share with perspective buyers.</p>
        <p>''She is a liar,'' Mr. Schwartz responded. ''She can say anything she wants to the press, but let her say that in court.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the merits of the suit, the timing could not be more devastating to Ms. Wachner. Warnaco, which makes underwear and clothing under numerous names besides Calvin Klein's, has seen its stock plunge for almost a year as the company has repeatedly missed earnings estimates. Yesterday, the news of the suit pushed the stock to a 52-week low of $6.6875, down from a high of $29.156 a share last June. Ms. Wachner, whose compensation ranks among that of the top chief executives in the nation despite her company's performance, is already a target of irate shareholders.</p>
        <p>The complaint singled out Ms. Wachner as the source of friction between the companies. It called her ''abusive and unprofessional,'' a topic Mr. Klein angrily expanded on in an interview. ''She runs it like a monarchy,'' Mr. Klein said of Ms. Wachner's performance at Warnaco. ''She is abusive to our people. Verbally, the language is disgusting.''</p>
        <p>At least in the short term, the Klein suit will surely put the already cash-short Warnaco into more of a bind. ''No one is going to step into the gap and be by her side financially,'' said Josie Esquivel, who is a stock analyst at Morgan Stanley. The long-term effect, however, will depend on how the court rules, and longtime Linda watchers do not count her out. ''She has shown great wherewithal,'' Ms. Esquivel noted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
