<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan Is Disclosed to Curb Role Of Hyundai Founding Family</title>
    <meta content="Y01HYU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hyundai Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hyundai Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Len, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung Ju Yung</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung Mong Koo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung Mong Hun</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED8153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan Is Disclosed to Curb Role Of Hyundai Founding Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL LEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Len, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hyundai Group founder and chairman Chung Ju Yung announces radical changes that will greatly dimish his family's management role and help the company repay billions of dollars in debt through asset sales; surprise announcement is nearly overshadowed by refusal of Chung's eldest son, Chung Mong Koo, to relinquish control of Hyundai's flagship automaker, Hyundai Motor; Chung says he will relinquish his position and that his sons, Chung Mong Hun and Chung Mong Koo, will resign as well; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The founder and chairman of the Hyundai Group announced radical changes today that will greatly diminish his family's management role and help the company, South Korea's biggest conglomerate, repay billions of dollars in debt through asset sales. But the surprise announcement was nearly overshadowed by the refusal of the chairman's eldest son to relinquish control of Hyundai's flagship automaker.</p>
        <p>The defiance was an unusual public display of family bickering, and it was unclear tonight how it might be resolved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The founder and chairman of the Hyundai Group announced radical changes today that will greatly diminish his family's management role and help the company, South Korea's biggest conglomerate, repay billions of dollars in debt through asset sales. But the surprise announcement was nearly overshadowed by the refusal of the chairman's eldest son to relinquish control of Hyundai's flagship automaker.</p>
        <p>The defiance was an unusual public display of family bickering, and it was unclear tonight how it might be resolved.</p>
        <p>Investors have grown increasingly nervous about the financial pressures on Hyundai, which disclosed some weeks ago that one of its lending subsidiaries was deeply exposed to the bad debts of another large South Korean conglomerate, the Daewoo Group. The changes announced today by Hyundai's chairman and family patriarch, Chung Ju Yung, were intended in part to allay investor anxieties about Hyundai's future.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, Hyundai will raise about $5.2 billion in cash through the sale of shares and real estate and through cutbacks in investment projects, and will effectively reduce the number of subsidiaries from 52 to 16 by year-end. The money raised will be used to help repay some of Hyundai's $46.5 billion in debts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chung also said that he would relinquish his position and that his two sons, Chung Mong Hun, chairman of the main business group, and Chung Mong Koo, chairman of Hyundai Motor Company, would resign as well. There was no word on who would replace them.</p>
        <p>''I believe that the only way to succeed in a competitive international climate is for professional managers to lead each company,'' the elder Chung said in a letter released by Kim Jai Soo, head of corporate restructuring at Hyundai. ''Instead, we will remain solely as shareholders in Hyundai companies.''</p>
        <p>But shortly after the announcement, Chung Mong Koo, the elder of the two sons and the chairman of Hyundai Motor, said he could not follow his father's decision. In a statement, Hyundai Motor said its workers needed the guidance of its current chairman.</p>
        <p>Korean press reports said the elder Chung even failed to persuade his son to change his mind over dinner at a restaurant near Hyundai's Seoul headquarters.</p>
        <p>''Hyundai is one of the most feudalistic companies in Korea in terms of ownership,'' said Chang Ha Sung, a prominent advocate for minority shareholder rights and a management professor at Korea University.</p>
        <p>The elder Chung's announced retirement from day-to-day management of Hyundai came as a surprise. The 84-year-old patriarch, who began the business by opening a rice shop in 1940, has been a central figure in Hyundai and is regarded as a symbol of South Korea's family-controlled conglomerates.</p>
        <p>The stock market responded positively to the news, with the main share index jumping nearly 6 percent. The market had slumped in the last week because of concern over Hyundai's finances.</p>
        <p>The South Korean government said nothing about the family bickering but welcomed Hyundai's announcement of a revamping. Over the last two years, the government has been prodding the nation's big conglomerates to reduce their size and indebtedness, which are regarded as important contributors to the financial crisis that nearly paralyzed the South Korean economy in late 1997.</p>
        <p>''The self-rescue plan announced by Hyundai will be reflected positively to outside investors,'' said Lee Hun Jai, the minister of finance and economy.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
