<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health Insurance Provides Buffer to Rising Drug Prices for Most Americans</title>
    <meta content="Y01DRU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DA123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health Insurance Provides Buffer to Rising Drug Prices for Most Americans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of increasing insurance coverage of prescription drugs; trend, result of shift to health maintenance organizations and other forms of managed care, has muted reaction to skyrocketing drug prices; elderly who depend on Medicare, which does not cover outpatient drugs, bear brunt of price rises and are up in arms; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More and more in recent years, private insurance has been picking up the cost of prescription medicine. Only about one-quarter of Americans' total drug costs are now paid out of pocket.</p>
        <p>That is why there is no general political uproar even though drug prices in the United States have been rising by as much as 15 percent a year, the drug makers are among the most profitable businesses in the world and many new drugs in Canada and Europe cost a small fraction of what they do here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More and more in recent years, private insurance has been picking up the cost of prescription medicine. Only about one-quarter of Americans' total drug costs are now paid out of pocket.</p>
        <p>That is why there is no general political uproar even though drug prices in the United States have been rising by as much as 15 percent a year, the drug makers are among the most profitable businesses in the world and many new drugs in Canada and Europe cost a small fraction of what they do here.</p>
        <p>Imagine the political swivet Americans would be in if that were the case with gasoline or some other staple of daily life.</p>
        <p>The elderly, however, are up in arms. Those who are completely dependent on Medicare, which does not cover the cost of outpatient prescriptions, bear the brunt of the skyrocketing prices.</p>
        <p>But most Americans never face these high drug prices. They pay no more than $5 or $10 for each prescription. The rest is covered by their health insurance.</p>
        <p>''When people don't have to pay out of pocket, it lowers the political tension enormously,'' said Prof. Robert J. Blendon of Harvard, an expert on public opinion and health.</p>
        <p>Insurance coverage of prescription medicine is a relatively new phenomenon, a consequence of the shift to health maintenance organizations and other forms of managed care.</p>
        <p>Today, government figures show, 77 percent of Americans under 65 have health insurance, either public or private, and 99 percent of those with insurance have some drug coverage.</p>
        <p>In 1970, only 8 percent of the nation's total drug costs were covered by private insurance. By 1980, the figure had risen to 20 percent, and by 1990 it had reached 34 percent.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's the proportion rose steadily, and by last year more than half of all spending on prescription drugs in the country was covered by private insurance. Another 21 percent was paid with public money, mostly for people in the military or those covered by Medicaid or veterans' programs.</p>
        <p>Put another way, the average amount of their own money that Americans spend for prescription medicine each year has not even kept pace with inflation in the overall economy over the last 30 years. But the nation's per capita spending on prescription drugs has risen to more than $300 this year from $26 in 1970, government actuaries report.</p>
        <p>The Department of Health and Human Services expects the fraction of drug costs paid out of pocket to keep dropping over the next 10 years, even if Medicare still excludes drug coverage.</p>
        <p>Medicaid covers the drug bills of poor people. A survey by the Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation, which focuses on health care issues, shows that, except for the elderly, the people who are uninsured tend to be low-paid workers, who are not generally influential politically.</p>
        <p>Change may be on the horizon. Employers who must pay higher insurance premiums for their workers are shouldering the burden of the rising drug prices. Some companies have begun to reduce prescription drug benefits, requiring workers to make larger copayments or putting some expensive drugs off limits.</p>
        <p>If that trend continues and people begin taking a hit in their wallets, the political ramifications can be substantial. But so far, high drug prices are low on the list of Washington priorities.</p>
        <p>Both parties in Congress and both parties' presidential candidates say they want to expand Medicare coverage to include prescription medicine. But they disagree so much on the details that action this year is problematic.</p>
        <p>Bills have been introduced in Congress to hold down prescription costs. One, for instance, would allow pharmacies to buy American-made drugs abroad and sell them here. But such bills are going nowhere, at least not this year.</p>
        <p>There has been some movement in the states. This month, a law was enacted in Maine threatening the pharmaceutical industry with price controls. The law created a commission that would negotiate drug prices for uninsured Maine residents and could impose price limits, starting in 2003. Similar measures are being considered in a few other states. But in most instances, this seems to be a case of politicians seizing an issue and drumming up support rather than responding to demands from their constituents.</p>
        <p>An analysis by the Kaiser foundation found that in 1997, the last year for which data is available, private insurance plans required beneficiaries to pay on average a $5.53 copayment for each generic drug prescription and $9.96 for a brand name drug. The average retail price, the analysis showed, was $30.76. For drugs taken on a regular basis, a prescription is normally for a 90-day supply.</p>
        <p>Employers are paying the tab. At the Ford Motor Company, for example, Dr. Woodrow A. Myers Jr., the director of health care management, calculated that the company's pharmaceutical bill would increase by nearly 25 percent this year alone, to $470 million from $380 million in 1999. The company, he said, paid nearly as much for drugs as for workers' hospitalization.</p>
        <p>Ford employees never feel the pinch. Hourly workers pay $5 for each prescription. Salaried workers pay $12 for brand name drugs and $2 for generic drugs. Retirees get the same benefits.</p>
        <p>Dr. Myers said 24 percent of Ford's health care premiums go to drugs. That percentage seems to be typical of large companies. The money is withheld from paychecks, and most workers never think about it.</p>
        <p>One of the anomalies created by most people's insulation from rising drug prices was that Americans tended to insist on the newest medicine on the market -- the drugs that cost the most. For example, Dr. Myers said Ford workers often demand that their doctors prescribe Prilosec, a new, heavily advertised ulcer drug that costs $3.80 a day. In many cases, said Dr. Myers, a physician, the workers had nothing but a routine case of heartburn that would respond just as well to older, generic medicine and would cost a few cents a day.</p>
        <p>This does not seem to happen so much in other countries. In part, that is because drug advertising aimed at the public is not allowed in Canada and Europe the way it is in the United States. But it also reflects a cultural difference. A study in 1993, before pharmaceutical advertising became prominent on television in this country, found that 66 percent of Americans were interested in the latest medical discoveries, compared with 45 percent of Europeans.</p>
        <p>No one disputes that these new drugs cost much more in the United States than they do abroad. A survey last fall by USA Today found that Prilosec, for instance, cost only $1.47 a day in Canada, $1.67 in Britain, $1.29 in Australia and 99 cents in Mexico. The governments in those countries negotiated the lower prices.</p>
        <p>The elderly who have no insurance except Medicare and other Americans without insurance pay the prices. But it is not clear that Americans overall pay more for drugs than people in other countries.</p>
        <p>The most recent extensive study, by Patricia M. Danzon, a professor of health management at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, concluded that Americans might not pay more when factors were counted like the discounts received by American drug companies, the widespread use of generic drugs in this country and the different dosages prescribed in different countries.</p>
        <p>Prof. Ernst R. Berndt, an economist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said he had been unable to determine whether Americans pay more than people elsewhere. But he noted that in the United States in 1997, 10 percent of all health expenditures went for drugs. The figure was 13.8 percent in Canada, 16.7 percent in Britain and more in some other developed countries.</p>
        <p>''Why is it,'' Professor Berndt asked, ''if pharmaceutical prices are highest in the U.S., their cost share is so low?''</p>
        <p>The pharmaceutical companies say the higher prices for new drugs in the United States are necessary to pay for research and development. Industry officials often note that other expenses, like college tuition, are also higher in the United States.</p>
        <p>This rationale drives some academics and health policy experts up the wall. They argue that the drug companies are making out like bandits. But it does not seem to bother the public much.</p>
        <p>William D. McInturff, a pollster who has often done work for Republican politicians and for lobbies affiliated with the pharmaceutical industry, conducted a survey this spring in which he tried to determine the public image of the drug companies.</p>
        <p>Only 28 percent of Americans with private health insurance, he found, had an unfavorable view of the industry.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to minimize the pressure politicians are feeling from the elderly who have to pay top dollar,'' Mr. McInturff said. ''But other than that vocal group, there's no great public outcry about drug prices.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
