<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Company to Buy Struggling Dutch Software Concern</title>
    <meta content="Y01BAA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baan Nv</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Invensys Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D7153CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Company to Buy Struggling Dutch Software Concern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Invensys PLC, British manufacturer of factory controls, agrees to buy Baan NV for $802 million, promising to turn around company that has lost money and share value for nearly two years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Invensys P.L.C., a British manufacturer of factory controls, agreed today to buy Baan N.V. for $802 million, promising to turn around the company, a Dutch software maker that has relentlessly lost money and share value for nearly two years.</p>
        <p>Baan, once seen as one of Europe's most promising high-technology companies, has been looking for a buyer since January, when Mary Coleman, the chief executive, and a string of other senior managers resigned. Lazard Freres &amp; Company, the investment bank, was retained to look for a buyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Invensys P.L.C., a British manufacturer of factory controls, agreed today to buy Baan N.V. for $802 million, promising to turn around the company, a Dutch software maker that has relentlessly lost money and share value for nearly two years.</p>
        <p>Baan, once seen as one of Europe's most promising high-technology companies, has been looking for a buyer since January, when Mary Coleman, the chief executive, and a string of other senior managers resigned. Lazard Freres &amp; Company, the investment bank, was retained to look for a buyer.</p>
        <p>Founded 22 years ago by two brothers, Jan and Paul Baan, the company expanded steadily until April 1998, when new accounting rules forced it to defer licensing revenue. It has since reported a series of quarterly losses, and its shares are down nearly 90 percent. In May, Baan shares reached a low of 1.26 euros, or about $1.18, on fear the company would seek bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Today, Baan shares rose 13 percent, to 2.97 euros, or about $2.79, on word of the Invensys deal. Investors punished Invensys, however, driving down its share price 13 percent, to 230 pence, or about $3.45. With today's losses, Invensys stock has fallen 32 percent this year.</p>
        <p>Invensys said it would pay 2.85 euros in cash for each Baan share and assume $65 million in debt. The price represented an 8.8 percent premium on the Dutch company's closing price Tuesday in Amsterdam of 2.62 euros.</p>
        <p>Allen Yurko, the Invensys chief executive, said the acquisition fitted the Invensys ''vision to create the leading industrial software company,'' offering products to link factories to customers, suppliers and workers on the factory floor. He said Baan would return to profitability within a year.</p>
        <p>''We have turned around numerous software companies,'' Mr. Yurko said. ''We have done it before.'' He acknowledged disappointment about the stock market's reaction to the deal, but said the combination represented ''the right thing for the long-term value of the group.''</p>
        <p>Invensys, based in London, was created in February 1999 by the merger of Siebe P.L.C. and BTR P.L.C., which specialized in automation and controls to enable companies to monitor manufacturing. Mr. Yurko said Baan would operate under its own name in a new Invensys software and systems division.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
