<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentagon Test-Fires Missiles To Finish T.W.A. Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="01MISS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trans World Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Transportation Safety Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3D7123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentagon Test-Fires Missiles To Finish T.W.A. Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal crash investigators reportedly had Pentagon test-fire Stinger missiles last month off coast of Florida to see if resulting streaks resembled those described by witnesses to explosion of TWA Flight 800; spokesman for National Transportation Safety Board says that test results did not change conclusion that plane was not taken down by missile (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal crash investigators had the Pentagon test-fire Stinger missiles last month off the coast of Florida to see if the resulting streaks resembled those described by witnesses to the explosion of T.W.A. Flight 800, a spokesman for the National Transportation Safety Board said this evening.</p>
        <p>The board has already concluded that the plane, a Boeing 747 that blew up off the coast of Long Island minutes after it left Kennedy International Airport for Paris in July 1996, was not brought down by a missile. And the spokesman said last month's test did not change their conclusion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal crash investigators had the Pentagon test-fire Stinger missiles last month off the coast of Florida to see if the resulting streaks resembled those described by witnesses to the explosion of T.W.A. Flight 800, a spokesman for the National Transportation Safety Board said this evening.</p>
        <p>The board has already concluded that the plane, a Boeing 747 that blew up off the coast of Long Island minutes after it left Kennedy International Airport for Paris in July 1996, was not brought down by a missile. And the spokesman said last month's test did not change their conclusion.</p>
        <p>''Nothing here should be construed to show that there's been any new finding or change in the wreckage that we've been studying,'' said Ted  Lopatkiewicz, the board's spokesman. ''This is part of our effort to close all the open parts of the investigation.'' The tests were first reported in Thursday's Washington Post.</p>
        <p>The Safety Board plans to meet on Aug. 22 to consider a report on the cause of the crash, which killed all 230 people aboard.</p>
        <p>The board has already said that the cause was an explosion in the center fuel tank, and has conducted extensive laboratory work demonstrating that an explosive atmosphere often develops in such tanks.</p>
        <p>The board's investigation has also shown that wiring defects could, in theory, introduce a spark that would set off an explosion. But it has not established precisely what set off the tank, according to investigators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopatkiewicz said the board could issue a final report without identifying the precise source of ignition.</p>
        <p>The board has already said that there is no hole in the wreckage that would indicate a missile entry, and no metal bent by high explosives of the kind used in a missile or a bomb.</p>
        <p>In major crashes, the safety board routinely prepares a report on what witnesses saw. But in this case, the investigators got a very late start on that element of the investigation, because it was handled by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, which initially suspected terrorism, until only recently.</p>
        <p>Because it is unusual for an airplane to explode in flight, investigators looked hard for signs of a bomb or missile immediately after the crash, but eventually ruled out both possibilities.</p>
        <p>Last month's tests were conducted at Eglin Air Force Base in Florida at a time of day when the sun was at an elevation similar to its position at the time the plane exploded, and in similar weather conditions. The team postponed the test on several occasions until visibility was similar to the haze at dusk at the time of the crash, he said.</p>
        <p>The Stinger is an Army missile. Civilian experts say its range is probably insufficient to have reached Flight 800.</p>
        <p>There were 244 witnesses to the crash who said they saw streaks of light.</p>
        <p>At hearings after the crash, board investigators said that after an explosion severed the front part of the airplane, the remaining part of the plane, including the wings and the bulk of the fuselage, would have pitched up and climbed steeply, causing an upward streak of light.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
