<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Tells His Story In His Body Language</title>
    <meta content="01YANK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2D7123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Tells His Story In His Body Language</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Athletics defeat New York Yankees, 8-7; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Cone's right hand was locked on his hip, his eyes were focused on the grass and his mind seemed to be wondering what he could do to emerge from this predicament. It was only the first inning and the Yankees trailed the Oakland Athletics by a mere three runs, but Cone already looked deflated.</p>
        <p>The body language of slumped shoulders, frustrated expressions and deep exhales told as much about Cone as the numbers dotting the scoreboard. It was an awful evening for the right-hander, who knew that he did not have an effective repertory of pitches and quickly discovered that he could not trick the Oakland batters either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Cone's right hand was locked on his hip, his eyes were focused on the grass and his mind seemed to be wondering what he could do to emerge from this predicament. It was only the first inning and the Yankees trailed the Oakland Athletics by a mere three runs, but Cone already looked deflated.</p>
        <p>The body language of slumped shoulders, frustrated expressions and deep exhales told as much about Cone as the numbers dotting the scoreboard. It was an awful evening for the right-hander, who knew that he did not have an effective repertory of pitches and quickly discovered that he could not trick the Oakland batters either.</p>
        <p>Cone was gone by the fourth inning, and though they Yankees rallied more than once, they stumbled to an 8-7 loss at Yankee Stadium, leaving Cone with a 1-5 record after the first two months of the season.</p>
        <p>Cone was battered and bruised because he could not summon a decent fastball, a decent slider or a decent anything. The 37-year-old pitcher allowed six earned runs on six hits and four walks in three and one-third innings and jogged to the dugout amid some cheers and some boos. He had a look of resignation across his reddened face.</p>
        <p>''I'll be back,'' Cone said. ''I'm not done by a long shot. Certainly, there are a lot of valid questions about whether I still have anything left. I feel I have something left.''</p>
        <p>No one had even asked Cone if he thought his career was over. He offered the defensive remarks unsolicited, his face still red and his words still crisp. Then Cone turned and trudged out of a clubhouse that was as silent as a morgue.</p>
        <p>Cone put the Yankees in 4-0 and 7-3 ditches and, despite comebacks, the holes Cone created were too deep.</p>
        <p>''He couldn't throw a strike,'' his catcher, Jorge Posada, said. ''He was battling with himself. You could see a little frustration. He tried everything. Today, it didn't work out.''</p>
        <p>The panic button is never too far in George Steinbrenner's world, even if the two-time defending World Series champions have a winning record. But the Yankees have now lost four of their last six games and they are about to begin a treacherous stretch in which they will play seven straight series against teams with winning records, starting with the Braves tomorrow night in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>That is why the Yankees are aggressively pursuing someone to help improve their underachieving offense. The Yankees have had discussions with the Houston Astros about Moises Alou and they are still talking to the Cincinnati Reds about a trade that would involve Dmitri Young and Ramiro Mendoza. The more the Yankees falter, the more eager Steinbrenner will get to make a change, although the owner's scapegoat, Ricky Ledee, helped the Yankees climb back into the game twice last night with a three-run homer and a run-scoring double.</p>
        <p>Cone needs to make some changes soon. With two out in the first, he gave up a single and a walk, and Matt Stairs lined a three-run homer. Eric Chavez walked and scored in the second, but Chuck Knoblauch's three-run homer off Gil Heredia made it 4-3.</p>
        <p>Still, Cone labored. He walked two more in the third and was fortunate to emerge unscathed, but he could not pull off another Houdini act in the fourth. Chavez bashed a homer to put the A's ahead, 5-3, and, after two more hard singles, Manager Joe Torre burst out of the dugout to end the fiasco. Both runners scored off Allen Watson to increase Oakland's lead to 7-3.</p>
        <p>After Ledee's homer cut the deficit to 7-6, the Yankees botched a chance to tie the score when Scott Brosius was caught stealing. Jason Giambi lined a run-scoring single in the eighth that almost knocked Mike Stanton's cap off and made it 8-6, but Ledee doubled home the Yankees' seventh run in the bottom of the inning.</p>
        <p>Jason Isringhausen then struck out Derek Jeter with a 3-2 fastball on the inside corner with two on to preserve the one-run lead.</p>
        <p>Cone wound up facing 20 batters and he went to a 2-0 count or a 3-1 count on eight of them, a definite sign of a pitcher creating his own trouble. Two of the A's Cone did not fall behind by 2-0 or 3-1 were the batters who whacked homers. Cone threw first-pitch balls to 10 batters and 41 of his 81 pitches were balls.</p>
        <p>''It didn't look like his body was responding to what he wanted it to do,'' said Torre, who added that Cone had been fighting the flu recently.</p>
        <p>With a 1-5 record and a 6.24 earned run average, Cone now has the fewest victories and the highest e.r.a. he has had after 11 starts in any season of a stellar 14-year career. The Yankees (28-21) have played 49 games, but Cone is stuck on one victory.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Before ORLANDO HERNANDEZ tossed about 30 pitches to test his stiff back yesterday, he said, ''I don't pitch here and I get fat.'' Then Hernandez laughed, but the point was clear: El Duque wants to pitch and he does not want to gain more weight. He will return to face Atlanta and KEVIN MILLWOOD tomorrow. The Yankees will start the five-time Cy Young Award winner ROGER CLEMENS against the four-time Cy Young winner GREG MADDUX on Saturday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
