<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial Opens in Columbia Student's Murder</title>
    <meta content="01MURD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ko, Edmund</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hong, Hyeseung Lynda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3D7123CF932A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial Opens in Columbia Student's Murder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trial of Edmund Ko, accused of brutally murdering Columbia University law student Hyeseung Lynda Hong, opens in New York City Criminal Court, Manhattan; opening statements noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trial of a young man accused of brutally murdering a Columbia University law student opened yesterday with prosecutors contending that the man, Edmund Ko, killed his former girlfriend in a twisted effort to prove his devotion to his obsessively jealous new girlfriend.</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers accused the police of planting evidence against Mr. Ko, and blamed the new girlfriend for the killing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The trial of a young man accused of brutally murdering a Columbia University law student opened yesterday with prosecutors contending that the man, Edmund Ko, killed his former girlfriend in a twisted effort to prove his devotion to his obsessively jealous new girlfriend.</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers accused the police of planting evidence against Mr. Ko, and blamed the new girlfriend for the killing.</p>
        <p>The trial of Mr. Ko, 25, of Cliffside Park, N.J., the son of a wealthy Korean corporate executive, opened in a packed a courtroom in the Manhattan Criminal Court building yesterday. The family and friends of the murdered student, Hyeseung Lynda Hong, 26, who grew up in Short Hills, N.J., sat behind prosecutors, while Mr. Ko's friends and relatives filled rows behind the defense table.</p>
        <p>Both sides made it clear in their opening statements that a central element in the trial would be Mr. Ko's bizarre relationship with Claudia Seong, his girlfriend at the time of the killing. Prosecutors and defense lawyers described Ms. Seong as a domineering, obsessively jealous woman who demanded complete loyalty from Mr. Ko, a privileged young man eight years her junior.</p>
        <p>In a jealous rage four months before the murder, Ms. Seong slashed another former girlfriend of Mr. Ko repeatedly across the face, head and legs as Mr. Ko and Ms. Seong's young sister held the victim down, according to prosecutors. She also persuaded Mr. Ko and another man to call Mr. Ko's ex-girlfriends and friends and order them to sever ties with him, both sides said, adding that the acquaintances were told not to acknowledge Mr. Ko if they bumped into him.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seong's earlier statements to the police that Mr. Ko confessed to her were expected to be a crucial part of the prosecution's case. But the assistant district attorney, Ann Prunty, hedged yesterday on whether Ms. Seong would testify. Jack Litman, the defense lawyer, said he wanted to call Ms. Seong to the stand and would argue that Mr. Ko never confessed and was an unwitting dupe framed by a manipulative and vindictive older woman.</p>
        <p>Both sides said that the night before the murder, Ms. Seong grew enraged when she was told that Ms. Hong responded to an ultimatum to stay away from Mr. Ko by saying that he had dated only prostitutes since the couple broke up two years earlier. But prosecutors contended that Mr. Ko then murdered Ms. Hong to show his devotion to Ms. Seong, while the defense said that Ms. Seong carried out the attack with the aid of Jae Young Shin, a young man who has since moved to Korea.</p>
        <p>Ms. Prunty said that Ms. Hong had been on the telephone on the night of the murder and hung up when Mr. Ko arrived at her apartment. Less than an hour later, Ms. Hong did not respond to phone calls and was dead, prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>Videotapes show Mr. Ko leaving his apartment building at the time of the killing, Ms. Prunty said, and his hair was found on bloody clothes left at the murder scene.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman, the defense lawyer, did not deny that Mr. Ko was at Ms. Hong's apartment, but he accused the police of planting Mr. Ko's hairs on the bloody clothing, which was found by the F.B.I. a year after the killing. He also accused the police of planting blood from Ms. Hong on a knife found in an apartment Mr. Ko once lived in but had had no access to at the time of the murder.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors opened their case by showing a videotape of the crime scene in the cramped apartment where Ms. Hong died in March 1998 of a slash to the throat. Amid law textbooks and cluttered papers, Ms. Hong's body lay prone, face down on the floor in a large pool of blood. After seeing the tape, Ms. Hong's sister, Amy, cried out in the courtroom and fled into the hall, weeping.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
