<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pacers Know The Last Step Is the Hardest</title>
    <meta content="02PACE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DF103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pacers Know The Last Step Is the Hardest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Indiana Pacers preparing for Game 6 of NBA Eastern Conference championship series against New York Knickerbockers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His team is on the cusp of taking its first trip to the National Basketball Association finals and Reggie Miller is concerned.</p>
        <p>''This is the same team that was down 15 or 16 points against Miami in Game 6 at halftime and found a way to win that ballgame, force a Game 7 and go down and win in Miami,'' Miller said today after the Pacers' practice at Conseco Fieldhouse. ''So I'm not counting nothing. I'm not overlooking nothing from them. They are a very scary and dangerous team that you got to put the dagger in and you got to make sure the heart ain't pumping no more. Because if there's any type of life in them, you never know what's going to happen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His team is on the cusp of taking its first trip to the National Basketball Association finals and Reggie Miller is concerned.</p>
        <p>''This is the same team that was down 15 or 16 points against Miami in Game 6 at halftime and found a way to win that ballgame, force a Game 7 and go down and win in Miami,'' Miller said today after the Pacers' practice at Conseco Fieldhouse. ''So I'm not counting nothing. I'm not overlooking nothing from them. They are a very scary and dangerous team that you got to put the dagger in and you got to make sure the heart ain't pumping no more. Because if there's any type of life in them, you never know what's going to happen.</p>
        <p>''So, you got to kill the dog.''</p>
        <p>Hopping onto a flight for Game 6 Friday night at Madison Square Garden, they know the drill -- having lost in the Eastern Conference finals four of the past six seasons, including the last three in a row. Whether it was Patrick Ewing in 1994 or Latrell Sprewell, Allan Houston and Larry Johnson in 1999 -- or the Orlando Magic of Shaquille O'Neal and Anfernee Hardaway in 1995 or the Chicago Bulls of Michael Jordan and Scottie Pippen in 1998 -- the Pacers have fallen short.</p>
        <p>With major free-agent questions to be answered in the off-season, the Pacers never have had a greater sense of urgency to close out the Knicks. ''I think it is now or never,'' Miller said. ''If you can't get it done now, then there probably will never be another golden opportunity like it is now. But like I said, it's up to the 12 guys in the locker room to get it done. You can only blame yourself if you don't get the job done. So, it's all on our shoulders.''</p>
        <p>Mark Jackson said, ''We've been down, 3-2, but to be up, 3-2, and to have all the pressure on the other team, what a great opportunity for us to finally seal the door shut.'' The Knicks' season is close to expiring because they blew a 37-19 second-quarter lead and lost by 88-79 on Wednesday in Game 5. The Game 5 comeback changed the mood inside the Pacers' locker room.</p>
        <p>''I think we're hungry,'' Jalen Rose said. ''We need to create a scenario in our locker room that this isn't the third straight year. That this is the first time we need to treat it like we're excited about the moment, something that we can't take for granted, and we've got to also treat it as though we won't get to this point again. I think getting down 18 woke us up and made us realize that playoff life is short.''</p>
        <p>''This is as focused as I've seen this team,'' Coach Larry Bird said. ''Yeah, we have our ups and downs. But they know what's on the line here. I don't think they've ever been in this situation here. Well, maybe when they played New York and New York came in here and beat 'em and then beat 'em in a Game 7. But this a little bit different.'' For the record,  the dog would not die in 1994.</p>
        <p>Miller is the lone Pacer holdover from that season, and he remembers well how Indiana let the series slip away. The parallels are almost eerie. The Pacers had a 3-2 lead after a pulsating Game 5 victory at the Garden and needed only to close out the Knicks in Game 6 at Market Square Arena or Game 7 at the Garden. They could not do it. ''If I remember right, it's all the little things,'' Miller said. ''Rebounds. Loose balls. Throughout the course of a game, making shots and defending will take care of itself, but it's who does the little things that really separated us from New York in '94. I think they got all the loose balls, a lot of second shots and they played much harder. I remember them getting up big and us coming back. But we could never get over that hump in '94.''</p>
        <p>The largest obstacle next to outplaying the Knicks may be overcoming their recent misfortune at Madison Square Garden. Indiana has not won at the Garden since Game 4 of last season, having dropped five straight games. Going back to Larry Johnson's controversial 4-point play in Game 3 of the 1999 conference finals, they have had their share of bad calls on the Knicks' floor.</p>
        <p>''We don't count five straight,'' Jackson said. ''There's been fluke calls. There's been missed calls to be quite honest. Which happens. We feel we haven't put together 48 minutes of basketball at Madison Square Garden the last couple times, especially Games 3 and 4.''</p>
        <p>If they played poorly in Game 3, the Pacers were abysmal in Game 4 on Memorial Day, unable to stop the Knicks on defense and find an offensive rhythm until it was too late.</p>
        <p>Miller's fondest memory is of knocking the Knicks out at the Garden in Game 7 of the second-round playoff series in 1995.</p>
        <p>''Given the opportunity to have one place to get the job done -- other than our place -- that would be the top choice,'' Jackson said. ''It'll be a lot of fun and should be a great time tomorrow night in New York City.''</p>
        <p>Finally, Jackson was asked how it felt to be so close to advancing to the finals. ''Unbelievable,'' he said. ''I thought about it last night. I got a little choked up just thinking about it. We're right there. And it's great to be right there, but it's nothing like being there. I don't want to look at it and say, 'We were right there.' We have to knock down the door because we're facing a team that has no quit. They're not going to lay down tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''And it's up to us to go into Madison Square Garden in an ideal situation for us and take care of business. And then dance.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
