<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="02SPAR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6DC133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="5490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Opening today, ''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries From Mongolia,'' which focuses on one of the most famous fossil finds in the world; through Oct. 29. In conjunction with the exhibition, a celebration of the cultural heritage of Mongolia, with public programs through Sunday, featuring live performances, lectures, films and demonstrations. Tomorrow (from 1 to 6 p.m.) and Sunday (1 to 4:45 p.m.), film and video screenings followed by discussions. Imax films are ''Epic Journeys: The Great Migrations'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available; for example, a combination ticket  that includes museum admission and one Imax film or any special exhibition: $15; students and the elderly, $11; children 12 and under, $9; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. Opening today, ''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries From Mongolia,'' which focuses on one of the most famous fossil finds in the world; through Oct. 29. In conjunction with the exhibition, a celebration of the cultural heritage of Mongolia, with public programs through Sunday, featuring live performances, lectures, films and demonstrations. Tomorrow (from 1 to 6 p.m.) and Sunday (1 to 4:45 p.m.), film and video screenings followed by discussions. Imax films are ''Epic Journeys: The Great Migrations'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available; for example, a combination ticket  that includes museum admission and one Imax film or any special exhibition: $15; students and the elderly, $11; children 12 and under, $9; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY'S ROSE CENTER FOR EARTH AND SPACE, Central Park West at 81st Street. The Hayden Planetarium contains the Space Theater, presenting ''Passport to the Universe,'' and the Big Bang Theater, featuring narrated visual and audio effects simulating the beginning of the universe. ''Starry Nights: Fridays Under the Sphere,'' 6 to 8 p.m., music with Jerry Gonzalez and the Fort Apache Band, through June 16. Free with admission; food and cash bar. Hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays to 8:45 p.m. Space shows run throughout the day. Admission (suggested donation) to the American Museum of Natural History, which includes the Rose Center: $10; for students and the elderly, $7.50; children 12 and under, $6; under 2, free. Admission to the museum, the Rose Center and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $19; students and the elderly, $14; children 12 and under, $11.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100. Reservations: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. ''New York Now 2000: Contemporary Work in Photography,'' through Oct. 15. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a performance of Latin jazz featuring the singer Carmen Jimenez and quintet. Sunday at 1 p.m., a screening of ''La Ciudad,'' about garment workers, followed by a panel discussion on immigrant labor featuring filmmakers, labor organizers and film participants. Free with museum admission. Hours: Tuesdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. for registered groups only; Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $7; the elderly, students and children, $4; families, $12. Information: (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST, 18 First Place, at West Street and Battery Place, Battery Park City. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videos and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. Other exhibitions: ''Children of a Vanished World: Photographs by Roman Vishniac,'' through Oct. 20. ''Yiddish on Stage: Posters and Artifacts From the World of Yiddish Theater,'' through Jan. 23. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays and the eves of Jewish holidays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; closed Saturdays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; age 5 and under, free. Tickets can be bought in advance through Ticketmaster, (212) 307-4007, or by calling the museum on the day of the visit, (212) 945-0039. Information: (212) 509-6130.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 170 Central Park West, near 77th Street. ''Stork Club,'' including an environmental installation that mimics the floor plan of the club, photographs and memorabilia belonging to the family of Sherman Billingsley, the owner of the club; on view through Oct. 1. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Stork Club,'' a 1945 movie starring Betty Hutton. Free with museum admission. ''Magnum, Our Turning World: Photographs, 1989-1999,'' through June 18. ''Without Sanctuary: Lynching Photography in America,'' images from the 1870's through the 1950's, through Aug. 13. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; students and the elderly, $3; 12 and under, free. Information: (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM AND MARKETPLACE, South and Fulton Streets, Lower Manhattan. ''American Tattoo: The Art of Gus Wagner,'' in the Whitman Gallery, through June 11. ''S O S Festival,'' a day with the Coast Guard, learning how to stay safe on the water, all day tomorrow. Free with museum admission; $2 materials fee, at the Children's Center, 165 John Street. A sail on the Pioneer, owned and operated by the museum, daily from Pier 16 through end of September. Information: (212) 748-8786. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; closed Tuesdays. Stores in the marketplace: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Museum admission: $6; the elderly, $5; students, $4; children 12 and under, $3. Information: (212) 748-8600; reservations for special events: (212) 748-8786; the marketplace, (212) 732-7678.</p>
        <p>Cruises</p>
        <p>CIRCLE LINE CRUISES, leaving from Pier 83, 42nd Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. A two-hour 24-mile cruise around southern Manhattan, passing landmarks like Ellis Island and the United Nations, daily at 11 a.m. and 3:30 p.m. Tickets: $18; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. A three-hour, 35-mile cruise around all of Manhattan, today at 10 a.m., noon, 1:30 and 2:30 p.m.; beginning tomorrow, daily at 9:30 and 10:30 a.m., 12:30, 1:30, 2:30 and 4:30 p.m. Tickets: $22; children 12 and under, $12; the elderly, $19. ''Harbor Lights,'' Fridays through Sundays, 7 p.m. Tickets: $18; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. Information: (212) 563-3200.</p>
        <p>WORLD YACHT, leaving from Pier 81, 41st Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. Daily dinner cruises along the West Side of Manhattan and around New York Harbor, from 7 to 10 p.m., boarding at 6 p.m. Prices: Fridays, $75; Saturdays, $79; Sundays, $67 (does not include beverages, taxes or gratuities). Brunch cruises sail on Sundays from 12:30 to 2:30 p.m., with boarding at 11:30 a.m. Price: $39.95. Information: (212) 630-8100.</p>
        <p>N.Y. WATERWAY, leaving from Pier 78, West 38th Street and 12th Avenue, Manhattan. Daily two-hour full Manhattan cruise, at 10:30 a.m. and 1:30 p.m., through Nov. 12. Tickets: $24; $19 for the elderly; $12 for children. Daily, a 90-minute cruise of New York Harbor; at 10 a.m., noon, 2 and 4 p.m.; through May 26. Tickets: $19; the elderly, $16; ages 3 to 12, $9; 2 and younger, free. Fridays at 10:15 p.m., Disco cruise. Price: $19; $9 for children. A 70-minute twilight tour leaves daily, except Tuesday, at 8:45 p.m.; additional tours on Saturdays at 7:15 and 10:15 p.m. and on Sundays at 7:15. Tickets: $19; the elderly, $16; children, $9. Information: (800) 533-3779.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 900 Washington Avenue, Prospect Heights. More than 12,000 kinds of plants from around the world are displayed on 52 acres. The roses are in bloom through June. The Japanese Hill and  Pond Garden has recently reopened; with specially guided tours (hourly from 1 to 4 p.m.), programs and events through June 18. Sunday from 1 to 5 p.m., origami and crafts day. Gallery hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $3; $1.50 for students and the elderly; free for children 15 and under; free on Tuesdays, except holidays; and free from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. The conservatory closes 30 minutes before the grounds close. Information: (718) 623-7200.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, 200th Street and Kazimiroff Boulevard, Fordham, the Bronx. Roses Week, tomorrow through June 11, featuring music, storytelling, tours, classes and crafts, in the Peggy Rockefeller Rose Garden. The Chinese Peony Show is through Sunday in the Haupt Conservatory, with the tree peonies in bloom; featuring lectures, demonstrations and workshops. Events include a performance by the Early Music Ensemble, tomorrow and Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. (also next weekend), and a class on growing roses, tomorrow from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. Tomorrow, tea from 3 to 5 p.m., $24.50 for adults and $18 for children. Information and reservations: (718) 220-8398. Saturdays and Sundays at 12:30 p.m., 90-minute bird walks; this week the focus is on Northern orioles. Garden hours: Tuesdays through Sundays and Monday holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Everett Children's Adventure Garden hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 1 p.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Conservatory admission: $3.50; students and the elderly, $2.50; children 2 to 12, $2; under 2, free. Grounds admission free for all on Wednesdays and from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. There are also combination packages. Parking: $5. Information: (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>BRONX ZOO, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham. Some 265 wooded acres are devoted to naturalistic habitats, including Jungle World, African Plains, the Baboon Reserve, the World of Birds, the Aitken Sea Bird Colony (with daily penguin feedings at 3:30 p.m., weather permitting), Big Birds and the Congo Gorilla Forest. The Butterfly Zone has reopened through Oct. 1, with thousands of butterflies and moths and an area where visitors can see the metamorphosis of chrysalides, or cocoons, into butterflies or moths. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission, $9; $5 for children 2 to 12 and the elderly; free for everyone on Wednesdays. Parking: $6. Information: (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK ZOO, Fifth Avenue at 64th Street. The zoo has tamarin monkeys, polar bears, colobus monkeys, gentoo penguins, chinstrap penguins and red pandas. Sea lion  feedings and penguin feedings daily. Hours, including the Tisch Children's Zoo: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; weekends and holidays, 10:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $3.50; the elderly, $1.25; children 3 to 12, 50 cents; under 3, free. Admission includes entry to the Tisch Children's Zoo. Information: (212) 861-6030.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>YAI CENTRAL PARK CHALLENGE AND FAMILY FUN DAY. Two races tomorrow; a five-kilometer race begins at 9 a.m. followed by a three-kilometer run at 9:45 a.m. Races for children begin at 11:15 a.m. Registration begins at 7:30 a.m.; fee, $15 ($10 for children). Sponsored by the National Institute for People With Disabilities. Information: (212) 273-6120.</p>
        <p>''RACE AGAINST TEEN SMOKING,'' Central Park. Three runners' events on Sunday -- from a 1.5-mile walk at 8:30 a.m., to a race for children of 50 to 300 yards at 9 a.m., to a four-mile run at 9:30 a.m. Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Advance registration fee, $17; $12 for club members; $10 for junior and senior club members. Information: (212) 860-4455.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>WALL STREET COMMUNITY DAY FESTIVAL SERIES, from South to Water Streets, Lower Manhattan. With crafts, antiques and food. Today, 11 a.m. to 6 pm. Sponsored by Community Board No. 1.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE OUTDOOR ART EXHIBIT, on the sidewalks north, south and east of Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village. Tomorrow and Sunday, noon to sundown.</p>
        <p>MURRAY HILL MILLENNIUM FESTIVAL, 35th Street, between Madison and Lexington Avenues. Entertainment and food. Tomorrow, noon to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Murray Hill Neighborhood Association.</p>
        <p>BLOCK PARTY, St. Paul the Apostle Catholic Church, 60th Street, between Ninth and 10th Avenues, Manhattan. Rides, games and food. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>SEVENTH LENOX HILL NEIGHBORHOOD HOUSE STREET FAIR, First Avenue, from 68th to 78th Streets, Manhattan. Crafts, antiques, food and health workshops. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN OF THE WORLD FESTIVAL, Avenue of the Americas, from 42nd to 57th Streets. International foods, crafts and antiques. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by Children of the World Foundation.</p>
        <p>SALUTE TO ISRAEL PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 57th to 79th Streets, east to Second Avenue. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINE INDEPENDENCE DAY PARADE, Madison Avenue, from 41st to 27th Streets. Sunday at noon. Followed by a street fair on Madison Avenue, from 23rd to 26th Streets.</p>
        <p>WEST FOURTH STREET FESTIVAL, from Broadway to Macdougal Streets. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Sponsored by Community Board No. 2.</p>
        <p>GRAMERCY PARK SPRING FAIR, Irving Place, from 14th to 20th Streets, Manhattan. Crafts, food, antiques, displays. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by Seafarers and International House.</p>
        <p>COLUMBUS AVENUE BLUES FESTIVAL, from 86th to 96th Streets, Manhattan. With entertainment, crafts and exhibits on health care. Sunday, 11 am. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Westside Crime Prevention Program.</p>
        <p>EAST 80TH STREET FESTIVAL, from Second to Third Avenue, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Second and Third East 80th Street Block Association.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY FAIR, Co-op City, Section I Greenway, the Bronx. With flea market, rides, food, entertainment. Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Riverbay Fund.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>THIRD METROTECH GARDEN FESTIVAL, Metrotech Commons, Myrtle Avenue between Jay Street and Flatbush Avenue Extension, adjacent to the New York Marriott Brooklyn, downtown Brooklyn. Features a 1,000-square-foot garden in which games will be held. Also, exhibits presented by the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, the Brooklyn Children's Museum and Barnes &amp; Noble. Today, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Information: (718) 488-8200.</p>
        <p>SEVENTH CHANGE YOUR MIND DAY, Central Park, Great Hill. Music, poetry and meditation. Tomorrow, 12:30 to 5:30 p.m. Free. Sponsored by Tricycle: The Buddhist Review. Information: (800) 950-7008.</p>
        <p>PATHMARK MULTICULTURAL ARTS FESTIVAL, South Street Seaport, Pier 16, at the East River. A three-day festival of performances highlighting African, Chinese and Latin cultures. Hours: today, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.; tomorrow, 1 to 6 p.m., and Sunday, 11:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. Information: (888)  486-4656.</p>
        <p>PAWS WALK 2000 POOCH PARADE, Central Park, Northeast Meadow, Fifth Avenue and 97th Street. Contests, demonstrations and a walk with soap opera stars and their dogs to promote responsible pet ownership and care. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Registration begins at 9:45 a.m. Fee: $15 (two-dog maximum). Sponsored by Friends of Van Cortlandt Park and the Parks and Recreation Department. Information: (718) 601-1460.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''OLD AND NEW MONEY: THE ORIGINS OF CENTRAL PARK WEST AND FIFTH AVENUE.'' How the architecture reflects the history of its early communities, with stops at  the Harry Sinclair and Henry Frick mansions, the Dakota and the Hotel des Artistes. Tomorrow and Sunday, 2 p.m. Fee: $12. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''LOWER EAST SIDE I: RADICAL JEWS.'' A walk past sites associated with turn-of-the-century activists like Abraham Cahan, a founder of The Jewish Daily Forward, and Sidney Hillman, a labor adviser and the founder of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, who spent time at the original buildings on Henry Street, off Pitt Street, where the Henry Street Settlement was founded. Sponsored by Radical Walking Tours. Meets Sunday at 1 p.m. in front of the old Jewish Daily Forward building at 175 East Broadway. Fee: $10. Information: (718) 492-0069.</p>
        <p>''TRIBECA: THE CREATIVE EXPLOSION.'' A look at an area that was transformed from an estate into an industrial center and then into a chic enclave. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. in Duane Park, at the intersection of Duane and Hudson Streets. Fee: $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>''THE AMERICAN INDIAN HERITAGE OF MANHATTAN ISLAND: FROM WAMPUM TO WALL STREET,'' Lower Manhattan. Traces the interaction of American Indians with Dutch and English settlers. Meets tomorrow at 2 and 6 p.m. inside Blimpie's, 38 Park Row, between Beekman and Spruce Streets. Fee, $12. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>''AYN RAND'S NEW YORK.'' Two tours exploring the architecture that influenced Rand and sites associated with her. ''Skyscrapers of 'The Fountainhead' '' meets tomorrow at 11 a.m. inside Bowling Green Park. ''Cerf's Up,'' with a focus on architecture and the media, meets Sunday at 11 a.m. on the northwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 58th Street. Fee for each tour: $15. Information: (201) 433-0946.</p>
        <p>''LITTLE ODESSA,'' Brighton Beach, Brooklyn. Covers the culture and foods of the growing community of Jews from the former Soviet Union, ending with an optional meal at a restaurant. Meets Sunday at 2:45 p.m. in Brooklyn at the corner of Brighton Beach and Coney Island Avenues. Fee, $5, plus $5 for food. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information and meeting places: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''COLLECTOR'S SHOW OF THE WORLD'S FAIRS: CELEBRATE THE THREE NEW YORK WORLD'S FAIRS OF 1853, 1939-40 and 1964-65,'' a bus and walking tour that features stops at the locations of the fairs: Bryant Park in 1853, and Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, in 1939-40 and 1964-65. Meets Sunday at 9 a.m. at the southeast corner of Avenue of the Americas and 42nd Street. Fee, $30, includes all admissions and transportation. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
