<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yonkers Girl, 3, Found Safe After Abduction, Police Say</title>
    <meta content="02ABDU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E5DB103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yonkers Girl, 3, Found Safe After Abduction, Police Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three-year-old girl turns up in Harlem, unhurt but terrified, after she was abducted from outside her grandmother's house in Yonkers, NY, by seven armed men this morning; police are searching for suspects and motive (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 3-year-old girl turned up in Harlem, unhurt but terrified, after she was abducted from her grandmother by seven armed men this morning.</p>
        <p>A passer-by told police that the girl, who had been taken from outside the grandmother's house here, was dropped off by a black car at the corner of Bradhurst Avenue and 149th Street shortly before noon. The police took her to a nearby precinct, where she was later reunited with her mother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 3-year-old girl turned up in Harlem, unhurt but terrified, after she was abducted from her grandmother by seven armed men this morning.</p>
        <p>A passer-by told police that the girl, who had been taken from outside the grandmother's house here, was dropped off by a black car at the corner of Bradhurst Avenue and 149th Street shortly before noon. The police took her to a nearby precinct, where she was later reunited with her mother.</p>
        <p>The Yonkers police commissioner, Charles A. Cola, said the police were still looking for the seven suspects and had not ruled out any motives. ''We always look at drugs first,'' he said. ''But there could be other motives, like custody or robbery.''</p>
        <p>It was not clear how or even whether the 36-year-old grandmother knew her assailants.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Cola said the woman was driving with the child on McLean Avenue, not far from her house in the Park Hill section of Yonkers, when two cars boxed in her car. Two of the seven men, who were all armed with handguns, then got into her car, a Honda Accord, and drove her and the child to her house on Park Hill Avenue while the five others followed, the police said.</p>
        <p>There, an unarmed man whom police described as an occupant of the house came outside and confronted the seven men, who then grabbed the girl and fled in another car. ''He just showed his face, and they bolted,'' Commissioner Cola said of the occupant. ''Obviously, they were intimidated by that male.''</p>
        <p>Neighbors identified the grandmother as Minerva Robles, the owner of a hair salon who had been renting the bottom floor of the two-family house since February. They described the man who confronted the abductors as her boyfriend or husband. The two of them lived with the 3-year-old girl and her 10-year-old brother. The girl's mother visited the house occasionally, they said.</p>
        <p>Joan Horgan, a real estate agent and Ms. Robles's neighbor, who found her the apartment, said she and the man, who is in his 20's, stood out in the modest neighborhood for their four cars, including a new Lexus and Toyota Landcruiser, as well as their motorized water scooter.</p>
        <p>Police from New York City, Yonkers and Westchester County searched the area for the suspects, both on foot and in helicopters, and temporarily closed a nearby stretch of the Saw Mill River Parkway. At least a dozen officers descended on the house in the early afternoon with police dogs, and Ms. Robles and her companion left with police.</p>
        <p>Residents in the Park Hill section, a neighborhood in southwest Yonkers with an unusual mix of two-family houses and stately Colonials, said they were shocked by the kidnapping.</p>
        <p>''This is a little enclave with nice neighbors and nice houses,'' said Deborah Holcombe, a medical technician who is vice president of the Park Hill Residents Association. ''People make an effort to respect each other and each other's property.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
