<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Vendors Charged With Price Fixing</title>
    <meta content="02BIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lunch and Breakfast Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4DD103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Vendors Charged With Price Fixing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Department charges more than dozen food vendors that supply New York City schools with rigging prices on multimillion dollar contracts for produce and frozen foods; Federal prosecutors charge that 13 contractors conspired to fix prices for more than $210 million in food contracts for city schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department yesterday charged more than a dozen food vendors that supply New York City schools with rigging prices on multimillion dollar contracts for produce and frozen foods.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors charged that 13 contractors conspired to fix prices for more than $210 million in food contracts for the city schools. They said that part of the price-fixing arrangement lasted nearly a decade. Six of the 13 companies have agreed to plead guilty and cooperate with the investigation, prosecutors said. They said 22 officers and employees of the companies have also been charged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department yesterday charged more than a dozen food vendors that supply New York City schools with rigging prices on multimillion dollar contracts for produce and frozen foods.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors charged that 13 contractors conspired to fix prices for more than $210 million in food contracts for the city schools. They said that part of the price-fixing arrangement lasted nearly a decade. Six of the 13 companies have agreed to plead guilty and cooperate with the investigation, prosecutors said. They said 22 officers and employees of the companies have also been charged.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors estimated that the vendors inflated prices of the food contracts by about 10 percent, or roughly $21 million for the entire scheme.</p>
        <p>''This money should have been spent on the schoolchildren of New York, not to line the pockets of greedy vendors,'' Joel L. Klein, assistant attorney general for the antitrust division, said in a statement on the charges.</p>
        <p>Justice Department officials said that some of the vendors were also charged in another bid-rigging conspiracy involving other city agencies, including city hospitals, jails and homeless shelters. City contracting officials said yesterday that four of the companies accused in the Board of Education case also sold to those city agencies.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Manhattan yesterday afternoon, Mr. Klein said that as a graduate of Brooklyn public schools, he was personally offended by the evidence of ''despicable behavior'' uncovered by federal agents.</p>
        <p>''To see people come in and rip off these schools that are trying to do a good job really tugs at one,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said the companies charged with the bid rigging included almost all of the Board of Education's suppliers of frozen food, like fish sticks, meats and french fries, as well as most suppliers of fresh produce.</p>
        <p>The Board of Education has known about the investigation for nearly six months, and has been working on a contingency plan to ensure that food delivery to the schools would not be interrupted, board officials said yesterday. The board has also hired an independent monitor to oversee the operations of all food vendors. Chad Vignola, general counsel to the chancellor, said the board would continue to do business with some of the companies ''as we attempt to work our way through this problem.''</p>
        <p>''Obviously, the reason we would continue to do business with a company is that it is under an independent monitor,'' he said.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, finding new vendors could prove to be very difficult, mainly because the board is such a large and complex customer. The city schools supply meals to 1.1 million children in the public system as well as children in some parochial and private schools. The board serves over 800,000 meals each day during the school year and 300,000 a day during the summer, spending $250 million each year on food. It is the second-largest food buyer in the country, after the Defense Department.</p>
        <p>Other city agencies buy about $70 million worth of food each year, with most of that going to hospitals and city jails. Claude M. Millman, director of the mayor's office of contracts, said the city would probably continue to use the charged vendors for several weeks while it searched for new contractors.</p>
        <p>The question of whether a vendor can continue to hold a city contract after being charged with a crime is not clear-cut. Mr. Vignola said it depends on several factors, including the seriousness of the charges, the evidence against the company and efforts the company has taken to correct the problems.</p>
        <p>''In some cases, the city continues to do business with entities that have been convicted of crimes,'' he said. Typically, he added, those companies have taken drastic steps to address the situation, like selling the business to new management or firing the employees responsible for the crime.</p>
        <p>In the past, the city has allowed companies charged with crimes to continue to maintain city contracts as long as they pay for an independent monitor to oversee their operations, said David Neustadt, a spokesman for the city comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi. He said the comptroller's office has recommended that the Board of Education follow that course in dealing with the food vendors.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said yesterday that they have not uncovered any incidents of bribery or public corruption in the case. Instead, they said, the conspiracy involved vendors agreeing to submit false bids to stifle competition for the food contracts. The prosecutors said that vendors would designate one company as the low bidder for a particular contract and would arrange their bids so that the designated company would win.</p>
        <p>Barry W. Mawn, the assistant director in charge of the F.B.I. in New York, said the investigation, which began about 18 months ago, established that the vendors secretly controlled the prices on many of the contracts.</p>
        <p>''They had secret meetings,'' he said. ''They had secret agreements.''</p>
        <p>''They used the tactics to control the marketplace and to stifle competition.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein said the Justice Department heard allegations of bid rigging in the school food contracts while working on a case several years ago that involved drug rehabilitation companies. He said it would have been extremely difficult for city officials to uncover the bid rigging without such inside information.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department said in a statement that the companies charged included: the Nick Penachio Company; Irving Libertoff Inc.; West Side Foods Inc.; M &amp; F Meat Products Inc.; DiCarlo Distributors Inc.; FHR Inc.; the Landmark Food Corporation; Loeb &amp; Mayer Inc.; Food Service Purchasing Agency Inc.; A. Bohrer Inc.; Kanowitz Fruit &amp; Produce; Clifton Fruit &amp; Produce; and the Baiardi Chain Food Corporation.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the lawyer for one of the companies, the Nick Penachio Company, said the firm would work to resolve the suit in a responsible way. Gerald Shargel, the lawyer, said the company holds a contract with the city's Board of Education and expects to retain it.</p>
        <p>''Nick Penachio Corporation has been a responsible corporate citizen for 63 years,'' he said. ''The company will survive and the business will continue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
