<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Impressionism in Its Hour of Sunlit Bliss</title>
    <meta content="02COTT$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Gallery of Art (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotter, Holland</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DC133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1419" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Impressionism in Its Hour of Sunlit Bliss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Holland Cotter reviews National Gallery exhibition The Impressionists at Argenteuil; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S always high noon on a bright June day in the well-tailored Paris suburb of Argenteuil. Or so one gathers from the pearly exhibition titled ''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' at the National Gallery of Art.</p>
        <p>The show is, of course, the umpteenth repackaging of an evergreen late-19th-century painting style. But scolding this art for being popular is by now a cliche in itself. Better to give it a fresh squint, admiring its manifest beauties but also suggesting what made it daring in its day and what can make it a complex experience still.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S always high noon on a bright June day in the well-tailored Paris suburb of Argenteuil. Or so one gathers from the pearly exhibition titled ''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' at the National Gallery of Art.</p>
        <p>The show is, of course, the umpteenth repackaging of an evergreen late-19th-century painting style. But scolding this art for being popular is by now a cliche in itself. Better to give it a fresh squint, admiring its manifest beauties but also suggesting what made it daring in its day and what can make it a complex experience still.</p>
        <p>This is what, in a quiet way, the Washington exhibition does. As organized by Paul Hayes Tucker, it takes 50 or so works by familiar figures -- Monet, Renoir, Sisley -- and passes them through an astringent solution of social and personal history, focusing on a single place where these artists spent some of their most innovative and prolific years.</p>
        <p>Argenteuil, a few miles from Paris, was a bourgeois town of a few thousand people when Monet moved there in 1871. Known for its gypsum deposits, asparagus beds and a cheap, bad wine, it was built on the banks of the Seine at a point where the river widened and deepened, making it an ideal site for both industry and aquatic sports. (It was famous for its sailing regattas.)</p>
        <p>To Monet, who had spent the previous year in England to escape the Franco-Prussian War, it seemed like a little paradise. He was 31 when he arrived with his wife, Camille, and their young son. His reputation as a vanguard painter was secure. He had money in his pocket from painting sales. He was ready to settle down.</p>
        <p>And Argenteuil seemed like the place to do it. It was quiet and verdant but a quick train ride from Paris; village-cozy but also urbane and entrepreneurial. Monet saw himself as a landscape painter of the modern world, and the right balance of ingredients, old and new, was here: glorious river views criss-crossed by railroad bridges, horizon lines broken by smokestacks and church steeples.</p>
        <p>Whatever he saw seemed to enchant him. He painted the town's main commercial strip, standing in the middle of the street to do so, and depicted the scaffolding of a reconstructed highway bridge with an engineer's precision. He captured strollers along the Seine in early summer, then turned his attention to the lush garden in his own backyard.</p>
        <p>The earliest garden painting, from 1872, is a kind of controlled delirium, as if fragrance had somehow been mixed with pigment. Lilacs are in flower, the pink blossoms so profuse that leaves are barely visible. Two figures sit on the grass. The one in white is Camille, who is knitting; the other, a woman in a butter-yellow gown, holds a parasol against the noon sun. The scene is a triumph of suburban well-being. It is also a magical, Watteauvian place, where a patch of blue sky descends to caress the hem of a dress.</p>
        <p>Camille appears again in a sumptuous portrait by Renoir. Here she is indoors reading, but still in garden mode, surrounded by pillows covered in a splashy floral print fabric. Renoir was one of several painters (Sisley was the first) who visited the Monet home, which functioned as a kind of Impressionist headquarters. He stayed for long stretches, working side by side with his host. Other artists, like Pissarro and Cezanne, made only brief appearances. The aggressively bourgeois Argenteuil just wasn't their scene.</p>
        <p>And Manet showed up. A celebrity and a confirmed urbanite, he realized that his younger colleagues were taking art in new directions, and he didn't want to be left behind. Reigning in his natural competitiveness, he followed Monet's plein-air lead, and the results, as seen in the show, were memorable.</p>
        <p>The iconic, erotically charged ''Boating,'' painted, or at least begun, at Argenteuil, is here. So is a large oil sketch of Monet and Camille on loan from the Staatsgalerie in Stuttgart. Can anything personal be read into the fact that her features are deftly notated while her husband's are rendered as a defacing smear? Apparently not: Manet gave the sketch to Monet, who treasured it.</p>
        <p>Finally, there was Gustave Caillebotte. A boating fanatic who bought a home across the river from Argenteuil, he was best known in his day as a collector: the Impressionist paintings he owned now form the core holdings of the Musee d'Orsay. But he was also an artist, and an interesting one.</p>
        <p>He was a funny sort of Impressionist. By inclination a figurative painter, he carried his feel for solid forms into landscapes. When he depicts the shadow of a bridge on water, it has the heft of an iron bar. In his near-abstract painting ''Yellow Fields at Gennevilliers,'' beds of flowers lie side by side like deep-pile carpets.</p>
        <p>No two pieces by him in the show look alike, but none could have been done by anyone else. It's as if some resistance to Impressionism's de materializing impulse made his engagement with the style an experiment every time. In his wonderful picture of the Paris newspaper editor Richard Gallo walking by the Seine with a poodle, the two sides of his art come together yet remain distinct. The water reflections are all pure Impressionist scintillation. But Gallo, in his dark coat and bowler, is solid as a rock.</p>
        <p>By the time Caillebotte painted this picture in 1884, Monet was long gone from the area. After a few rapturous years, his attitude toward Argenteuil had soured. The air of progress he once found stimulating had become an irritant. Tourism and industry, heavily promoted, were increasing. The population was becoming working class.</p>
        <p>In 1874 he depicted the town's new railroad bridge as if it were a Greek temple, its massive supports crisp, white and majestic. But gradually he turned to more escapist, pastoral subjects. The parklike setting in ''Ball-Shaped Tree, Argenteuil'' (1876), for example, an exotic salad of lavender, orange and green, might have come from Fragonard.</p>
        <p>During his early days, he often recorded the dynamic riverside scene with its smoke-spewing factories and day-tripping ladies and gents from inside a covered boat he used as a floating studio. This is where Manet sketched him, in the modern thick of things, looking dapper and larky in a straw hat and a billowy shirt. In 1874 Monet himself painted the boat. Moored offshore in still water, it looks like a hermit's retreat, fragile and somewhat forlorn.</p>
        <p>More and more, the artist stuck to his garden, and in ''Argenteuil, the Bank in Flower'' (1877), he envisions the town as a distant hallucination, steaming away in a hot summer glow and viewed from behind the protective barrier of a hedge of flowers. A year later, he moved out, first to Vetheuil, then farther on to Giverny, some 40 miles from Paris, where he lived in a vegetative Eden of his own making until he died.</p>
        <p>Monet's retreat is in some sense our retreat at the beginning of the 21st century; his conflicted view of the world is our view, too. We love his paintings for their reassurances that the material world is real, and enough, and belongs to us. And we're grateful for what they don't say, at least on the surface, about disintegration, darkness, things ending.</p>
        <p>In reality, Impressionism was thinking about all of these things -- the frozen sun-drenched moment, the clock moving past the hour -- all the time, just as we are. Each intelligent new presentation, and the Washington show is one, reveals this art's depths along with its pleasures. Surely that's why we keep coming back for more.</p>
        <p>''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' remains at the National Gallery of Art, Fourth Street at Constitution Avenue, N.W., Washington, (202) 737-4215, through Aug. 20. It will travel to the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art in Hartford (Sept. 9 to Dec. 3).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
