<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and 28 States Plan Attack Against Promissory-Note Fraud</title>
    <meta content="02FRAU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">IRM Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fucilo, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tomshaw, Tiber</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McNerlin, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0DC103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and 28 States Plan Attack Against Promissory-Note Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal and state authorities say they will join forces in fighting fixed-rate investment frauds that bilk thousands of American investors, particularly older people, out of hundreds of millions of dollars a year; cases involve promissory notes--investments that typically involve loan to a company in exchange for fixed rate of return; officials estimate that more than 3,000 Americans were victims of promissory-note fraud last year; Securities and Exchange Commission and 28 attorneys general say they plan to dedicate more resources to investigation and prosecution of these cases; regulators in Michigan brought charges earlier this year against IRM Corp, accusing it of bilking 2,435 people out of more than $82 million through fraudulent promissory-note investments; in New York, prosecutors working for Attorney General Eliot Spitzer, file civil suit against two insurance agents in Kingston, NY, Frank Fucilo and Tiber Tomshaw; James McNerlin of Kingston explains how he lost $103,000 investing with Fucilo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal and state authorities said yesterday that they would join forces in fighting fixed-rate investment frauds that bilk thousands of Americans, particularly older people, out of hundreds of millions of dollars a year.</p>
        <p>The cases involve promissory notes -- investments that typically involve a loan to a company in exchange for a fixed rate of return. Officials estimated that more than 3,000 Americans were victims of promissory-note frauds last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal and state authorities said yesterday that they would join forces in fighting fixed-rate investment frauds that bilk thousands of Americans, particularly older people, out of hundreds of millions of dollars a year.</p>
        <p>The cases involve promissory notes -- investments that typically involve a loan to a company in exchange for a fixed rate of return. Officials estimated that more than 3,000 Americans were victims of promissory-note frauds last year.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission and 28 attorneys general said they planned to dedicate more resources to the investigation and prosecution of these cases. So far, the cases have received little attention and have been hampered by the difficulty of proving that many participants were knowingly involved in deceptions.</p>
        <p>''These promissory-note scams have cost investors tens of millions of dollars,'' said Brad Skolnik, the Indiana securities commissioner, and president of the North American Association of Securities Administrators. Working together, he said, the states and the S.E.C. can use their resources to prevent the suspects in such frauds from eluding regulators by moving from state to state.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. announced that it had recently filed 13 enforcement actions against 38 individuals and 22 companies accused of defrauding investors of more than $300 million in total. State regulators have also filed scores of cases in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Some business leaders have quietly objected to the initiative, reported yesterday in USA Today, because they fear that it may scare people away from legitimate promissory-note investments.</p>
        <p>In the schemes, bogus companies often enlist insurance agents or brokers, who sometimes do not even know that they are taking part, to persuade clients to make large investments ostensibly guaranteeing high returns, law enforcement officials said.</p>
        <p>The investors are generally given notes that are said to insure the returns through offshore insurance companies. But in most cases, the issuers in fact have no such insurance, nor do they have collateral or other ways to guarantee payment.</p>
        <p>The swindlers often focus on affluent older people, leading to a high number of cases in states like California, Florida, New York and Arizona, officials said.</p>
        <p>''There is a certain demographic that people go after,'' said Myles Edwards, senior adviser for industry compliance and enforcement matters at the North American Association of Securities Administrators, ''and older Americans are often more trusting -- especially when it is someone they have dealt with before, like an insurance agent. And the problem is growing.''</p>
        <p>The particularly insidious element of the promissory-note schemes, the authorities say, is that the elderly are often defrauded by people with whom they have successfully done business in the past.</p>
        <p>For example, regulators in Michigan brought charges earlier this year against the IRM Corporation, accusing it of bilking 2,435 people out of more than $82 million through fraudulent promissory-note investments in real estate and limited partnerships.</p>
        <p>In New York State, prosecutors working for Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer filed a civil suit yesterday in State Supreme Court in Manhattan against two insurance agents in Kingston, N.Y., Frank Fucilo, 68, and Tiber Tomshaw, 52.</p>
        <p>The suit accuses them of swindling 69 people, most of them elderly, out of more than $3.8 million in a promissory-note scheme that included making investments in petroleum, entertainment, technology and transportation companies. Mr. Fucilo's lawyer declined to comment, and Mr. Tomshaw's lawyer did not return telephone calls.</p>
        <p>James McNerlin, 68, a retired businessman in Kingston, said he lost $103,000 after Mr. Fucilo, who had helped him with his retirement account and other investments, persuaded him to invest in the Red Bank Petroleum Company of Dallas. The company went bankrupt and the insurance that backed the promissory notes proved not to exist.</p>
        <p>''You never expect this to happen to anyone,'' Mr. McNerlin said yesterday, ''especially when you have dealt with the person before and he gives you a promissory note that says you can't lose anything. You feel -- you really feel embarrassed. Who wants to say that you lost $300,000 at the click of a finger? I am not the only one; there are a lot of people getting scammed like this.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer called the case an example of the ''the worst kind of scam'' that ''preyed on people who had placed their trust in them through their insurance dealings,'' and he pledged to increase efforts to go after the suspects in such cases.</p>
        <p>But officials said this case also underlined some of the difficulties they have had in prosecuting promissory-note schemes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tomshaw and Mr. Fucilo, both longtime insurance agents in Kingston, about 100 miles north of New York City, offered clients a chance to invest in several start-up companies, prosecutors said, holding out a ''risk-free, guaranteed return of 10.5 percent'' on their money within nine months.</p>
        <p>Many of the victims cashed life insurance policies, retirement savings and college education funds for their children, which all offered much lower returns. Mr. Fucilo and Mr. Tomshaw collected commissions totaling $366,000 from Saferate Financial Services, a California company that enlisted the two men, according to the suit.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say they have so far been unable to bring criminal charges against Mr. Fucilo and Mr. Tomshaw because of the difficulty in proving that they were knowing participants in the scheme.</p>
        <p>''We have to prove that they knew what they were doing was a basic scheme to defraud,'' an official said. ''We have to prove that they knew that everything they said was untrue, that the investment was bad and that the money was not really insured.''</p>
        <p>In the civil suit, Mr. Fucilo and Mr. Tomshaw are both accused of fraud, failure to register as brokers and making unsuitable investment recommendations. At this point, the same reasons make it difficult for the attorney general's office to file criminal charges against Saferate or any of the other companies involved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer said yesterday that he would like to recover the $366,000 that Mr. Tomshaw and Mr. Fucilo received, as well as the rest of the money that went to Saferate.</p>
        <p>''We have to work vigorously to trace the proceeds and recover some of the millions of dollars that were lost,'' the attorney general added. ''We want to stop people from preying on people whom they have developed a relationship of trust with.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
