<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Final Ruling in Microsoft Antitrust Case Is Unexpectedly Delayed for About a Week</title>
    <meta content="Y02SOF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Thomas Penfield (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DC103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Final Ruling in Microsoft Antitrust Case Is Unexpectedly Delayed for About a Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson, who is trying Microsoft Corp antitrust case, unexpectedly agrees to delay his final ruling for about a week, giving Justice Department time to reply to Microsoft's proposal to water down government's breakup plan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal judge trying the Microsoft antitrust case unexpectedly agreed to delay his final ruling for about a week today, giving the Justice Department time to reply to Microsoft's proposal to water down the government's breakup plan.</p>
        <p>The judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, had planned to issue his final ruling, widely expected to call for a breakup of the company, today or Friday. But Justice Department officials called him this morning to ask if they could reply to Microsoft's comments on the government's remedy proposal; the comments were filed with the court on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal judge trying the Microsoft antitrust case unexpectedly agreed to delay his final ruling for about a week today, giving the Justice Department time to reply to Microsoft's proposal to water down the government's breakup plan.</p>
        <p>The judge, Thomas Penfield Jackson, had planned to issue his final ruling, widely expected to call for a breakup of the company, today or Friday. But Justice Department officials called him this morning to ask if they could reply to Microsoft's comments on the government's remedy proposal; the comments were filed with the court on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The comments were supposed to be the final filing in the case, the last step before Judge Jackson's ruling. But in a conference call this morning with Microsoft and the government, Judge Jackson gave the Justice Department until Monday to respond, and Microsoft until Wednesday to file a counterresponse. His ruling will probably come almost immediately after that.</p>
        <p>During the remedy hearing in Judge Jackson's courtroom on May 24, the judge asked the federal and state governments that are partners in the suit to file a final ''clean'' version of their remedy proposal by May 26. The plaintiffs agreed, but a Microsoft lawyer, John Warden, then said the company wanted an opportunity to ''comment on the form of the proposed decree prior to its entry.''</p>
        <p>Another Microsoft lawyer, Steven Holley, said outside the courthouse later that ''comment on the form'' meant looking for typographical errors and ''internal inconsistencies'' in the government plan.</p>
        <p>Instead, Microsoft's response heavily revised the government proposal -- gutting it, in the view of some government officials. Some proposals the government viewed as important were deleted, others were eviscerated, and the timetables for carrying them out were lengthened -- doubled in some cases.</p>
        <p>The government plan would create two new companies; one would hold the Windows operating systems, the other everything else, including the Office suite of programs like Word for word processing and Excel for spreadsheet calculations. It would also impose restrictions on the company's conduct that would remain in place while the breakup was being carried out.</p>
        <p>Microsoft's brief explained that the changes were necessary because the government proposal ''is vague and ambiguous in numerous respects,'' littered with ''many flaws.''</p>
        <p>''Were the court to accept all of Microsoft's proposed changes,'' the brief continued, ''the government's proposed final judgment would be improved, but much of the vagueness and ambiguity would remain because it is inherent in the structure of document.''</p>
        <p>A Microsoft spokesman, Mark Murray, said, ''We view our revisions as putting lipstick on a pig.''</p>
        <p>Vivek Varma, another Microsoft spokesman representing the legal department, said Mr. Warden ''had not misspoken'' in court. But ''we had every intention of showing the inadequacies, including substantively, in the government's proposed order,'' particularly since Judge Jackson rejected Microsoft's request for remedy hearings.</p>
        <p>During the conference call this morning, David Boies, the government's lead trial lawyer in the case, told the judge that the Justice Department had found at least a few useful comments among the dozens of proposed revisions in the Microsoft brief.</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Murray leapt on that, saying, ''They told the court that there wasn't any need for additional remedies hearings, and now it turns out that there were defects and problems with their proposal.''</p>
        <p>One participant in the call said Judge Jackson was irritated by the request for further delay; he has repeatedly said he wants to conclude the case quickly and allow it go forward on appeal. But in the end, he acceded to the request, after winning assurance from both sides that this would be the final delay.</p>
        <p>Gina Talamona, a spokesman for the Justice Department, said, ''We believed that it was appropriate to request a short opportunity to comment on Microsoft's specific changes, both to determine whether there are a few that we can accept without undermining our remedy proposal, while also offering our reasoning for urging rejection by the court of the others.''</p>
        <p>In its filing on Monday, the Justice Department is certain to oppose most of the substantive changes, like Microsoft's proposal to delete the prohibition on continuing to offer special marketing deals to certain computer manufacturers. In his ruling, Judge Jackson found that Microsoft had used the special deals to reward cooperative companies and punish others that did not follow Microsoft's directions on issues of importance to the company.</p>
        <p>But the department may choose to take into account Microsoft's concerns about the timetable for the breakup plan. Microsoft noted that the company would have to win approval for elements of the plan from several federal agencies, including the Securities and Exchange Commission and the Internal Revenue Service, as well as governments of countries where the company has subsidiary offices.</p>
        <p>''Obtaining such approvals,'' the Microsoft brief said, ''would be a time-consuming process.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
