<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Literature's Greatest Hits: Instructions for Users</title>
    <meta content="02BOOK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloom, Harold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">How to Read and Why (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDF133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Literature's Greatest Hits: Instructions for Users</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews book How to Read and Why by Harold Bloom; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW TO READ AND WHY</p>
        <p>By Harold Bloom</p>
        <p>283 pages. Scribner. $25.</p>
        <p>Not so long ago, it would have seemed preposterous for a serious scholar to bother writing a book titled ''How to Read and Why,'' but in our digital, image-driven age, the eminent teacher and critic Harold Bloom apparently feels it is necessary to reiterate the reasons why we read. The resulting book, like so many of the author's recent works, is a hodgepodge of erudite analysis, familiar arguments, pompous grandstanding and lengthy digressions; it might well have been subtitled ''My Favorite Books and Why I Like Them.''</p>
        <p>Most of the reasons Mr. Bloom gives for reading will be obvious to anyone who loves books: that we read to ''enlarge life,'' to enter an ''alternate reality,'' to be ''liberated into perspectives not previously available'' to us. We read for knowledge -- of the world, of others and of ourselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW TO READ AND WHY</p>
        <p>By Harold Bloom</p>
        <p>283 pages. Scribner. $25.</p>
        <p>Not so long ago, it would have seemed preposterous for a serious scholar to bother writing a book titled ''How to Read and Why,'' but in our digital, image-driven age, the eminent teacher and critic Harold Bloom apparently feels it is necessary to reiterate the reasons why we read. The resulting book, like so many of the author's recent works, is a hodgepodge of erudite analysis, familiar arguments, pompous grandstanding and lengthy digressions; it might well have been subtitled ''My Favorite Books and Why I Like Them.''</p>
        <p>Most of the reasons Mr. Bloom gives for reading will be obvious to anyone who loves books: that we read to ''enlarge life,'' to enter an ''alternate reality,'' to be ''liberated into perspectives not previously available'' to us. We read for knowledge -- of the world, of others and of ourselves.</p>
        <p>''Why read?'' Mr. Bloom asks. ''Because you can know, intimately, only a very few people, and perhaps you never know them at all. After reading 'The Magic Mountain' you know Hans Castorp thoroughly, and he is greatly worth knowing.''</p>
        <p>Other reasons that Mr. Bloom offers for reading are less persuasive, couched, as they are, in the utilitarian -- and for this author unlikely -- language of a self-help manual. We read, he writes, ''to strengthen the self, and to learn its authentic interests.'' Poems, he contends, ''can help us to speak to ourselves more clearly and more fully, and to overhear that speaking,'' while novels can treat the ''dark inertia, the sickness-unto-death'' we experience in daily life. ''Our despair requires consolation,'' he adds, ''and the medicine of a profound narration.''</p>
        <p>Though such observations on the how and whys of reading are supposedly this book's raison d'etre, they actually feel like afterthoughts, grafted onto a meandering discussion of works of literature Mr. Bloom admires. Among others, he talks about short stories by Turgenev, Chekhov, Hemingway and Calvino; poems by Tennyson, Dickinson, Wordsworth and Keats; novels by Austen, Dickens, Proust and Mann; and plays by Shakespeare, Ibsen and Wilde. Mr. Bloom, who is Sterling Professor of Humanities at Yale University and Berg Professor of English at New York University, explicates such authors' works as if he were lecturing to a class, setting forth his prodigiously learned but often arbitrary judgments with sweeping grandiosity.</p>
        <p>As he did in his 1994 magnum opus, ''The Western Canon,'' Mr. Bloom demonstrates his taste in these pages for categorizing literary works and ranking them in strict hierarchies. He declares that modern short stories are either Chekhovian or Borgesian, the first gratifying ''our hunger for reality,'' the second teaching us ''how ravenous we still are for what is beyond supposed reality.'' He asserts that ''Don Quixote'' is the best of all novels, and that Cormac McCarthy's ''Blood Meridian'' is ''the strongest imaginative work by any living American writer.'' As for human nature, he suggests that all people -- not to mention all literary characters -- can be divided into four types: Hamlets, Falstaffs, Don Quixotes or Sancho Panzas.</p>
        <p>The author of ''The Anxiety of Influence'' (1973), Mr. Bloom is perhaps best known for his Freudian theory of poetic influence, which suggests that writers are shaped by their Oedipal struggle to free themselves from the legacy of their literary forefathers, and this volume underscores what a fierce hold this theory still exerts over his critical imagination.</p>
        <p>Indeed, ''How to Read and Why'' often reads like a complicated genealogical chart, with virtually every writer eventually tracing his lineage back to Shakespeare, Mr. Bloom's all-time hero and the subject of his last book, ''Shakespeare: The Invention of the Human.'' Apparently it's not only Dostoyevsky who took character-writing lessons from Shakespeare, but Chekhov, too; and Chekhov, in turn, Mr. Bloom argues, was ''the major influence upon all story writers after him.'' Novelists who write about characters who change -- that is, characters who evolve in the course of the story -- also owe a debt to Shakespeare, Mr. Bloom contends; included in this group, he says, are writers like Austen, Goethe, Stendhal, Philip Roth and Cormac McCarthy.</p>
        <p>In another chapter, Mr. Bloom points out Melville's considerable debts to Shakespeare, comparing Ahab to the likes of King Lear and Macbeth, and he goes on to argue that writers as disparate as Faulkner, Nathanael West, Thomas Pynchon, Ralph Ellison and Toni Morrison ''are Melville's children.''</p>
        <p>Though this sort of genealogical analysis can illuminate certain writers' evolution, it can also obscure genuine differences in their voices and their visions, and the ways they have been shaped by the cultural zeitgeist of their day.</p>
        <p>In this volume, Mr. Bloom is so obsessive on the subject that he sees influence everywhere he looks -- never mind whether that influence is so vague as to seem illusory, or whether it actually sheds light on a writer's work.</p>
        <p>He contends that Hemingway ''is most Shakespearean'' when he ''is most ambitious in his stories,'' as in the case of the quasi-autobiographical ''Snows of Kilimanjaro.'' He insists that ''Turgenev is one of the most Shakespearean of writers in that he too refrains from moral judgments.''</p>
        <p>And he argues that Coleridge's ''Rime of the Ancient Mariner'' is ''Shakespearean in its detachment of tone.''</p>
        <p>There are other problems with this book as well. Many of Mr. Bloom's assessments of individual writers and larger cultural developments are debatable at best.</p>
        <p>He highhandedly declares that ''literary parody expired'' with Nathanael West. And he contends that contemporary culture suffers from a ''loss of irony,'' rather than a surfeit.</p>
        <p>More alarmingly, he repeatedly asserts that writers like Milton and  Wallace Stevens ''require mediation'' if the lay reader is to understand them. There is the suggestion in such remarks that there is only one way to read such writers, and that most people need someone like Harold Bloom to tell them how to do it. Such an outlook manages to be patronizing and self-congratulatory all at the same time.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
