<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Crude Even Daddy the Porn King Disapproves</title>
    <meta content="02VIRG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marois, Jean-Pierre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suvari, Mena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loggia, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoskins, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Live Virgin (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DD133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Crude Even Daddy the Porn King Disapproves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Live Virgin, directed by Jean-Pierre Marois; Bob Hoskins, Robbert Loggia and Mena Suvari star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here's a conundrum: How can a movie effectively satirize the bottom-feeding world of talk show television without stooping to its level of prurience and being as crude and boisterous as a roaring, profanity-spattered brawl on ''The Jerry Springer Show''? The answer, of course, is that it can't. But that's not necessarily a bad thing as long as the movie wears its nose-thumbing attitude on its sleeve.</p>
        <p>During much of ''Live Virgin,'' the farcical tale of a Los Angeles pornography kingpin who goes on the warpath after his rebellious daughter arranges to be deflowered (for $200,000) on her 18th birthday on pay-per-view television, the movie's blunt sexual humor succeeds in staying one outrageous step ahead of Mr. Springer. Only at the end, when the movie retracts its bloody claws and opts for a halfheartedly sentimental conclusion, does ''Live Virgin'' lose its considerable nerve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here's a conundrum: How can a movie effectively satirize the bottom-feeding world of talk show television without stooping to its level of prurience and being as crude and boisterous as a roaring, profanity-spattered brawl on ''The Jerry Springer Show''? The answer, of course, is that it can't. But that's not necessarily a bad thing as long as the movie wears its nose-thumbing attitude on its sleeve.</p>
        <p>During much of ''Live Virgin,'' the farcical tale of a Los Angeles pornography kingpin who goes on the warpath after his rebellious daughter arranges to be deflowered (for $200,000) on her 18th birthday on pay-per-view television, the movie's blunt sexual humor succeeds in staying one outrageous step ahead of Mr. Springer. Only at the end, when the movie retracts its bloody claws and opts for a halfheartedly sentimental conclusion, does ''Live Virgin'' lose its considerable nerve.</p>
        <p>Until that moment, ''Live Virgin,'' which opens today at the AMC Empire 25, should tickle the revenge fantasies of anyone who has chortled in disgust at the hypocrisy of a format that peddles freak show voyeurism in the guise of truth and emotional healing. The movie's ruthless porn merchants and talk show personnel, who suddenly turn pious when what they do for a living comes too close to home, are skewered with a mockery as funny as it is scalding.</p>
        <p>''Live Virgin'' adds an extra blip of futuristic fantasy by having the pay-per-view customers, whom it portrays as panting, sex-starved geeks, buy special outfits in which they wire themselves through the telephone to have a vicariously ''authentic'' sexual experience. For in the world of ''Live Virgin,'' technology has advanced to the point where it is possible to have remote-control intercourse through electrical stimulation and body-part attachments. The process, which isn't spelled out, is clearly the next step in home entertainment beyond virtual reality. In a nifty comic touch, these auto-erotic body suits make those who wear them look like space travelers dressed as Kermit the Frog.</p>
        <p>The movie's casting coup is having the rebel daughter, Katrina, played by Mena Suvari, who was so memorable as a potty-mouthed, pseudosophisticated Lolita in ''American Beauty.'' In that movie, Ms. Suvari was the sultry blond incarnation of every middle-aged man's lustful cheerleader fantasy. Here the actress, giving a performance that's not so assured as her ''American Beauty'' vixen, is brown-haired until nearly the end. Preparatory to her $200,000 payoff, she is crowned with a ludicrous black wig for a scene in which she plays a soft-core Joan of Arc being tried in a court where the aristocrats are too busy having sex to pay attention to the proceedings.</p>
        <p>''Live Virgin,'' directed by Jean-Pierre Marois from a screenplay he wrote with Ira Israel, is as tightly plotted as a standard French farce. It happens that the producer of the televised deflowering, Joey Quinn (Bob Hoskins), is the former protege and partner of Katrina's porno-king daddy, Ronny Bartoloti (Robert Loggia parodying Robert Guccione).</p>
        <p>Years earlier, Ronny stole away Joey's bimbo of a wife, Raquel (Bobbie Phillips), who is first shown whining about the rigors of plastic surgery. For years, Joey has been sexually impotent, a condition to which the movie alludes in several nastily funny comic bits. Meanwhile, Katrina is being ardently pursued by her dewy-eyed high school sweetheart, Brian (Gabriel Mann), with whom she broke up under the mistaken assumption that he had slept with another girl. Brian happens to be the son of Quaint McPherson (Sally Kellerman), the imperious talk-show host who is overseeing the television special.</p>
        <p>With her honeyed voice dripping with solicitous hauteur, Ms. Kellerman's dead-on parody of Sally Jessy Raphael by way of Diane Sawyer skewers the bogus empathy that these multimillion-dollar television personalities can turn on and off with the flick of a switch. Although Quaint is jittery with excitement about the sky-high ratings the show is expected to garner, she is absolutely mortified that her darling son should be enamored of Katrina.</p>
        <p>As ''Live Virgin'' fearlessly lurches forward (this is not a graceful movie), it takes gleeful swipes at everything and everyone in its path until its cop-out of a denouement. Had the movie had the courage to go all the way with its satire, it would have contrived a socko ending reminiscent of the Terry Southern-Mason Hoffenberg novel ''Candy.'' Oh, well, the movie still works. How unsubtle is it? The American flag flown proudly in the front yard of Ronny's Hollywood palace of a home says it all.</p>
        <p>''Live Virgin'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has nudity, profanity and many off-color jokes.</p>
        <p>LIVE VIRGIN</p>
        <p>Directed by Jean-Pierre Marois; written by Mr. Marois and Ira Israel; director of photography, Agle Egilsson; edited by Georges Klotz; production designer, Christian Wagener; produced by Aissa Djabri, Farid Lahouassa and Manuel Munz; released by Granite Releasing. At the AMC Empire 25, 42nd Street near Eighth Avenue. Running time: 87 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Bob Hoskins (Joey), Robert Loggia (Ronny), Mena Suvari (Katrina), Gabriel Mann (Brian), Bobbie Phillips (Raquel), and Sally Kellerman (Quaint).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
