<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEAL IN MIDEAST IS 'WITHIN VIEW,' CLINTON DECLARES</title>
    <meta content="02PREX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDE103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEAL IN MIDEAST IS 'WITHIN VIEW,' CLINTON DECLARES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>LISBON, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton says historic peace agreement between Israelis and Palestinians is finally 'within view,' and urges both sides to make necessary compromises to reach agreement; remarks follow meeting with Prime Ehud Barak in Lisbon, Portugal; Clinton says he will send Sec of State Madeleine K Albright to Middle East to work with leaders on narrowing gaps; will meet with Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat in Washington, and is reportedly prepared to convene three-way summit including Barak and Arafat if both sides make substantial progress; Barak accuses Palestinians of stalling in negotiations; Arafat blames Israelis; accuses them of wasting time and of not moving toward peace; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton said today that a historic peace agreement between the Israelis and Palestinians was ''within view now,'' and he urged both sides to make whatever compromises were needed to reach an agreement.</p>
        <p>In remarks after a 90-minute meeting with Israel's prime minister, Ehud Barak, in this seaside capital, Mr. Clinton also announced that he was sending Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright to the Middle East next week in an effort to ''work with both leaders on narrowing the gaps'' between them. And he said that he would meet soon with the Palestinians' leader, Yasir Arafat, in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton said today that a historic peace agreement between the Israelis and Palestinians was ''within view now,'' and he urged both sides to make whatever compromises were needed to reach an agreement.</p>
        <p>In remarks after a 90-minute meeting with Israel's prime minister, Ehud Barak, in this seaside capital, Mr. Clinton also announced that he was sending Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright to the Middle East next week in an effort to ''work with both leaders on narrowing the gaps'' between them. And he said that he would meet soon with the Palestinians' leader, Yasir Arafat, in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is also prepared to convene a three-way Camp David-style summit meeting in Washington with Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat, a senior administration official briefing reporters afterward said. But before that could happen, both sides would have to make substantial progress, the official said.</p>
        <p>''Both leaders know from me and they know from their own experience that they now have to be prepared to make an intense effort and to do things that they have not done in the past with real courage and vision if we're actually going to get a framework agreement that deals with the outstanding issues,'' said Mr. Clinton, who met with Mr. Barak before heading to Berlin for the second leg of a weeklong trip that is to be his last visit to Europe as president.</p>
        <p>The president's remarks underscored his frustration that the Israelis and Palestinians have not made more progress toward completing a final peace accord by their self-imposed deadline of Sept. 13. Negotiations in Stockholm aimed at drafting an outline for a final settlement were suspended last week after violent protests in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
        <p>That agreement is supposed to settle issues that have been unresolvable for decades: the size and shape of a Palestinian state, the future of Jerusalem and the fate of Palestinian refugees.</p>
        <p>Before the meeting today, Mr. Barak showed just how tense the atmosphere between the Israelis and Palestinians is when he accused Mr. Arafat of stalling in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>''In recent weeks, we have seen some dragging of feet in regard to the running of negotiations,'' Mr. Barak told reporters. He added, ''We are trying to initiate a major move forward.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat responded, saying it was Israel that was stalling the talks, not the Palestinians. ''They are the side that is wasting time and not moving toward peace,'' Mr. Arafat said today in Gaza.</p>
        <p>The strong language was a significant change in tone for Mr. Barak, who almost never engages in public criticism of any of his adversaries, even his political opponents at home. His comments today could have simply reflected that he is actually upset with the Palestinians and the lack of progress. Or his statement could have been part of the routine back-and-forth of public diplomacy that Mr. Barak is known to loathe, and seldom use.</p>
        <p>But his uncharacteristically strong words may have been timed to appear resolute before the Israelis just as he is apparently ready, according to leaks in the press, to make long-delayed concessions in the negotiations, which are expected to resume this weekend or sooner, though it is not yet clear where.</p>
        <p>It has also been evident from Mr. Clinton's tone during this trip just how much he wants to conclude a peace agreement between Israel and the Palestinians in the final months of his presidency, and that he is prepared to invest the time it would take to do so. On some issues, like Kosovo, European security and trade, Mr. Clinton has sounded at times as if business is over. For instance, his discussion of a proposal on a limited missile defense system lacks the passion that he brings to his discussion of peace between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''The United States will do everything we can to help them pass this milestone,'' he said in remarks made to the staff at the American Embassy in Lisbon. ''This is tough work. If it were easy somebody would have done it a long time ago. But actually, it is within view now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and his top aides on the Middle East believe that Israel's withdrawal from Lebanon a week ago has transformed the political landscape in the region and created a new opening for a breakthrough.</p>
        <p>Several times in briefing reporters, the senior administration official referred to ''the new reality'' on the ground and the ''moment'' that will not last forever.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made that clear at a news conference on Wednesday when he called the Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon ''daring,'' adding that it ''imposes a much greater sense of urgency'' on all the parties to make peace.</p>
        <p>The flurry of activity by Mr. Clinton as his presidency nears its end is reminiscent of the push for an Arab-Israeli peace by the Reagan administration in 1988. Back then, the ''moment'' to be seized was the Palestinian uprising known as the intifadeh, which prompted a new peace initiative by Secretary of State George P. Shultz.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat have said their goal is to reach agreement by mid-September. If they do not, Mr. Arafat has threatened to unilaterally declare a Palestinian state.</p>
        <p>But ''moments'' and deadlines for Middle East peace agreements come and go. After two days of meetings with Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat in Norway last November, for example, Mr. Clinton said he was beginning a ''last sprint'' for a peace settlement. At the time, the goal was to forge a ''framework'' agreement by February 2000 that would serve as a blueprint for a final peace accord.</p>
        <p>Then the deadline slipped to May. But the two sides were too far apart to do even that, and now the focus has shifted to the September deadline.</p>
        <p>As usual, administration officials were unwilling to discuss the details of the meeting between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Barak, but one senior administration official said that Mr. Clinton tried to draw out Mr. Barak on each of the outstanding issues: borders, refugees, Jerusalem and security arrangements.</p>
        <p>So far, Israel has handed over 42.9 percent of the disputed West Bank to the Palestinians. And it has agreed to turn over three Arab villages near Jerusalem to the Palestinian Authority, though that hand-over has not been completed. The most difficult issues continue to be worked out through several secret channels between the Israelis and Palestinians, with only unsubstantiated details coming through leaks to the press.</p>
        <p>For instance, one report by a Barak critic said that for a final deal to be reached, Israel will have to give up 95 percent of the West Bank, not 60 to 75 percent, which has always been the working assumption. But none of the actual details of the negotiations are being released.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright will travel to the Middle East directly from Kiev next Monday, where Mr. Clinton will meet Ukrainian leaders on the final stop of his trip, the senior administration official said. The official added that the differences are still so great that Dr. Albright would have to make another trip before there could be a three-way summit meeting in Washington.</p>
        <p>The summit meeting, if it occurs, would be modeled on the one that President Carter held at the Camp David presidential retreat in 1978 that pushed Israel and Egypt to make peace.</p>
        <p>The challenges facing Dr. Albright are not new, plus she had plenty of problems on her earlier trips to the Middle East. On her first trip there in September after Mr. Barak came to power, Dr. Albright encountered a typical snag when the Israelis and the Palestinians failed to deliver an agreement for a signing ceremony in Egypt that she had hoped to preside over.</p>
        <p>And in 1997, just two weeks after her first official visit to the Middle East, in which she urged the Israelis to take ''time out'' from expanding settlements on the West Bank, former Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu announced plans for building more housing there.</p>
        <p>The senior administration official also confirmed that the United States has agreed, at Israel's request, to earmark $50 million of Israel's $1.8 billion in United States military aid to shore up Israel's border with Lebanon. Israel estimates that a new defense line will cost between $300 million to $400 million. The withdrawal of Israel's Army from southern Lebanon last week after 18 years eliminated a buffer zone that had shielded northern Israel from attacks from Lebanese territory.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright will not stop in Syria during her trip to the Middle East, the official said. Talks between Israel and Syria collapsed in January and have not resumed despite direct talks between Mr. Clinton and President Hafez al-Assad of Syria.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mr. Clinton spoke by telephone with Mr. Arafat, who recently described the talks with Israel as deadlocked and was said to be unhappy with ideas proposed by Israel in recent talks in Sweden. Mr. Arafat ''informed President Clinton about the current situation of the peace process, especially the current stalemate and the deadlock it has reached,'' Nabil Abu Radineh, a senior aide to Arafat, told Reuters in Jerusalem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
