<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Finding A Home Onstage</title>
    <meta content="02SCIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frayn, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wellman, Mac</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auburn, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Copenhagen (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hypatia (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Proof (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Michael Frayn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DE133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Finding A Home Onstage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber Critic's Notebook comment on plays that tackle difficult scientific subjects, and audience reactions; reviews Copenhagen by Michael Frayn, Hypatia by Mac Wellman and Proof, David Auburn's new play about world of higher mathematics; playwrights comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DURING previews for ''Copenhagen,'' the playwright Michael Frayn received a letter from a woman who had just seen it. ''She said that neither she nor anyone she was with liked all the science in the show,'' Mr. Frayn recalled in a recent interview, ''and that unless I took it out it wasn't going to last long on Broadway.''</p>
        <p>There is, of course, a great deal of science not to like in ''Copenhagen,'' if that's your inclination, and indeed, anyone paying attention to word of mouth about the play is sure to hear complaints that its erudition is off-putting. It is a play, after all, about nuclear fission, the making of the atomic bomb and the esoteric concepts -- known as the uncertainty principle and complementarity -- that are the fundamentals of quantum physics. But it is also a play about friendship, personal loss, patriotism and the gravest of moral responsibilities. And, being performed nightly to full or nearly full houses, it is probably the favorite to win the Tony Award for best new play on Sunday. So some people like the science, or are at least willing to accept it in the service of drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DURING previews for ''Copenhagen,'' the playwright Michael Frayn received a letter from a woman who had just seen it. ''She said that neither she nor anyone she was with liked all the science in the show,'' Mr. Frayn recalled in a recent interview, ''and that unless I took it out it wasn't going to last long on Broadway.''</p>
        <p>There is, of course, a great deal of science not to like in ''Copenhagen,'' if that's your inclination, and indeed, anyone paying attention to word of mouth about the play is sure to hear complaints that its erudition is off-putting. It is a play, after all, about nuclear fission, the making of the atomic bomb and the esoteric concepts -- known as the uncertainty principle and complementarity -- that are the fundamentals of quantum physics. But it is also a play about friendship, personal loss, patriotism and the gravest of moral responsibilities. And, being performed nightly to full or nearly full houses, it is probably the favorite to win the Tony Award for best new play on Sunday. So some people like the science, or are at least willing to accept it in the service of drama.</p>
        <p>Presenting difficult concepts is always risky for a playwright, but it is particularly so in an era when audiences have been conditioned by lowbrow entertainment to have their senses tickled but not to have their brains massaged. As it happens, though, Werner Heisenberg and Niels Bohr, the two great physicists that Mr. Frayn resurrects (literally) in ''Copenhagen,'' are not alone in their challenging speeches or the connections they make between the mysteries of the universe and the mysteries of the human experience. Science and scientists have been onstage all over the place this season.</p>
        <p>Off Broadway, Tina Landau's ''Space,'' which appeared at the Public Theater last fall, presented astronomers on the lookout for communication from the far reaches of the galaxy, and last week ''Proof,'' David Auburn's fine new play about the world of higher mathematics, opened at the Manhattan Theater Club.</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway, Target Margin Theater presented ''The Five Hysterical Girls Theorem'' by Rinne Groff, another play trafficking in the lyrical perplexities of number theory; the Ensemble Studio Theater staged ''Moving Bodies'' by Arthur Giron, a biography of the physicist Richard Feynman; and playing now at SoHo Rep is ''Hypatia,'' Mac Wellman's willfully muddling theater tapestry based on the life and death of the title character, a fifth-century mathematician and philosopher.</p>
        <p>In the wings is a new musical by Joshua Rosenblum and Joanne Sydney Lessner, also called ''Proof'' -- I saw a staged reading by the York Theater Company last month -- which is about Andrew Wiles, the Princeton professor who explained one of mathematics' most famously lingering enigmas, Fermat's Last Theorem. (It declares that for integer values of n greater than 2, no whole number solution exists for xn  + yn  = zn . Can you whistle that tune?)</p>
        <p>And at the Ivanhoe Theater in Chicago, Penny Penniston's ''Now Then Again,'' a charming if unheralded play about young physicists in love -- ''Copenhagen'' is not the only show of the season to use Heisenberg's uncertainty principle metaphorically -- closed on Sunday after an extended run. Its ingenious structure -- the first half moves forward to a point in time; the second act moves backward from the same point, but the events that preceded it have altered -- is intended to illustrate Heisenberg's declaration that observable phenomena are not necessarily as they appear.</p>
        <p>The works achieve a range of success, and they wander to varying degrees into the explication of the science. ''Copenhagen'' does the most with the most; even if you can't reiterate Heisenberg's theories after you leave the theater, you feel as if you understand them while you're in it. (For the record, Heisenberg stated that it is impossible to know both an atomic particle's position and its momentum exactly; to observe a particle, he argued, you have to hit it with a photon of light, and such a collision will affect the particle's course. Full disclosure: I looked it up and also discussed it with Mr. Frayn.)</p>
        <p>But in all of these works, the pursuit of scientific knowledge looms as a search for beauty and truth, which a number of these plays argue is precisely what playwrights and other artists do. (To this end, Ms. Groff's ''Five Hysterical Girls'' concludes with a play within the play.) Several -- ''Now Then Again'' and Mr. Auburn's ''Proof,'' for example -- equate the difficult search for scientific truth with the search for human connection and love. And all make the case that science, like art or love, is a deeply human endeavor, all but doomed, pardon the expression, to uncertainty.</p>
        <p>The Technology Revolution</p>
        <p>This flowering use of science as narrative material and scientific concepts as metaphors for the stage is worth remarking on for several reasons. For one thing, it provides evidence that science is re-entering the realm of popular culture, not just in imaginative, futuristic fiction but also in other mainstream and alternative forms: from historical reconstruction and theoretical abstraction to fluffy romance and contemporary realism.</p>
        <p>Why this is so is a matter for speculation. ''One explanation is that it's completely random,'' Mr. Auburn said in an interview, a sly invocation of a mathematical concept in itself. But the revolution in technology is surely a factor. The World Wide Web, e-mail, cell phones (particular favorites of theatergoers, it seems) have all been around long enough to have saturated public consciousness yet are still new enough to feel like magic; you don't have to be able to explain them to use them or be impressed by their prevalence. And it's clear that scientific discoveries, or at least their manifestations, have entered public discourse and the acquisitive, boom-time culture with the force of fashion. The high-minded mysteries of science suddenly seem, um, hip.</p>
        <p>Tapping into a societal mood has always been the theater's stock in trade, and the emergence of science on stage is a sign of this, just as a stream of plays about gender politics, sexual identity and AIDS have been over the last two decades, or  plays dealing with the widening gap between the affluent and deprived. Not to say that the theater is undergoing a sea change, but writers do seem to be taking note of a new country to explore.</p>
        <p>''It is a technological age we're living in,'' said Mr. Auburn, whose background in mathematics peaked, he said, with a B- in college calculus, ''and technology is a field that produces a lot of drama. Maybe the divide between the two cultures'' -- that is, the one that separates scientists from nonscientists -- ''is breaking down a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Explaining Physics and Math</p>
        <p>For playwrights this territory is full of challenges, the main one being the issue of how much to explain about concepts that few if any audience members are familiar with. In ''Copenhagen,'' Mr. Frayn used the character of Bohr's wife, Margrethe, a highly intelligent woman but not a world-class physicist, as an intermediary between her husband and Heisenberg and in some ways as a stand-in for the audience. To include her in their conversations, they have to explain things they would silently assume with each other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Auburn purposely shied away from equation-solving in his play -- the proof of the title has to do with prime numbers, but what it proves is never made explicit -- but in the opening act one character believes that another is not mathematically savvy, and as he condescends to her he's also helping the audience. And Mr. Auburn did have his play vetted by members of the math department at New York University, who also visited rehearsals.</p>
        <p>''What the cast got from them,'' Mr. Auburn said, ''more than any specific math information, was a feel for what the discourse is like. It isn't dry or analytical; they were having fun, argumentative discussions about their field, really scrapping with each other. It was surprising to the performers, I think.'' In any case, he said, the focus of his play is less on math than it is on relationships.</p>
        <p>'Essential to the Story'</p>
        <p>Mr. Frayn, on the other hand, went the opposite way.</p>
        <p>''There probably is too much explication,'' he said. ''But I wouldn't have done it if it didn't seem essential to the story. It's difficult to understand why everyone felt they were absolutely safe, as far as the usage of atomic bombs is concerned, unless you explain about the two uranium isotopes and fast neutrons. And you can't make clear why the balance of probability began to change unless you explain the change of uranium into plutonium in a reactor. You simply cannot tell the story without explaining those things. It's not to everyone's taste.''</p>
        <p>Making the science comprehensible, said Mr. Frayn, whose academic background is in philosophy, was, indeed, difficult.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of writing and rewriting, to make it clear to myself,'' he said. ''I did find that difficult, but if I could make it clear to myself, I thought other people could follow.''</p>
        <p>Potential perplexities aside, the new science plays add welcome elements to the theatrical landscape. There's a whole new vernacular afoot, a scientific argot whose music is just beginning to be parsed. Terms like lepton, composite number, photon and isotope haven't exactly been part of the stage's working vocabulary until now, and watching playwrights work with them and struggle to make them useful as communicative, sonorous tools can be a nifty pleasure for theatergoers. And if the grand concepts of science they connote can be lassoed by playwrights well enough to make them a little more accessible and applicable to you and me, that's a service.</p>
        <p>One thing I particularly like is the spate of unusual new characters that science brings to the stage. These include people like Heisenberg and Bohr (played with great verbal elan by Michael Cumpsty and Philip Bosco), whose high-minded retrospective debate (they are brought back from the dead for the purpose) makes excruciatingly clear the application of intellectual abstraction to concrete events. But there is also a whole collection of younger people with young people's immediate concerns.</p>
        <p>In ''Proof'' and in ''Now Then Again'' the main characters, all in their 20's, find the pursuit of difficult knowledge no less enlivening and nervous-making than things like their careers, their families, their social graces, their hormones and their heartaches. I can't recall having seen similar types on the stage before, and the two pairs of actors involved -- Mary-Louise Parker and Ben Shenkman in ''Proof,'' Joseph Wycoff and Katie McLean in ''Now Then Again'' -- make their characters revelatory. All four performances were thoroughly rounded and persuasive, illuminating an obviously extant kind of life experience I'd never before considered but was delighted to discover.</p>
        <p>Intelligence and Emotion</p>
        <p>Not least among the satisfactions of these plays is that they add ammunition to the combat against American culture's troubling anti-intellectualism. Whatever the artistic achievement of these works, what each of them accomplishes is the lesson that intelligence is not a quality that exists as an antithesis to -- or even apart from -- conscience, emotional capability or common sense.</p>
        <p>''It's fun to write about smart people,'' Mr. Auburn said. ''You're not condescending to your own characters when you write about them. You're looking up to them and trying to do them justice.''</p>
        <p>May there be more of them.</p>
        <p>Where They Play</p>
        <p>Here are the current Manhattan plays mentioned in the critic's notebook article on science and the theater:</p>
        <p>''COPENHAGEN,'' Royale, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays at 8 p.m.; Wednesdays and Saturdays at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. Tickets: $40 to $65; $25 student rush tickets at the box office on the day of performance.</p>
        <p>''HYPATIA,'' SoHo Rep, 46 Walker Street, (212) 334-0962. Through tomorrow. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30. Tickets: $12 and $15.</p>
        <p>''PROOF,'' City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. Tuesdays through Fridays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; Sundays at 2:30 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $50.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
