<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marketers bet on the concept of good luck as a selling tool.</title>
    <meta content="Y02ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D8133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marketers bet on the concept of good luck as a selling tool.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertisers and media magnates are celebrating concept of good fortune with lengthening list of products, publications and pitches centered on the word 'lucky'; some examples noted; photos (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO knew when Barbra Streisand asked the musical question ''How Lucky Can You Get?'' that Madison Avenue would provide this answer: You ain't seen nothing yet.</p>
        <p>Advertisers and media magnates are celebrating the concept of good fortune with a lengthening list of products, publications and pitches centered on the word ''lucky.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO knew when Barbra Streisand asked the musical question ''How Lucky Can You Get?'' that Madison Avenue would provide this answer: You ain't seen nothing yet.</p>
        <p>Advertisers and media magnates are celebrating the concept of good fortune with a lengthening list of products, publications and pitches centered on the word ''lucky.''</p>
        <p>For instance, a magazine named Lucky is being introduced nationally by Conde Nast Publications. A cool character called Mr. Lucky is the focus of a quirky series of television, print and poster ads for the Excite Web site. And the venerable Lucky Strike cigarette brand is being reintroduced with a big advertising and promotional push that plays up the iconic Lucky name.</p>
        <p>Those newcomers join users of luck as a sales tool like Lucky Charms cereal; Lucky Dog, a long-distance telephone service operated by AT&amp;T; Lucky jeans; the Lucky chain of supermarkets; and games with ''lucky'' in their names sold by various state lotteries.</p>
        <p>Why are Lady Luck and Dame Fortune becoming almost as popular with marketers as Britney Spears and Christina Aguilera are with teenage music fans?</p>
        <p>''It's the state of the U.S. right now,'' said Jeff Weiss, creative director at Amster Yard in New York, part of the McCann-Erickson unit of the Interpublic Group of Companies that is bringing out the Excite campaign for the At Home Corporation. ''People are feeling good.''</p>
        <p>''And the advertising has to be about using technology to make us more human,'' he added. ''People like things that are warm, and the whole air of 'lucky' is warmth.''</p>
        <p>John Allen, senior partner at Lippincott &amp; Margulies in New York, a corporate identity consulting company owned by Marsh &amp; McLennan, echoed Mr. Weiss.</p>
        <p>''There's something warm and approachable about words with old roots like 'lucky,' '' Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>''You know what 'lucky' is, and it's good,'' he added. ''It's something people want.''</p>
        <p>That philosophy helped guide Conde Nast, part of Advance Publications, in picking Lucky as the moniker for its magazine, covering shopping for young women.</p>
        <p>''There's that moment when you find something on the racks and it's beautiful, but you wonder whether it will pay out in the dressing room,'' said Kim France, editor in chief at Lucky in New York. ''When it does, you feel you got lucky.''</p>
        <p>'' 'Lucky' feels inclusive and happy,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Decades ago, ''Be happy, go Lucky'' was a slogan for Lucky Strike, which flourished in that prefilter era. The brand faltered badly after the 50's, despite adding filtered and light styles to its nonfiltered offerings. But British American Tobacco, which acquired the United States rights to Lucky Strike in 1995, believes a revival is possible.</p>
        <p>''We're working to regenerate a fantastic trademark with a great pedigree and heritage and authenticity that new brands don't have,'' said Susan Ivey, senior vice president for marketing at the Brown &amp; Williamson Tobacco Corporation in Louisville, Ky., the American unit of British American Tobacco.</p>
        <p>The goal, she added, is to create perceptions of Lucky Strike as ''a free-spirited brand with a sense of humor'' by concentrating on ''the name, the package design, the slogans like 'It's toasted' and 'L.S.M.F.T.' ''</p>
        <p>The latter slogan -- which stands for ''Lucky Strike means fine tobacco' -- is the subject of ads by the brand's agency, Bates USA in New York, part of the Bates Worldwide unit of the Cordiant Communications Group. One print ad carries the headline ''We wouldn't say it if we didn't mean it.''</p>
        <p>Brown &amp; Williamson is also sponsoring a contest with the ''L.S.M.F.T.'' theme, which will award what is being billed as ''a dream prize beginning with the letters 'F' and 'T.' ''</p>
        <p>As for the word beginning with the letter ''L,'' it is ''very optimistic,'' said Liv Lane, a spokeswoman for General Mills in Minneapolis, which sells Lucky Charms. ''So it's no surprise it's becoming more popular these days.''</p>
        <p>As if to keep up with the lucky come latelies, General Mills periodically changes the shapes and colors of the Lucky Charms ''marbits,'' a company term for the marshmallow bits mixed in with the cereal. The newest one is ''sparkling rainbows,'' Ms. Lane said, which ''for a limited time have replaced the regular rainbow marbits.''</p>
        <p>The idea of ''lucky'' as a good luck charm predates Lucky Charms, which was introduced in 1964. There was a 1943 film, ''Mr. Lucky,'' starring Cary Grant as a suave gambler, which inspired a television series of the same name, sponsored by Lever Brothers, that ran on CBS during the 1959-60 season. Coincidentally, Lever sold a Good Luck brand of margarine from 1948 into the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Does luckocentric marketing always work?</p>
        <p>''There's a saying that you can't just be good, you have to also be lucky,'' said Marian Salzman, director at the Brand Futures Group in New York, a trend-watching unit of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc.</p>
        <p>''In other words, you can do all the work and preparing and obsessing,'' she added, ''but without a stroke of luck you won't get there.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
