<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The F.C.C.'s Ownership Rules</title>
    <meta content="02FRI2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1DC103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The F.C.C.'s Ownership Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial scores plan by Federal Communications Commission to loosen rules that limit ability of television networks to own other networks and newspapers; says it is not in public's interest to relax rules that protect diversity of information</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Communications Commission, under heavy political pressure, is preparing to loosen rules that limit the ability of television broadcasters to own other communications properties. This is a bad idea. There is no evidence that weakening the rules will help consumers.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the rules exist to preserve something precious and fragile in a democracy -- the diversity of information that flows into everyone's home. The commission already has all the power it needs to grant exemptions where necessary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Communications Commission, under heavy political pressure, is preparing to loosen rules that limit the ability of television broadcasters to own other communications properties. This is a bad idea. There is no evidence that weakening the rules will help consumers.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the rules exist to preserve something precious and fragile in a democracy -- the diversity of information that flows into everyone's home. The commission already has all the power it needs to grant exemptions where necessary.</p>
        <p>One important rule prevents a network from buying another network. The commission recently invoked the rule to require Viacom, which recently purchased CBS, to divest itself of UPN, a newer, financially weak network. Those who want to soften the rule argue that UPN can thrive only if it combines with another network with which it can share costs. But turning to CBS to save UPN creates a bigger CBS, without necessarily preserving a valuable independent voice for news and entertainment. If the commission can prove that an independent UPN can survive only by combining with CBS, then it has the legal power to reverse its earlier ruling and grant a well-argued waiver.</p>
        <p>Another key rule prevents a broadcaster from owning a newspaper in the same city. The commission appears poised to lift that rule in large cities like New York, where joint ownership poses little threat because several newspapers and television stations coexist. The immediate issue is the Tribune Company's agreement to buy Times Mirror, which would give the Tribune ownership of newspapers and television stations in three cities, including New York. There it would own Newsday, the Long-Island-based daily that circulates in the city, and WPIX, a television station already owned by the Tribune Company.</p>
        <p>But the argument for relaxing the rule is weak. The commission can and does grant exemptions in the rare instances where a local newspaper's sole chance for survival is to be purchased by a broadcaster. The commission ruled in this fashion to allow Rupert Murdoch, who already owned a New York television station, to buy The New York Post. By loosening the rule for large cities, the commission would in effect grant a blanket waiver without the need to prove the case. Threats to diversity need not be put on such automatic pilot.</p>
        <p>A third rule, which the commission does not seem prepared to change, prevents broadcasters from owning stations that reach more than 35 percent of households in the country. This is a sound rule for preserving diversity of ownership, even in a time when cable is eroding broadcast boundaries. Weakening the rule could, for example, stifle the voice of independent programmers. Programmers who refuse to conform to the tastes of a huge broadcaster, one whose reach extends well beyond the 35 percent figure, could find themselves shut out of too many of the nation's homes to survive.</p>
        <p>Any media company has an interest in the commission's decisions, and The New York Times Company is no exception. A change in the commission's rules could affect the business activities of the Times Company, which owns The New York Times, 23 other newspapers and 8 television stations. But the issue is not the well-being of the Times Company or any other company, but rather the preservation of a diverse group of independent sources for news and entertainment.</p>
        <p>The rules that govern concentration in telecommunications are unlike antitrust laws. In the bottled water and sneaker markets, mergers are allowed  unless antitrust authorities can prove that added concentration would do harm. If the authorities err, and permit excessive consolidation, about all that happens is that the price of bottled water rises and innovation slacks off in the design of sneakers. But in telecommunications, the threat that concentration might shut off sources of information is profound.</p>
        <p>The commission has no legal obligation to bend over backward on behalf of the telecommunications industry. Instead, it is charged with protecting the public interest. Before the commission changes its rules, it needs to prove that ordinary citizens will benefit from the change. So far, that case does not exist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
