<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canadian Aluminum Maker to Buy Swiss Rival</title>
    <meta content="Y02ALU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aluminum</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alcan Aluminium Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Algroup Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BZ Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pechiney Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ebner, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bougie, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D6133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canadian Aluminum Maker to Buy Swiss Rival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alcan Aluminium of Canada reaches agreement to buy Algroup of Switzerland after BZ Group, influential Swiss shareholder group controlled by investor Martin Ebner, throws its support behind sweetened deal worth $4.7 billion; Alcan announced in April that it intended to bid for Algroup, formerly known as Alusuisse Lonza, after European regulators scuttled more ambitious three-way deal that would have included Pechiney of France; BZ Group tenders to Alcan shares it controls amounting to 34 percent of Algroup; Alcan chief executive Jacques Bougie comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alcan Aluminium of Canada reached an agreement today to buy Algroup of Switzerland, after an influential Swiss shareholder group threw its support behind a sweetened deal worth $4.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Alcan had announced in April that it intended to bid for Algroup, formerly known as Alusuisse Lonza, after European regulators scuttled a more ambitious three-way deal that would have included Pechiney of France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alcan Aluminium of Canada reached an agreement today to buy Algroup of Switzerland, after an influential Swiss shareholder group threw its support behind a sweetened deal worth $4.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Alcan had announced in April that it intended to bid for Algroup, formerly known as Alusuisse Lonza, after European regulators scuttled a more ambitious three-way deal that would have included Pechiney of France.</p>
        <p>The breakthrough for Alcan came after the BZ Group, controlled by the Swiss investor Martin Ebner, said it would tender to Alcan shares it controls amounting to 34 percent of Algroup. BZ made that decision after Alcan agreed to reduce the amount it would pay with its own shares and added cash to the offer.</p>
        <p>Alcan said it would exchange 17.1 of its common shares, plus a cash payment and special cash dividend totaling 225 Swiss francs, or about $133, for every Algroup share. That amounted to a 5 percent increase over what Alcan had originally offered under the three-way deal, an Algroup official said.</p>
        <p>The plan to unite Alcan, Algroup and Pechiney failed after European Union regulators objected to the dominant position that the combined companies would have had in Europe and after Alcan refused to divest itself of European factories.</p>
        <p>The BZ Group's support makes it likely that the agreement, which requires 67 percent of Algroup shares for approval, would succeed. Approval is expected to be announced at a stockholder meeting in July.</p>
        <p>Executives of Alcan and Algroup said their deal is expected to bring annual cost savings before taxes of about $150 million. The three-way combination, originally announced in August, had been expected to generate savings of $600 million.</p>
        <p>Based on 1999 results, today's two-way combination would have annual revenue of $12.4 billion, and rank second in size to Alcoa of the United States, the global market leader.</p>
        <p>Experts say Alcan and Algroup fit well, since Alcan specializes in bulk aluminum and rolled aluminum sheets, while Algroup has increasingly focused in recent years on aluminum parts for the automobile industry, like engine blocks, and specialized aluminum packaging for the food and drug industries.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
