<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even the Egalitarian Bauhaus Had a Hausfrau Tendency</title>
    <meta content="02SMIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weaving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bauhaus Movement</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albers, Anni</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DC133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even the Egalitarian Bauhaus Had a Hausfrau Tendency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews Jewish Museum's exhibit on woven art by Anni Albers, central member of Bauhaus Weaving Workshop; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's always startling to be reminded that the Bauhaus, that font of modernist invention, did not allow  women to participate in its architecture, wall-painting and furniture workshops because they were considered too physically demanding. Such genteel, if chauvinistic, concern  seems out of character at a place where aesthetic equality -- the elevation of craft and design to fine-art status -- was a founding principle. But no, at the Bauhaus, women had only gentler options: ceramics, metalwork and especially the ancient, implicitly female craft of weaving.</p>
        <p>Such policies must have saved a lot of breath. After all, the elevation of craft, or anything else, requires bodies: dedicated souls willing to learn the basics, bend the rules and inspire disciples. Surely it was easier to guide women toward the loom en masse than to convince individual men and women that weaving could be as expressive and important as any other art, fine or applied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's always startling to be reminded that the Bauhaus, that font of modernist invention, did not allow  women to participate in its architecture, wall-painting and furniture workshops because they were considered too physically demanding. Such genteel, if chauvinistic, concern  seems out of character at a place where aesthetic equality -- the elevation of craft and design to fine-art status -- was a founding principle. But no, at the Bauhaus, women had only gentler options: ceramics, metalwork and especially the ancient, implicitly female craft of weaving.</p>
        <p>Such policies must have saved a lot of breath. After all, the elevation of craft, or anything else, requires bodies: dedicated souls willing to learn the basics, bend the rules and inspire disciples. Surely it was easier to guide women toward the loom en masse than to convince individual men and women that weaving could be as expressive and important as any other art, fine or applied.</p>
        <p>One wonders if the school's founding fathers fully appreciated the extent to which the women of the Weaving Workshop proved them right. Theirs was the only workshop that spanned all of the Bauhaus's stormy 14-year history, an existence characterized by financial difficulties, internal discord, physical relocation (from Weimar to Dessau to Berlin) and an increasingly unsympathetic political climate. Despite everything, the workshop established the fundamentals of contemporary textile design and created one of the most important, if least studied, aspects of the Bauhaus legacy.</p>
        <p>This confluence of opposed and dovetailing agendas comes to mind in the Jewish Museum's illuminating, densely packed survey of the life and art of Anni Albers, perhaps the most significant member of the Bauhaus Weaving Workshop. Organized by the Albers Foundation and the Peggy Guggenheim Museum in Venice, ''Anni Albers'' is part art exhibition, part weaving seminar, part biography and altogether fascinating.</p>
        <p>It is not without flaws, most notably cramped space compounded by intrusive display tables that cornily resemble looms. These last are the salient characteristic of Gae Aulenti's exhibition design; but while they obstruct the viewing of Albers's handloomed wall hangings, they efficiently display nearly 100 examples of the textile samples she designed for possible commercial production.</p>
        <p>The show brings together work done over five decades on two continents in several media. In addition to a broad range of textiles, it includes gouache and watercolor textile studies, jewelry and examples of the lithographs to which Albers turned in the 1960's, somewhat relieved to give up the physical complexities of the loom. Its driving force is Albers's thorough exploration of weaving as both a fine and an applied art, her appreciation of the structural and imagistic possibilities of its basic grid structure and her sensitivity to the subtleties of texture and color possible on the loom.</p>
        <p>Annelise Fleischmann, born in Berlin in 1900, arrived at the Bauhaus in 1922. By 1925, she had completed its famous foundation course, which included color instruction from the mystical Johannes Itten, and overcome her initial suspicion that weaving was ''sissy.'' She had also married the painter and color theorist Josef Albers, who was 13 years her senior and the first Bauhaus student to become a master (as they called teachers). They were perhaps an unlikely pair: she was the cosseted but artistically inclined  daughter of a Jewish furniture manufacturer in Berlin; he was from the coal-mining city of Bottrop in the Ruhr, a Catholic and the son of a skilled laborer who taught him to take pride in working by hand.</p>
        <p>In 1933, just after the Nazis closed the Bauhaus for good, the Alberses were invited by Philip Johnson and Edward M. M. Warburg to emigrate to the United States, where they continued to spread the Bauhaus gospel. They spent their first 16 years teaching at Black Mountain College, the experimental art school in Asheville, N.C. In 1950, they moved to Connecticut, where Josef taught at Yale until his retirement in 1958. (He died in 1976 at 88, she in 1994 at 94.)</p>
        <p>Photographs of the Alberses at home indicate their faithfulness to Bauhaus simplicity and spareness, even in a small house in Connecticut. These pictures are part of a personal-history gallery that includes letters, memorabilia, a selection of the pre-Columbian textiles that Albers collected (and learned from), and examples of the Chanel-inspired jackets she made for herself, as well as curiosities like little squares of corrugated cardboard, gouged and colored to resemble rough-textured weaving samples, that she used as teaching aids to sharpen what she called ''tactile awareness.''</p>
        <p>Albers could be as less-is-more and as true to materials as the next Bauhauslern, as is evinced by the textile samples -- drapery, upholstery fabric, wall coverings -- that she designed both at the Bauhaus and in the United States, mostly for Knoll and Sunar. (Some are still available.) These fabrics give pre-eminence to structure and materials. Their weaves are often as open and simple as a basic dishcloth, but Albers also understood the cumulative effect of little changes, like knots or twists, or irregularities on an expanse of fabric. Over the years, she experimented with a range of materials now taken for granted in fabric design -- raffia, fiberglass, jute, horse hair, harnessmaker's thread, metal thread and foil, Lurex and plastic. (Their variety would have impressed Donald Judd, who deeply admired her husband's paintings.)</p>
        <p>Following the lead of Gunta Stolzl, her colleague and teacher at the Bauhaus, Albers began working with cellophane as early as 1929, producing a design for a wall covering for a school auditorium in Bernau that  both absorbed sound and reflected light, and also earned her her Bauhaus diploma. (A swatch of this material is in this show and also in ''Making Choices'' at the Museum of Modern Art, which includes a small but impressive selection of Albers's work, as well as a handsome wall hanging by Stolzl.)</p>
        <p>It is significant that one of Albers's favorite teachers at the Bauhaus was Paul Klee. Klee taught a course for weavers only, and works like Albers's ''Red and Blue Layers'' (1954), which is actually mostly orange and pink, echo the influence of his vibrant palette. More important, Klee encouraged his students both to  attend to and take expressive liberties with the implicitly modern structure of weaving: the grid.</p>
        <p>Especially after Albers came to the United States and became more familiar with pre-Columbian textiles, she introduced suggestions of landscapes (''Monte Alban,'' 1936) and cityscapes into her weaving. In some of her most successful pieces, like ''From the East'' and ''Under Way,'' she allowed rogue threads to wander in a kind of abstract script across the face of a weaving. In the boldly scaled ''Red Meander,'' this wandering determines the labyrinthine pattern of the entire weaving.</p>
        <p>In 1949, Albers became the first textile artist to be given a solo show at the Museum of Modern Art; both her work and her writings made her revered within the textile field. Today, her work commands a broader stage. It benefits from heightened attention to the histories of design and the crafts, including the Weaving  Workshop; increased consciousness of the role of women in the formation of modernism; and the frequency with which contemporary art employs fabric, weaving and other kinds of ''women's work.''</p>
        <p>This exhibition confirms that Albers is equal in importance to her husband, both for her work and as a link between European and American modernisms. It also reveals how perfectly weaving met the basic conflict, never really resolved, at the heart of the Bauhaus: between the artist as creative autodidact pursuing personal expression and the artist as versatile master craftsman, figuring out ways to use technology to make beautiful everyday objects available to all. This conflict was never a problem for the weavers, who pushed their medium toward decoration, abstraction and function as the situation demanded. No one did this as effortlessly as Anni Albers.</p>
        <p>''Anni Albers'' remains at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 423-3200, through Aug. 20.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
