<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CBS's 'Survivor' Is Winner for Network; Real-Life Show Pulls in Younger Viewers</title>
    <meta content="Y02TUB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor! (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Who Wants to Be A Millionaire (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DE103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CBS's 'Survivor' Is Winner for Network; Real-Life Show Pulls in Younger Viewers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Survivor, new summer series about group of people forced to live together in primitive circumstances on island off Borneo, gets off to stunning start on CBS network; program pulls in 15.5 million viewers in its debut; show draws surprising number of young viewers; beats ABC's hit show Who Wants To Be A Millionaire? in certain age categories, but not in overall rating; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last summer, ''Who Wants to Be A Millionaire'' turned the television world on its head by defying every expectation and seizing huge audiences, eventually catapulting ABC to overall network ratings leadership.</p>
        <p>Now a new summer series, about a group of people forced to live together in primitive circumstances on an island off Borneo, has got off to a similarly stunning start, and television executives are already wondering whether it can do the same thing for CBS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last summer, ''Who Wants to Be A Millionaire'' turned the television world on its head by defying every expectation and seizing huge audiences, eventually catapulting ABC to overall network ratings leadership.</p>
        <p>Now a new summer series, about a group of people forced to live together in primitive circumstances on an island off Borneo, has got off to a similarly stunning start, and television executives are already wondering whether it can do the same thing for CBS.</p>
        <p>''Survivor,'' the CBS experiment in mixing ''Lord of the Flies'' with ''Gilligan's Island'' and ''Treasure Island,'' came out of the gate roaring Wednesday night, pulling in 15.5 million viewers, a figure that dwarfed any show CBS has used on a Wednesday night in two years -- during the regular TV season, never mind the summer. In a reverse for CBS, the network with the oldest audience, the show drew a surprising number of young viewers, providing a glimpse of the marketing power of a combined CBS and Viacom Inc., with its youth-oriented radio and cable stations, like MTV and VH-1.</p>
        <p>That promotional push may have created an initial curiosity for the show that will be tested in the coming weeks. Even CBS executives will not predict if the ratings will hold up. But the early success is likely to intensify the market for programs that record real people doing real-life things. Indeed, networks were said to be lining up yesterday to acquire the rights to other such televoyeur shows, including one set on a bus, one set in a futuristic house supposedly on another planet, and one in which an actor tries to sabotage his teammates in a series of contests.</p>
        <p>CBS itself is set to capitalize immediately with the debut next month of ''Big Brother,'' possibly the most elaborate effort in the movement toward voyueristic shows, in which 10 people spend three months together in a house, with their every movement recorded live on camera.</p>
        <p>The initial ratings for ''Survivor,'' huge by summer standards, can only feed the trend. The show proved to be more than competitive with ''Who Wants To Be A Millionaire,'' which ABC scheduled at the last minute to try to hold down the audience for ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>ABC did edge ''Survivor'' in one respect; it attracted more viewers over all, 16.8 million. But ''Survivor's'' most noticeable feat was in the number of young viewers it brought to CBS. ''Survivor'' not only beat ''Millionaire'' in every category of young viewers -- from teenagers through adults between the ages of 18 and 49, and 25 and 54 -- but it also managed to triple the average CBS prime-time audience among viewers between the ages of 18 and 34.</p>
        <p>That achievement shocked a number of CBS competitors. An executive with one competing network said, ''Those are simply incredible numbers for CBS.''</p>
        <p>Leslie Moonves, the president of CBS Television, called the ratings ''a great corporate victory,'' saying ''We had people doing interviews everywhere -- on radio, on VH-1, on MTV,''</p>
        <p>The show stirred so much interest that Mr. Moonves decided to schedule a repeat broadcast of the first episode, tomorrow night at 10.</p>
        <p>In the first of the 13 scheduled ''Survivor'' episodes, two teams of eight people each, carefully cast to include a wide range of ages, ethnic groups and, especially, personalities, were thrown together on the island of Pulau Tiga, where they had to do everything from build latrines to forage for food to start a fire.</p>
        <p>They were also bitten by bugs, harassed by rats (which viewers have been promised they will later see these folks eat for dinner), and challenged by a raft-racing task with the reward of some waterproof matches. The losing team had to vote one person off the island. (Each show ends with someone's ignominious departure.)</p>
        <p>Because she fell and cost her team a victory in the raft race, a 62-year-old woman named Sonja Christopher was the first victim of the show's Darwinian ethos.</p>
        <p>Still, ''Survivor's'' instant ascent to event status provided some solace for Ms. Christopher, who was interviewed all over television yesterday, from CBS's own ''Early Show'' (which, every Thursday for the next 13 weeks, has first claim on every one bounced from the island), to MSNBC, Fox News, and even ''The Daily Show'' on Comedy Central.</p>
        <p>Almost as busy as Ms. Christopher yesterday was Ben Silverman, an agent with the William Morris Agency, who spent four years in Europe and was an early advocate of the European reality shows whose formats are now making their way into the United States. Mr. Silverman had a hand in bringing ''Millionaire'' to ABC and was involved in the heated negotiations for ''Big Brother,'' in which CBS outbid ABC by putting up a reported $20 million.</p>
        <p>''The ratings for 'Survivor' have put the networks into overdrive for other formats,'' Mr. Silverman said. ''Right now CBS and ABC are the most involved.'' He said he expected several shows he represented to be sold shortly.</p>
        <p>These include ''The Bus,'' which examines ordinary people on a bus tour, and ''The Mole,'' the one in which an actor surreptitiously plays havoc with contestants in a series of scenic challenges like bungee jumps.</p>
        <p>Another show sets up a house as though it is on some outer-space colony in a distant future. Mr. Silverman said he also represented several other shows in the genre but he could not yet disclose them.</p>
        <p>What all the shows have in common, beyond their initial success in European countries, from Britain to the Netherlands to Belgium, is their use of real people interacting on camera. Most of the shows also have extensive Internet components, enabling fans to follow the progress of the contestants even when the show is not on the air.</p>
        <p>How real these ''reality shows'' actually are has been questioned, but Mark Burnett the executive producer of ''Survivor,'' said yesterday: ''It is exactly real. I refuse for any reason to manipulate what really happens. These people are on camera and they say what they say, but I'm not going to manipulate them.''</p>
        <p>The rats, he said, are real and ever-present on the island. The snakes, he said, are real and truly dangerous, enough so that he ensured that anyone bitten could be evacuated by helicopter to a hospital within 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnett argued that the events are in no way staged or re-edited to build drama. Each show represents three days of taping on the island. Each ends with one member voted out until a winner is selected, and takes home the $1 million prize.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Burnett said he did edit the show to set up future plot lines, as he did in the first episode, which showed a brief shot of one contestant reading his Bible. ''We are setting that up, because clearly religion does become a factor,'' he said. ''Some people don't like being preached to, particularly on an island where you can't get off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moonves said he was being cautious about the show's initial ratings success: ''I don't want to declare victory after one episode.'' But he acknowledged that ''the show has tremendous economic upside.'' That upside cannot be exploited in the current set of shows, no matter how big the ratings get, because all of them were sold out to eight full sponsors, including Reebok, Bud Lite beer and the United States Army.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Moonves said, ''The advertisers saw those ratings and got phenomenally jacked.'' This was especially because of exceptional numbers among younger viewers.</p>
        <p>If that keeps up, CBS can expect to sell its commercials in ''Big Brother'' for higher prices, as well as those for future editions of ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>And there will almost certainly be future editions. Mr. Moonves said he was not yet ready to start up the process of picking another group of people to be isolated in another exotic locale, though the mechanism was already in place to do so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnett said, ''I don't think we'll go back to an island, but we may go some place like Africa or the Andes or the Australian outback.''</p>
        <p>The decision for another ''Survivor'' adventure series may not take much longer, Mr. Moonves suggested. ''We could have another 'Survivor' ready by January,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That would again parallel ''Millionaire,'' which ABC brought back quickly after its summer success, installing it first as a two-week event in November, a ratings sweep month.</p>
        <p>January is not a sweep month, but February is -- and the ''Survivor'' format calls for 13 weeks of shows. ''If it works well in January, it will work well in February,'' Mr. Moonves said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
