<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Freedom Trail With a Talking Horse</title>
    <meta content="02FREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bodrov, Sergei</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Running Free (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DE133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Freedom Trail With a Talking Horse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie Running Free, directed by Sergei Bodrov; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Horses are noble, spirited creatures, but what do they think about? If they were granted the power of speech, what would they say? The old television series ''Mr. Ed'' presented one version of equine consciousness, but you won't hear any stable-door wisecracks in ''Running Free,'' Sergei Bodrov's earnest, music-drenched story of a plucky young colt's adventures in the deserts of southern Africa. It turns out that horses -- or Lucky, at least, who narrates the film in the pleasant adolescent tenor of Lukas Haas -- are masters of the obvious who think and speak entirely in movie cliches.</p>
        <p>Lucky is born in the midst of an ocean voyage from Germany to Africa, where his mother is being shipped to work in the copper mines. ''Africa was far away,'' he notes perceptively. At first the white human characters speak German until, for the convenience of the audience, they switch to Afrikaans -- and British-accented English. Meanwhile Lucky channels horse language for us. When an imperious stallion named Caesar whinnies and snorts, Lucky explains that he is ''furious that a lowly workhorse had dared to enter his domain.'' And when Caesar's spunky daughter Beauty shakes her mane around to announce her presence as Lucky's love interest, her beau remarks that she's ''funny and full of life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Horses are noble, spirited creatures, but what do they think about? If they were granted the power of speech, what would they say? The old television series ''Mr. Ed'' presented one version of equine consciousness, but you won't hear any stable-door wisecracks in ''Running Free,'' Sergei Bodrov's earnest, music-drenched story of a plucky young colt's adventures in the deserts of southern Africa. It turns out that horses -- or Lucky, at least, who narrates the film in the pleasant adolescent tenor of Lukas Haas -- are masters of the obvious who think and speak entirely in movie cliches.</p>
        <p>Lucky is born in the midst of an ocean voyage from Germany to Africa, where his mother is being shipped to work in the copper mines. ''Africa was far away,'' he notes perceptively. At first the white human characters speak German until, for the convenience of the audience, they switch to Afrikaans -- and British-accented English. Meanwhile Lucky channels horse language for us. When an imperious stallion named Caesar whinnies and snorts, Lucky explains that he is ''furious that a lowly workhorse had dared to enter his domain.'' And when Caesar's spunky daughter Beauty shakes her mane around to announce her presence as Lucky's love interest, her beau remarks that she's ''funny and full of life.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps she could have shared some of her jokes with the filmmakers, who mistake muzzy, mystical sentimentality for childlike wonder. This is somewhat surprising, in view of the accomplishments of Mr. Bodrov, best known in this country for his Oscar-nominated ''Prisoner of the Mountains,'' and the screenwriter Jeanne Rosenberg, who collaborated on the script of Carol Ballard's ''Black Stallion,'' a horsy flick of unusually broad and durable appeal. But then again, Ms. Rosenberg shares a story credit with Jean-Jacques Annaud, the film's producer and the perpetrator of such acts of high-concept cinematic paganism as ''Quest for Fire'' and ''The Bear.''</p>
        <p>Like those films. ''Running Free'' can be very beautiful to look at. Shot on location in Namibia, it includes some gorgeous aerial shots of the vast orange emptiness in which Lucky longs to run free. But the equine action sequences are poorly edited, and the voice-over and the sugary Windham Hill-inspired world music score combine to mar the glories of nature, one of which, after all, is silence.</p>
        <p>The plot blends a bit of ''Bambi'' with a dollop of ''Lassie,'' as the film's treatment of animals vacillates between cutesy Disney-style anthropomorphism and ''Born Free'' exoticism. Lucky befriends an orphaned stable boy named Richard (Chase Moore), who works for the grouchy Boss Man (Jan Decleir), owner of Caesar, and the two of them, on a desert ramble, befriend a young African girl named Nyka (Maria Geelbooi), who stars in the film's most emblematically ridiculous scene. As boy, girl and horse sit around a campfire, Richard pulls out his harmonica, plays a few bars and then hands it to Nyka, who faultlessly reels off the movie's love theme, which obligingly swells to its full orchestration as the camera lifts into the desert night. But why didn't Lucky get a turn?</p>
        <p>RUNNING FREE</p>
        <p>Directed by Sergei Bodrov; written by Jeanne Rosenberg, based on a story by Jean-Jacques Annaud and Ms. Rosenberg; director of photography, Dan Laustsen; edited by Ray Lovejoy; music by Nicola Piovani; production designer, Wolf Kroeger; animal handlers, Sled Reynolds, Bobby Lovgren and Heath Harris; produced by Mr. Annaud; released by Columbia Pictures. Running time: 82 minutes. This film is rated G.</p>
        <p>WITH: Lukas Haas (Narrator), Chase Moore (Young Richard), Jan Decleir (Boss Man), Arie Verveen (Adult Richard) and Maria Geelbooi (Nyka).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
