<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico's Dot-Com Generation Is Voting for Change</title>
    <meta content="Y02MEX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DF103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico's Dot-Com Generation Is Voting for Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <dateline>QUERETARO, Mexico</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The presidential campaign has opened a vast demographic divide between the old and new Mexicos, a political fault line that runs smack through the Martinez household, tucked along a tidy suburban street in central Mexico.</p>
        <p>Eduardo Martinez is a 29-year-old accountant. His wife, Karina, once worked at a Ford dealership, but now does aerobics at a gym and tends their children. Mention the party that has run Mexico since the 1920's and they respond with contemptuous talk about its legacy of graft and fraud. Like most young urban Mexicans, they intend to vote for Vicente Fox, the first opposition candidate with a shot at victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The presidential campaign has opened a vast demographic divide between the old and new Mexicos, a political fault line that runs smack through the Martinez household, tucked along a tidy suburban street in central Mexico.</p>
        <p>Eduardo Martinez is a 29-year-old accountant. His wife, Karina, once worked at a Ford dealership, but now does aerobics at a gym and tends their children. Mention the party that has run Mexico since the 1920's and they respond with contemptuous talk about its legacy of graft and fraud. Like most young urban Mexicans, they intend to vote for Vicente Fox, the first opposition candidate with a shot at victory.</p>
        <p>''The country needs a change and Fox can bring it,'' Mrs. Martinez said, strapping her two toddlers into car seats for a shopping trip.</p>
        <p>But their maid, Lucia Hernandez, a gray-haired woman of 53 who commutes from her tin-roofed home outside this state capital, still praises the governing party, known as the PRI, for building a school in her rural village 20 years ago. Like millions of older, semiliterate, rural voters, she plans to vote for its candidate, Francisco Labastida.</p>
        <p>The Martinezes and their maid reflect the dramatic voter polarization recorded all across Mexico in  polls before the country's presidential election on July 2. Although the leading candidates appear virtually tied, they draw their support from radically contrasting constituencies. The traditional Mexico of aging peasants, hardscrabble farms and corn subsidies supports Mr. Labastida. The new Mexico, where millions of young college graduates are modernizing an economy already bubbling with scores of new dot-com startups, backs Mr. Fox.</p>
        <p>''This is quite a political cleavage,'' said Alejandro Moreno, the chief pollster at the Mexico City newspaper Reforma. ''In no previous election have we seen such sharp differences between voters supporting the PRI and younger voters looking for change.''</p>
        <p>A nationwide survey conducted for  Reuters by Zogby International in early May found the same split that Mr. Moreno has measured in several Reforma soundings.</p>
        <p>Older, semiliterate voters in farm areas were supporting Mr. Labastida. ''But less than a third of Mexicans under 29 years old said the PRI deserves to be elected again,'' said Andrew Hurst, Reuters' Mexico bureau chief.</p>
        <p>The country's divided electorate has grown by 12 million voters since 1994, when Ernesto Zedillo won election comfortably as the country's 13th consecutive PRI president. The trends make it all but certain the party will eventually lose the presidency, since the rural vote that for decades has been its bedrock support is disappearing as farmlands give way to industrial parks all across this nation of 100 million people.</p>
        <p>In 1994, 30 percent of Mexico's election precincts were classified as rural. Today, only 20 percent of the precincts, home to 12 million of Mexico's 59 million registered voters, are rural. Ten percent of the voters live in ''mixed'' precincts, part rural, part urban, said Eduardo Badillo, the federal official who directed the three-year effort to compile the voter list for this year's balloting. In contrast, Mexico's youth vote has become dominant, with half the electorate under 35 years old, he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Karina de Martinez, 26, is one of an estimated six million young Mexicans expected to vote this year for the first time.</p>
        <p>''I never saw any reason to vote before, because I knew the PRI would win and it'd just be more of the same,'' she said. Her husband, who manages a federal toll highway running through Queretaro, says he does not like Mr. Fox's brash style, but will vote for him anyway to bring change. ''Being in the government, you see all the corruption that exists,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One day in early May, Lucia Hernandez, the maid, paused as she loaded clothes into the washing machine to ask Mrs. Martinez whom she planned to vote for.</p>
        <p>''I said Fox,'' Mrs. Martinez said. ''Lucia said she was going to vote for Labastida. And to tell you the truth, it made me angry! This is why the PRI could still win, because of people like our maid. I asked myself, 'How can that be?' ''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hernandez has nine children; five others died as infants. She lives in Chichimiquillas, a gritty village where the business district consists of a tiny store stocked with crackers and Coca-Cola, a tire repair shop, and a sherbet stand. To arrive at the Martinez home, she rides a bus for an hour through bone-dry hills.</p>
        <p>''Everybody votes for the PRI there,'' she said in a conversation with a visitor in the Martinez living room, even though many of her neighbors lost their life savings in  Mexico's 1994 peso devaluation. Hundreds of straw-hatted villagers flocked to a recent rally in the Chichimiquillas square, she said, at  which PRI officials alternately praised Mr. Labastida as a patriot and raffled off refrigerators and washing machines.</p>
        <p>''I didn't win anything,'' she said wistfully of the rally. ''Still, we have a lot of confidence in the PRI. Whenever I've needed a hand they've always helped me. Why not say so?''</p>
        <p>A searing incident a decade ago appears to have sealed her PRI loyalties forever. Mrs. Hernandez took a neighbor's young daughter, suffering from dysentery, on a bus to a county hospital, she said. The child died in the hospital, and her parents did not have enough money to pay for a coffin and retrieve her body. Hat in hand, Mrs. Hernandez went to the local PRI political boss to ask for help. He gave her $50 to pay for a funeral, she recalled.</p>
        <p>''When somebody helps me like that, I don't forget it,'' Mrs. Hernandez said.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the PRI often seems forgotten in this state capital, even though until just three years ago the state had never had an opposition governor. Today both the state governor and the mayor of the state capital are from Mr. Fox's center-right National Action Party. The city's prosperous economy is based on dozens of factories that turn out everything from tractors to cornflakes. As in many Mexican cities, National Action has grown so rapidly in Queretaro that Labastida advisers say his campaign has virtually written it off as a lost cause.</p>
        <p>One young voter who helped elect National Action in Queretaro is Rodrigo Marvan Cuevas, 26, who is just embarking on an architectural career. His father, a well-known architect, has built office buildings for PRI governments for several decades, but Rodrigo considers the party's long monopoly on politics an embarrassing anachronism.</p>
        <p>''Our political system is still in diapers!'' he mused during a conversation at his studio in a leafy Queretaro neighborhood. ''How can it be that only recently the vote in Mexico has begun to count?'' Mr. Marvan intends to vote for Mr. Fox.</p>
        <p>''No private business ever does well without competition, and it's the same thing in politics,'' he said, adjusting the volume on a recording by Duke Ellington as he talked.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a single PRI friend,'' he said. ''In my generation and at my educational and professional level, there just are no PRI members.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
