<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="02BRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D9103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>LUXEMBOURG: HOSTAGE-TAKER SHOT -- Police officers used a gun disguised as a television camera and the lure of an interview to shoot a gunman, critically injuring him and freeing 25 children and 3 adults who had been held hostage for more than 28 hours at a day-care center. None of the hostages were hurt. The hostage-taker, left, who had demanded to be flown to Libya, was armed with a pistol, grenades and a knife.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: LONDON BOMB BLAST -- A small bomb blew up under the Hammersmith Bridge over the Thames , causing structural damage and traffic chaos but no injuries. No one claimed responsibility, but authorities speculated that the blast was timed by dissident Irish republicans to disrupt the power-sharing Northern Ireland government. The bridge has been the target of two prior Irish republican bombs.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>LUXEMBOURG: HOSTAGE-TAKER SHOT -- Police officers used a gun disguised as a television camera and the lure of an interview to shoot a gunman, critically injuring him and freeing 25 children and 3 adults who had been held hostage for more than 28 hours at a day-care center. None of the hostages were hurt. The hostage-taker, left, who had demanded to be flown to Libya, was armed with a pistol, grenades and a knife.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: LONDON BOMB BLAST -- A small bomb blew up under the Hammersmith Bridge over the Thames , causing structural damage and traffic chaos but no injuries. No one claimed responsibility, but authorities speculated that the blast was timed by dissident Irish republicans to disrupt the power-sharing Northern Ireland government. The bridge has been the target of two prior Irish republican bombs.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: DUNKIRK REVISITED -- Sixty years after the ragtag flotilla that Churchill called Britain's ''great tide of small vessels'' helped rescue 340,000 soldiers from the beaches of Dunkirk, some 60 boats will cross the English Channel from Dover today in commemoration. In 1940 hundreds of fishing boats, pleasure craft and tugs braved German fire for 10 days to ferry soldiers pinned down by the Nazi advance to navy ships in deeper waters.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: LOWER HOUSE DISSOLVED -- Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori dissolved Parliament's Lower House today, a widely anticipated move that clears the way for snap elections on June 25. Mr. Mori's popularity has plummeted since his remark last month that Japan is a ''divine nation'' centered on the emperor, but his Liberal Democrats were not expected to lose their position as the country's ruling party.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: SEPARATIST REPORTED SLAIN -- An exiled separatist leader fighting for independence for Aceh Province was shot dead in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, hours before a truce between the rebels and Indonesia took effect, his wife said. Putri Mei Abdullah said her husband, Teuku Don Zulfahri, secretary general of the Free Aceh Movement, based in Malaysia, was gunned down at a restaurant.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>INDIA: NEPAL FLIGHTS RESUME -- Indian Airlines has resumed flights to Nepal five months after Islamic militants hijacked one of its planes from Katmandu. The national carrier suspended flights because of what India saw as security lapses. The shutdown cost Nepal millions of dollars in lost tourism revenues.</p>
        <p>Celia W. Dugger (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>EGYPT: NO E-MAIL DIVORCE -- A Muslim can divorce his wife by uttering the words ''I divorce you'' three times, but he cannot end a marriage by pronouncing his decision in an e-mail message, a court in Alexandria has ruled. The court said Islam, which is the basis of family law in Egypt, does not accept electronic documents as evidence. The issue arose in the case of a woman who remarried after receiving an e-mail divorce message from her first husband, who later changed his mind and demanded she come back to him.</p>
        <p>Susan Sachs (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: GOLAN BUILDING -- The Israel Lands Authority issued tenders for the marketing of 86 housing units in the Golan Heights settlement of Katzrin. Leftist lawmakers criticized the move, saying that if peace talks with Syria resume, the new construction will be ''like a bone stuck in Israel's throat,'' as Mossi Raz, a legislator,  put it.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: DAY 4 OF BOMBING -- American and British jets bombed air defenses for a fourth day running after coming under fire over a no-flight zone in the north, the European Central Command said. It was the 39th such incident this year but the first time an exchange of fire has continued for four straight days.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>MOZAMBIQUE: FLOOD VICTIMS RESETTLED -- Seventy percent of the people displaced by this year's devastating floods have been resettled or returned home, the government reported. Of the more than 490,300 people displaced, about 4,500 were still living in resettlement camps last month. All told, about 700 people died in the floods that ravaged this country in February and March.</p>
        <p>Rachel L. Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>ECUADOR: COUP PLOTTER PARDONED -- Congress has pardoned the former armed forces chief of staff, Gen. Carlos Mendoza, and 116 other military officers involved in the January coup in which President Jamil Mahuad was overthrown and replaced by Vice President Gustavo Noboa. The amnesty, suggested by Mr. Noboa, eliminates the need for what was expected to be a politically divisive trial of General Mendoza, above, who has said other senior military commanders were involved in the plot but refused to identify them.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>CANADA: ENVOY BACKS GORE -- Canada's ambassador to the United States has effectively endorsed Al Gore over George W. Bush in the presidential race. ''We know Vice President Gore, he knows us; he's a friend of Canada,'' Raymond Chretien said in a speech to Canadian officials. The ambassador, a nephew of Prime Minister Jean Chretien, said, ''Governor Bush, on the other hand, doesn't know us as much,'' adding, ''When he thinks of borders, he thinks of Mexico, not of Canada.''</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: CARDENAS PARTY FINED -- The party of the leftist presidential candidate Cuauhtemoc Cardenas was hit with fines of $253,082 by the federal elections agency for filing incomplete accounts of its spending last year, the highest of the sanctions levied against 11 political organizations. The governing Institutional Revolutionary Party was fined only $6,571.</p>
        <p>Julia Preston (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
