<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="02ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DE153CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="8388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free.  * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ''ART AND ORACLE: SPIRIT VOICES OF AFRICA,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through July 30). This is the first big international loan exhibition of African art to appear at the Met outside the Michael C. Rockefeller wing, and it is gorgeous. The subject is divination, the practice of channeling superhuman knowledge to predict the future, diagnose illness and promote social harmony. Nearly every object here has a role in that process or reflects its effects, from a ''power figure'' that looks as explosive as a stick of dynamite to a Yoruba divination tray believed to be the oldest African wood sculpture in the West to the portrait of a king who was warned by diviners to beware of water and had himself depicted as half-fish. (He ended up in exile far across the Atlantic in Martinique.) Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:15 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 8:45 p.m. Admission: $10; $5, students and the elderly (Holland Cotter).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The New York Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free.  * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ''ART AND ORACLE: SPIRIT VOICES OF AFRICA,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through July 30). This is the first big international loan exhibition of African art to appear at the Met outside the Michael C. Rockefeller wing, and it is gorgeous. The subject is divination, the practice of channeling superhuman knowledge to predict the future, diagnose illness and promote social harmony. Nearly every object here has a role in that process or reflects its effects, from a ''power figure'' that looks as explosive as a stick of dynamite to a Yoruba divination tray believed to be the oldest African wood sculpture in the West to the portrait of a king who was warned by diviners to beware of water and had himself depicted as half-fish. (He ended up in exile far across the Atlantic in Martinique.) Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:15 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 8:45 p.m. Admission: $10; $5, students and the elderly (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>* WILLIAM MERRITT CHASE, ''Modern American Landscapes, 1886-1890,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 (through Aug. 13). Chase (1849-1916) had a long, distinguished run as a painter, teacher and art politician. But this show zeroes in on the five-year period when, in a transitional phase between the brown, murky tones of his Munich training and his arrival at a lighter style based on French Impressionism, he painted genteel views of park landscapes in Brooklyn and Manhattan. Aside from their engaging scenic content, the 35 oils and pastels in the show are important because they are the first paintings in which an Impressionist style was used to depict American subjects. Recent examinations corrected some errors about their locales. And new scholarly speculations on Chase's motives for painting them suggest that he wanted them to serve as examples of ''civilized urban landscapes'' that accorded with the European avant-garde model of modern life. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (to 11 p.m. on the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $4; $2, students and the elderly (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''MAKING CHOICES, 1920-1960,'' Museum of Modern Art, 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9480 (through Sept. 26). The main event at the Modern these days is the museum itself. This has been the case since last fall, when the project ''MOMA 2000'' began the first of what will be three successive top-to-bottom reinstallations of the permanent collection galleries. The affair has been billed as a test drive toward the future, a chance for an institution to rethink the modern art tradition it helped to invent and to consider its own identity in what is often called a postmodern world. This second installment, which looks denser, weirder, messier and more truly modern (or maybe postmodern) than the first, is a big leap in the right direction. Hours: Thursdays through Tuesdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays, to 8:15 p.m. Admission: $10; $6.50, students and the elderly (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''MASTERPIECES OF JAPANESE ART FROM THE MARY GRIGGS BURKE COLLECTION,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through June 25). The good news is this ravishing exhibition of Japanese art, ranging from Neolithic pottery to knee-weakening Edo-period screens with a breadth and depth rarely seen in New York. Even better news is that a large part of the collection from which these 200 works are drawn is a promised gift to the Met, placing it suddenly among the top five museums for Japanese art in the United States. The show includes Buddhist sculptures and mandalas, monochrome ink paintings and calligraphy, hand scrolls and hanging scrolls as well as occasional but outstanding examples of ceramics and lacquerware. A specific Japanese sensibility, alternately refined and earthy, discreet and rambunctious, spiritual and cosmopolitan, and always astoundingly attuned to materials, is revealed here. Hours and admission: See above (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''MICHELANGELO TO PICASSO: MASTER DRAWINGS FROM THE COLLECTION OF THE ALBERTINA, VIENNA,'' Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 (through June 18). The Albertina, which has one of the world's greatest collections of works on paper, houses 65,000 drawings and watercolors and nearly a million prints, from Gothic to contemporary. The small sampling of 45 drawings and watercolors here runs from Michelangelo to Jackson Pollock and includes many works that have never before left Austria. Standouts include Leonardo's ''Half-Length of an Apostle''; four drawings by Durer, including his ''Head of an Old Man'' (1521); Michelangelo's anatomical study ''Seated Male Nude With Two Arms''; and Raphael's ''Madonna and Child.'' There are  works by Rubens, Rembrandt, Poussin, Claude Lorrain, van Gogh, Picasso, Klimt, Schiele, Chagall and lesser-knowns. It is not often that one gets to see this range of masters packed into one small show, a fine teaser for the full Albertina experience. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Admission: $7; $5, students and the elderly (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''MAXFIELD PARRISH, 1870-1966,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 (through Aug. 6). A romantic fabulist who painted in a tight, finicky mode that left out no detail, Parrish (1870-1966) was a highly accomplished illustrator who could be considered the father of Norman Rockwell. As a more aspiring painter, he also pursued a never-never world of chaste but titillating young women and knightly men in pastoral landscapes that melded medieval towers with New England forests, Western gorges and the deep blue skies of fairy kingdoms. This show of more than 140 paintings, drawings, prints, illustrations and ephemera ranges from such well-known Parrish chestnuts as ''Daybreak'' (1922), depicting a young woman's ecstatic awakening to an erotically symbolic Dawn, to his coy, cartoonish ''Old King Cole'' mural of 1894. Aside from its campy entertainment value, there is enough here -- particularly his graphic art and some fine landscapes -- to sustain the revival of interest in his work that began with the Pop Art era. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''THE PRINZHORN COLLECTION: TRACES UPON THE WUNDERBLOCK,'' Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166 (through June 10). The legendary Prinzhorn Collection, amassed just before and after World War I in Heidelberg, Germany, is one of the originating points of the study and appreciation of art by the insane. The collection's first New York appearance is a mine of exciting new information: 200 drawings and handmade books that often stun the eye and always touch the heart, by mostly unfamiliar artists. Its suggestion that the art of the insane is not pure, timeless and autonomous but part of a larger continuum of art and visual culture may be the exhibition's most valuable lesson. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Free (Smith).</p>
        <p>''1900: ART AT THE CROSSROADS,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, Fifth Avenue at 88th Street, (212) 423-3500 (through Sept. 10). A wacky exercise in historical simulation, the excuse being a new century. It is hard to remember the last time so many bad pictures were in one place at one time, unless you consider eBay a place. There is also a good deal of excellent art mixed in among the dogs, and sometimes what is best is not what you would expect, which is partly the show's point. We're meant to look anew at a moment 100 years ago when it was not yet clear who would be the pioneers in the 20th century and who would be forgotten. The show provides just enough compensatory rewards for its schlock quotient. The weak-hearted and modern-day culture Pharisees may never get past the shock of confronting so much of the art that the abstractionists were rebelling against in a museum created as a shrine to 20th-century abstraction. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays ad Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission: $12; $7, students and the elderly (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''TREASURES FROM THE ROYAL TOMBS OF UR,'' Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, (212) 685-0610 (through Sept. 10).The Sumerians flourished in third-millennium Mesopotamia, creating one of the earliest civilizations as they devised such essentials as writing, numbers, the wheel and irrigation methods. This sumptuous exhibition attests to their visual achievement with gold, silver and carved calcite vessels; weapons, tools and cylinder seals; and ingenious jewelry made of lapis lazuli, carnelian and gold. On view as well are several of art history's most familiar, if least exhibited, masterpieces. All belong to the University of Pennsylvania and are part of one of archaeology's greatest discoveries: the intact, lavishly equipped royal tombs excavated at Ur in the 1920's by C. Leonard Woolley. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10:30 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; $6, students and the elderly (Smith).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>JOHN BOWMAN, Winston Wachter Mayer, 39 East 78th Street, (212) 327-2526 (through June 30). Since the 1980's, Mr. Bowman has been using traditional painting styles to allegorize postmodernist historical and philosophical conundrums. More interesting conceptually than formally, his new paintings include mysterious images of Renaissance-style theater prosceniums teeming with Ensoresque faces, masks and gargoyles. In one we look out from the stage over a serene, autumnal forest. Maybe the empty stage signifies the end of master narratives (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>VIK MUNIZ, '' 'Photographs' and Personal Articles,'' Ubu Gallery, 16 East 78th Street, (212) 794-4444 (through June 10). In a series of handmade ''snapshots'' and ingeniously concocted newspaper clippings, Mr. Muniz continues his special brand of trompe l'oeil, full of surreal wit, tell-tale signs of deception and insights into how the mind and eye construct and refute visual illusion (Smith).</p>
        <p>FRANCIS PICABIA, ''Late Works,'' Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623 (through June 8). From Cubism and Dada to postmodernism, there is hardly a 20th-century art movement that this maverick French modernist has not contributed to or presaged. This show confirms his prescience and his stylistic profligacy, but it also reveals the high levels of painterly experimentation, curiosity and passion basic to his perpetual motion (Smith).</p>
        <p>VITTORIO SELLA, ''Mountaineer and Photographer, 1879-1909,'' New York School of Interior Design, 161 East 69th Street, (212) 472-1500 (through June 10). Some of the world's most spectacular peaks sat for portraits by Sella (1859-1943), including the Matterhorn in Switzerland, Kangchengjunga in Nepal and K2 in the Himalayas. This intrepid Italian climber is thought by many to have been the greatest mountaineering photographer of all time. And his spectacular views of soaring summits, sprawling glaciers, breathtaking crevasses, awesome ice falls and the people who braved them tend to bear out that opinion. There have been mountaineering photographs before and since his time, but few with the freshness and compositional clarity of these (Glueck).</p>
        <p>JAMES SHEEHAN, Joseph Rickards, 1045 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street, (212) 924-0858 (through June 16). Scale is of the essence in Mr. Sheehan's painting. He makes robustly painterly pictures of crowds, swimmers or cruise ship scenes on panels smaller than two and a half inches square. A thumbnail-size piece of reflective paper bears an almost microscopic image of the artist's high school swim team. The imagery is not very exciting, but the combination of tiny scale and richly worked paint makes for attractively idiosyncratic objects (Johnson).</p>
        <p>LORRAINE SHEMESH, Allan Stone, 113 East 90th Street, (212) 987-4997 (through June 9). Swimming verges on religious experience in Ms. Shemesh's frothy but overly illustrative paintings. Immersed in luminous, painterly flux, male and female swimmers grasping one another's feet make a living yin-yang symbol; seen from below, a woman sitting in a pink inflated doughnut seems to float heavenward (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>ALEXANDER ARCHIPENKO, ''Terra Cotta Sculptures,'' Zabriskie Gallery, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 752-1223 (through June 10). These suave, mostly small terra cotta figures were made by Archipenko (1887-1964), an innovator in early 20th-century sculpture, in the 1930's. They deal with the female form, from solid, sensuous torso to near-abstraction in which open spaces play a role. One of their distinctive features is elegant surface finish, highly polished with the addition of colored elements and inlays to the basic structure. He is at his best in several beautifully modeled torsos of idealized figures that reach for the spiritual essence of form (Glueck).</p>
        <p>HANS HOFMANN, ''The Summer Studio,'' Ameringer/Howard Fine Art, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 935-1110 (through June 9). Cape Cod was the summer life and subject of Hofmann (1880-1966), who observed it for more than 30 years from his Provincetown studio. In oil, watercolor or pen and ink, he depicted it in many modes, from abstraction to outright realism. The works here vary from mere sketches to large finished paintings but collectively they have the exuberance of Hofmann's engagement with a very lively scene. Hofmann used many of the sketches as tryouts for larger painting ideas but they hold their own (Glueck).</p>
        <p>JOHN TORREANO, Littlejohn, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 980-2323 (through June 10). A gimmick like adding fake gemstones to paintings and sculptures should quickly wear thin, but Mr. Torreano has been doing it for almost 30 years and his new works look as fresh and vivid as ever. This show presents mostly smooth, round-ended, thematically decorated columns attached to the wall. ''Dalmation'' is white and studded with near-black gems; ''Pistachio'' has gold-leafed wooden balls imbedded in its ice-cream green surface (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>EDWIN SCHLOSSBERG, ''Figure: Ground,'' Ronald Feldman, 31 Mercer Street, (212) 226-3232 (through June 24). Mr. Schlossberg shows a series of text works: rectangular brass sheets with cut-out Jasper Johns-style letters spelling out portentous phrases like ''being conscious becomes our destruction'' or ''awake through every wave.'' The brass sheets were also used to stencil black-and-white paper versions activated by graphic and gestural additions (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DANIEL SPOERRI: ''LE CABINET ANATOMIQUE,'' Emily Harvey, 537 Broadway, at Spring Street, (212) 925-7651 (through June 10). One of the French Nouveaux Realistes along with Yves Klein, Arman, Jean Tinguely and others, Mr. Spoerri was known in the early 60's for turning chance arrangements of objects on tables into wall-hung sculptures. Here he presents small, framed assemblages, in each of which exotic and banal objects like shells, masks, tools, dolls, jewelry or bones are attached to old anatomical diagrams, producing a familiarly Surrealistic poetry (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JEFFREY STURGES, Spencer Brownstone, 39 Wooster Street, (212) 334-3455 (through June 30). Photography of corporate, industrial or otherwise anonymous functional architecture is a common genre now, but Mr. Sturges gives it a compelling beauty in large, richly colored prints. Pictures of a brick wall sandwiched between deep blue sky and intensely green grass or of a well-lighted and clean pedestrian tunnel in Zurich are compositionally perfect and dreamily vivid (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ROBERT ZANDVLIET, Peter Blum, 99 Wooster Street, (212) 343-0441 (through June 10). For his first New York solo show, this young Dutch painter presents a group of large black-and-white, Abstract Expressionist-style monotypes. They are less interesting, however, than five egg tempera-on-canvas paintings also on view. The latter, layered compositions of wide, crisscrossing brush strokes, call to mind Franz Kline, Gerhard Richter and David Reed but have their own attractively muted color and buttery sensuousness (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>OLADELE BAMGBOYE, Thomas Erben Gallery, 516 West 20th Street, (212) 645-8701 (through June 10). The first New York solo for this British artist includes a new, multipart interactive digital piece, which is an update on ethnology and its obsession with authenticity, and a cyberspace take on the question of the original in art. The show's main visual interest, though, comes from large-print 1980's photographs in which the artist's nude figure seems to be half-submerged in backgrounds of patterned fabric or wallpaper. The pictures look computer-assisted but were produced from studio setups (Cotter).</p>
        <p>ROBERT BREER, AC Project Room, 453 West 17th Street, (212) 645-4970 (through June 24). An original members of the 1960's group E.A.T. (Experiments in Art and Technology), Mr. Breer here presents vintage examples of one of his signature concepts: motorized Minimalist sculptures that move slowly and comically about as though they had lives of their own. A white Styrofoam square creeps purposefully across the floor; a rumpled silver blanket breathes; seven toylike black domes dragging eccentric linear trailers produce a constantly metamorphosing three-dimensional ''Floor Drawing'' (Johnson).</p>
        <p>HOVEY BROCK, Jeffrey Coploff, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 741-1149 (through June 17) Mr. Brock makes large, loopy watercolors of captivating subtlety. Using a wide brush and diluted paint on off-white panels or paper, he traces circulating, linear arabesques over and over, creating shimmering entanglements that seem to hover in space like knots of cosmic or submolecular energy (Johnson).</p>
        <p>E. V. DAY, ''Transformer,'' Henry Urbach, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 627-0974 (through June 10). Ms. Day takes the idea of exploding female stereotypes a little too literally: she creates installations in which glamorous evening gowns are shown in the process of being blown to bits. A close-fitting silver-sequined dress, evoking the one Marilyn Monroe wore to sing ''Happy Birthday'' to President Kennedy, gets the treatment here. Like a lot of political art today, the effect is suave, entertaining and subject to several interpretations, all of them more or less one-liners (Smith).</p>
        <p>WALTON FORD, Paul Kasmin, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474 (through June 30). An impressive, life-size watercolor of a rampaging Indian elephant dominates this exhibition. The galloping, sexually aroused pachyderm is rendered in faux-antique style on 22 separately framed pages assembled into one looming 12-by-18-foot rectangle. Curiously, the elephant has attracted dozens of birds -- owls, starlings, goldfinches, vultures, larks; they are meant to symbolize Western efforts to colonize India (Johnson).</p>
        <p>PAUL GEORGES, ''The Big Idea,'' Center for Figurative Painting, 115 West 30th Street, (212) 868-3452 (through June 30). Although he has stayed with traditional subject matter -- self-portraits, nudes, landscapes, flowers and mythological scenes -- Mr. Georges brings a modernist outlook to it. This miniretrospective of nearly 20 paintings in diverse styles reveals how he has brightened and lightened his palette over the years, tempering his affection for the old masters with the hereandnow. An example is an inviting self-portrait of 1989-90 whose welcoming informality is conveyed in a dazzlement of light and color. He is also a master at flower painting; his colorful blooms, in gardens or in vases, have a lusty freshness few contemporary painters can match (Glueck).</p>
        <p>ELLIOT GREEN, Postmasters, 459 West 19th Street, (212) 727-3323 (through June 24). Mr. Green's paintings look like Saturday morning cartoons filtered through a child's feverish delirium. Rubbery arms and legs, bizarrely swollen fingers, big scary shoes and sad, misshapen faces are packed into fragmented, emotionally-charged scenarios. Yet even as they tap into elemental desires and anxieties, they remain works of great formal elegance, with carefully penciled, serpentine lines, richly muted color and tightly interlocking, de Kooningesque compositions (Johnson).</p>
        <p>CHARLES MCGILL, ''Club Negro,'' Barbara Ann Levy, 453 West 17th Street, (212) 645-7810 (through June 17). Mr. McGill, an African-American artist who plays golf, has come up with a funny line of satiric mock-commodities for black golfers under the fictive label ''Club Negro.'' A faux-commercial display promotes new, Africanized golf balls like the ''New Spook'' (''If you can't beat them, scare them,'' reads the ad copy on the shelf) or the ''Malcom X,'' which is ''guaranteed to improve your game by any means necessary'' (Johnson).</p>
        <p>LUCA PIGNATELLI, Generous Miracles, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 352-2858 (through June 15). Big, brooding and theatrical, the paintings by this Italian artist could be overbearing and portentous, but they are not. Rather, ghostly pictures of a World War II bomber flying over a mountain lake or a massive, charging locomotive or snowy forests -- all realized in dark stains on distressed, stitched-together tarps -- are ruggedly physical and mysteriously romantic (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ROBERT STACKHOUSE, Urban Architecture, 210 11th Avenue, near 24th Street, (212) 924-1688 (through June 10). Mr. Stackhouse was one of a number of ambitious sculptors who in the 1970's turned from Minimalism to a more psychologically evocative, architectonic installation work. This disappointing exhibition, his first in New York in almost five years, presents illustrative painted images like a spiraling snake or a boatlike structure extended into Abstract Expressionistic space and a collection of big rocks organized on the floor into a shape like a ship's hull (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''TOPOLOGIES,'' White Box, 525 West 26th Street, (212) 714-2347 (through June 17). Inaugurating this gallery's expansive new basement site, ''Topologies'' brings together six conceptualist approaches to architectural basics: a wall incision by William Anastasi; poetic text on a column by Lawrence Weiner; archetypal building blocks by Barry Le Va; a partial reconstruction of a Peruvian ruin by Osvaldo Romberg; a sound piece by Shelley Hirsch to animate the entry ramp; and a video projection by Maria Marshall to dissolve a wall (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JASON YOUNG, Cristinerose, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 206-0297 (through June 17). Working more like a sculptor than a painter, Mr. Young pours, paints, layers, sands and otherwise tools synthetic resin on medium-size panels, producing sleek, biomorphically patterned abstractions. At once repellantly plastic and seductively tactile, they exude -- and perhaps critique -- the vacant allure of industrialized decoration (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''CLOCKWORK 2000,'' P.S 1 National and International Studio Program 1999-2000, Clocktower Gallery,108 Leonard Street, between Broadway and Lafayette Streets, Lower Manhattan, (718) 784-2084 (through June 17). A genial showcase of the 18 artists from 14 countries who have worked on the Lower Manhattan premises over the last year as part of P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center's studio programs. Self-invented systems, hybrid media (often discreetly computer-assisted), unshowy formal polish and a preference for understated ideas with resonant implications are threads that run through a show whose transnational mix confirms yet again that New York is an important cultural node on a global circulatory system (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''KEITH HARING: THE SVA YEARS (1978-1980),'' School of Visual Arts, 209 East 23rd Street, (212) 592-2010 (through June 17). This exhibition documents Haring's studies at S.V.A. and might interest his fans. Haring was evidently an exceptionally intelligent and energetic student, alive to all kinds of possibilities, from Abstract Expressionistic painting to text-based Conceptualism to video performance. Naturally it is his knack for comic graphic invention that shines, especially in a delightful series of 77 small pencil drawings made in one day called ''Manhattan Penis Drawings for Ken Hicks'' (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>''ART IN THE AGE OF QUEEN VICTORIA: TREASURES FROM THE ROYAL ACADEMY OF ARTS PERMANENT COLLECTION,'' National Academy of Design Museum, Fifth Avenue at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880 (through Sunday). The Royal Academy, founded in 1768 and still going strong, was a driving force in British art in the 19th century. The 76 paintings and sculptures here, spanning Victoria's reign, include biblical and mythological scenes, genre subjects with morality themes, swashbuckling costume portraits, idealized nudes, exotic tales, behind-the-battle glimpses, landscapes and seascapes. Among the more appealing and amusing works is Richard Redgrave's ''Outcast'' (1851), in which an outraged father dismisses his fallen daughter and her illegitimate baby. ''Treasures'' like these make this wonderfully fustian display worth visiting. Hours: Today, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; tomorrow and Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $5 (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''BIENNIAL 2000,'' Whitney Museum of American Art, Madison Avenue at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676 (through Sunday). A show without a theme: no strong point of view, not much sex, no dead pigs or rotting eggs, or mannequins with a penis for a nose. Sounds boring, no? This committee-organized Biennial goes out of its way to be ecumenical, independent, geographically diverse, representative of all media including the Internet and different from what the New York power brokers would do. All this may be admirable. It is also truer than previous biennials to what goes on across the country; truer to the character of the American scene, where artists come from other countries; more respectful of different generations and multiple strategies. And flat. Notwithstanding Hans Haacke's forgettable noisemaker, it is the most uncontroversial Whitney Biennial in years, which is not good. Hours: Today through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.. Admission: $12.50; $10.50, students and the elderly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>RENE DANIELS, Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-7100 (through tomorrow). Conceptual painting is in. Artists like Martin Kippenberger, Elizabeth Peyton and Luc Tuymans are fashionable and suddenly this neglected Dutch painter, whose career was stopped by illness in 1987, looks like a prophet. The pictures of trees, swans and the receding inside of a gallery, sometimes abstracted into the shape of a bow tie, wring symbolist poetry from ordinary stuff effortlessly (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>AGNES MARTIN, PaceWildenstein, 32 East 57th Street, (212) 421-3292 (through tomorrow). It is possible to experience in Ms. Martin's new paintings -- all five-foot squares bearing pale, watery stripes separated by penciled lines -- as shimmering, transcendental luminosity. The dingy, washed-out blues, oranges or yellows and the nondescript surfaces may also cause a feeling of sensory deprivation. How one responds may depend as much on faith as on taste (Johnson)</p>
        <p>''WOMEN OF WARHOL: MARILYN, LIZ AND JACKIE,'' C&amp;M Arts, 45 East 78th Street, (212) 861-0020 (through tomorrow). A ghostly evanescent power permeates this show, the result of Warhol's tissue-thin pictorial magic, his canny eye for the iconic potential of everyday images -- whether from movie magazines, publicity stills or newspapers -- and his correct assumption that the weight of history could anchor his seemingly ephemeral art (Smith).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
