<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Arabs Fight, Israelis Surf</title>
    <meta content="02FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0D9133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Arabs Fight, Israelis Surf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column lauds Prime Min Ehud Barak's courageous decision to unilaterally withdraw Israeli forces from Lebanon; says the restoration of a clear-cut border between Lebanon and Israel will only leave Israel more powerful and able to hold Lebanese and Syrian governments responsible without ambiguity</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Israeli Army's hasty withdrawal from Lebanon has triggered a debate both within Israel and in the surrounding Arab states -- a debate that could be headlined simply: ''Is Israel wimping out?''</p>
        <p>The right wing in Israel argues that the unilateral Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon was an embarrassing sign of weakness -- which will only invite more Arab attacks. The Shiite radicals in Lebanon describe this Israeli withdrawal as a sign of the Muslims' superior willingness to fight, and one that will only lead to more victories over Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Israeli Army's hasty withdrawal from Lebanon has triggered a debate both within Israel and in the surrounding Arab states -- a debate that could be headlined simply: ''Is Israel wimping out?''</p>
        <p>The right wing in Israel argues that the unilateral Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon was an embarrassing sign of weakness -- which will only invite more Arab attacks. The Shiite radicals in Lebanon describe this Israeli withdrawal as a sign of the Muslims' superior willingness to fight, and one that will only lead to more victories over Israel.</p>
        <p>How should one think about these arguments? Well, does the term hogwash mean anything to you?</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak's courageous decision to unilaterally withdraw Israeli forces from Lebanon has, for the first time in 22 years, restored a clear-cut border between Lebanon and Israel, and that will only leave Israel with a tighter fist and a more unified public, ready to protect what is really important. Why? It all starts with borders.</p>
        <p>''Barak discovered something extremely important in Lebanon,'' remarked the Israeli political theorist Yaron Ezrahi, ''that a border is a source of power. Because when you don't have a border, you have a constant problem justifying the use of power. Whenever Israel has found itself in conflicts without borders -- south Lebanon, the Palestinian intifada in the West Bank -- it has always lost, because it always found it difficult to win support, either at home or abroad, for the force that is required to win a war without borders. Israelis will only sanction such force and sacrifice for a war of clear-cut self-defense over a defined border.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Barak, by drawing such a clear-cut border with Lebanon, has enabled Israel to reassert its real strengths there: It can now use its powerful air force, unrestrained; it can hold the Lebanese and Syrian governments responsible, without ambiguity; it now has the backing of the world community for any self-defense along the Lebanon border.</p>
        <p>The Israeli right's favorite line about Lebanon is, ''If you won't fight for this thing, you won't fight for anything.'' But most Israelis know exactly the difference between what is worth fighting for and what isn't. Mr. Barak's drawing that distinction in Lebanon was not a loss of ''will,'' it was a loss of willingness to go on doing something self-defeating.</p>
        <p>The great mistake Western observers make when writing about Arab-Israeli affairs is assuming that only Israelis want to raise their living standards, send their kids to college and get better jobs, and that those aspirations never apply to Muslims, particularly Muslims fighting Israel. In the view of Israeli right-wingers, the Muslims just want to kill Jews and the Jews just wanna have fun; the Shiites live to die and the Israelis live to surf the Web. So the Jewish right accuses the Muslims of not wanting a better life for their families and they accuse Israel of wanting it too much, being too ready to compromise instead of fight.</p>
        <p>In reality, both peoples aspire to much the same things. Yes, there are Muslims in south Lebanon dedicated to destroying Israel. I've met them. But they are in the minority, and they can be effective only when the majority is ready to tolerate them and pay the price of their hatred. But the vast majority of south Lebanese simply wanted the Israelis out of their lives so they could make their own better. And now that the Israelis are gone, few Lebanese are prepared to sacrifice their future to a self-defeating fantasy of marching on Jerusalem. It is not because they have learned to like Israel, but because they want to live like Israel.</p>
        <p>Americans thought Vietnamese were subhuman too, ready to bear any sacrifice just to kill Americans. And then we quit Vietnam, and now the visa line at the U.S. Embassy in Hanoi for Vietnamese trying to get into the U.S. stretches down the block.</p>
        <p>You see, power is about a lot of things. It's about the strength of an economy, the democratic quality of a society, the shared values of a community and most of all the will of a people to fight to protect all those things when they are clearly endangered. Mao was only half right: Power grows out of the barrel of a gun -- but only if it is held by a soldier who knows what border he is protecting and why. In that sense, Israel today is more powerful than ever.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
