<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making It 'To Go'</title>
    <meta content="02EATI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6DD133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making It 'To Go'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eating Out reviews of restaurants with good food to take out; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York, with its large and diverse selection of restaurants, has always been a great place for dining out, but it also has an impressive range of cuisines available for takeout. Here are a dozen places for those times you prefer to eat in. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Campagna Home</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 420-1600</p>
        <p>29 East 21st Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York, with its large and diverse selection of restaurants, has always been a great place for dining out, but it also has an impressive range of cuisines available for takeout. Here are a dozen places for those times you prefer to eat in. (These summaries are taken from dining reviews, columns and articles in The Times by William Grimes, Eric Asimov and others.)</p>
        <p>1. Campagna Home</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 420-1600</p>
        <p>29 East 21st Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>What makes a pot roast Tuscan? Perhaps the rich gravy is made with Chianti, or olive oil is used to brown the brisket? Either way, the Tuscan pot roast at Campagna Home is fabulous, lean and tender enough to melt in your mouth. And while it may be called Tuscan, it is equally Jewish, reflecting the formula that the chef, Mark Strausman, has used so well in Campagna, his restaurant just across the street. This bright takeout shop offers prepared dishes as well as meats, cheeses and colorful Italian and Provencal tableware. The heartier the better seems to be the rule in selecting dishes, like the meaty, savory lasagna and the wonderfully gooey eggplant Parmesan, just as thick and as layered as the lasagna. Sausage and peppers in tomato sauce is made with spicy sausages.</p>
        <p>2. Dimple</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(718) 458-8144</p>
        <p>35-68 73rd Street</p>
        <p>Jackson Heights, Queens</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>The menu sounds prosaic at this bright little vegetarian Indian takeout spot. But taste the food and it takes your breath away. Everything is wonderfully spiced, providing not merely heat but a clear amplification of the flavors. Chopped potatoes are pleasantly sour, seasoned with cumin and mustard seeds. Cabbage is searingly hot, tossed with an oil infused with mustard seeds, while lentils taste earthy and deep. Thin lentil soup is just as wickedly hot, also thanks to mustard seeds. The thali comes with terrific paratha, excellent rice and one of the many sweets displayed behind a counter.</p>
        <p>3. It's a Wrap</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 362-7922</p>
        <p>2012 Broadway, near 69th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>The food can be excellent at this wrap specialist. The wraps are just about all tasty and inviting and have just the right proportion of wet-to-dry ingredients. The combination of tangy hummus and baba gannouj with carrots, tomatoes and mesclun is particularly good. The roast pork with bean sprouts, scallions, carrot and tomato has a vaguely Vietnamese flavor. For refreshment, you might try the blueberry smoothie. This may also be the only restaurant around that delivers food into Central Park. It's a Wrap has another branch in the Village at 367 Avenue of the Americas, near Fourth Street.</p>
        <p>4. Kumquat</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 253-0003</p>
        <p>1 Fifth Avenue, at Eighth Street</p>
        <p>Greenwich Village</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>While the menu at Kumquat, the dinner-delivery arm of Clementine, is significantly simpler and less expensive, it offers unusual and intriguing selections. There are excellent salads, like frisee and Roquefort sprinkled with tarragon. Sauteed skate wing is moist and delicious, and steamed trout is unexpectedly flavorful. Other hits include a well-charred hamburger and wonderful ravioli stuffed with ricotta.</p>
        <p>5. Lorenzo and Maria's Kitchen</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 794-1080</p>
        <p>1418 Third Avenue, at 80th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>If your eyes need a treat, you can count on the window display at this small, high-end caterer. Much of it tastes as good as it looks, like a great individual chicken pot pie, full of meat, peas, onions and carrots, with just enough sauce to keep everything moist, all sheltered under a crisp mushroom-shape pastry. This is also one of those rare places where the desserts taste even better than they look.</p>
        <p>6. Mitchel London Foods</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 563-5969</p>
        <p>542 Ninth Avenue, at 40th Street</p>
        <p>Clinton</p>
        <p>$ Cash Only</p>
        <p>Mitchel London, the caterer, opened this little cafe and takeout shop in the shadow of the Port Authority Bus Terminal nearly two years ago. His menu -- hamburgers, fried chicken, roast chicken, etc. -- makes up for its lack of exoticism with meticulous preparation and excellent ingredients. He uses fine thick-cut bacon, ripe tomatoes and a soft, glossy brioche to present the B.L.T. in all its glory. Fried chicken is likewise superb, crisp and crusty.</p>
        <p>7. Mosaico</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 213-4700</p>
        <p>175 Madison Avenue, near 33rd Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ All major cards</p>
        <p>This colorful takeout shop allows you to bring nuevo latino food, the artful combination of traditional Latin ingredients with contemporary cooking techniques, into the home. The bright, airy room, with its colorful mosaic counters, feels slightly unreal, like a Disney World Latino Land, but the food can be excellent. One such dish is the baked Bolivian picnic chicken, half a boned chicken coated with a fiery curry paste and bread crumbs. The chicken tamale, wrapped in a banana leaf and steamed, is another top choice; the burrito-size block of steamed cornmeal encases shredded chicken, corn and raisins, with subtle spices that creep up on you. For dessert, try the whole figs stuffed with cajeta, sweetened goat's milk that tastes as rich as caramel.</p>
        <p>8. Musette</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 477-3777</p>
        <p>228 Third Avenue, near 19th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ Visa and MasterCard</p>
        <p>This handsome takeout shop, with its Parisian pale-red facade, opened two years ago next to its parent, Pitchoune, the fine little Provencal bistro. Its small selection begins with remarkably good desserts, like a creamy, delicate coffee napoleon, an all-American fudgy brownie and excellent tarts in flavors like strawberry, blackberry and cherry. If you can take your eyes off the gorgeous desserts, you're likely to find a whole roast chicken, moist, crinkle-skinned and lemon-scented, stuffed with olives and hunks of light, pillowy bread that absorb the citrus, olive and herbal flavors. You will also see excellent baked salmon with a light coating of lemon and herbs, and terrific salads like slices of sweet beets flecked with refreshing fennel. There are also unusual sandwiches, like the tart combination of thick slices of grilled chicken breast on ciabatta with arugula, sage, parsley and green olive tapenade.</p>
        <p>9. Pepe Verde</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 255-2221</p>
        <p>559 Hudson Street, near Perry Street</p>
        <p>Greenwich Village</p>
        <p>$ Cash Only</p>
        <p>If you order by phone, you'll miss the aroma of fresh bread, olive oil and ripe tomatoes. Pastas are terrific and never oversauced, like fusilli with broccoli rape and crumbled fennel sausage, or ravioli with butter and herbs. Boneless sauteed chicken breasts that have been bathed in herbs and marinated in lemon come with a mammoth serving of rice. And Pepe's sandwiches, especially air-cured beef on focaccia with arugula and Parmesan, are exceptional.</p>
        <p>10. Sushiden</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 758-2700</p>
        <p>19 East 49th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$$ All major cards</p>
        <p>Sushiden is not exactly a takeout shop. It's a full-service restaurant, but its takeout sushi happens to be a great treat. Whether you order the least expensive assortment at $18 or one of three larger selections, you are handed an embossed bag holding a slender box wrapped as elegantly as an expensive gift. When you get home and open the box you find sushi assortments arranged so beautifully you may simply want to admire them. But the sushi is excellent, with clear, clean flavors, which may include rosy, silken tuna; rich, lightly broiled eel; sweet shrimp; fine yellowtail; fat, luscious salmon roe; and wedges of sweet omelet. For more exotic fare, you can order a la carte.</p>
        <p>11. Tokyo Lunch</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 608-1394</p>
        <p>10 John Street, near Broadway</p>
        <p>Lower Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>If you are far downtown, Tokyo Lunch is one of the best places around to grab a quick, inexpensive bite. This long, narrow shop, almost hidden in the area's maze and just one block south of Fulton Street, is barely wider than an aisle. The specialty is donburi, grilled food served over rice. Broiled eel glazed with teriyaki sauce is tender and delicious, served with spinach and a blend of sauteed mushrooms and hijiki, a mild black seaweed. Shrimp and scallops are perfectly grilled and served in a spicy sauce that sneaks up on you, and it comes with a nice lettuce salad with a sesame dressing. Tokyo Lunch also offers excellent soba noodles, served hot in a pleasant miso broth with shrimp tempura and spinach.</p>
        <p>12. Yazmin's Express</p>
        <p>+++</p>
        <p>(212) 580-1700</p>
        <p>564 Amsterdam Avenue, near 87th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan</p>
        <p>$ Cash only</p>
        <p>This little storefront serves authentic Mexican food. Unusual selections include pozole blanco, a thick soul-warming soup made with hominy and shards of tender pork; salsa verde de puerco, braised pork in a tomatillo sauce spiked with jalapenos and hot enough to make your mouth glow; and pipian de polo, chicken in a thick, tangy sauce made with toasted pumpkin seeds.</p>
        <p>Summaries taken from reviews use the star ratings. Others are taken from the $25 and Under column (+) and articles (++), and capsule revies from New York Today: www.nytoday.com (+++).</p>
        <p>What the Stars Mean</p>
        <p>**** -- Extraordinary  *** -- Excellent  ** -- Very Good  * -- Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  Based on the cost of a three-course dinner, per person, tax, tip and drinks not included.</p>
        <p>$ -- $25 and under  $$ -- $25 to $40  $$$ -- $40 to $55  $$$$ -- $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past Reviews -- Good Eating columns back to June 1998, along with reviews from The Times and capsule reviews by Times critics of additional restaurants not reviewed in the newspaper, are available on New York Today.</p>
        <p>EATING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
