<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Black Soldiers Get Bronze Stars for World War II</title>
    <meta content="02SOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campbell, Haywood</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osborne, Oscar Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DC103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Black Soldiers Get Bronze Stars for World War II</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Gov George E Pataki presents Bronze Star to Haywood Campbell and Oscar Osborne Jr, black soldiers who originally earned their medals in 1945 during World War II but had been denied them because of their race; they also receive New York State Conspicious Service Cross and Campbell is awarded New York State Conspicious Service Star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a wait of 55 years, the extra seconds it took for Gov. George E. Pataki to fumble with the medals and pin them to Haywood Campbell's suit coat yesterday did not faze the old soldier.</p>
        <p>Dressed in a dark suit coat with brass buttons, with a baseball cap perched on his head, Mr. Campbell, an 82-year-old veteran of World War II, stood in the central room of the Harlem Armory on Fifth Avenue with the help of a metal cane, holding his chin up and forward in a military pose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a wait of 55 years, the extra seconds it took for Gov. George E. Pataki to fumble with the medals and pin them to Haywood Campbell's suit coat yesterday did not faze the old soldier.</p>
        <p>Dressed in a dark suit coat with brass buttons, with a baseball cap perched on his head, Mr. Campbell, an 82-year-old veteran of World War II, stood in the central room of the Harlem Armory on Fifth Avenue with the help of a metal cane, holding his chin up and forward in a military pose.</p>
        <p>The ceremony was small. Yet, for Mr. Campbell and a fellow veteran, Oscar Osborne Jr., 77, it was significant. They each received the Bronze Star, a military honor they earned during the Battle of the Bulge in 1945 but were denied because of their race. They also received the New York State Conspicuous Service Cross, and Mr. Campbell was awarded the New York State Conspicuous Service Star.</p>
        <p>The overdue decorations came after decades during which history seemed to have been erased. ''We was fighting right along with the white buddies,'' said Mr. Campbell, a staff sergeant. ''We died together.''</p>
        <p>But at the end of the war, the survivors did not bask in the glory together. Instead, blacks who had volunteered to fight shoulder to shoulder with whites found that their discharge papers did not reflect their combat service,  instead listing them as members of units that unloaded supplies or dug graves.</p>
        <p>Black soldiers, normally restricted to labor battalions, had been asked by Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower to fight after United States troops suffered 75,000 casualties in the Battle of the Bulge. Five thousand signed up to join the intense fighting at the front. Many of the 2,221 who were selected had to give up their ranks and fight as privates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Osborne was shot in the arm and, after months in the hospital, discharged. Mr. Campbell stayed on the front until the end of the war. On one day, he said, his squad captured 22 German troops.</p>
        <p>Both men said they were among the first in their companies to volunteer, Mr. Osborne to defend American democracy and Mr. Campbell because of his opposition to Hitler.</p>
        <p>Another veteran attending the ceremony, Vincent Malveaux, said, ''If you're called to serve in an integrated army, maybe you'd better answer the call, because this was what the people back home were fighting for.''</p>
        <p>Although their service paved the way for President Harry S. Truman's integration of the armed forces in 1948, they and their comrades suffered the indignity of what Governor Pataki called a ''direct effort to suppress'' the heroism of blacks in combat. Veterans at the ceremony said they were unnoted by journalists, left out of official accounts and denied access to their records.</p>
        <p>In 1949, an announcement came that anyone who served in certain units during the Battle of the Bulge qualified for the Bronze Star, usually given on an individual basis. But the 2,221 Negro Volunteers, as they have become known, did not receive them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
