<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; A Month to Remember</title>
    <meta content="02COLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">fatima (portugal)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope (John Paul II)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Virgin Mary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1D7133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; A Month to Remember</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed article on notable events in May; comments on Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's replacement by Rick Lazio as Republican Senate candidate from New York and Vatican's disclosure of so-called third secret of Fatima as being vision of attempted assassination in 1981 of Pope John Paul II</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I tell you, it's good to have May over with.</p>
        <p>There was something apocalyptic going on in May, a post-millennial twitch. The pope spilled the third secret of Fatima. The National Rifle Association (led by Charlton Heston, the star of many, many movies about dyspeptic males fending off the end of the world) announced plans to open a theme restaurant on Times Square. And that enormous forest fire in New Mexico -- all right, we have enormous forest fires all the time, but very few set deliberately by the national government for our own good. (How far, by the way, is Los Alamos from Roswell?)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I tell you, it's good to have May over with.</p>
        <p>There was something apocalyptic going on in May, a post-millennial twitch. The pope spilled the third secret of Fatima. The National Rifle Association (led by Charlton Heston, the star of many, many movies about dyspeptic males fending off the end of the world) announced plans to open a theme restaurant on Times Square. And that enormous forest fire in New Mexico -- all right, we have enormous forest fires all the time, but very few set deliberately by the national government for our own good. (How far, by the way, is Los Alamos from Roswell?)</p>
        <p>Here in New York, Rudy Giuliani mutated into a variation on Barney the Dinosaur, a fluffy critter who prefers dinner with his new squeeze to a press conference announcing a big police bust. We've been a little edgy around him ever since, wondering if he's actually the same person. ''Invasion of the Body Snatchers''  pods may be at work here, or one of those ''X-Files'' aliens who looks like your best friend, but spouts green acid when he's poked. The city is disoriented. New York has had fighting mayors and crooked mayors, and the one before this one was extremely polite. But Love Mayor sounds so 90's, so -- Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Rick Lazio became the new, post-Giuliani Republican Senate candidate. Mr. Lazio, a Republican Congressman from Long Island, appeared to have popped out of the ground from nowhere, but actually he's been dying for the nomination all along, and spent most of the spring desperately waving his arms in crowd scenes, looking available. The split lip he collected when he took a header during a Memorial Day parade worked well for him, being as close as a young 21st-century politician can come to a war wound. Besides, it gave the Republican convention this week something to talk about besides Mr. Lazio's two great thundering qualifications:</p>
        <p>A) From here.</p>
        <p>B) Not unhinged.</p>
        <p>The only drawback is Mr. Lazio's strong resemblance to those unnamed ''Star Trek'' crewmen who get included on every expedition  so the mutants will have somebody to incinerate. And there was something a little eerie, not to say  unappetizing, about his promise  to the people of Buffalo that he would ''be here so often I'm going to be sweating Buffalo wings.''</p>
        <p>But for those of us who spent our formative years in pre-Vatican II parochial schools, the story of the month was still the Lady of Fatima letter. For kids who went to school on split shifts in trailers, we spent a lot of valuable class time speculating about the exact nature of the secret the Blessed Virgin was supposed to have passed on to the pope via a trio of Portuguese shepherd children in 1917. Most people believed it simply revealed the date of the end of the world. In my particular neighborhood, the word was out that Pope Pius XII had opened the letter, burst into tears and cried ''Oh Canada, poor Canada.'' We found this somewhat comforting, since we were in Ohio at the time.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, it was hard to escape the evidence that the final days were upon us, what with the air raid drills, the bomb shelters and a set of nuns who could always come up with a prophecy that made it seem extremely unlikely that anybody was going to be around for summer vacation. Our parents had moved to the suburbs so we could grow up in perfect safety, then sent us off to schools where the faculty assured us we were doomed. It was a rich culture, actually, and we probably have it to thank for the fact that these days, on television and in the movies, any character who moves into a gated community with a good security system is guaranteed to get eaten by werewolves.</p>
        <p>The actual secret of Fatima had to be a letdown for those who were expecting a timetable for Armageddon. The Vatican says the letter revealed the assassination attempt on the pope in 1981, although it seems to be couched in that really flexible, one-size-fits-all prose used by all truly successful future-forecasters. We appear to have gone through a lot of angst for nothing but the fun of it.</p>
        <p>Personally, I'm ready for a stretch of utter predictability. That's why it was so reassuring on Wednesday night when the only woman over 35 on the ''Survivor'' series was the first person to get thrown off the island.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
