<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Are Giving Sather Complete Control of the Team</title>
    <meta content="02RANG$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sather, Glen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3D9103CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Are Giving Sather Complete Control of the Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers name Glen Sather president and general manager; his career discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Glen Sather reign officially began yesterday, when Madison Square Garden's president, Dave Checketts, named him the Rangers' team president and general manager.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference at the Garden, Checketts said that Sather would have complete control of hockey operations for the Rangers, who have have missed the playoffs the last three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Glen Sather reign officially began yesterday, when Madison Square Garden's president, Dave Checketts, named him the Rangers' team president and general manager.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference at the Garden, Checketts said that Sather would have complete control of hockey operations for the Rangers, who have have missed the playoffs the last three years.</p>
        <p>Sather resigned from the Edmonton Oilers in May after spending 24 years with the organization and producing the dynasty that won five Stanley Cups from 1984-90. He said yesterday that he still had plenty to prove.</p>
        <p>''It's not like if you build a building on Madison Avenue, and it's up and over with,'' said the 56-year-old Sather, who was inducted into the Hockey Hall of Fame in 1997. ''There's a challenge every day in this business to be successful. And I enjoy the challenge.''</p>
        <p>Terms of the contract were not disclosed, but Checketts confirmed there were ''no option years, no outs.''</p>
        <p>A National Hockey League official said yesterday that Sather signed a seven-year deal before the morning news conference. The deal, which includes stock options in Cablevision, is believed to be worth more than $20 million, which would easily make Sather the highest-paid executive in the history of the game.</p>
        <p>''I want this to be his last stop, and I think this contract reflects that,'' Checketts said. ''He brings us instant respect.''</p>
        <p>Many around the N.H.L. are hoping that Sather brings with him a philosophy different from his predecessors in New York.</p>
        <p>The Rangers, who had an N.H.L. record payroll of $61.2 million last season and nothing to show for it, have long been known for their profligate spending ways.</p>
        <p>''I think my first responsibility is to try and build a winner,'' Sather said. ''I still believe you can't buy a winner.</p>
        <p>''It has to be built, through the draft and through trades.''</p>
        <p>Last season, the Rangers were built on a different model: they spent millions on free agents in a stopgap effort to make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''It obviously didn't work last year,'' Checketts said. ''I wouldn't go so far as to say it can't work. We have the resources to spend to win. But we want to spend those resources responsibly.</p>
        <p>''The final four teams in both the N.B.A. playoffs and the baseball playoffs were the ones with the highest payrolls,'' said Checketts, whose Knicks fit in the basketball subset. ''But hockey's a different sport. You can't expect to just spend money and produce results.''</p>
        <p>Sather also said it is not enough just to qualify for the playoffs, an achievement that might have saved the job of Neil Smith, his longtime friend.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is success unless you win the Stanley Cup,'' Sather said. ''If you tell me the goal is to make the playoffs, I think you're short-sighting yourself.''</p>
        <p>Checketts was possibly alluding to the Rangers' failures since winning the Stanley Cup in 1994 when he said:</p>
        <p>''We don't want to just have a great year and win the cup as a flash. We want to build a dynasty and have young players in our pipeline so we're not forced into a situation like we were last summer where you have to sign free agents to win.''</p>
        <p>Sather's first order of business will most likely be to appoint a new head coach. He said he would like to have someone in place by the draft, which is June 23-25.</p>
        <p>Although he did not say it yesterday, it is well known that Sather badly wants to bring with him from Edmonton Coach Kevin Lowe. But Lowe is torn between following Sather and remaining in Edmonton, where Sather's former general manager job is his if he wants it. If Lowe chooses to stay with the Oilers, his assistant coach in Edmonton, Craig MacTavish, is Sather's next choice as coach said a person familiar with Sather's thinking.</p>
        <p>Before agreeing to take the Rangers' helm, Sather wanted the assurance that he would be able to bring in his own ''strong, independent hockey people outside the corporate structure.''</p>
        <p>But to ensure some sort of continuity within the Ranger organization, Sather will apparently keep Don Maloney in his current role of assistant general manager, two league officials said.</p>
        <p>Although he would not address Mark Messier's situation, signing him will certainly be a priority come July 1, if the Vancouver Canucks do not pick up the $6 million option on his contract.</p>
        <p>As for answering to Checketts and Madison Square Garden's chairman, James Dolan, Sather referred to the ownership situation in Edmonton.</p>
        <p>''I just worked for 37 guys,'' Sather said. ''I don't think it's going to be a problem here.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
