<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is the Audience Being Rowdy? Americans Have Gotten Much Better</title>
    <meta content="27SHEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHELF LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butsch, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Making of American Audiences, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Shelf Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6DC103DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is the Audience Being Rowdy? Americans Have Gotten Much Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Rothstein reviews book The Making of American Audiences: From Stage to Television, 1750-1990, by Richard Butsch (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MAKING OF AMERICAN AUDIENCES  From Stage to Television, 1750-1990  By Richard Butsch  Illustrated. 438 pages. Cambridge University Press. 438 pp. $69.95 hardcover; $24.95 paperback.</p>
        <p>What is the difference between a performance of ''The Marriage of Figaro'' and a telecast of ''The Sopranos''? Or between a Britney Spears concert and ''The Jack Benny Show''? Or between a gamelan performance and a pornographic Web site?</p>
        <p>The audience. Or at least that is one way to look at it. It is so difficult to evaluate arts, compare their virtues and weigh their achievements and the entire debate over what was once called high culture is so politically charged that it is tempting simply to say that different entertainments attract different audiences. No aesthetic distinctions are needed. Mozart and Spears do not have different statures, just different devotees. There is no high, no low, only differing cultural attitudes toward what is high and what is low.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MAKING OF AMERICAN AUDIENCES  From Stage to Television, 1750-1990  By Richard Butsch  Illustrated. 438 pages. Cambridge University Press. 438 pp. $69.95 hardcover; $24.95 paperback.</p>
        <p>What is the difference between a performance of ''The Marriage of Figaro'' and a telecast of ''The Sopranos''? Or between a Britney Spears concert and ''The Jack Benny Show''? Or between a gamelan performance and a pornographic Web site?</p>
        <p>The audience. Or at least that is one way to look at it. It is so difficult to evaluate arts, compare their virtues and weigh their achievements and the entire debate over what was once called high culture is so politically charged that it is tempting simply to say that different entertainments attract different audiences. No aesthetic distinctions are needed. Mozart and Spears do not have different statures, just different devotees. There is no high, no low, only differing cultural attitudes toward what is high and what is low.</p>
        <p>One problem, though, is that if the audience is the measure of all things, then art becomes a reflection of sociology and dissecting audience tastes becomes the art. This approach lies behind market research, movie previews, television programming and most book publishing. Before anything is packaged, the producers of cultural commerce ask: Who is the audience? How can it be reached? What are the ages, incomes, professions, tastes and attitudes we desire?</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, academic analysis of culture often does something similar. Strip away the superstructure of cosmetics and form, and the artwork's true meaning can be found in demographics. Who is being addressed and why? What is being sold? The main difference is that here the categories are political, not commercial. Now they tend to focus on gender, race and class. Culture becomes a series of coded messages in which genders, races and classes negotiate for power.</p>
        <p>Rich insights can be gained by such market analysis, of course, but the risk is that the art itself may become inconsequential. This is one of the flaws of ''The Making of American Audiences,'' a survey spanning 240 years of drama, minstrelsy, vaudeville, film, radio and television. Richard Butsch, a professor of sociology at Rider University in New Jersey, has combed archives and newspapers, historical documents and recent histories, studies of television advertising and circus audiences, penny arcades and fan mail; his bibliography alone takes up 36 pages. The subject is fascinating and so are some of Mr. Butsch's ideas, but as the content of art is eclipsed by considerations of audience politics, culture ends up seeming like little more than a reflection of political tastes.</p>
        <p>But what a transformation of tastes is chronicled. Beginning in the 18th century and through the first half of the 19th, Mr. Butsch suggests, there was a tradition of ''audience sovereignty'' in the theater. Upper-class fobs might sit onstage and publicly chat with the actors. In the 1830's Tocqueville found that Americans ''paid not the slightest attention to the stage but walked about, drank together and argued as if nothing else were going on.'' ''Prostitution,'' Mr. Butsch points out, ''was important to the profitability of theaters.''</p>
        <p>Such manners seemed to cross all classes. During the 1840's New York had a coterie of working-class young men known as b'hoys who treated the theater as an extension of the street. One observer of a performance in the Bowery said that the audience ''heaves continually in wild and sullen tumult, like a red flannel sea agitated by some lurid storm . . . the yells and screams, the shuddering oaths and obscene songs tumbling down from the third tier.'' The b'hoys were such knowledgeable regulars that they would shout out prompts to Shakespearean actors who forgot their lines.</p>
        <p>Gradually, though, class divisions increased. Rowdy ''lower-class'' behavior became restricted to other forms of entertainment, like minstrel shows in the 1840's or vaudeville later in the century, while the legitimate theater began to take on more refined manners. Drama, once considered a masculine domain, was feminized. Shopping districts grew around theaters; fashion became important; a matinee audience of women developed. By 1910 women may have made up three-quarters of the American theater audience.</p>
        <p>While the lower classes were still actively engaged in variety shows, within the theater an elevated notion of art was put forward, encouraging passivity. Those who failed to appreciate art were considered as rude as those who had once lobbied for silence. One magazine mocked bored, wealthy theatergoers who ''came an act late, left an act early, slept during the second act and talked in between times.'' Silent attentiveness was expected.</p>
        <p>So the audience, once an active participant, became a passive recipient, a transformation, Mr. Butsch argues, that was amplified by the development of movies, radio and television. The participatory tumult of the theater was supplanted by the private experience of the screen. To Mr. Butsch, all this seems a decline of sorts, in which political vitality and communal experience is sacrificed for the sake of private entertainment. He often appears drawn to what was lost with ''the establishment of middle-class decorum.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Butsch's two distinctions, active/passive and public/private, are important. But the transformations are not clear-cut, and their meanings are ambiguous. Was the debate over audience behavior, for example, just a matter of ''class-based fears of lower-class disorder''? Demands for decorum may not have been just political. There are, after all, major differences between a vaudeville show and a performance of ''Othello,'' differences in complexity, nuance, beauty, construction, density and wit. More subtle aesthetic perceptions may have led to demands for greater decorum.</p>
        <p>There are, then, distinctions to be made that go beyond gender, race and class. And if, as Mr. Butsch asserts, the history of American audiences raises many issues that are still urgent in contemporary life, this one may be worth examining more closely.</p>
        <p>SHELF LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
