<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistan Battles Its Tax Scofflaws</title>
    <meta content="Y27PAK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bearak, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DA113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistan Battles Its Tax Scofflaws</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY BEARAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bearak, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan, May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pakistan's military government, nearly eight months after it seized power, is trying to crack down on tax evasion; is trying to do what before has proved impossible: find out who owes how much, and make them pay; teams of soldiers and revenue officers will start delivering tax survey forms to businesses and homes in 13 major cites; government wants to know about inventory, purchases, rents, utility bills and employees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WARNING!'' scream the big daily ads in the newspapers. ''All taxpayers are warned that a comprehensive tax survey is being launched soon in which your concealed income and assets will be unearthed.''</p>
        <p>In many countries, such an admonition might strike fear among a minority who forget, fudge or outright refuse to file. But here in Pakistan, where taxes have yet to join death as one of life's inevitabilities, the warning applies to just about everyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WARNING!'' scream the big daily ads in the newspapers. ''All taxpayers are warned that a comprehensive tax survey is being launched soon in which your concealed income and assets will be unearthed.''</p>
        <p>In many countries, such an admonition might strike fear among a minority who forget, fudge or outright refuse to file. But here in Pakistan, where taxes have yet to join death as one of life's inevitabilities, the warning applies to just about everyone.</p>
        <p>The military government, nearly eight months after it seized power, is trying to do what before has proven impossible: find out who owes how much and make them pay.</p>
        <p>Beginning on Saturday, teams of soldiers and revenue officers will start delivering tax survey forms to businesses and homes in 13 major cities. The government wants to know about inventory, purchases, rents, utility bills and employees. The penalty for ignoring the form can be as much as three months in jail, and the punishment for lying is up to five years.</p>
        <p>Many here in Pakistan and elsewhere consider the tax crackdown a major test of mettle for Gen. Pervez Musharraf, the military ruler who uses the title of chief executive: The nation is $38 billion in debt. Can he snatch solvency from the jaws of default?</p>
        <p>''Whatever forbearance the international community has had for this military government has come with the idea that it can take decisions that a political government cannot,'' said one Western diplomat. ''But this government has yet to take on any major interest group and win.''</p>
        <p>While General Musharraf presents himself as a tough-talking reformer, he has backed down from several confrontations, most recently when he withdrew a change to the nation's blasphemy laws that was opposed by Islamic fundamentalists.</p>
        <p>This time, he is up against a business community that has considered the payment of taxes as the behavior of suckers. Many shop owners vow to shutter their stores as soon as the survey teams enter the neighborhood. An indefinite strike has been threatened.</p>
        <p>Umer Sailya, part owner of a Karachi restaurant and chairman of the Association of Small Traders Organizations, is championing the resistance. He said that first, the government ought to root out corruption among its own in the tax department.</p>
        <p>''The bureaucracy doesn't want our taxes; they want our bribes,'' Mr. Sailya said in a telephone interview. ''Let the government first survey the revenue collectors, the civil bureaucrats, the army and the judiciary. Then they can come survey the businessmen.''</p>
        <p>In response to Mr. Sailya's criticism, the government this week leaked his income tax returns to the press, showing that he paid an average of only $28 during the past four years.</p>
        <p>Actually, if that is the case, then Mr. Sailya is one of Pakistan's more upright citizens. In a nation of 150 million, less than 1 percent pay any income tax at all, according to the government. An estimated 70 percent of the entire economy is run off the books.</p>
        <p>''Shameful!'' General Musharraf declared today at a televised news conference that was part pep talk, part fireside chat. ''We should be ashamed. Only 1.2 million people pay tax.''</p>
        <p>This is a very poor country -- and for some poverty may be something of an excuse.</p>
        <p>But, according to the government, there are 2.5 million business owners in Pakistan, and only 650,000 of them have even bothered to register with the income tax authorities. Of those, a meager 17,500 are collecting sales tax, which is not only considered a nuisance by shopkeepers but can also be used as incriminating evidence of their own unreported earnings.</p>
        <p>''The task ahead is momentous,'' said Shaukat Aziz, a former Citibank vice president who has returned to his native Pakistan as finance minister. ''We are trying to inculcate a culture of tax-paying. It is a defining moment for our nation.''</p>
        <p>The government's tax survey program has been preceded by its tax amnesty plan, which is the subject of those newspaper ads as well as similarly stern ones on TV.</p>
        <p>Deadbeats are being offered a ''rare opportunity'' to pay up on money earned before June 30, 1999. At a bargain tax rate, too: only 10 percent. All else is forgiven.</p>
        <p>''If you fail to avail the opportunity, you run the risk of paying tax at normal rates plus penalty and imprisonment of up to five years or both,'' the ads warn.</p>
        <p>The amnesty offer is four weeks old, and so far it has scared the stuffing out of very few wallets, bringing in a scant $3 million. Mr. Aziz has greater expectations, estimating that 10 times that amount will be recovered before a June 15 deadline. But even that is a far cry from the additional 12 billion dollars the government believes it ought to collect annually.</p>
        <p>The finance minister is not without sympathy for those who have long evaded the tax net. He admits that many in the revenue department are as dishonest as the day is long. Today, he fired 1,000 of the ''most corrupt.'' He said in an interview, ''Will this eliminate corruption? No. Will it put a check on it? Yes.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, Mr. Aziz was living in New York with a banker's set of headaches; a year ago, General Musharraf was commanding an army that was fighting a near all-out war with India in the mountains of Kashmir. These days, they worry a good deal about satisfying the international lenders who hold the paper on Pakistan's debt.</p>
        <p>A team from the International Monetary Fund is in Islamabad this week, trying to decide whether to re-open the valve on a suspended flow of loans to Pakistan. For years, the lenders have been demanding the kind of tax collection now being undertaken. This week, they will be hoping to see people paying up instead of shutting down.</p>
        <p>General Musharraf, who has quite a folksy manner for a stiff-backed military man, told his nation: ''It's high time we confronted problems and catch the bull by the horns.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
