<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rally in Belgrade Protests Early Closing of Serbian Universities</title>
    <meta content="Y27SER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D7103DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rally in Belgrade Protests Early Closing of Serbian Universities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several thousand students, teachers and parents rally to protest closing of universities week early by government of Yugoslav Pres Slobodan Milosevic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several thousand students, teachers and parents rallied today to protest the closing of universities a week early by the government of the Yugoslav president, Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>Under a decree issued on Thursday by the Serbian minister for higher education, Jevrem Janjic, today was the last day such a rally could be held on university property. After today, students and teachers will be allowed to enter only their own departments, and only for final examinations, with their documents checked at the door.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several thousand students, teachers and parents rallied today to protest the closing of universities a week early by the government of the Yugoslav president, Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>Under a decree issued on Thursday by the Serbian minister for higher education, Jevrem Janjic, today was the last day such a rally could be held on university property. After today, students and teachers will be allowed to enter only their own departments, and only for final examinations, with their documents checked at the door.</p>
        <p>At the rally today, in a crowded pedestrian space in front of the philosophy department building at Belgrade University, student activists of the Otpor, or Resistance, movement and professors sympathetic to the political opposition charged that the government was afraid of the students and was acting illegally to shorten the school year and avoid a student strike.</p>
        <p>They pointed to the beating on Tuesday night of several students who had intended to stay the night in protest at the architecture department. But when they ignored a janitor's demand that they leave, the lights for the entire street were shut off, and men in surgical masks drove them out of the building.</p>
        <p>''This rally is a general protest against everything that is happening in this country: repression, media darkness, beating of students,'' said an architecture student named Marko, 21, who was in the school when the masked men came.</p>
        <p>''We will go anywhere we must to awaken a sleepy Belgrade,'' said Branko Ilic, an Otpor activist, who urged students to raise their fists -- the Otpor symbol -- to show that ''you are not afraid of the state of emergency'' and will gather again at the university on Monday.</p>
        <p>Stevan Lilic, a law professor and member of the political opposition, said the latest decree was a continuation of the law on universities that put faculties under the state and has resulted in the firings or forced resignations of nearly 200 professors in the last three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lilic is the target of a campaign to fire him led by the Serbian deputy prime minister, Vojislav Seselj, who was recently made a professor of the law school.</p>
        <p>''This is political intimidation and an effort to threaten the faculty, and the reason for it is the student protest movement, Otpor,'' Mr. Lilic said. He said he had criticized his dean for not defending him against Mr. Seselj's threats, which he said included having thugs follow him in the street.</p>
        <p>Police officers gathered and watched the rally but did not interfere, and some students later marched on Belgrade's city hall. They demanded that the political opposition act more vigorously to protest the government's latest actions to shut the university, take Belgrade's main television station, Studio B, from the opposition and carry out a series of detentions of student and political activists across Serbia.</p>
        <p>The opposition has called a rally for Saturday in downtown Belgrade and is hoping for a large turnout from all over Serbia. The opposition political leaders have disagreed on the need for stronger action, like civil disobedience.</p>
        <p>They are struggling for a platform that might emphasize more than unity and the need to prepare for the local and federal elections that are due later this fall.</p>
        <p>They will hold down the number of speakers at the rally and include speakers from Otpor and well-known personalities from Serbian life, to try to give this rally a fresh feel.</p>
        <p>But it will be difficult for them to articulate a clear strategy of action that will answer criticism that the opposition favors the status quo more than confrontation with the government.</p>
        <p>Three senior opposition politicians -- Vuk Draskovic of the Serbian Renewal Movement, Zoran Djindjic of the Democratic Party and Vojislav Kostunica of the Democratic Party of Serbia -- intend to go to Moscow on Monday to seek Russian mediation. But it is not clear what level of  officials will see them there.</p>
        <p>The authorities justify their new, harsh push against the independent news media, the opposition and the students by citing the need to keep civic order and fight those who favor revolution.</p>
        <p>But the crackdown is also intended to show citizens that ''the state exists and will defend itself,'' said a senior official of one of the parties in the governing coalition, adding, ''Studio B could have continued to spew out political propaganda for Vuk Draskovic forever, but we could not let calls for armed rebellion be transmitted.''</p>
        <p>Government officials say they  are simply not going to allow  the university buildings, spread out all over Belgrade, to become centers for resistance to the authorities instead of an academy. They have accused the Otpor movement of having links to the NATO countries that bombed Serbia and want to oust Mr. Milosevic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
