<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Loses and Gains in Ruling on a Privacy Act Case</title>
    <meta content="Y27PRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Judicial Watch</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willey, Kathleen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Loses and Gains in Ruling on a Privacy Act Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three-judge panel of United States Court of Appeals for District of Columbia refuses to interfere in lawsuit brought by Judicial Watch, conservative group, that accuses Pres Clinton of violating Privacy Act of 1974; ruling is still seen partial victory for White House; appellate panel sharply criticizes lower court judge who asserted in March 29 ruling that Clinton committed 'a criminal violation of the Privacy Act' in releasing personal letters sent to him by Kathleen Willey, former White House volunteer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal appellate court refused today to interfere in a lawsuit brought by a group that accuses President Clinton of violating the Privacy Act of 1974. But the ruling was still a partial victory for the White House.</p>
        <p>The three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit said there was no need to issue an emergency order sought by the White House to block pretrial information gathering, or discovery, in the suit brought by Judicial Watch, a conservative group that has been a persistent opponent of Mr. Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal appellate court refused today to interfere in a lawsuit brought by a group that accuses President Clinton of violating the Privacy Act of 1974. But the ruling was still a partial victory for the White House.</p>
        <p>The three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit said there was no need to issue an emergency order sought by the White House to block pretrial information gathering, or discovery, in the suit brought by Judicial Watch, a conservative group that has been a persistent opponent of Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>In response to today's ruling, a White House spokesman, Jim Kennedy, said that while White House lawyers were disappointed by the decision on discovery, they would abide by it. But he added that the lawyers were ''very pleased'' by other elements of the ruling.</p>
        <p>The appellate panel sharply criticized a lower court judge who asserted in a March 29 ruling that the president committed ''a criminal violation of the Privacy Act'' in releasing personal letters sent to him by Kathleen Willey, a former White House volunteer.</p>
        <p>In March 1998, Ms. Willey accused Mr. Clinton on the CBS News program ''60 Minutes'' of making a sexual advance toward her in the fall of 1993. Her account added to the burdens of the president during the investigation of his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky and the sexual misconduct lawsuit filed by Paula Corbin Jones.</p>
        <p>Soon after Ms. Willey's television appearance, the president released her letters -- reluctantly, he said -- in the hope that their friendly tone would undercut her accusations. She had written them after the time she said the advance took place.</p>
        <p>Ms. Willey is not a party to the suit by Judicial Watch, which contends that the White House improperly obtained hundreds of files from the Federal Bureau of Investigation on former appointees and employees of the Reagan and Bush administrations. Judicial Watch has focused on the handling of the Willey letters in the hope of uncovering evidence that might buttress its allegations involving misuse of the bureau's files.</p>
        <p>On March 29, Judge Royce C. Lamberth of United States District Court here ruled that White House lawyers should submit to questioning by lawyers from Judicial Watch. He went further, declaring that Mr. Clinton had acted unlawfully in releasing Ms. Willey's letters, which were kept among White House records. The Privacy Act generally prohibits release of information about a person from federal records without that person's consent; violations of the law can result in fines.</p>
        <p>Today, the appellate judges -- Harry T. Edwards, Douglas H. Ginsburg and David S. Tatel -- said Judge Lamberth's ''sweeping pronouncements'' about supposed criminal activity were inappropriate and ''entirely superfluous.''</p>
        <p>The White House has contended that much of its business is exempt from the Privacy Act, and that many lawyers from both political parties have long said so. The appellate panel said today that, in matters unrelated to the Judicial Watch case, the White House could continue to operate under that assumption unless a court declared otherwise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and his allies have made no secret of their feeling that Judge Lamberth, who was appointed by President Ronald Reagan in 1987, is unfriendly to the administration.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
