<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Whose Words Are They, Anyway?; A New Sontag Novel Creates a Stir by Not Crediting Quotes From Other Books</title>
    <meta content="27SONT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Ellen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Modjeska, Helena (1840-1909)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In America (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1D9103DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Whose Words Are They, Anyway?; A New Sontag Novel Creates a Stir by Not Crediting Quotes From Other Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ellen Lee, amateur historian, has found at least 12 passages in Susan Sontag's new book, In America, that are similar to passages in four other books about legendary actress Helena Modjeska, model for main character in Sontag's book; Sontag notes that passages in dispute amount to fewer than three pages in her 387-page book, and she has offered various explanations for using language of others--from indulging in whimsical inside literary joke, to drawing on direct words of people she considers primary sources; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Ellen Lee, an 81-year-old amateur historian, read Susan Sontag's new novel about a grand 19th-century actress, she was startled by words that seemed oddly familiar in language and tone.</p>
        <p>Two times more she read through ''In America,'' underlining passages that echoed to her from 30 years of lecturing about Helena Modjeska, the Polish immigrant actress who had inspired Ms. Sontag's historical novel and its main character, Maryna Zalezowska.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Ellen Lee, an 81-year-old amateur historian, read Susan Sontag's new novel about a grand 19th-century actress, she was startled by words that seemed oddly familiar in language and tone.</p>
        <p>Two times more she read through ''In America,'' underlining passages that echoed to her from 30 years of lecturing about Helena Modjeska, the Polish immigrant actress who had inspired Ms. Sontag's historical novel and its main character, Maryna Zalezowska.</p>
        <p>By the time she was done, Mrs. Lee had highlighted at least 12 passages in Ms. Sontag's 387-page book that were similar to passages in four other books about Modjeska. They were presented without credit or attribution -- other than a line in the preface expressing a debt to books and articles about Modjeska ''for material and anecdotes used (and altered.)'' No writers were credited by name in the novel.</p>
        <p>The authors were a varied lot, ranging from Willa Cather to Helena Modjeska herself to a Polish Nobel laureate in literature who is also a model for a character in Ms. Sontag's novel.  The familiar passages ranged from an elaborate description of Modjeska's rose-colored cashmere robe to Ms. Cather's evocative account of a toast delivered by the actress ''looking into the blur of the candlight.'' In length, they ranged from a sentence or two to eight lines of rhyming verse.</p>
        <p>''My first reaction was really bewilderment,'' recalled Mrs. Lee, a volunteer museum docent who helped found the Helena Modjeska Foundation in Southern California. ''Why would a writer of Susan Sontag's stature and prestige use sources without quotation marks and without documentation? And then it occurred to me that maybe the rules have changed and there are different rules for fiction now.''</p>
        <p>That question is oddly debatable in a literary arena where popular writers have already pushed the limits of artistic license to treat history as a melange of fact and fiction. But in the case of ''In America,'' the issue is highlighted because in some passages the language itself is taken almost verbatim from other authors.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Sontag, whose wide-ranging writing career has encompassed fiction, essays, plays and films, standards have evolved for the historical novel as a form of literature. She considers it ''a work of art'' that belongs to a new genre that doesn't require the footnotes of traditional histories.</p>
        <p>''All of us who deal with real characters in history transcribe and adopt original sources in the original domain,'' said Ms. Sontag, who noted that the passages in dispute amounted to fewer than three pages in total. ''I've used these sources and I've completely transformed them. I have these books. I've looked at these books. There's a larger argument to be made that all of literature is a series of references and allusions.''</p>
        <p>In her quest to capture a period with precision, Ms. Sontag offers various explanations for using the language of others -- from indulging in a whimsical inside literary joke, playing with Cather's words, to drawing on the direct words of people she considers primary sources.</p>
        <p>''I distinguish between writers and sources,'' she said. ''Willa Cather is a writer, but the others are sources. The sources themselves are working from sources and they are using quotations of actual words. I don't consider Modjeska's memoirs the work of a writer. So what interests me is the transformation. She's the source of my character and you can use a sentence that's exactly the same because it is from her words. Of course, I've used her words to create a completely different character.''</p>
        <p>Using the writings of Helena Modjeska and the 1905 Nobel laureate, Henryk Sienkiewicz, a Polish journalist and author of ''Quo Vadis,'' Ms. Sontag wove their words into scenes involving her fictional immigrant actress, Maryna Zalezowska, and an imaginary journalist, much like Sienkiewicz, who is called Ryszard Kierulck.</p>
        <p>In some passages, it does appear that Ms. Sontag used descriptions, Polish quotations translated into English and verses collected and written by an obscure writer, Marion Moore Coleman, who in 1969 self-published ''Fair Rosalind: The American Career of Helena Modjeska.'' But Ms. Sontag said the similarities arose from her and Mrs. Coleman's use of  some of the same original newspaper accounts and letters.</p>
        <p>''Fair Rosalind'' was a title that Mrs. Lee knew well because she had befriended Mrs. Coleman while she was researching the more than 1,000-page book.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lee started underlining passages after she was approached by an Orange County Register reporter who described some similarities in language but who focused on differences between the facts of Modjeska's life in a home in the Santa Ana foothills in the 1870's and the fictional tale of Ms. Sontag's actress, Maryna.</p>
        <p>By the time she was through, Mrs. Lee had collected similar passages from two other books of nonfiction, including Modjeska's 1910 memoirs, ''Memories and Impressions,'' and the translated letters of Sienkiewicz, ''Portrait of America.''</p>
        <p>But the more detailed information and wording came from Mrs. Coleman's biography, which included extensive footnotes.</p>
        <p>For example, ''In America'' contains a lavish description of Maryna Zalezowska's dress that Mrs. Coleman attributes to an 1878 Louisville Courier-Journal report: ''Cashmere robe of peach-blossom pink, trimmed with a cascade of lace down the front and one narrow flounce around the bottom, lace ruffles on the elbow sleeves, a lace fraise at the neck and one shell-shaped lace pocket on the left side ornamented with a pink rosette.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sontag's description -- with a line eliminated and some minor words changed -- closely parallels Mrs. Coleman's. Ms. Sontag said: ''I have that newspaper account where Marion Coleman got her information. I have all this in my computer. It comes from a newspaper account, I think from Philadephia.''</p>
        <p>In the same biography, Mrs. Coleman painstakenly chronicles the verses delivered in tribute to Modjeska by various admirers and critics. Some of them are virtually unchanged in Ms. Sontag's novel. For example, Mrs. Coleman's biography described a poem sent with a bouquet to Modjeska by newspaper men.</p>
        <p>Hither, unheralded by voice of fame,</p>
        <p>Except as a fair foreigner you came:</p>
        <p>Light was the welcome that we had prepared</p>
        <p>Even our symphathies you scarcely shared:</p>
        <p>Not as the artist whom your people knew</p>
        <p>As some fresh novice did we look on you.</p>
        <p>In Ms. Sontag's novel, the same lines surface in an unsigned note from an admirer to the fictional Maryna with slight changes of wording and a character's interruption.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Sontag, the use of such lines reflects a zeal to capture a historical period. In her previous novel, ''The Volcano Lover,'' she said, about 1 or 2 percent of the sentences or phrases came from the written words of her real-life characters, like the letters exchanged between Lady Emma Hamilton and Lord Nelson. ''There are phrases and letters, part of a sentence in another sentence, all reworked,'' she said. ''You get very haunted by this question of fact, of making it absolutely right.''</p>
        <p>Particularly striking to Mrs. Lee was a passage that was clearly borrowed from Cather's own description, in ''My Mortal Enemy,'' of a toast delivered by Modjeska.</p>
        <p>Cather wrote: ''When Oswald asked her to propose a toast, she put out her long arm, lifted her glass, and looking into the blur of the candlelight with a grave face, said: 'To my coun-n-try!' ''</p>
        <p>The Sontag version is slightly different: ''When asked to propose a toast, she put out her long arm, lifted her glass, and looking into the blur of the candlelight, crooned, 'To my new country!' '' ''Country,'' muttered Miss Collingridge. ''Not 'coun-n-try.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sontag said that she had not read ''My Mortal Enemy,'' but that a friend had sent her the description of the toast and she had incorporated Cather's material as a ''literary joke.''</p>
        <p>''It was certainly a reference that I hoped people would pick up,'' she said, adding that she had transformed the passage because her character delivers a toast to the United States, rather than to Poland, as in the Cather version.</p>
        <p>With other similiar passages, Ms. Sontag said, she used the words not of ''writers, but sources in the public domain'' that inspired similar characters in her novel. For example, she draws on passages from the memoirs of Modjeska, who wrote about her memories of chasing away boredom by killing flies after rummaging through toys and discovering ''two tiny little bows.'' Modjeska continues: ''The arrows were simply made of matches, with a needle at the end. We aimed at the drowsy, sprawling sleeping flies which ornamented the wooden walls of the room, and one by one our victims fell at our feet. What do you think of that kind of occupation for Juliet or Mary Stuart?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sontag also used some similar sentences from ''Portrait of America,'' the letters of Sienkiewicz, who wrote of ''ripe acorns breaking loose from their pedicles and rustling through the leaves as they fell to the ground.''</p>
        <p>Among the many writers experimenting with historical fiction, there is some disagreement about exactly what the standard is for using the words of others. Some purists argue they will not change any historical facts, although they insert imaginary characters into the mix. Others are more flexible about facts, but not language; Russell Banks, for instance, created an underground railroad stop that didn't exist in ''Cloud Splitter,'' his novel about the real abolitionist John Brown.''</p>
        <p>''When I have a book like 'Cloud Splitter,' '' Mr. Banks said, ''the contract with the reader is that I'm telling a story. I'm not writing a history, so I will tell you things that may not have happened. But the assumption is that the language is mine, and if I have taken language from elsewhere, I feel obliged to make that evident.''</p>
        <p>It is an accepted technique to develop characters by employing what the author Thomas Mallon calls the ''scraps and traces of history.'' Many writers draw the line at borrowing the language of other writers,  although some are willing to quote real-life figures who become characters in historical novels.</p>
        <p>''Once you're working in this genre, you're on a slippery slope,'' said Mr. Mallon, the author of several historical novels and a book called ''Stolen Words: Forays Into the Origins and Ravages of Plagiarism.'' ''A certain degree of pastiche is acceptable and even necessary to the establishment of historical figures as believable literary characters. But that doesn't absolve the novelist from respecting the language that was crafted by other contemporary scholars. Novelists should go to scholars for information, not for language.''</p>
        <p>Tracy Chevalier, the author of the historical novel ''Girl With a Pearl Earring,'' said she had purposely chosen to write about Vermeer and the anonymous model who posed for his famous portrait because the 17th-century setting and scarcity of information about the artist gave her great room to use her imagination.</p>
        <p>''You are taking an awful responsibility if you try to transform the language of others,'' Ms. Chevalier said. ''For better or worse, there aren't any standards that have been set out. I was trained as an editor, so I'm somewhat anally retentive about getting everything accurate. If I can verify a fact, I won't change it. But other things are open to interpretation -- all that blurry stuff in between. I think the interesting thing about the 'Girl With the Pearl Earring' is that we really don't know who she is. If I had known, I probably wouldn't have written about her.''</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Lee, borrowing is unacceptable. But Ms. Sontag remains surprised by such a reaction, given that her novel brought fresh attention to a historical figure who had become obscure.</p>
        <p>''I actually thought that they would be quite thrilled,'' Ms. Sontag said. ''Modjeska was quite forgotten. She was a great figure. I made her into a marvelous person. The real Modjeska was a horrible racist.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
