<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Vote on China Trade: The Politics Was Local</title>
    <meta content="Y27CONG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDF113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Vote on China Trade: The Politics Was Local</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of United States' House 237-to-197 approval of China trade deal, most important foreign policy vote so far this year; vote seen reflecting reality that members vote their districts, calculating impact of legislation on jobs gained and lost (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most important foreign policy vote so far this year, the 237-to-197 House approval of the China trade deal, was no new affirmation of internationalism by an often provincial Congress, but a reaffirmation of one of its oldest truths: Members vote their districts.</p>
        <p>That is, they vote their districts if their constituents have an interest, and a trade bill is a singular foreign policy measure because the question of jobs gained and lost commands attention from lawmakers and constituents ordinarily not much concerned about the rest of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most important foreign policy vote so far this year, the 237-to-197 House approval of the China trade deal, was no new affirmation of internationalism by an often provincial Congress, but a reaffirmation of one of its oldest truths: Members vote their districts.</p>
        <p>That is, they vote their districts if their constituents have an interest, and a trade bill is a singular foreign policy measure because the question of jobs gained and lost commands attention from lawmakers and constituents ordinarily not much concerned about the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>But other foreign policy matters have far smaller constituencies, and are much more subject to Washington's political influences, especially partisanship. To put it meanly, each party plays politics with foreign policy; to put it kindly, each trusts presidents of its own party but discerns grave weaknesses on the other side.</p>
        <p>In any case, the ''internationalist'' Republicans who supported President Bush's Persian Gulf war in 1991 suddenly became ''isolationist'' Republicans who opposed President Clinton over military action in Somalia (where Mr. Bush actually had sent the troops), as well as in Bosnia and Kosovo. The Democrats, meanwhile, eagerly seized the labels the Republicans had dropped.</p>
        <p>There are some members of Congress who take the ''internationalist'' view on trade, intervention abroad, United Nations financing and comparable issues regardless of party, at least most of the time.</p>
        <p>But looking at a dozen key votes dating back to the gulf war, there are only 10 current House members who voted that way all the time. Several are Southern Democrats with no union pressure over trade to worry about. Two are Democrats from Washington State, where union desires to sell Boeing airplanes to China overcome all other trade questions. And one is a moderate Republican, Representative Constance A. Morella from the suburbs of Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>But most representatives rise or fall on domestic records, and for them ''foreign policy is totally unimportant most of the time,'' said Barbara Bardes, a political scientist at the University of Cincinnati. ''They are available for those swing votes as long as it doesn't hurt them.''</p>
        <p>And more of them are available these days because two factors encouraging instinctive support of a president no longer matter.</p>
        <p>One was the cold war, which drew the argument that the United States would seem weak to the Soviet Union if the president could not enforce his foreign policy views, even in areas of no concern to Moscow.</p>
        <p>A second is the departure of the World War II generation from Congress. Only nine veterans of that war now serve in the House. The Senate has lost the voice of Bob Dole, who could tell his colleagues that once the president had made a decision, even a weak one, he must be supported.</p>
        <p>The ''sort of 'president knows best' attitude is gone,'' said another student of Congressional behavior on foreign policy, James McCormack, an Iowa State University political scientist.</p>
        <p>Indeed, that generation has been replaced by the skeptical veterans and nonveterans of the Vietnam era, for whom ''the commander-in-chief thing doesn't work,'' Dr. Bardes said. ''They are worried about becoming too involved.''</p>
        <p>That attitude produces resolutions demanding withdrawal of troops from Bosnia and Kosovo, delays in appropriations for drug wars in Colombia and, at its most intense level, Senate rejection of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty.</p>
        <p>The consequence is that, ''given the polarization of the parties, almost any major initiative requires a major effort'' by the president, said Bob Pastor, a political scientist at Emory University in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>This China trade bill got that intense effort, not just from the administration, but from business and House Republicans, too.</p>
        <p>But without outside allies of the weight of the business interests that backed this bill, the administration lost the nuclear test treaty and faces continual difficulties in getting the money to pay back dues to the United Nations.</p>
        <p>That effort was required because even if this was fundamentally a trade bill, where most of the votes depended on jobs gained for Florida fertilizer mills or lost to textile plants in North Carolina, it also carried the baggage of a foreign policy measure about a Chinese government that no one in Congress will defend. This was not a pure trade measure, like the question of extending lower tariffs to Chile.</p>
        <p>The 57 Republicans who voted no were primarily motivated by China's treatment of Christians and political dissidents, plus its reported espionage activity against the United States. And others were tempted, doubting the argument that trade would broaden Chinese society.</p>
        <p>Representative Tom Tancredo of Colorado dripped with sarcasm: ''We have been told wonderful things will flow from expanded trade with China. Workers' rights will be respected, religious freedom will be enhanced, and probably Jeffersonian study groups will be popping up all over China.''</p>
        <p>But supporters like Representative Nancy L. Johnson, Republican of Connecticut, disagreed. She quoted a clergyman, Rev. Daniel Baida Su, who told the Ways and Means Committee that the deal and membership in the World Trade Organization obliged ''China to play by the rules.''</p>
        <p>''In the process, China will need to strengthen its legal institutions, train more legal professionals, learn to follow international legal procedures, and educate its people about the concept of rights, law and international norms,'' Ms. Johnson quoted Mr. Su as saying. ''This process alone is a breakthrough with important philosophical implications for China as a nation. When a Chinese realizes he has rights as an investor that government should not violate, then more likely he will also realize that he has other rights as a human being.''</p>
        <p>But her argument would not have prevailed without the sense in Congress that more jobs were to be gained than lost, and without the labor opposition suffering from the label of ''protectionism,'' concerned about saving the jobs of union members at the expense of the American economy in general.</p>
        <p>John J. Sweeney, president of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., called that label ''very unfair.'' He said in an interview: ''We realize the value of trade with any country. We recognize the expansion of globalization. But in this new global economy, we must strive for rules that protect human rights and workers rights and the environment and not just profits.''</p>
        <p>It was the bill itself that was protectionist, he said, as an ''outright attempt to protect profits without any concern for human rights and workers' rights.''</p>
        <p>That argument was often heard on the House floor. Representative Janice D. Schakowsky, an Illinois Democrat, said the bill encouraged United States companies to take ''advantage of the nearest slave labor conditions and wages.'' That sort of attack went largely unchallenged.</p>
        <p>But arguments like those of Representative Marge Roukema prevailed. The New Jersey Republican saw huge opportunities for American energy, gas, construction, telecommunications and engineering companies in China. ''Not only for New Jersey,'' she said, ''but for the nation, the bottom line here is that this is a jobs bill.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
