<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COST OF INSURANCE FOR CARS IS RISING ACROSS THE NATION</title>
    <meta content="27AUTO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Progressive Insurance</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Geico Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Farm Insurance Cos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allstate Insurance Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDD113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COST OF INSURANCE FOR CARS IS RISING ACROSS THE NATION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Car insurance premiums around country are rising again after falling for two years, resuming steady quarter-century rise; several big insurers--including Progressive, Geico, State Farm and Allstate--have begun imposing higher prices, and analysts say that by end of year most other leading companies are likely to follow suit; insurers say they are forced to act because of rising expenses for repairs and treatment of injuries; while size of rises has varied--and some companies are still cutting prices--rises of at least 4 to 5 percent have not been uncommon; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After falling for two years, car insurance premiums around the country are climbing once again, resuming a steady quarter-century rise.</p>
        <p>Several big insurers -- including Progressive, Geico, State Farm and Allstate -- have begun imposing higher prices, and analysts say that by the end of the year most other leading companies are likely to follow suit. The insurers said they were forced to act because of rising expenses for repairs and treatment of injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After falling for two years, car insurance premiums around the country are climbing once again, resuming a steady quarter-century rise.</p>
        <p>Several big insurers -- including Progressive, Geico, State Farm and Allstate -- have begun imposing higher prices, and analysts say that by the end of the year most other leading companies are likely to follow suit. The insurers said they were forced to act because of rising expenses for repairs and treatment of injuries.</p>
        <p>''The trend is clearly upward,'' said Thomas V. Cholnoky, who follows auto insurance for Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>While the size of the increases has varied widely -- and some companies are still cutting prices -- rises of at least 4 to 5 percent have not been uncommon. And a few companies have raised prices in some states by more than 10 percent. Analysts and industry executives say they expect more of the same next year.</p>
        <p>In New York and Connecticut, the first signs of the shift are appearing. But the situation is less clear in New Jersey, where spending on car insurance -- averaging $1,150 a year a car, compared with $700 nationally -- has been the highest in the country. Last year the legislature took the unusual step of ordering a 15 percent cut in prices.</p>
        <p>While expenses for insurers may well be rising in New Jersey, as elsewhere, industry executives said it was difficult to predict whether those costs would be offset by legislative changes aimed at reducing fraud and litigation and, if not, to what extent political leaders would permit price increases.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates say the increases may not be justified. J. Robert Hunter, director of insurance at the Consumer Federation of America, said that while some costs were rising, expenses for insurers, over all, were still declining.</p>
        <p>Americans spent an estimated $126 billion last year on car insurance, which is mandatory in all states. That was nearly four times what they paid to insure their homes. There are many more claims involving cars and passengers than for homes, though, and liability claims in the hundreds of thousands of dollars are much more common in car crashes than in incidents related to homes.</p>
        <p>Besides raising prices, insurers are reducing or eliminating discounts and screening applicants more carefully so that they apply the highest rates to the riskiest drivers and simply refuse to sell to some. Several companies have also been hacking away at administrative expenses, with layoffs in some cases.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates say that to make sure of getting the best deal as prices are rising, people should review their bills and check prices with several companies. But rather than basing coverage decisions on price alone, the advocates advise people to talk with friends and insurance regulators to learn how various companies treat customers.</p>
        <p>Prices for auto insurance had risen steadily since 1973, and in the  years through 1997 they rose more than twice as fast as inflation, according to the Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
        <p>But in 1998 they fell 2.8 percent and last year 3.2 percent, said Robert P. Hartwig, chief economist at the Insurance Information Institute, an industry group in New York. Insurers said they had cut their prices to reflect falling costs for claims.</p>
        <p>Fewer and less serious accidents were occurring, partly because of safety features like air bags and antilock brakes. There had also been declines in drunken driving and auto theft, and signs that aging baby boomers were becoming safer drivers. Mr. Hartwig said body shop costs and medical expenses had leveled off.</p>
        <p>While many of those trends are continuing, Mr. Hartwig said, their financial benefits are being eclipsed by a resurgence in costs for repairs and treatment of injuries. He said repair costs are up partly because many companies stopped using generic replacement parts after State Farm was sued by consumers last fall and ordered to pay $1.2 billion for not using original manufacturers' parts.</p>
        <p>Randy Stoddard, a top executive at Safeco, the nation's 15th-largest insurer, said that while the number of accidents was still declining, ''the severity is up.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said: ''The new cars are smarter and more expensive to repair. And people are more expensive to repair; we call that medical inflation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunter said he had no doubt that the insurers' costs per accident were going up. ''But,'' he said, ''the number of accidents is falling faster than the increase in costs.''</p>
        <p>Safeco, which reported a nearly $40 million loss in its auto insurance business in the first quarter, has increased rates in 20 states so far this year, from just under 1 percent in Colorado to 8.2 percent in Michigan. Last year it cut prices in 18 states.</p>
        <p>The two biggest companies -- State Farm and Allstate -- are still cutting rates in more states than they are raising them, but they, too, are showing the early signs of a shift. Last year, State Farm cut rates in 48 states and increased prices in only one, Massachusetts. So far this year, State Farm says it is cutting rates in 15 states and increasing them in 10, including a 5.6 percent rise in Montana.</p>
        <p>State Farm is seeking a decrease of nearly 5 percent in California, the state with the most drivers. But Mr. Cholnoky said that an analysis of rates in California showed that State Farm's prices were among the highest in the state, 31 percent higher than Allstate's and 55 percent higher than Progressive's.</p>
        <p>So far this year, Allstate has raised prices in two states -- Louisiana and South Carolina; last year there were no increases. While it trimmed rates in 10 states last year, only 4 states have had cuts this year.</p>
        <p>In New York, where regulators have taken steps to ease costs for insurers, just as they did in New Jersey, one of the largest companies, Progressive, has raised rates 4.3 percent. Nineteen small companies have put in place increases ranging from less than 1 percent to 18.6 percent; six other small companies cut prices. In Connecticut, one of the largest insurers, Nationwide Mutual, increased prices 4.9 percent and six other insurers have come in with smaller increases. Five small insurers cut prices. Last year price decreases outnumbered increases nearly 3 to 1.</p>
        <p>One small New Jersey company, GSA, raised premiums 15 percent, and several New Jersey insurers are asking regulators for even higher increases. But John Tiene, executive director of the Insurance Council of New Jersey, said these increases had been requested two years ago and did not reflect current expenses. The increase for GSA, however, had the effect of nullifying the 15 percent legislative rollback.</p>
        <p>Geico, Progressive, Safeco and several other major insurers do not operate in New Jersey, saying that it is difficult to do so profitably.</p>
        <p>Across the country, Progressive and Geico have been leading a price war and gaining market share at the expense of companies like State Farm and Allstate, which have been either losing market share or merely holding even as the number of drivers has been growing.</p>
        <p>Now, both Progressive and Geico, after suffering significant losses in earnings, are shifting toward higher prices. Since last year, for example, Progressive has increased prices by an average of 7.4 percent in 41 states, according to Charles B. Gates, an insurance analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston. Progressive has raised rates about 4 percent in Missouri and is asking for an increase of 9.9 percent in Florida.</p>
        <p>As it announced an underwriting loss of $86 million in the first quarter of this year, Geico said it expected to increase rates in many states, but gave no details. Geico is a unit of Berkshire Hathaway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said the increase in prices by Progressive and Geico, which have been the fastest-growing big insurers, were likely to be taken as a sign by other insurers that it was safe to raise prices. Previously, he said, the others may have feared that price increases would drive customers to Progressive and Geico.</p>
        <p>Several analysts said they expected State Farm and Allstate to raise prices more slowly than other big companies because over the previous two years they had reduced their prices less than many competitors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hunter said that in their zeal to capture market share, Progressive and Geico might have cut prices too much for their own good. ''Those companies might have to raise rates,'' he said. ''But some companies may be taking advantage of this opportunity to raise their rates. I'm saying, 'Wait a minute. You don't need to raise your rates. You should be continuing to lower them.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
