<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congressional Primary in New Jersey Mirrors G.O.P.'s Divisions</title>
    <meta content="27TWEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pappas, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, Richard A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holt, Rush D (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6DC113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congressional Primary in New Jersey Mirrors G.O.P.'s Divisions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>WHITEHOUSE, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Pappas, former Republican congressman from New Jersey's 12th Congressional District, is trying to win back his seat in unusual primary race with another former congressman, Richard A Zimmer; race figures to be one of most hotly contested House elections in nation; June 6 primary is matchup between Pappas, unvarnished conservative, and Zimmer, social moderate; Pappas has been endorsed by some top Republicans, while Zimmer has been endorsed by others; both men seek nomination in hopes of unseating Democratic incumbent, Rep Rush Holt; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever you do, don't ask Mike Pappas to sing.</p>
        <p>During the impeachment proceedings against President Clinton, Mr. Pappas, then a freshman Republican, stood up on the House floor and sang a ditty honoring Kenneth W. Starr, the prosecutor, to the tune of ''Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.'' Coming just as public impatience with the Republican-led proceedings was boiling over, the performance became infamous enough that Mr. Pappas's Democratic rival, Rush Holt, was able to turn it into prime advertising fodder and take over the reliably Republican seat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whatever you do, don't ask Mike Pappas to sing.</p>
        <p>During the impeachment proceedings against President Clinton, Mr. Pappas, then a freshman Republican, stood up on the House floor and sang a ditty honoring Kenneth W. Starr, the prosecutor, to the tune of ''Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.'' Coming just as public impatience with the Republican-led proceedings was boiling over, the performance became infamous enough that Mr. Pappas's Democratic rival, Rush Holt, was able to turn it into prime advertising fodder and take over the reliably Republican seat.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Pappas, trying to win back his seat, finds himself in an unusual primary race in which he faces another former congressman -- Richard A. Zimmer, who gave up the job in 1996 for an unsuccessful Senate bid against Robert G. Torricelli.</p>
        <p>The race for the seat, which had been Republican for decades, figures to be one of the most hotly contested House elections in the nation, with control of the House up for grabs and Republicans now holding a slim six-seat majority.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the most vulnerable seats in the country,'' said Marit Babin, a spokeswoman for the National Republican Congressional Committee. ''Rush Holt better watch out.''</p>
        <p>But before Republicans can take aim at Mr. Holt, the party must endure a messy fight in the June 6 primary between Mr. Pappas, an unvarnished conservative, and Mr. Zimmer, a social moderate.</p>
        <p>It is a matchup of two very different Republicans, one that is exposing the deep divisions within the national party. The House majority whip, Tom DeLay, and the House majority leader, Dick Armey -- both staunch conservatives -- are supporting Mr. Pappas, while Mr. Zimmer has been endorsed by the House speaker, J. Dennis Hastert, and Representative Thomas M. Davis III, head of the party's Congressional election committee.</p>
        <p>''The N.R.C.C. has vowed to target Rush Holt, but so far we've seen nothing but an unending food fight among Republicans,'' said John Del Cecato, a spokesman for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''These two guys are clawing at each other, and whoever emerges is going to be damaged goods for the fall.''</p>
        <p>After months of unexpected civility, the two candidates began attacking each other late this week. Mr. Zimmer, not surprisingly, began running a radio ad featuring his opponent singing, and Mr. Pappas sent out a mailing that accuses his rival of inspiring New Jersey's income tax when he was the head of Common Cause in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Zimmer's supporters circulated a videocassette of the recital among party stalwarts to scare off potential backers of Mr. Pappas.</p>
        <p>That tactic seems to have worked. Mr. Zimmer has rounded up endorsements from most every top party official in the state, including Gov. Christine Todd Whitman, former Gov. Thomas H. Kean and Chuck Haytaian, the party chairman. The district's five county committees are also supporting Mr. Zimmer, who has raised just over $1 million, compared with $225,000 for Mr. Pappas.</p>
        <p>Most of those supporting Mr. Zimmer say electability, not ideology, was the deciding factor.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see that district come back into Republican hands, and the bottom line is that Dick has the better chance of beating Rush Holt,'' Mr. Haytaian said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pappas may lack money and big-name boosters, but he has the impassioned support of local abortion opponents, gun enthusiasts and social conservatives. Angry over  what they say is Mr. Zimmer's flip-flopping on their issues, groups like New Jersey Right to Life and the New Jersey Sportsman Association are vowing to mobilize their troops on June 6.</p>
        <p>Leonard Lance, a Republican assemblyman who lost to Mr. Pappas in a three-way Congressional race in 1996, said low turnout, especially in a year without a contested presidential primary in the major parties, could swing the election away from Mr. Zimmer.</p>
        <p>''The true believers always vote,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rick Shaftan, a consultant who ran the first Pappas campaign for Congress, predicted that Mr. Pappas would defy conventional wisdom like he did four years ago, when many  political writers treated him like an afterthought. ''Conservatives feel so abused by the Republican Party, they're going to come out in droves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Those who live in the narrow band that cuts across New Jersey's midsection are, by and large, a contented lot. The 12th District, which stretches on either side of United States Route 1, boasts the state's best-educated and most prosperous residents. It includes the gentleman-farmer estates of Hunterdon County, the new-money McMansions of greater Princeton and the solidly middle-class towns of East Brunswick, Holmdel and Freehold.</p>
        <p>With good schools, no cities and negligible crime, there is not much to fire up the average voter. ''The only thing uniting the district is that it contains most of the horse farms in the state,'' said Steven Salmore, a Republican consultant.</p>
        <p>When they are not arguing over who was the better congressman, the two candidates talk mostly about cutting taxes, fighting sprawl and saving Social Security. Mr. Zimmer supports gun control and abortion rights, although he recently switched his position on the late-term procedure that critics call partial-birth abortion, which he now opposes. His most widely recognized accomplishment in Congress was a federal version of Megan's Law, the sex-offender notification law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pappas, who earned a 100 percent voting-record rating from the Christian Coalition, wears his conservative credentials with pride. He speaks proudly of his vote to impeach Mr. Clinton, and he held a news conference earlier this month announcing his endorsement by Phyllis Schlafly, president of the conservative Eagle Forum. He agrees with the decision of the Boy Scouts of America to eject an openly gay scoutmaster, an issue that Mr. Zimmer declined to weigh in on. ''It's a very complicated matter,'' Mr. Zimmer said. ''I do, however, oppose all forms of discrimination.''</p>
        <p>Born in Newark and brought up in a strongly Democratic working-class family, Mr. Zimmer lives on an organic farm in Delaware Township, where his wife raises sheep. Soft-spoken and bespectacled, Mr. Zimmer, 55, hardly looks the part of the hungry politician. Supporters say he is more comfortable drafting legislation than schmoozing voters, but those who remember his failed Senate race know he can give as good as he gets. Even today, many Republicans shake their heads when recalling the viciousness of that campaign. ''This time,'' Mr. Zimmer said, ''I'm just going to promote my record.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Zimmer uses his war chest on radio and television ads (some of which refer to him as Congressman Zimmer), Mr. Pappas spends his days going door to door.</p>
        <p>''When you go see someone in their home, you show them you know the roads they drive on and what kinds of recreational facilities their kids have,'' he said. ''More often than not, I find they'll support you.''</p>
        <p>Like his opponent, Mr. Pappas, 39, is not much of a backslapper. He spends some of his free time with the local 4-H club or a drug prevention program for teenagers. Before his election, he worked for his family's insurance business.</p>
        <p>Occupying the basement of a ranch house on Route 22 here in Whitehouse, the Pappas headquarters was buzzing on a recent afternoon as volunteers coordinated literature mailings or the placement of campaign signs on the lawns of supporters. Rush Limbaugh played on the radio, and a National Rifle Association membership certificate hung near a photograph of Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Jack Grimes, the Pappas campaign's youthful director, said an outpouring of volunteer help had made up for the paucity of cash and party support.</p>
        <p>''We made a conscious decision not to sit around and make fund-raising calls,'' he said. ''The proof is out there: if you drive around the district, all you see are Pappas signs. You rarely see a Zimmer sign.''</p>
        <p>He attributed Mr. Pappas's loss in 1998 to Mr. Holt's use of his advertising dollars to tap into the anti-impeachment fury.</p>
        <p>''I guess his passion got the best of him,'' Mr. Grimes said of Mr. Pappas's singing on the House floor. ''Anyway, he's promised everyone that from now on, he'll only sing in the shower.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
