<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chance Discovery on a Train Led to a Ring of Counterfeiters</title>
    <meta content="27MONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Money and Financial Instruments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bulgaria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simeonov, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Money and Financial Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDC113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chance Discovery on a Train Led to a Ring of Counterfeiters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Simeonov pleads guilty in Manhattan court to conspiracy to distribute counterfeit $100 bills; he is part of group responsible for distributing at least $500,000 in counterfeit money in 1999; chance find of counterfeit bills on Amtrak train led to ring whose trail stretched from Queens through Canada to Bulgaria, where federal prosecutors say group of men produced some of highest-quality fake money now circulating; five other men have already pleaded guilty; all are awaiting sentencing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Amtrak train to New York rolled into Niagara Falls last October, customs officers boarded it for a routine inspection. What they found, stacked and wrapped in a newspaper in a bathroom stall, was anything but routine: $200,000 in $100 bills.</p>
        <p>That chance find last October led to a counterfeiting ring whose trail stretched from Queens through Canada to Bulgaria, where federal prosecutors say a group of men produced some of the highest-quality fake money now circulating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Amtrak train to New York rolled into Niagara Falls last October, customs officers boarded it for a routine inspection. What they found, stacked and wrapped in a newspaper in a bathroom stall, was anything but routine: $200,000 in $100 bills.</p>
        <p>That chance find last October led to a counterfeiting ring whose trail stretched from Queens through Canada to Bulgaria, where federal prosecutors say a group of men produced some of the highest-quality fake money now circulating.</p>
        <p>This week, the last member of the counterfeiting operation pleaded guilty in United States District Court in Manhattan to conspiracy to distribute the $100 bills. Prosecutors said the man, Peter Simeonov, a native of Bulgaria, was part of a group responsible for distributing at least $500,000 in counterfeit money in 1999. Five other men have also pleaded guilty to various charges in the case. They are all awaiting sentencing</p>
        <p>After finding the money in the train bathroom, customs officers alerted the Secret Service, which is responsible for pursuing counterfeiters. The agents met the officers at the train and, according to court documents, immediately identified the bills as the type believed to originate in Bulgaria. Documents filed in court say the agents checked the passenger roster and identified one rider as a Bulgarian. After questioning him, the agents were able to find the ring members who were passing the money in Queens.</p>
        <p>Secret Service agents, who had begun an investigation of counterfeit $100 bills before the discovery on the train, quickly identified the Amtrak find as part of the bills flooding New York City. Prosecutors said that $35,000 to $40,000 worth of the bogus bills were being passed every week in the New York area.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors in the United States attorney's office for the Southern District of New York said that the counterfeiting ring had been passing both old and new versions of the bills. Court papers said the men either gave the bills to unsuspecting merchants or sold them at a discount, typically for 40 cents on the dollar.</p>
        <p>Bruce A. Townsend, the special agent in charge of the Secret Service's counterfeit division, said that the Bulgarian bills were of high quality, but that new currency, with its off-center portraits and sophisticated security features, was very difficult to copy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Townsend said the $100 bills had been made with an offset printing press, which is a traditional way of making counterfeit money. Much counterfeit money detected recently was reproduced with computer technology, he said, which tends to produce bills of lower quality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Townsend said that less than 1 percent of the more than $500 billion in U.S. currency in circulation throughout the world is estimated to be counterfeit.</p>
        <p>''A counterfeit-proof bank note does not exist,'' he said. ''But what we do is add layers of security to make it as difficult as possible.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
