<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serbia's Muzzled Media</title>
    <meta content="27SAT3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1202626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DF113DF934A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serbia's Muzzled Media</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds 2 AM raid by masked police on Serbia's most important opposition television and radio stations last week signals escalation of Slobodan Milosevic's attacks on media; sees Milosevic trying to control the news as elections approach</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When masked police staged a 2 a.m. raid on Serbia's most important opposition television and radio stations last week, it signaled an escalation of Slobodan Milosevic's attacks on the media. Independent journalists throughout Serbia have been beaten and arrested, and their transmitters are mysteriously failing. Mr. Milosevic is apparently desperate to control the news as elections approach, which makes it particularly important for friends of democracy in Serbia to help these broadcasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic previously attacked the independent media mainly by yanking their licenses, suing them and imposing steep fines. A small group of radio and television stations managed to broadcast anyway. The most important are Studio B, controlled by Vuk Draskovic, an opposition leader whose party runs Belgrade, and Radio B2-92. Both were closed last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When masked police staged a 2 a.m. raid on Serbia's most important opposition television and radio stations last week, it signaled an escalation of Slobodan Milosevic's attacks on the media. Independent journalists throughout Serbia have been beaten and arrested, and their transmitters are mysteriously failing. Mr. Milosevic is apparently desperate to control the news as elections approach, which makes it particularly important for friends of democracy in Serbia to help these broadcasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic previously attacked the independent media mainly by yanking their licenses, suing them and imposing steep fines. A small group of radio and television stations managed to broadcast anyway. The most important are Studio B, controlled by Vuk Draskovic, an opposition leader whose party runs Belgrade, and Radio B2-92. Both were closed last week.</p>
        <p>The raids are the culmination of an increasingly desperate campaign to label independent journalists as terrorists and to paint them as shills for the NATO alliance. The Serbian government is also threatening to pass a new anti-terrorism law, which would certainly be used against these journalists.</p>
        <p>One reason for Mr. Milosevic's panic is that polls show his support dropping, and the Constitution provides for local and parliamentary elections by the end of the year. His political opposition is hapless, divided and easily manipulated, and has responded to the media crackdown with silence and confusion. But a new student movement, called Otpor, is drawing substantial public support.</p>
        <p>The independent media can reach much of their  public with help from outside. Serbia's sister republic, Montenegro, which is in open rebellion against Mr. Milosevic, has offered its satellite stations. In 1996, when B2-92's predecessor was briefly closed, the Voice of America broadcast its news programs. The V.O.A., BBC and other foreign stations can be heard on FM radio in Serbia. Their transmitters could allow B2-92's news to reach a large audience.  Western governments and news outlets are also increasing aid to Serbia's independent journalists. A new fund for the legal defense of persecuted journalists will be particularly important as Mr. Milosevic intensifies his campaign.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
