<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From President Bush's Answers</title>
    <meta content="Y15DTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George (Former Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDA103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From President Bush's Answers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from answers by former Pres George Bush to questions about Gov George Bush's campaign; in response to request for an interview, former Pres Bush agreed to answer several questions in writing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In response to a request for an interview about his son's campaign, former President George Bush agreed to answer several questions in writing. Following are some of the questions and excerpts from Mr. Bush's answers:</p>
        <p>Q.  Friends have said you were extremely wounded by the reaction among some journalists and political analysts to the fact that you called your son ''this boy'' during a joint appearance just before the New Hampshire primary. Is that true?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In response to a request for an interview about his son's campaign, former President George Bush agreed to answer several questions in writing. Following are some of the questions and excerpts from Mr. Bush's answers:</p>
        <p>Q.  Friends have said you were extremely wounded by the reaction among some journalists and political analysts to the fact that you called your son ''this boy'' during a joint appearance just before the New Hampshire primary. Is that true?</p>
        <p>A.  Frankly, when the journalistic pack took a loving comment and gesture from a father about his son and used it to attack the son, it darn sure did hurt. Certainly, I would never do anything to damage George. Of course I hug my sons. And I have called all four of them my ''boys'' all during their lives. For these to have been used to diminish George in some way damn sure did hurt.</p>
        <p>Q.  Did it make you any warier about joint public appearances?</p>
        <p>A.  It added to convictions already held that I should not get out front, that I should continue to stay behind the scenes, off TV, out of the papers.</p>
        <p>Q.  Did you concur with the assessment of some analysts that the comments had a detrimental effect on your son's candidacy in New Hampshire?</p>
        <p>A.  I never felt the ''assessment'' was correct. I worried more that it might hurt George just because of the piling on of negative interpretation placed on my comment, my gesture, by some in the press.</p>
        <p>Q.  How does one balance and reconcile the roles of father and experienced candidate with much accumulated wisdom and perspective?</p>
        <p>A.  I have no inclination to share my ''experience'' -- in fact, issues have changed so much that I don't consider myself as possessed of valuable ''wisdom  and perspective.'' Mainly, I want to be George's dad, give him love and support. I want to be there for him.</p>
        <p>Q. What else would you like to add about the emotional experience of watching your son go through a difficult process you know all too well?</p>
        <p>A.  I would only add that 1992 was not the most pleasant year for me with the national press, but it is far worse for Barbara and me when George is criticized than when I was. He is my son. We are close.</p>
        <p>I guess after four national campaigns I might know what to expect; but I can tell you none of the flak I took affected me as much as when I see George unfairly criticized. If the shots are justified -- fine. But if they are cheap shots then, of course, this father does not like it. I know all this goes with the territory, and I know this is the big league and I know I have taken on my share of shots; but, believe me, it is different when it is your own flesh and blood.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
