<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Next Big Antitrust Case</title>
    <meta content="15THU3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Visa International Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mastercard International Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DA103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Next Big Antitrust Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial supports Justice Department antitrust case against Visa and MasterCard; says government's arguments that the two credit card networks are too cozy with each other and use their enormous financial power to stifle competition mirror arguments that Justice made against Microsoft, and consumers should hope for same outcome</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week the Justice Department began its antitrust case against Visa and MasterCard. The government argues that the Visa and MasterCard networks are too cozy with each other and use their enormous financial power to knock out potential competitors, thereby stunting innovation. Some of the arguments mirror those that Justice made against Microsoft. Consumers should hope for the same outcome -- a resounding victory for Justice.</p>
        <p>Thousands of banks offer Visa and MasterCard credit cards. Many banks offer both. The trouble comes from the fact that some banks that serve on the governing board of one network do substantial business with the other. This ''dual governance,'' says Justice, discourages competition between the networks, stifling the desire to create new products.</p>
        <p>It is important to note what this case is not about. The individual banks set interest rates and frequent-flier and other benefits in order to compete for cardholders. Justice does not argue that the banks are conspiring to deny customers good deals. Instead, it makes two other antitrust accusations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This week the Justice Department began its antitrust case against Visa and MasterCard. The government argues that the Visa and MasterCard networks are too cozy with each other and use their enormous financial power to knock out potential competitors, thereby stunting innovation. Some of the arguments mirror those that Justice made against Microsoft. Consumers should hope for the same outcome -- a resounding victory for Justice.</p>
        <p>Thousands of banks offer Visa and MasterCard credit cards. Many banks offer both. The trouble comes from the fact that some banks that serve on the governing board of one network do substantial business with the other. This ''dual governance,'' says Justice, discourages competition between the networks, stifling the desire to create new products.</p>
        <p>It is important to note what this case is not about. The individual banks set interest rates and frequent-flier and other benefits in order to compete for cardholders. Justice does not argue that the banks are conspiring to deny customers good deals. Instead, it makes two other antitrust accusations.</p>
        <p>First, neither network has a powerful incentive to undertake innovation. As one illustration, Justice argues that Visa or MasterCard might have offered smart cards -- cards with chips that could make health and other data instantly available -- had they not settled into a cozy relationship. Visa and MasterCard say they do not offer smart cards because they make no business sense. But Justice's point is that dual governance can rule out even sensible innovations. Justice would therefore prevent banks that do a large amount of business with one network from setting policy at the other.</p>
        <p>Justice also wants the networks to allow member banks to issue rival cards. The fact that member banks cannot do so under current rules could create a huge problem for American Express if debit cards -- which directly tap a cardholder's bank account -- become the next big innovation.</p>
        <p>The networks dispute whether these remedies will in fact help consumers. MasterCard says that without dual governance it might not survive as a worthy rival to Visa. Currently, it entices banks with heavy Visa enrollments to promote MasterCard by offering them positions on its governing board. If Justice ends dual governance, then MasterCard fears the attractive banks will flock to Visa, the larger network. But the answer to this problem is not to preserve a cartel, but to force MasterCard to come up with a better business strategy.</p>
        <p>Justice may not be able to show decisive harm to consumers as yet. But all it needs to do is show that these practices stifle competition. Visa and MasterCard control about 75 percent of the credit card business. The antitrust laws are designed to force them to compete. Justice's proposed remedies would do just that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
