<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater for Fun or Profit; Producers' Two Camps Remain Uneasy Allies</title>
    <meta content="T15DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">League of American Theaters and Producers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Theater Communications Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Contact (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/New York Theater Workshop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5D7103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater for Fun or Profit; Producers' Two Camps Remain Uneasy Allies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commercial theater and nonprofit theater have been collaborating more and more, but two camps remain uneasy allies; some Broadway producers resent New York's large nonprofits for reaping benefits of producing shows on Broadway without risk that comes with raising money from people who expect a return; nonprofit Lincoln Center Theater has been criticized for being eligible for coveted Tony Awards--like this year's best-musical prize for Contact--without having burden of repaying investors; some nonprofit executives resent commercial producers for taking their work while cutting them out of process and sometimes out of financial rewards; two camps are coming together at Harvard University for weekendlong conference called Act Two, the Second American Congress of Theater; conference was organized by League of American Theaters and Producers, which represents commercial theater, and Theater Communications Group, which has 360 nonprofit members; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a gathering of commercial theater producers and nonprofit theater executives at Princeton University in June 1974, Julian Beck of the experimental Living Theater emphatically called for the death of Broadway: ''The alternative theater is a theater which has always been opposed to the Broadway theater. We want to destroy it. It is now being destroyed. It is in fact dying, and that is good.''</p>
        <p>Things have calmed down considerably in the last 26 years. Back then most nonprofit theaters were merely burgeoning artistic outposts; now many are formidable producing operations. Although the two worlds used to regard each other with suspicion and even disdain -- some of which still lingers -- commercial and nonprofit producers have increasingly become partners. The commercial side looks to the nonprofit for new material and chances to test costly projects; the nonprofit looks to the commercial to shoulder some expenses of ambitious productions and to help give shows longer lives on larger stages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a gathering of commercial theater producers and nonprofit theater executives at Princeton University in June 1974, Julian Beck of the experimental Living Theater emphatically called for the death of Broadway: ''The alternative theater is a theater which has always been opposed to the Broadway theater. We want to destroy it. It is now being destroyed. It is in fact dying, and that is good.''</p>
        <p>Things have calmed down considerably in the last 26 years. Back then most nonprofit theaters were merely burgeoning artistic outposts; now many are formidable producing operations. Although the two worlds used to regard each other with suspicion and even disdain -- some of which still lingers -- commercial and nonprofit producers have increasingly become partners. The commercial side looks to the nonprofit for new material and chances to test costly projects; the nonprofit looks to the commercial to shoulder some expenses of ambitious productions and to help give shows longer lives on larger stages.</p>
        <p>''You cannot afford the luxury any longer of thinking of two distinct isolated worlds of theater,'' said Gerald Schoenfeld, chairman of the Shubert Organization, New York's most powerful theater owner. ''Economics have been the driving force between profit and nonprofit, or taxpaying and nontaxpaying, as I call it.''</p>
        <p>But although the two spheres have been collaborating more and more, disputes still rankle. Some Broadway producers, for example, resent New York's large nonprofits for reaping the benefits of producing shows on Broadway without the risk that comes with raising money from people who expect a return. The nonprofit Lincoln Center Theater, for example, has been criticized for being eligible for coveted Tony Awards -- like this year's best-musical prize for ''Contact'' -- without having the burden of repaying investors. Some nonprofit executives resent commercial producers for taking their work while cutting them out of the process and sometimes out of the financial rewards.</p>
        <p>As a result questions remain: When projects are jointly developed, who has artistic control? Are nonprofits becoming too much like their commercial counterparts and abandoning a commitment to daring work? Has the commercial theater become overly dependent on the nonprofits for ideas it should be developing itself? (All of the American dramas nominated this year in the Tony Awards' best new play category originated in the nonprofit world, along with all three American productions competing for best revival of a play and two of the four best-musical nominees. And since 1976, with the exception of Neil Simon's ''Lost in Yonkers'' in 1991, every Pulitzer Prize winner for best play has been developed in a nonprofit theater.)</p>
        <p>To tackle some of these sensitive issues, the two camps are coming together again, this time at Harvard University for a weekendlong conference that begins tomorrow. The conference, called Act Two, the Second American Congress of Theater, was organized by the League of American Theaters and Producers, which represents commercial producers, and the Theater Communications Group, which has 360 nonprofit members.</p>
        <p>Among the country's estimated 1,100 nonprofits, most have annual budgets under $500,000. In New York they range from the Roundabout Theater Company, which has a budget of about $20 million and produces plays like the current ''Uncle Vanya,'' to the Collapsible Giraffe, with a budget of about $25,000, which combines video and theater in new productions like its recent ''Three Virgins,'' performed in a Times Square strip club. Conference participants will include a range of theater professionals -- artistic directors of regional theaters, Broadway producers, a few playwrights and actors -- as well as government officials.</p>
        <p>Even though most of the conference will be closed to the press and the public to encourage candid discussion, there is some question about how frank participants will be about their real concerns. In an effort to spur some frank discussion, the Broadway producer Rocco Landesman -- writing in the June 4 Arts &amp; Leisure section of The New York Times -- accused nonprofit theaters of modeling themselves after ''the commercial arena, which is, in the end, not dedicated to the art so much as to the audience.'' In particular, Mr. Landesman, president of Jujamcyn Theaters, which owns several Broadway houses, criticized the Roundabout's artistic director, Todd Haimes, for playing it safe with audience-pleasing work and for selling the name of his new theater to a corporation; it will now be the American Airlines Theater.</p>
        <p>''It would, I suppose, be hyperbolic to say that Todd Haimes has had a more pernicious influence on English-speaking theater than anyone since Oliver Cromwell (and it wouldn't be nice, either, since Mr. Haimes is a personable and honorable man),'' Mr. Landesman wrote, ''but it can be reasonably argued that the forces of the marketplace through the years have been just as effective a censor as government edicts.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Haimes called Mr. Landesman's assertions ''absolutely ridiculous,'' as did several other nonprofit executives. While some nonprofit theaters with large groups of loyal subscribers have to worry about pleasing big audiences, Mr. Haimes said, most of them continue to concern themselves primarily with producing a body of work they can be proud of, not looking for the next commercial score.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately they just don't want any more competition,'' Mr. Haimes said of producers like Mr. Landesman. ''They should spend more energy focusing on doing plays.''</p>
        <p>As for agreeing to name the renovated Selwyn Theater on West 42nd Street in Manhattan for an airline sponsor, Mr. Haimes, whose company is known for producing revivals and musicals that appeal to a broad subscriber base, said: ''I have absolutely no reservations about it. If they want to put their name on our theater and give us money and give us artistic control, I think it's a wonderful thing.''</p>
        <p>Roche Schulfer, the executive director of the Goodman Theater in Chicago, which originated the current New York production of ''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' and helped move it to Broadway, said he bristled when Broadway producers like Mr. Landesman accused nonprofits of selling out.</p>
        <p>''Yes, we did 'A Moon for the Misbegotten,' '' Mr. Schulfer said, speaking of the revered O'Neill play that has become one of the season's hits. ''But there are 10 other things we did this year. I don't know how familiar he is with any of them.''</p>
        <p>''We work together with commercial producers when something is in line with our artistic priorities,'' he added. ''We do business when our goals intersect.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Schoenfeld of the Shubert Organization said the lines between the two camps had been blurred, often beyond recognition. ''The larger nonprofit institutions are really replications of Broadway,'' he said. ''Some are just booking houses for Broadway shows.''</p>
        <p>Aside from debating the role of the nonprofits, theater professionals say they hope the conference will address several other issues. With commercial producing now so costly, for example -- Broadway plays can run $1 million to $2 million, musicals as much as $12 million -- the traditional out-of-town tryout has become too expensive in most cases. Workshops, on the other hand -- rough versions of shows performed before invited guests -- are not considered a realistic gauge of a show's prospects because they lack critics and a paying audience.</p>
        <p>As a result producers have started to use regional theaters as places to mount what are essentially workshop versions of their productions.  These days ''almost no commercial plays start on Broadway or even off Broadway,'' said Thomas Viertel, a Broadway producer. ''They were developed someplace else. Economically it's safer to do it that way. Till you get something up in front of an audience, there's no way to know what works and what doesn't.''</p>
        <p>Too much of this, some warn, is not a good thing. ''You don't want to be perceived as a laboratory for every commercial producer that comes along,'' said John Breglio, an entertainment lawyer and president of the Theater Development Fund, which runs the TKTS discount-ticket booths and several theater support programs.</p>
        <p>Increasingly nonprofits do not want simply to hand over their productions to commercial producers. As their shows move to the commercial realm, some nonprofits will settle for a financial percentage; others want to move with the show as co-producers. The role of the nonprofit was dramatically redefined by Joseph Papp, who moved the Public Theater's ''Chorus Line'' to Broadway on his own in 1975, holding onto 100 percent of the production.</p>
        <p>Now the relationships between commercial and nonprofit producers take many different forms. This season Claudia Shear's ''Dirty Blonde'' started at the nonprofit Vineyard Theater on Martha's Vineyard in Massachusetts in a production financed by the Shuberts. Then it was produced at the nonprofit New York Theater Workshop with backing from the Shuberts, who finally moved it to Broadway with several other commercial producers, all of whom shared the cost equally.</p>
        <p>The nonprofit Manhattan Theater Club plans to move ''The Tale of the Allergist's Wife,'' which received strong notices earlier this season, to Broadway in the fall with commercial producing partners.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Joseph Papp Public Theater's version of ''The Wild Party,'' commercial producers shared the cost of producing that new musical, although the Public retained creative control. This became a source of tension when the commercial producers wanted to close the struggling show, but the Public decided to keep it open until the Tony Awards. It was shut out of the awards and closed on Sunday at a loss of $5.5 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breglio, the lawyer, said it was important for commercial producers who back a nonprofit's production to respect the originating theater's decision-making. ''If a nonprofit is going to put its resources at risk, it has to maintain control,'' he said. ''It's, financially speaking, too dangerous to permit outside commercial forces to dictate how the money is to be spent.''</p>
        <p>Theater professionals say they hope the conference also deals with the question of how to develop talent and commission new work to maintain the flow of productions. With theater so economically forbidding, that challenge has become particularly daunting.</p>
        <p>''The question of how we nurture the talent that we ultimately all depend on is an area none of us is paying much systemic attention to,'' Mr. Viertel said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
