<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Silent Senior Partner in Bush's Campaign</title>
    <meta content="15DAD.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kennebunkport (Me)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rove, Karl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine/Kennebunkport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DC113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Silent Senior Partner in Bush's Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Pres George Bush has outwardly maintained a cautious distance from Gov George W Bush's presidential campaign, seldom making joint appearances with his son and rarely commenting on election, but behind the scenes he is anything but remote; former president is in regular contact with Gov Bush's senior campaign staff, including chief strategist Karl Rove; Mr Bush says, in written response to an interview request, that he and his son talk often and that he gives advice when asked for it; in recent interviews with nearly a dozen of the two men's associates, no one comes even close to suggesting that the elder Bush is trying to mold his son's candidacy; Gov Bush is currently on weeklong visit to family compound in Kennebunkport, Me, that includes celebration of Barbara Bush's 75th birthday; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By most outward signs, former President George Bush has maintained a cautious distance from Gov. George W. Bush's quest for the White House, seldom making joint appearances with his son and rarely commenting on the election.</p>
        <p>But behind the scenes, Mr. Bush is anything but remote. On several occasions between December and May, Karl Rove, the chief strategist for his son's campaign, traveled from Austin, Tex., to Houston, where the former president spends the winter, to give him private briefings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By most outward signs, former President George Bush has maintained a cautious distance from Gov. George W. Bush's quest for the White House, seldom making joint appearances with his son and rarely commenting on the election.</p>
        <p>But behind the scenes, Mr. Bush is anything but remote. On several occasions between December and May, Karl Rove, the chief strategist for his son's campaign, traveled from Austin, Tex., to Houston, where the former president spends the winter, to give him private briefings.</p>
        <p>His friends say that Mr. Bush regularly exchanges calls or e-mail messages with about a half-dozen senior officials in the Texas governor's campaign and that his chief of staff, Jean Becker, is on the phone with Mr. Rove almost every day.</p>
        <p>And neither father nor son is shy about reaching out to the other. One close family friend said they usually chatted within 15 to 30 minutes after the end of each of the debates in the Republican primaries.</p>
        <p>''George and I do talk often,'' former President Bush said this week in written responses to questions that were electronically mailed to Ms. Becker. (Mr. Bush had declined through Ms. Becker to be interviewed on the telephone or in person for this article.) ''When he asks for advice,'' the former president added, ''I give it. He knows I will never breach a confidence or tell anyone.''</p>
        <p>Their closeness was suggested by the fact that the Texas governor, who arrived at the family compound in Kennebunkport, Me., late Friday for a weekend celebration of Barbara Bush's 75th birthday, extended his stay until today, and punctuated meetings of his campaign's senior staff with plenty of time with Dad. They golfed together twice, Ms. Becker said, and fished every day.</p>
        <p>In recent interviews with nearly a dozen of the two men's political and personal associates, no one came even close to suggesting that the elder Mr. Bush was trying to mold his son's candidacy and act the part of a political Pygmalion.</p>
        <p>But they did make clear that he was a large and constant presence in the campaign, hungry for the latest morsels of information, riveted by each new poll, quick to pass along the names of people who tell him they want to help, and always available as a sounding board or emotional release valve for the candidate.</p>
        <p>At the same time, they said, the former president understood that too visible a role could feed into skepticism about whether his son was creating his own political good fortune or simply riding on his father's name. His son's aides are equally cognizant of that danger, and several said that there had been extensive discussions about how best to integrate the former president into the Republican National Convention.</p>
        <p>By many accounts, including his own, the former president was deeply pained by journalists' and political analysts' suggestions that when he shared a stage with the governor in New Hampshire just a few days before the state's primary and referred to him as ''this boy,'' the effect on his son's campaign was negative.</p>
        <p>The former president said that the fallout from the event ''damn sure did hurt.''</p>
        <p>''It added to convictions already held that I should not get out front, that I should continue to stay behind the scenes, off TV, out of the papers,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>An adviser to the Texas governor said the Bush campaign had combed through polling data after the New Hampshire rally, found no evidence that the event had damaged the governor and made a point of reassuring the former president.</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' the adviser said, ''it was very hard to convince him of that.''</p>
        <p>In some respects, Mr. Bush's situation is similar to that of President Clinton's, and his son's challenge is like Vice President Al Gore's. Both the former president and the current one have knowledge, contacts and public clout that can help the men following in their footsteps. But they must marshal those resources discreetly and recede far enough into the background to let their heirs prove their own mettle.</p>
        <p>In other ways, the circumstance encountered by the older and younger Bush is almost unique. Only once before in American history did a president's son, John Quincy Adams, also end up in the job, and that was nearly two centuries ago. So former President Bush has no real point of reference for balancing his dual roles as his party's most recent occupant of the White House and the proud, doting father of its presumptive presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>''He wants to be more like a regular dad,'' Ms. Becker said in a telephone interview this week. ''Unfortunately, that's not practical.''</p>
        <p>''If you ran for president,'' she noted, ''and your dad wanted to help in the campaign, that would be fine and everybody would think it was great.'' But she said that former President Bush knew that if he assisted his son in any way that became publicly apparent, ''Everybody tries to overanalyze it.''</p>
        <p>So he walks a fine line. One of his son's advisers expressed certainty that the former president and the Texas governor discussed foreign policy, ''because I've caught whispers of it,'' the adviser said. But neither father nor son has ever given out a hint of that, and the former president steered clear of policy meetings in Kennebunkport over the past few days, two advisers said.</p>
        <p>The former president gave speeches in support of his son's candidacy during the most intense phase of the Republican primaries, and since early last year, he has been the star attraction at 16 fund-raisers that brought in about $2.4 million, campaign officials said. (His wife, over 10 events, brought in another $1.5 million, officials said.)</p>
        <p>But he appeared onstage with his son only once, in New Hampshire, and their attendance at a church service in Kennebunkport on Sunday represented one of the rare times since then that the two had ventured into such a public place together.</p>
        <p>The former president did little, Republican officials in Washington said, to press some of his longtime political confidants onto his son, even when they loudly groused about being spurned by the Austin-based campaign. But he established an informal dialogue with members of his son's inner circle, partly as a way to keep pace with all the twists and turns of the campaign.</p>
        <p>And members of that inner circle said he called them repeatedly on Feb. 19, when South Carolina held its pivotal Republican primary, to check on the exit polls.</p>
        <p>People close to him say that he is a sponge for information about the campaign. His wife has described him as obsessed with the race and jokingly complained about having to tear him away from C-Span, and he receives faxes and e-mail messages from political contacts with thoughts on the race. In turn, he shares these bulletins with others, sometimes sending messages about the campaign to extended family members as often as once a week, said the oldest of his 14 grandchildren, George P. Bush.</p>
        <p>And Republican officials who talk with the former president say his analysis of his son's campaign is several paces ahead of any news coverage of it.</p>
        <p>''Bush is consumed with this,'' one of these officials said. Another described the former president as ''his own little hot line,'' referring to a daily political journal on the Internet that collects newsy tidbits from a dizzying array of sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's friends and associates reject any notion that the former president sees his son's campaign as a chance to avenge his loss to Bill Clinton in 1992. They say he relates to the campaign mostly in the manner of a watchful, nervous father rooting for his son to make it through a soccer match without injury and with several goals to his credit.</p>
        <p>When Thomas D. Rath, one of his son's advisers in New Hampshire, ran into the former president just before that state's primary on Feb. 1, Mr. Bush did not interrogate him on his son's chances of victory. Instead, he fretted over his son's health, mentioning that he had seen him on television the previous night and thought he looked worn down. ''Make sure he gets enough rest,'' Mr. Rath recalled the father as saying.</p>
        <p>Answering questions for this article, the former president said it had been more emotionally grueling to watch his son endure the ups, downs, slings and arrows of a presidential campaign than it had been to go through the process himself.</p>
        <p>''Nineteen ninety-two was not the most pleasant year for me with the national press, but it is far worse for Barbara and me when George is criticized than when I was,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I guess after four national campaigns I might know what to expect,'' he added, ''but I can tell you none of the flak I took affected me as much as when I see George unfairly criticized. If the shots are justified -- fine. But if they are cheap shots then, of course, this father does not like it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he mainly tried to give his son emotional support, but his influence and assistance irrefutably extend beyond that. His vast network of political acquaintances contributed to the ability of his son's advisers to collect more contributions than anyone had ever raised for a primary campaign.</p>
        <p>And the former president's contacts meant that his son was already familiar with many experts and prominent political figures who have recently advised him on policy or flanked him at public appearances.</p>
        <p>Richard B. Cheney, who is supervising the process by which the governor is winnowing a list of Republican vice-presidential prospects, was his father's defense secretary.</p>
        <p>Condoleezza Rice, the governor's chief foreign policy adviser, worked in the Bush administration and became personally friendly with the former president. So did Gen. Colin  L. Powell, who recently helped the governor pitch his proposal for a more expansive national missile defense system than President Clinton had proposed. And the list goes on.</p>
        <p>So does the dialogue between father and son, and the former president obviously relishes it.</p>
        <p>''Over all, life is very good and when it comes to politics, there can be no prouder father in the land,'' the father said, referring as well to his another of his four sons, Jeb, who is the Florida governor.</p>
        <p>''Two governors of big states, one of whom might just be president,'' he added. ''What a country!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
