<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Briefing</title>
    <meta content="15MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3D7103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BRONX: GIRL'S DEATH RULED HOMICIDE  The medical examiner's office ruled yesterday that the death of a 5-year-old girl who suffered from cerebral palsy and weighed only 17 pounds when she died was a homicide.  The girl, Ahsianea Carzan, who was found dead in her family's Bronx apartment on May 17, died of ''severe malnutrition, including dehydration and bronchopneumonia due to cerebral palsy and parental neglect,'' according to Ellen Borakove, the office's spokeswoman. No charges were filed yesterday against her mother, Ebony, 24. Ms. Carzan's three other children were placed in foster care.</p>
        <p>Somini Sengupta (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>BRONX: GIRL'S DEATH RULED HOMICIDE  The medical examiner's office ruled yesterday that the death of a 5-year-old girl who suffered from cerebral palsy and weighed only 17 pounds when she died was a homicide.  The girl, Ahsianea Carzan, who was found dead in her family's Bronx apartment on May 17, died of ''severe malnutrition, including dehydration and bronchopneumonia due to cerebral palsy and parental neglect,'' according to Ellen Borakove, the office's spokeswoman. No charges were filed yesterday against her mother, Ebony, 24. Ms. Carzan's three other children were placed in foster care.</p>
        <p>Somini Sengupta (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: A YEAR ON STRIKE  The 250 strikers at the Domino Sugar refinery in Brooklyn will mark the one-year anniversary of their walkout today with no resolution in sight. For the first eight months, not one union member crossed the picket line, but in recent months, about 50 workers, squeezed financially and seeing little progress in the strike, have returned to work. The strikers, members of Local 1814 of the International Longshoremen's Association, say they cannot accept Domino's demands to eliminate 100 jobs. Some strikers say their parent union has not done enough to support their cause. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. is stepping up its call for consumers to boycott Domino sugar.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: WOMAN SAVED FROM SUBWAY TRACKS  A woman who jumped onto the tracks of the G line in Queens yesterday was pulled to safety from under a train and suffered only minor injuries, police and transit officials said. The incident occurred at 9:29 a.m. on the southbound side of the G, at the 65th Street station. Service on the E, F, G and R trains, between Roosevelt Avenue and Queens Plaza, was suspended for half an hour. The woman, who was not identified, was treated at Elmhurst Hospital.</p>
        <p>Sarah Kershaw (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: WIDOW SENTENCED  A woman who admitted slowly administering prescription sedatives to her husband so she could steal from him, and ultimately killed him, pleaded guilty yesterday to second-degree manslaughter and will face 5 to 15 years in prison when she is sentenced. The woman, Sylvia Mitchell, married Andrew Vlasto in 1993 when she was 28 and he was 85 and already so weak that she carried him down the aisle, according to prosecutors. She gave him Tylenol with codeine and Valium, leading to his death three months after they were married, and she withdrew almost $80,000 from his bank account and had much of it wired  to a casino in Atlantic City. Yesterday, before Justice  Bonnie Wittner of State Supreme Court in Manhattan, she pleaded guilty to recklessly and repeatedly administering sedatives that caused his death. Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
        <p>AUBURN: FIGHTS LEAD TO PRISON LOCKDOWN  Two fights in three days have led to a lockdown at the maximum-security Auburn Correctional Facility, where guards  fired warning shots to quell the disturbances. The lockdown is to last at least until Saturday while guards search the entire prison for weapons and drugs, said James Flateau, a spokesman for the State Department of Correctional Services. One inmate suffered a dislocated shoulder in a fight on Saturday. One prison guard was cut but remained on duty.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>GOSHEN: WEST POINT PLEA  Two sergeants stationed at West Point pleaded guilty in Orange County Court to the armed robbery of a New Windsor jewelry store last December. Sgt. Wayne Brower and Sgt. Irwin Taylor entered their plea on Tuesday before Judge Jeffrey G. Berry after a plea agreement of 5 to 15 years in prison. A West Point spokesman said the two remained in the Army pending a possible administrative separation procedure.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: SUNY APPOINTMENT  A top executive with the Stickley furniture company, Aminy Audi, was nominated yesterday by Gov. George E. Pataki to join the State University of New York's 16-member board. If she is approved by the State Senate, Ms. Audi, 62, will serve until 2002. She would replace Nicole Kim, a judge for the United States Immigration Court, who resigned.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: UNION DEMONSTRATION  First the Cow Parade came to New York. Now it's the Rat Parade's turn. A procession of 15 giant inflatable rats that various labor unions around the city have used to protest the  use of nonunion labor will be part of a demonstration scheduled for 3 p.m. today at Union Square. It is being organized by the New York City Central Labor Council and is part of a series of demonstrations across the nation this week.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>NEWARK: SCHOOL SUIT  The parents of a Paterson teenager have sued the local school district, asserting that their learning-disabled son was excluded from a special education program. According to a complaint filed last month in United States District Court here, the student, now 19, first received a diagnosis of ''receptive and expressive language delays'' when he was 3. Independent speech pathologists and the district's own psychologists recommended special education, but the Paterson Board of Education ignored those reports until he turned 17, according to Mary Hartnett, a lawyer representing the family, which was not named. A lawyer for the school board said he would not comment on the case until the district had filed a formal response.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>NEW BRITAIN: AREA CODE PLAN  State utility regulators approved a telephone number conservation program yesterday intended to delay the need for a third area code in Connecticut. The Department of Public Utility Control voted to assign telephone numbers in blocks of 1,000 instead of 10,000 in the 860 area code starting on Oct. 1. Telephone companies using standard wired service, not cellular or pager service, will return blocks of unused numbers for reassignment to other companies. The rule comes after Federal Communications Commission approved measures to save telephone numbers and reduce the need for new area codes.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
