<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Financial Fugitive Fights Extradition to the United States</title>
    <meta content="Y15FRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frankel, Martin R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D6103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Financial Fugitive Fights Extradition to the United States</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>HAMBURG, Germany, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin R Frankel, businessman accused of looting more than $200 million from insurance companies he acquired, seeks to avoid extradition back to the United States from Germany, court hearing, Hamburg; judge postpones proceedings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin R. Frankel, the Connecticut businessman accused of looting more than $200 million from insurance companies he acquired, sought here today to avoid extradition back to the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel, wearing a heavy wool overcoat over khaki pants and a wrinkled plaid shirt, arrived in handcuffs at a Hamburg courtroom where he faces German charges of using false passports and evading customs duties on about $5 million worth of diamonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Martin R. Frankel, the Connecticut businessman accused of looting more than $200 million from insurance companies he acquired, sought here today to avoid extradition back to the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel, wearing a heavy wool overcoat over khaki pants and a wrinkled plaid shirt, arrived in handcuffs at a Hamburg courtroom where he faces German charges of using false passports and evading customs duties on about $5 million worth of diamonds.</p>
        <p>He fled from the United States last spring, shortly before his mansion in Greenwich caught fire and the police found smoldering documents. The F.B.I. chased him for the next several months across Europe, narrowly missing him in Rome and then tracing him to a hotel here.</p>
        <p>Acting on a request from the F.B.I., the German police arrested Mr. Frankel last August and have kept him in prison pending trial and then extradition.</p>
        <p>German officials have already approved his extradition to the United States, where he faces more than 30 charges of fraud and the possibility of spending the rest of his life behind bars. But they wanted to prosecute Mr. Frankel on local violations first.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Frankel made it clear he wanted to stay in Germany as long as possible. ''In Germany, it is against the Constitution to put people in jail for the rest of their lives,'' he said shortly before the proceedings began.</p>
        <p>But he refused to plead guilty or to issue any kind of statement in his defense. Then he announced that he needed to call four witnesses -- two female associates who had accompanied him to Europe, as well as a friend in New York and another who had helped him in Rome.</p>
        <p>After mulling over his request, the judge here postponed the proceedings until Friday morning. He angrily told Mr. Frankel's lawyer, Dirk Meinicke, that he was ''astounded'' by the defense team's lack of preparation.</p>
        <p>By comparison with the charges he faces in the United States, the charges against Mr. Frankel in Germany are almost technicalities.  When the police arrested him last year, they found him with at least eight forged passports bearing names like Roger Jon Ellis, Michael John Patterson and Christopher Winslow.</p>
        <p>They also found diamonds that Mr. Frankel had reportedly brought to finance his stay in Europe.</p>
        <p>According to the charges presented today, the diamonds were worth nearly $5 million and were liable to a customs duty of roughly $1 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel befuddled the judge by refusing to make any response to the charges. He briefly balked when asked to confirm his full name and place of birth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meinicke asserted that Mr. Frankel could not speak in his defense because he feared providing information that could help prosecutors in the United States.</p>
        <p>''You have to understand that my client is in an extremely difficult situation,'' Mr. Meinicke said. ''He is facing a sentence of 200 to 400 years in prison, and my client has to consider the effect of statements here on the broader case.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel, asked by one of the judges what he wanted to demonstrate with his witnesses, said he expected them to lie. ''They would have exactly known all the facts,'' he said. ''I am assuming that they would lie, but at least I could confront them.''</p>
        <p>In an interview after Mr. Frankel was led back to jail, Mr. Meinicke said he was almost as nonplussed as the two judges on the court.</p>
        <p>''The problem is with the client,'' he maintained, ''because he keeps changing his mind about what he wants.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
