<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Who Will Fill Gap At Open?</title>
    <meta content="15ANDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD9103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Who Will Fill Gap At Open?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>PEBBLE BEACH, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses outlook for US Open golf tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BYRON NELSON and Sam Snead are golf's sunshine boys. At 88, each is truly a living legend. Together, they now hit the ceremonial tee shots that open the Masters. Together, they are considered two of the best golfers in history. In Golf Digest's career ranking, Snead is No. 3, Nelson No. 5.</p>
        <p>But when more than two dozen living United States Open champions gathered at this 100th Open, which begins today at Pebble Beach, Nelson and Snead were not together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BYRON NELSON and Sam Snead are golf's sunshine boys. At 88, each is truly a living legend. Together, they now hit the ceremonial tee shots that open the Masters. Together, they are considered two of the best golfers in history. In Golf Digest's career ranking, Snead is No. 3, Nelson No. 5.</p>
        <p>But when more than two dozen living United States Open champions gathered at this 100th Open, which begins today at Pebble Beach, Nelson and Snead were not together.</p>
        <p>Nelson was here, Snead was not. Nelson was the Open champion in 1939, the year that Snead should have won but didn't because of a triple-bogey 8 on the 72nd hole at the Philadelphia Country Club.</p>
        <p>''It was great for me,'' Nelson was saying now, ''because it was the only Open I won.''</p>
        <p>It was haunting for the smooth-swinging Snead, who would never win a United States Open.</p>
        <p>''And if you don't win the Open,'' Gene Sarazen once said, ''there's a gap in your record.''</p>
        <p>That's the only gap in Snead's remarkable career: three Masters, three Professional Golfers Association titles, one British Open and a record 81 PGA Tour victories. But not winning the Open, the world's most prestigious and most difficult golf tournament, is the gap that has haunted Snead, just as it is now the gap that now threatens to haunt many of today's best golfers.</p>
        <p>Of the top 108 golfers in the current world golf ranking, only two have won the Open -- No. 9 Ernie Els and No. 40 Lee Janzen, each twice.</p>
        <p>Of the other Open winners in the past decade, Hale Irwin and Tom Kite are now on the Senior PGA Tour, Steve Jones has slipped to No. 109 in the ranking, Corey Pavin has dropped to No. 154. Payne Stewart, who won in 1991 and last year, died Oct. 25 on a ghostly Learjet that crashed into a South Dakota field.</p>
        <p>Except for Els and Janzen, none of the marquee names in this 100th Open have won the Open.</p>
        <p>Some have won other major titles, notably Tiger Woods, Davis Love III, Hal Sutton, Vijay Singh, Nick Price, Tom Lehman and Justin Leonard. But others have yet to win a major: David Duval, Colin Montgomerie, Phil Mickelson, Jesper Parnevik, Lee Westwood, Sergio Garcia, Darren Clarke and Jim Furyk.</p>
        <p>At 24, Woods still has plenty of time to win the Open, if not four Opens, which would tie the record set by Willie Anderson a century ago and later equaled by Bobby Jones, Ben Hogan and Jack Nicklaus.</p>
        <p>That Jones, Hogan and Nicklaus, each the best of his era, won four Opens is proof that the Open, with its narrow fairways and thick rough, is the most difficult golf tournament to win.</p>
        <p>But unless Els or Janzen wins again, only one of those marquee contenders in the world ranking will erase that gap in his record. For all those who haven't won an Open, that gap will continue to exist next year at Southern Hills in Tulsa, Okla., and possibly throughout their careers.</p>
        <p>And the longer that gap exists, the heavier the burden, as Snead discovered.</p>
        <p>''If I'd won that 1939 Open,'' Snead has often said, ''I'd have won a bunch more.''</p>
        <p>In addition to his 1939 blowup, Snead finished second four times -- in 1937 to Ralph Guldahl by two strokes at Oakland Hills, in 1947 to Lew Worsham at St. Louis Country Club in an 18-hole playoff when he missed a 30-inch putt on the final green, in 1949 to Cary Middlecoff by one stroke at Medinah, and in 1953 to Ben Hogan by six strokes at Oakmont.</p>
        <p>''I was always afraid of three-putting those fast Open greens, so I didn't use my normal stroke,'' Snead has said. ''A day doesn't go by that I don't think about not winning the Open.''</p>
        <p>Especially that 1939 Open. In retrospect, Snead had needed only a par 5 on the 558-yard final hole to win, but in that era before leader boards, he thought he needed a birdie. After he hooked his drive into trampled rough, he drilled a 2-wood low into a bunker. He left an 8-iron in the sand, then exploded into a greenside bunker. On in five, he three-putted for an 8 and 286.</p>
        <p>Nelson, who was already in with 284, won the next day in a playoff with Craig Wood and Denny Shute.</p>
        <p>''Whenever Sam and I discussed that Open,'' Nelson said, ''we talk about how in most Opens, somebody doesn't win it so much as somebody else gives it away.''</p>
        <p>As Sam Snead did. As somebody in this Open may instead of filling the gap in his record.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
