<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nervous Tics and Wonderment From a Protege</title>
    <meta content="15PARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parsons Dance Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4D8133EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nervous Tics and Wonderment From a Protege</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews Parsons Dance Company's production of Dementia at Joyce Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Battle made bodies move in a striking fashion in ''Dementia,'' which the Parsons Dance Company presented in its world premiere on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater. Yet one wondered what was on his mind when he choreographed the piece.</p>
        <p>Mr. Battle is a member of the troupe, and David Parsons, its artistic director, deserves praise for encouraging his dancers to choreograph. That Mr. Battle can put unusual steps together was certainly evident in this work for Jaime Martinez, Mia McSwain, Jason McDole, Ruth-Ellen Kroll, Henry Jackson, Sumayah McRae, Katarzyna Skarpetowska and George Smallwood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert Battle made bodies move in a striking fashion in ''Dementia,'' which the Parsons Dance Company presented in its world premiere on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater. Yet one wondered what was on his mind when he choreographed the piece.</p>
        <p>Mr. Battle is a member of the troupe, and David Parsons, its artistic director, deserves praise for encouraging his dancers to choreograph. That Mr. Battle can put unusual steps together was certainly evident in this work for Jaime Martinez, Mia McSwain, Jason McDole, Ruth-Ellen Kroll, Henry Jackson, Sumayah McRae, Katarzyna Skarpetowska and George Smallwood.</p>
        <p>They were first seen standing in a square of light designed by Howell Binkley, looking as if they were imprisoned within its boundaries. They soon moved out of its confines to a darkly dramatic score by John Mackey, the company's music director, which was played by the Elm City Ensemble. However, no matter how much space they had at their disposal, Mr. Battle's choreography made these people appear uncomfortable in it.</p>
        <p>There were many sequences of fidgets, twitches and staggers. When Mr. Mackey filled his score with what sounded like Latin-American rhythms, Mr. Battle had dancers pair off in a trembling tango. Later everyone thrashed on the floor.</p>
        <p>The simple costumes resembled institutional uniforms and the men wore white headpieces. All this raised the nagging question: What was on Mr. Battle's mind when he created ''Dementia?''</p>
        <p>As the work now stands, it is little more than a collection of nervous tics. Its characters are obviously distressed. But Mr. Battle reveals little about who they are or why he feels their agitation is worth watching.</p>
        <p>''Strange Humors,'' another dance by Mr. Battle, was much more satisfying. Although, as the title promised, much that happened in it was strange, the work as a whole was thematically coherent, even though it dealt with mysterious passions. In this male duet to a sultry score by Mr. Mackey, Mr. McDole and Mr. Jackson twisted and quivered, as they drew ever nearer. They acted as if they were possessed by the force of feelings beyond their control. But their sense of wonderment conveyed a sense that these feelings were good ones.</p>
        <p>The program's other works were by Mr. Parsons. And the fact that the music for all but those with electronic accompaniments was played by the Elm City Ensemble added to the evening's pleasure.</p>
        <p>''Bachiana'' was a romp to Bach in which dancers assembled in lines and circles, sped across the floor, stood on their heads and clung to one another. The choreography's briskness made it fun to watch. It was equally hard to take one's eyes off the performers in ''Scrutiny,'' as they moved with sudden changes of speed and intensity to music by Michael Raye. The program also included repeat performances of ''Caught'' and ''The Envelope.''</p>
        <p>The company continues through Sunday night at the Joyce Theater.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
