<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DF113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Korean Leaders Sign Reconciliation Accord  The presidents of North and South Korea, meeting in Pyongyang, reached an agreement to work for peace and unity on their divided peninsula, the biggest step by either side to ease tensions in 50 years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials said that within a week they would announce the lifting of a broad set of economic sanctions that have been in place against North Korea since it invaded the South 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Korean Leaders Sign Reconciliation Accord  The presidents of North and South Korea, meeting in Pyongyang, reached an agreement to work for peace and unity on their divided peninsula, the biggest step by either side to ease tensions in 50 years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials said that within a week they would announce the lifting of a broad set of economic sanctions that have been in place against North Korea since it invaded the South 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Legal Advice on Missile Shield  Administration lawyers have advised President Clinton that he could begin building the first piece of a national missile defense system without violating a landmark arms control treaty with Russia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Russian's Remains Identified  The Kremlin said genetic tests had proved that remains found in Chechnya were those of Maj. Gen. Gennadi Shpigun, whose kidnapping in March 1999 helped touch off Russia's latest war against Chechnya.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Executive's Arrest Protested  Russia's most powerful businessmen condemned the arrest of Vladimir A. Gusinsky, the owner of Russia's leading independent media conglomerate, and warned that it threatened the nation's hard-won freedoms.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Putin Arrives in Berlin  President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia arrived in Berlin for a three-day visit that will include four meetings with Chancellor Gerhard Schroder. The visit is seen as part of a strategy to tie Russia firmly to Western Europe, attract investment and, if possible, drive a wedge between Europe and the United States.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Germany to End Nuclear Power  Chancellor Gerhard Schroder said the government and energy companies had agreed on a plan to gradually shut down Germany's 19 nuclear power plants.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Pope's Attacker Back in Turkey  Mehmet Ali Agca, who was pardoned in Italy for shooting Pope John Paul II in 1981, arrived in Istanbul and was taken to a high-security prison to serve out a sentence for a 1979 murder conviction .</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-25</p>
        <p>Ex-Army Official Accused Of Spying for the K.G.B.  Federal authorities arrested a former high-ranking civilian employee of the Army on espionage charges and accused him of providing classified documents to the Soviet Union over a period of at least 25 years. Prosecutors said the 73-year-old suspect, George Trofimoff, a naturalized American whose parents were Russian emigres, was arrested in Florida and charged with passing the documents to a childhood friend, a Russian Orthodox priest who had recruited him for the K.G.B.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>New Chief of Nuclear Security  The Senate unanimously confirmed the nomination of Gen. John Gordon as director of the National Nuclear Security Administration, a new agency created to oversee the nation's nuclear laboratories, including the one at Los Alamos, N.M., which has been grappling with security breaches. General Gordon has most recently been deputy C.I.A. director.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>House Passes Spending Bill  The House ignored a veto threat by President Clinton and voted, 217 to 214 along party lines, to approve the biggest and most hotly contested spending bill of the year, a $339.4 billion measure for education, health and labor programs.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Medical Marijuana Bill Signed  Gov. Ben Cayetano signed into law a bill legalizing the medical use of marijuana in Hawaii. Seven other states and the District of Columbia have similar laws, but those laws resulted from voter initiatives. Marijuana possession, cultivation and use remain offenses under federal law, but enforcement is generally carried out at the state and municipal levels.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Opposing Women as Pastors  The Southern Baptist Convention declared that women should no longer serve as pastors. The declaration of faith is not binding on congregations, and so the effect on the denomination's 1,600 or so clergywomen, about 100 of whom are pastors leading congregations, is unclear.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Proposal on E.P.A. Research  A panel of experts recommended that the E.P.A. strengthen the research it conducts to support its regulations and that it create a position to oversee science agencywide.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-24</p>
        <p>Cigarette-Fire Bill Passes After Pataki Agrees to Sign  The Legislature approved a bill making New York the first state to impose fire-safety standards on cigarettes. Governor Pataki, who had vetoed a similar bill three weeks ago, agreed to the measure after lawmakers pledged to strengthen penalties for cigarette bootlegging and restrict cigarette sales on the Internet.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Drive to Enroll Uninsured  Mayor Giuliani announced a health initiative aimed at enrolling nearly one million uninsured New York City children and adults in Medicaid and other government health care programs. Mr. Giuliani said his ambitions for the plan came about partly because of his change in attitude toward illness after he learned he had prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hillary Clinton Assails Lazio  Hillary Rodham Clinton, reflecting an aggressive new approach to her Senate campaign, accused Representative Rick A. Lazio of voting in Congress ''against the interests of women, children and families.'' Mr. Lazio said she was ''mudslinging'' and distorting his record.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Photos of Park Suspects  The police released photos of seven men taken from amateur videotapes of a melee in which at least two dozen women were sexually abused in Central Park after the Puerto Rican Day Parade on Sunday. The Police Department said it would review its handling of the parade.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-16</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16  A Magazine for Fathers  A new lifestyle magazine, Dads, is the first to be aimed exclusively at men in their roles as parents.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Lakers Beat Indiana  Los Angeles beat the Pacers in overtime, 120-118, in the fourth game of the N.B.A. Championship series. The Lakers lead the series 3-1.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28  Federal Charges in Stock Case  Federal prosecutors in Manhattan charged dozens of people -- including members of organized crime, stock brokers and promoters and a former police union official -- with using stock manipulation, fraud and violence to rob thousands of investors across the country. DMN Capital Investments, a Manhattan firm, figures prominently in the case.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>3 Plead Guilty in CUC Fraud  Three former executives of CUC International pleaded guilty to federal charges in what prosecutors said was a $19 billion accounting fraud. CUC, formerly Comp-U-Card International, went public in 1983 and grew through mergers into the giant Cendant Corporation.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Deal in Coke Bias Case  Coca-Cola said it had reached a tentative settlement with several black employees who had sued the company asserting discrimination.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Legal Weight for Digital ID  The House passed a bill to give new technologies like fingerprint scans and encryption keys the legal weight of ink-and-paper signatures.</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Korean reconciliation; lost at Los Alamos; the next big antitrust case; a chilling prosecution in Moscow.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E10  Weather</p>
        <p>D7  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
