<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summerstage Is Back for a 15th Year, Eclectic as Ever</title>
    <meta content="15SUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0D6133EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summerstage Is Back for a 15th Year, Eclectic as Ever</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Central Park Summerstage festival begins its 15th summer of free concerts with sampler of eclectic programming for which it is famous (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the executive producer of Central Park Summerstage, Erica Ruben thought she had prepared herself for just about anything, at any time. Still, she was stunned the evening that a group of rowdy Verdi listeners started flinging food from their perches on the Rumsey Playfield and briefly shut down a performance of the New York Grand Opera.</p>
        <p>''Ninety-nine percent of our crowd monitors themselves,'' she said. ''We're not immune to incidents of unruliness, but this was by far the biggest, and maybe the oddest.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the executive producer of Central Park Summerstage, Erica Ruben thought she had prepared herself for just about anything, at any time. Still, she was stunned the evening that a group of rowdy Verdi listeners started flinging food from their perches on the Rumsey Playfield and briefly shut down a performance of the New York Grand Opera.</p>
        <p>''Ninety-nine percent of our crowd monitors themselves,'' she said. ''We're not immune to incidents of unruliness, but this was by far the biggest, and maybe the oddest.''</p>
        <p>Not bad statistics for a festival that tonight will kick off its 15th summer of free concerts with a sampler of the eclectic programming for which it is famous. The performance starts at 6 with the French disc jockey Alex Gopher and continues with Nile Rodgers and his R&amp;B funk band, Chic; the dancer Bill Shannon; the poet Miguel Algarin; and Zuco 103, an ''electro-tropicalism'' ensemble from Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>''The concert will be very celebratory, very multicultural,'' Ms. Ruben said. ''We're famous for creating a dance-party environment out in the park.''</p>
        <p>Central Park Summerstage came to life in 1986, the brainchild of Parks Commissioner Henry J. Stern and Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, the park's administrator. It was an effort to revitalize the mall around the Naumberg Band Shell, which was rife with ''drugs and a bad element,'' Mr. Stern said.</p>
        <p>The program, playing to the diversity of the park's users and operating on a $400,000 budget, quickly became a success. That was largely because of its skillful mix of top-drawer American and world music, modern dance and spoken word, programmed in 40 concerts in the inaugural season by Joe Killian, the festival's first producer. In 1990 the New York Grand Opera Company, directed by Vincent La Selva, which already presented park concerts, was added to the mix.</p>
        <p>''By default, it became an international music festival,'' said Ms. Ruben, who took over as executive producer in 1993.</p>
        <p>In 1990, bolstered by corporate sponsorship, Summerstage moved to Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 72nd Street, which was better suited to  expanding audience and increasingly public profile of the series.</p>
        <p>Originally overseen by the Central Park Conservancy, the festival in 1994 became a program of the City Parks Foundation, a nonprofit group that works to provide free programming in parks throughout New York.</p>
        <p>It hasn't all been smooth sailing. In the early 1990's, Summerstage drew complaints from residential neighbors about the noise level.</p>
        <p>''It became a very serious problem,'' Ms. Ruben said. ''We met with Community Board 8 to explore the problem and got very interactive.''</p>
        <p>To that end, the festival measured the level of noise reaching nearby homes, employed a consultant and reconfigured its stage and sound system. It also limited decibel levels and established stricter curfews.</p>
        <p>Summerstage now runs a sound meter at each performance, and Ms. Ruben operates a complaint hot line. ''When someone calls, I call them back and lower the sound system if necessary,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Under Ms. Ruben's leadership, Summerstage has recently developed several new programs, including workshops, electronic music and disc jockeys, and a cabaret series at which listeners may eat at tables in front of the stage. (So far, the food has stayed grounded.)</p>
        <p>''Summerstage has a terrific location and very current programming,'' Mr. Stern said of the festival's success. ''It has remained free of the political provocations that have hamstrung other government art institutions.''</p>
        <p>''Not that it's a Disney kind of entertainment either,'' he added. ''It's cutting edge. But it never goes over the edge.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
