<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bryant Feasts, Especially In Clutch</title>
    <meta content="15HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Kobe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDC113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bryant Feasts, Especially In Clutch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of Los Angeles Lakers player Kobe Bryant in victory over Indiana Pacers in Game 4 of NBA championship series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He started tentatively, moving gingerly, though without a limp. Kobe Bryant was back in the lineup for the Los Angeles Lakers tonight, but he was not quite himself. He did not have his typical lift on jump shots and was unable to shoot comfortably over Indiana's Mark Jackson. His forays to the basket were few as he settled on the perimeter.</p>
        <p>While a partial Bryant was better than no Bryant at all, it was not enough for the Lakers to stay with the Pacers in the early going of Game 4 tonight. So, with their star shooting guard struggling, contributing just 6 points and no rebounds in the first half, the Lakers trailed throughout the first 24 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He started tentatively, moving gingerly, though without a limp. Kobe Bryant was back in the lineup for the Los Angeles Lakers tonight, but he was not quite himself. He did not have his typical lift on jump shots and was unable to shoot comfortably over Indiana's Mark Jackson. His forays to the basket were few as he settled on the perimeter.</p>
        <p>While a partial Bryant was better than no Bryant at all, it was not enough for the Lakers to stay with the Pacers in the early going of Game 4 tonight. So, with their star shooting guard struggling, contributing just 6 points and no rebounds in the first half, the Lakers trailed throughout the first 24 minutes.</p>
        <p>But Bryant apparently had a heart-to-heart with himself during the halftime break. He evidently decided to give his signature acrobatic play a try, gimpy left ankle and all. In the second half, he cut, he drove, he took off and he scored. And in overtime, he never let up as he sparked the Lakers to a 120-118 victory and put them within one victory of a National Basketball Association title.</p>
        <p>When the overtime buzzer sounded, Bryant had erased the memory of his apprehensive start by registering 28 points, 5 assists and 4 rebounds on 14-of-27 shooting. He had 8 points in the extra session, 6 of them after Shaquille O'Neal fouled out with two and a half minutes remaining.</p>
        <p>With O'Neal on the bench, Bryant feasted as the Lakers' top option. Having already given them a 4-point lead with a short jumper early in the extra session, he buried a 22-footer over Reggie Miller with 1 minute 58 seconds left to put Los Angeles ahead by 114-111.</p>
        <p>The Pacers answered, but Bryant was not through. Rolling offensively and relishing the pressure placed upon his 21-year-old shoulders, Bryant nailed another long jumper over Jackson. Still not done, he scored the game's final basket on an over-the-head follow-up layin off a Brian Shaw miss with 5.9 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>Bryant entered the game thinking he was capable of making the huge plays despite his injury. ''I'll probably be limited when I come back, but so what?'' he said. ''I just got to find a way to get around it, and we're going to find a way to get around it.''</p>
        <p>Playing as if uninjured, Bryant let every member of the boisterous Conseco Fieldhouse crowd know that he was back by scoring the Lakers' first three baskets of the third quarter. One came on a pretty pull-up jumper on the fast break, another on a midrange shot in which he used his dribble to create space for himself, and the third on a fashionable one-handed leaner close to the basket.</p>
        <p>Moments later, after Ron Harper and Glen Rice canned shots to give the Lakers their first lead, it became official. With Bryant inching closer to true form, the real Lakers were back -- the Lakers not only of O'Neal, but of Bryant as well.</p>
        <p>For those who thought Bryant might have simply been on a quick burst, he drove around Miller for an emphatic slam dunk with 2:36 left in the third period to give the Lakers a 73-70 lead. It was the kind of move that players whose availability was a game-time decision aren't supposed to make.</p>
        <p>''Kobe smelled it at the end of the game,'' Lakers Coach Phil Jackson said. ''He knew it was his opportunity when Shaq was out and he lifted us. I broke down our offense and went to an open floor game because when Kobe's in the groove and he needs some room to operate.''</p>
        <p>The Pacers watched helplessly as Bryant scored 10 points and grabbed 3 rebounds in the third quarter. With him back on both ends, the Lakers outscored Indiana by 29-23 in the quarter and held the Pacers, who shot a blazing 52.6 percent in the first half, to 40 percent shooting (8 for 20).</p>
        <p>Indiana, which like everyone else expected Bryant to play, figured that he would come with force. If anything, the Pacers were probably surprised, albeit pleasantly, by his unanimated first-half performance.</p>
        <p>''We just couldn't stop him,'' Pacers Coach Larry Bird said. ''Kobe did a good job of going one on one and making plays for them.''</p>
        <p>Miller went at Bryant as if he were a Knick in the fourth quarter, hitting his first four baskets, including a 2-pointer that had the potential to break the Lakers' collective back.</p>
        <p>But after Miller hit a 3-pointer to put the Pacers ahead by 101-99, Bryant followed an O'Neal free throw with a pull-up jumper from above the foul line to give the Lakers a 102-101 lead with 1:39 remaining.</p>
        <p>To the dismay of the Pacers, he was only getting warm.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
