<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mendoza Helps Yanks Dodge a Sweep</title>
    <meta content="15YANK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DC113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mendoza Helps Yanks Dodge a Sweep</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Boston Red Sox, 2-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stacks of homemade placards and rolls of tape were carried into Yankee Stadium yesterday, for Pedro Martinez was supposed to pitch against Roger Clemens and there would be a lot of strikeouts to record on the facing of the upper deck. There would be a lot of fastballs, a lot of batters ducking.</p>
        <p>Nobody figured that Clemens would hobble off the field after one inning, or that Martinez, who dominates large bat-wielding sluggers, would be conquered by something as benign as a pitch count. Nobody figured that the game-winning hit would come off a knuckleball at about 75 miles an hour. But by the time Tino Martinez smashed Tim Wakefield's knuckler into the upper deck with two outs in the bottom of the eighth inning to beat the Boston Red Sox, 2-1, the Yankees' fans among the 54,834 happily settled for the victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stacks of homemade placards and rolls of tape were carried into Yankee Stadium yesterday, for Pedro Martinez was supposed to pitch against Roger Clemens and there would be a lot of strikeouts to record on the facing of the upper deck. There would be a lot of fastballs, a lot of batters ducking.</p>
        <p>Nobody figured that Clemens would hobble off the field after one inning, or that Martinez, who dominates large bat-wielding sluggers, would be conquered by something as benign as a pitch count. Nobody figured that the game-winning hit would come off a knuckleball at about 75 miles an hour. But by the time Tino Martinez smashed Tim Wakefield's knuckler into the upper deck with two outs in the bottom of the eighth inning to beat the Boston Red Sox, 2-1, the Yankees' fans among the 54,834 happily settled for the victory.</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza relieved Clemens -- who will be placed on the disabled list with a strained groin and will miss at least two weeks -- and pitched well for five and two-thirds innings, and the Yankees managed a split of the two games with the Red Sox. The Yankees are talking about dealing for a slugger, like Sammy Sosa, and may seek a pitcher to take Clemens's place. Their owner is annoyed, pushing for action.</p>
        <p>But there is the bottom line: the Yankees (34-25) are in first place in the American League East, one game ahead of the Red Sox (34-27), and will begin a four-game series against the Chicago White Sox, who own the A.L.'s best record.</p>
        <p>''It was a good game for us,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''You never want someone you're competing with to come into your house and take two games.''</p>
        <p>There was every reason to believe in the first inning that the Red Sox would sweep the two games. Clemens struggled to hold the Red Sox scoreless in the top half of the inning, and before the Yankees batted, the phone rang in the Yankees' bullpen. ''Mendoza, get ready,'' the coach Tony Cloninger yelled.</p>
        <p>Clemens was finished, and it was more than a year since the Yankees generated runs against Martinez. With Chuck Knoblauch at second base in the bottom of the first, Paul O'Neill beat out a broken-bat roller -- the Yankees' first hit with a runner in scoring position against the Red Sox ace since the fifth inning of a game played in Fenway Park on May 18 . . . of last year.</p>
        <p>Martinez bounced a breaking ball off the left foot of Bernie Williams to load the bases. Tino Martinez struck out before Jorge Posada drew a walk to force in the first run of the game. But Ricky Ledee popped out, and there was a sense that the Yankees might have blown their one real chance to get to Pedro Martinez. After all, they have 15 hits and 51 strikeouts in their last 112 at-bats against him (for a .134 average).</p>
        <p>But Mendoza was throwing strikes, mixing fastballs and change ups and sliders, and keeping hitters off balance, demonstrating again, in an important game, why Torre and others have lobbied to keep him every time Mendoza's name is mentioned in trade talks. ''He's my pet, I guess,'' Torre said. ''I would really have a tough time trading him.''</p>
        <p>It was a waiting game, a question of how long Mendoza could hold off the Red Sox, how quickly the Yankees could drive up his pitch count and force him from the game.</p>
        <p>The Yankees swung at the first pitch in only three of their first 24 at-bats, patiently driving up Martinez's pitch count. Mendoza shut out the Red Sox through the top of the sixth, and in the bottom half of the inning a reliever started throwing in the Boston bullpen. Martinez was done after six innings and 101 pitches.</p>
        <p>Mendoza had a chance for a victory and retired the first two batters in the seventh. But Nomar Garciaparra pulled a ball down the left-field line. Ledee ran toward the line, right arm outstretched, glove extending above the wall.</p>
        <p>The ball hit Ledee's glove; Ledee felt a fan hit the back of his glove, and when Ledee landed, he looked inside his glove. No ball. Ledee jumped in frustration, then looked around. No ball. It had gone over the wall. But what Ledee didn't know was that it had skipped off his glove, bounced along the top of the fence and into foul territory, in front of the pole. Garciaparra rounded the bases with the game-tying home run, and it was not until a couple of batters later that the Yankees' hitting coach, Chris Chambliss -- who had been in the clubhouse -- informed everybody that replays showed the path of the ball, and that it should have been a ground-rule double.</p>
        <p>Ledee saw a man with the ball in foul territory and kept glaring at the man who had hit his glove. ''I was so mad,'' Ledee said.</p>
        <p>The umpires refused to comment after the game. Torre said: ''I didn't know if it hit his hand or his glove. I would hope someone who was 200 feet closer'' -- an umpire, for instance -- ''would have seen it.''</p>
        <p>Wakefield relieved Martinez in the seventh, stranding a runner at third with his knuckleball and retiring the first two hitters in the eighth. Tino Martinez went to the plate with a general idea of how he wanted to attack Wakefield's knuckler. Darryl Strawberry, a great knuckleball hitter when he played, sometimes liked to hold his feet in place and use his hands only in his swing.</p>
        <p>But Martinez's approach was to look for any knuckleball thrown high. If you swing at a low knuckler, he said, you are going to hit it in the dirt. Wakefield flipped a high knuckler and Martinez pounced on it, with several Yankees thrusting their hands into the air when the ball landed a row or two into the upper deck.</p>
        <p>In the last week, the Yankees played the Mets twice and won once, played the Red Sox and split. They survived.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
