<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vivendi Chief Bets on His Ability to Create Media Empire</title>
    <meta content="Y15VIV0AE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messier, Jean-Marie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DE113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vivendi Chief Bets on His Ability to Create Media Empire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jean-Marie Messier, chairman of Vivendi SA, confirms that he is in talks to acquire Seagram Co; investors, however, are not enthusiastic, with shares of Vivendi down 10 percent, Paris, to $99 (US); Messier career sketch (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his boyish good looks and knack for relentless deal-making, Jean-Marie Messier has dazzled investors by transforming France's biggest water utility into a media conglomerate.</p>
        <p>As chairman of Vivendi S.A., Mr. Messier now controls Europe's biggest pay-television company, France's second-largest mobile telephone operator and a major publishing house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his boyish good looks and knack for relentless deal-making, Jean-Marie Messier has dazzled investors by transforming France's biggest water utility into a media conglomerate.</p>
        <p>As chairman of Vivendi S.A., Mr. Messier now controls Europe's biggest pay-television company, France's second-largest mobile telephone operator and a major publishing house.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Messier confirmed today that he was in talks to acquire the Seagram Company, including the Universal movie studio, investors were far from enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>Shares of Vivendi plunged 10 percent, to 103.5 euros, or $99, in Paris today while shares of Canal Plus S.A., the pay-television company that Vivendi controls, dropped nearly 3 percent by midafternoon. That reaction reflected fears that Mr. Messier is about to take on a huge new burden and get little in return except for the glamour of becoming a Hollywood player.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, the deal risks being very expensive for Vivendi, and that is the risk that the market is reacting to,'' said Andrew Shepherd-Barron, an analyst in London at the Dutch bank ABN Amro. ''To pay for it, they are going to have to do something very clever.''</p>
        <p>But there are other problems as well. For all of Mr. Messier's nimbleness and vision about new media,  Vivendi is one of Europe's most complicated and messy companies.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Vivendi is the kind of European company that infuriates American investors. Though Mr. Messier is a passionate advocate of shareholder value, Vivendi is a maze of old-  and new-economy businesses, many controlled through partial holdings and partnerships.</p>
        <p>More than half of Vivendi's roughly $40 billion in revenue still comes from water distribution, waste management and construction. Its expanding portfolio of high-technology and media companies remains a mish-mash that provided only about one-quarter of Vivendi's $2.28 billion in operating profit last year.</p>
        <p>As a wireless operator, Vivendi remains largely limited to France, while companies like Vodafone AirTouch are rolling out pan-European networks. Canal Plus, though profitable in France, is losing money over all in order to finance expansion in other European countries. To be sure, the 43-year-old Mr. Messier has achieved remarkable results. A former investment banker who became chairman in 1996, he has engineered huge acquisitions in both the old and new sides of the business. Last year, Vivendi acquired US Filter, one of the biggest water-treatment companies in the United States, for $6.2 billion. It also acquired the industrial waste business of Waste Management Inc.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messier has been on a relentless buying binge in media and telecommunications. Like other brash European business executives, Mr. Messier has financed part of his expansion with the cash thrown off by the old-line businesses. Vivendi was a founding investor in Cegetel, a consortium that included Vodafone and British Telecommunications, which in turn created France's second wireless telephone network as well as a small but growing fixed-line competitor to France Telecom.</p>
        <p>Much like Chris Gent of Vodafone or Roberto Colaninno of Olivetti, Mr. Messier has increasingly used Vivendi's own stock or bonds convertible into Vivendi stock as his acquisition currency. In 1997, he used Vivendi convertible bonds to acquire Havas, a large publishing and advertising company. Last year, he used Vivendi stock to acquire a 15 percent stake in Canal Plus from Richemont S.A., raising Vivendi's existing stake to 49 percent. Also last year, Vivendi acquired Pathe, which owned many media properties.</p>
        <p>In his quest to become a global media player, Mr. Messier seems bent on making Vivendi a distributor of media and entertainment rather than an operator of telecommunication networks. But Vivendi remains an off-again-on-again player in Europe's torrid market for wireless telephone services. By siding with Vodafone Airtouch in its hostile takeover of Mannesmann A.G., Mr. Messier cut a deal with Vodafone to acquire its stakes in Cegetel and SFR, the French wireless carrier. That gave Vivendi control of SFR. Mr. Messier and Vodafone now plan a multimedia portal that would provide customers access to wireless services, television entertainment and the Internet. In negotiations to acquire the Universal movie studio as well as Polygram record label through Seagram, Mr. Messier appears to be betting that his control over rights to music and movies will greatly strengthen his hand as a distributor in Europe.</p>
        <p>''It will give them access to English-language content that they would not otherwise have,'' said one French analyst. It might also have a curious effect on French cultural policies, which are still geared to preserving French culture by limiting the influx of Hollywood movies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messier is also busy shoring up his balance sheet. He raised nearly $8 billion last year in stock and convertible bond offerings. In July, Vivendi hopes to raise as much as $4 billion more through a public offering of Vivendi Environment, which contains the water treatment, waste management and construction businesses. Vivendi will still own about 60 percent of Vivendi Environment, but company executives say the partial spinoff will make the company much easier to understand. Vivendi Environment will assume about $14 billion of the company's overall debt.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
