<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Shows Inflation Level in May but Rising Long-Term</title>
    <meta content="15ECON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popkin, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDF113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Shows Inflation Level in May but Rising Long-Term</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Labor Department reports Consumer Price Index rose an unremarkable 0.1 percent in May, however, measured over 12 months, inflation rate through May was half percentage point higher than it was last fall; with May included, overall Consumer Price Index rose 3.1 percent over 12 months and 2.4 percent when energy and food are left out; in each case, rate was half percentage point higher than the annual rate late last year; Joel Popkin, head of economic consulting firm, says there is no longer any doubt that inflation has accelerated (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The national inflation rate, which has been inching up this year, leveled off in May, the Labor Department reported yesterday. But rising gasoline prices promised a fresh increase in inflation for June.</p>
        <p>The Consumer Price Index, the best-known measure of American inflation, rose an unremarkable 0.1 percent in May. What is striking about this latest report, however, is not what happened in May, but the long-term trend that is finally emerging. Measured over 12 months, the inflation rate through May was half a percentage point higher than it was last fall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The national inflation rate, which has been inching up this year, leveled off in May, the Labor Department reported yesterday. But rising gasoline prices promised a fresh increase in inflation for June.</p>
        <p>The Consumer Price Index, the best-known measure of American inflation, rose an unremarkable 0.1 percent in May. What is striking about this latest report, however, is not what happened in May, but the long-term trend that is finally emerging. Measured over 12 months, the inflation rate through May was half a percentage point higher than it was last fall.</p>
        <p>''There is no longer any doubt that inflation has accelerated,'' said Joel Popkin, president of Joel Popkin &amp; Company, an economic consulting firm. Like many other economists, he attributed the acceleration mainly to months of strong consumer demand that have permitted many companies to gradually raise prices.</p>
        <p>Only recently has consumer demand appeared to ease a bit, the principal evidence being a decline in retail sales in April and May. The Federal Reserve, in a separate report yesterday, took note of the incipient easing. Its periodic survey of economic conditions, called the beige book, found that ''solid economic performance continued in April and May,'' but with ''signs of some slowing from the rapid pace earlier in the year.'' The Fed also found ''indications of worsening price inflation'' in some parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Rising prices are often attributed to increasing labor costs. Labor shortages give workers the leverage to obtain higher wages, this argument goes, and then companies raise prices to cover the higher costs of labor. Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve, has raised this concern recently. But other economists argue that labor costs, while rising, have played no role so far in the gradually accelerating inflation rate. Most companies, they argue, would first cut back profits to pay for labor, and profits have not yet fallen.</p>
        <p>''Inflation today is not the conventional story,'' said Dean Baker, an economist at the Center for Economic and Policy Research. ''It is clearly not wage growth that is pushing up prices.''</p>
        <p>With May included, the overall Consumer Price Index rose 3.1 percent over 12 months, and 2.4 percent when energy and food were left out. In each case, the rate was half a percentage point higher than the annual rate late last year. Because energy and food prices fluctuate rapidly, many economists prefer the so-called core rate, which eliminates these items.</p>
        <p>Food prices jumped by 0.5 percent in May, the biggest increase since October 1998. But fluctuating gasoline prices -- they were found to have fallen in May -- more than offset the food price increase. As a result, the overall Consumer Price Index rose only 0.1 percent, while the core rate was up 0.2 percent.</p>
        <p>Timing played a big role in this idiosyncratic result. With OPEC's production cutbacks apparently ending, gasoline prices had fallen in April and then, on May 1, they began to rise again. But when the Bureau of Labor Statistics surveyed prices in early May, gasoline had not yet returned to its early April level.</p>
        <p>It has since gone much higher, reaching $1.66 a gallon on average this week, according to the Energy Department. Other things being equal, gasoline prices at $1.66 could add three-tenths of a percentage point to the overall Consumer Price Index in June, said Patrick Jackman, a senior economist at the bureau.</p>
        <p>Housing and medical care have made steady contributions to the gradually accelerating core inflation rate, and they did so again in May. Housing was up 0.2 percent, mostly because of higher rent and an equivalent increase in the monthly cost of owning a home. Many hotels raised their daily rates, and that helped to push up housing costs.</p>
        <p>Those costs have now risen 2.9 percent over the 12 months that ended in May, while medical costs have gone up 4 percent in the corresponding period, including a 0.3 percent increase in May. Ever more costly prescription drugs and rising hospital rates have played big roles in the rising medical costs.</p>
        <p>Airline fares were up 0.8 percent in June, starting in mid-month when Continental Airlines raised fares and the other airlines followed. The airlines cite higher fuel costs as a reason for the increases, but other than airline fares, very little of the increased cost of petroleum has been passed through to other products and services -- to trucking rates, for example, and to plastics made from petroleum-based petrochemicals.</p>
        <p>''It is tough to see the secondary effect yet,'' Mr. Jackman said.</p>
        <p>Among other items, apparel prices fell 0.2 percent in May. They often decline, driven down by huge quantities of imported clothing. Tobacco prices, which often fluctuate, fell in May. They rise and fall as tobacco companies discount cigarette prices one month and remove the discounts the next. Auto prices, which have remained fairly steady, rose in May, driven up mainly by higher prices for used vehicles.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Evidence of a Slowdown</p>
        <p>(By Reuters), WASHINGTON, June 14 -- The booming United States economy showed signs of cooling during April and May but there also were indications in several regions of increased price inflation, the Federal Reserve said today.</p>
        <p>The central bank's latest summary of coast-to-coast conditions, known as the beige book, reported ''solid economic growth'' but with glimmers of slowing in areas like borrowing and home building.</p>
        <p>''All but Minneapolis said scattered signs of cooling are in evidence or the pace of growth is slowing,'' the Fed said.</p>
        <p>''Indications of worsening price inflation, while not widespread, are reported by several districts,'' it added.</p>
        <p>The beige book's findings will be used by members of the Fed's policymaking Federal Open Market Committee when they meet June 27 and 28 to consider interest rate strategy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
