<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prosecutors Argue Greed Led Pirro to Tax Fraud</title>
    <meta content="15PIRR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Albert J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siebel, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pirro, Jeanine (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5DF113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prosecutors Argue Greed Led Pirro to Tax Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal prosecutor Cathy Siebel, closing government's tax-fraud case in frank and forceful language, accuses Albert J Pirro Jr of arrogantly cheating on his taxes so he could 'spend like a Rockefeller with a subsidy from the taxpayers;' charges Pirro and his brother Anthony with conspiring to improperly deduct $1.2 million in personal expenses as business expenditures in order to skirt more than $400,000 in taxes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Closing the government's tax-fraud case in frank and forceful language, a federal prosecutor accused Albert J. Pirro Jr. today of arrogantly cheating on his taxes so he could ''spend like a Rockefeller with a subsidy from the taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Pirro's wife, Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney, occupied her usual spot in a front-row gallery seat, the prosecutor, Cathy Seibel, repeatedly stabbed the air with an index finger in arguing that Mr. Pirro was a ''crook'' with tremendous ''chutzpah'' who improperly deducted $1.2 million in personal expenses as business expenditures in order to skirt more than $400,000 in taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Closing the government's tax-fraud case in frank and forceful language, a federal prosecutor accused Albert J. Pirro Jr. today of arrogantly cheating on his taxes so he could ''spend like a Rockefeller with a subsidy from the taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Pirro's wife, Jeanine F. Pirro, the Westchester County district attorney, occupied her usual spot in a front-row gallery seat, the prosecutor, Cathy Seibel, repeatedly stabbed the air with an index finger in arguing that Mr. Pirro was a ''crook'' with tremendous ''chutzpah'' who improperly deducted $1.2 million in personal expenses as business expenditures in order to skirt more than $400,000 in taxes.</p>
        <p>And the reason Mr. Pirro, along with his brother and co-defendant, Anthony G. Pirro, conspired to do so, she suggested, was pure greed.</p>
        <p>''Albert Pirro was living like Donald Trump, but he was earning like Albert Pirro,'' Ms. Seibel told the jury and an overflow crowd at the federal courthouse here. So he made up the difference, she said, by cheating on his taxes. ''He got twice the bang for the buck.''</p>
        <p>But in a vigorous rebuttal, Albert Pirro's lead lawyer, Gustave H. Newman, repeated some of the themes advanced by the defense, which called no witnesses during the four-week trial, in both its opening arguments and its cross-examinations.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Mr. Newman argued, it was the government, and not Albert Pirro, that was guilty of chutzpah and excess by relentlessly investigating every ''nook and cranny'' of Mr. Pirro's family's life and by harassing several potential witnesses. And besides, he asked, if Albert Pirro had anything to hide, why did he fail to shred his tax records and invoices?</p>
        <p>''Maybe that's because he's acting with a very clean conscience,'' Mr. Newman said.</p>
        <p>So began the closing arguments in this trial, which has attracted much attention because of Albert Pirro's prominence as an influential real estate development lawyer and powerful Republican lobbyist, as well as the repercussions the verdict may have on his wife's political career.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Newman is expected to conclude his presentation for the defense. He will be followed by Roger L. Stavis, Anthony Pirro's lawyer, and then the prosecution, once again, before Judge Barrington D. Parker Jr. instructs the jury on the legal parameters of the 61-count indictment against the two brothers.</p>
        <p>But for most of the day, the government had the stage. Ms. Seibel tried to be both blunt and precise in highlighting the greatest hits of what had sometimes been a dry foray into the arcana of tax law.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seibel acknowledged as much, saying that the government's presentation during the trial had occasionally ''sounded like accounting 101.'' And while she warned that she would be no match for Mr. Newman's entertaining style, she said the case, nevertheless, was a serious matter testing the tenet that all taxpayers are supposed to pay their fair share.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Pirro did instead, she argued, was to mastermind convoluted financial transactions to disguise illegitimate deductions.</p>
        <p>''He's in the loop,'' she said of Mr. Pirro. She also accused his younger brother and accountant, Anthony, of being entangled in the conspiracy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seibel often leavened her remarks with sarcasm in an attempt to demonstrate how far-fetched the deductions were: a Mercedes for his mother-in-law in Elmira written off as an expense for a real estate company in Yonkers?</p>
        <p>And she ridiculed the defense's calculation that only 5 percent of Mr. Pirro's business deductions had been challenged, saying that Mr. Pirro apparently felt that people who do more business could cheat more on their taxes.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure Bill Gates would be happy to learn about this,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Then again, it was Mr. Newman who seemed to generate more smiles or laughs from the jury, even though he spoke for only about one and a half hours, compared with Ms. Seibel's five and a half.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman, a vigorous septuagenarian, joked about his advancing age and admitted that he was nervous because his two grandsons were in the gallery. But then, turning serious, he expressed incredulity at why the government had pursued his client even though the Internal Revenue Service encourages wayward taxpayers to file amended returns and pay back taxes -- which is exactly what Albert Pirro did, to the tune of about $1 million.</p>
        <p>He asked jurors to apply their common sense in gauging why Albert Pirro would bother to engage in tax fraud, considering his wife's political aspirations. And he criticized the government's reliability, reading back testimony from the government's main witness, John Dennehy, a revenue agent with the I.R.S., that seemed to counter some of Ms. Seibel's closing arguments.</p>
        <p>''Are you being dealt a complete hand?'' Mr. Newman asked. ''Are you being told everything by the government, which has the burden of proof? You be the judges of that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
