<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Admit Guilt In Falsifying CUC's Books</title>
    <meta content="15CEND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cuc International Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cendant Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corigliano, Cosmo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pember, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sabatino, Casper</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silverman, Henry R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelton, E Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reno, Janet (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henriques, Diana B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DE113EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Admit Guilt In Falsifying CUC's Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS and DIANA B. HENRIQUES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henriques, Diana B; Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cosmo Corigliano, Anne Pember and Casper Sabatino, former executives with CUC International, formerly Comp-U-Card International, appear in United States District Court, Newark, NJ, to plead guilty to federal charges in what authorities call largest and longest accounting fraud in history, covering at least 12 years and costing investors $19 billion; three executives say that for most of entire history of CUC, its top executives directed conspiracy to inflate profits in order to meet Wall Street forecasts and keep stock price high; Corigliano says he worked 'in culture that had been developed over many years'; says conspiracy was directed by his superiors, though he does not identify them; Henry R Silverman, founder of HFS and now chairman and chief executive of Cendant, attends hearing; says he will not be satisfied until all people responsible have been brought to justice; people fimiliar with Cendant's legal plans say company will take action against E Kirk Shelton, president and chief operating officer, and Stuart L Bell, former chief financial officer of CUC; Attorney General Janet Reno says case 'involves grave betrayal of public trust'; CUC grew through mergers into giant Cendant Corp; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three former executives of CUC International pleaded guilty today to federal charges in what the authorities said was the largest and longest accounting fraud in history, continuing at least 12 years and costing investors $19 billion.</p>
        <p>CUC, formerly Comp-U-Card International, went public in 1983 and grew through mergers from a tiny company into the giant Cendant Corporation, which oversees franchises and consumer services including Days Inn hotels, Century 21 real estate and Jackson Hewitt tax offices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three former executives of CUC International pleaded guilty today to federal charges in what the authorities said was the largest and longest accounting fraud in history, continuing at least 12 years and costing investors $19 billion.</p>
        <p>CUC, formerly Comp-U-Card International, went public in 1983 and grew through mergers from a tiny company into the giant Cendant Corporation, which oversees franchises and consumer services including Days Inn hotels, Century 21 real estate and Jackson Hewitt tax offices.</p>
        <p>But the three former executives said today that for almost the entire history of CUC, its top executives directed a conspiracy to inflate profits so as to meet Wall Street analysts' forecasts and to keep the price of the stock high.</p>
        <p>The disclosures, in United States District Court here, indicated that the fraud, which was exposed in 1998, lasted far longer and rose higher in the company than had been thought.</p>
        <p>''It was a culture that had been developing over many years,'' Cosmo Corigliano, the former chief financial officer of CUC and the most senior official to plead guilty today, said when asked by Judge William H. Walls why he had participated in the conspiracy.</p>
        <p>''It was just ingrained in all of us, ingrained in us by our superiors, over a very long period of time, that that was what we did,'' said Mr. Corigliano, 40, of Old Saybrook, Conn. He said the conspiracy to falsify the books had been directed by his corporate superiors, though he did not identify them. The others who pleaded guilty -- Anne Pember, 40, of Madison, Conn., a former controller of CUC, and Casper Sabatino, 47, of Sherman, Conn., a CUC accountant -- also said they had been following orders. Robert J. Cleary, the United States attorney in Newark, said that the investigation, involving several agencies, was continuing and that the officials who pleaded guilty were cooperating.</p>
        <p>Previous investigations had indicated that the conspiracy began by 1995, but the Securities and Exchange Commission said that in fact it started as early as 1985 and continued after CUC merged with HFS to become Cendant. It was exposed on April 15, 1998, after Mr. Sabatino reported it to former HFS executives at the company.</p>
        <p>Cendant stock immediately collapsed, shaving $14 billion from the company's market value in one day and ultimately $19 billion when the stock bottomed a few months later.</p>
        <p>''Please keep in mind that the real story is about people, the investors who trusted, and the greedy people who today admitted that they breached that trust,'' said Neil Schorr, who directed the investigation by the Postal Inspection Service. The victims included the state pension funds of New York and Connecticut as well as owners of numerous mutual funds and individual retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corigliano's superiors at CUC at the time of the merger with HFS were Walter A. Forbes, the chairman and chief executive, and E. Kirk Shelton, the president and chief operating officer. Mr. Shelton's lawyer denied today that his client knew of the fraud or played any role in it. A lawyer for Mr. Forbes, who has previously denied any wrongdoing, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>In a packed courtroom, Judge Walls tried to cut through the accounting lingo. ''Don't we call that cooking the books?'' he asked Mr. Sabatino.</p>
        <p>''Yes, sir,'' Mr. Sabatino replied.</p>
        <p>''Why did you do it?'' the judge asked.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, your honor, I just thought I was doing my job,'' Mr. Sabatino replied.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. brought charges today against seven former CUC employees, including the three who pleaded guilty, and released a report detailing how the fraud was committed. The actions included entering numbers into earnings reports that were completely fictional, and then shifting accounts around in an effort to deceive the company's auditors, Ernst &amp; Young.</p>
        <p>''For more than a decade, these and other employees of CUC manipulated and falsified CUC's earnings,'' said Thomas H. Newkirk, associate director of enforcement for the S.E.C. ''Their goal was one that has become all too familiar -- to inflate the company's stock price and meet the earnings expectations of analysts by reporting 25 percent earnings increases every year.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said the company's officers inflated profits by hundreds of millions of dollars in recent years.</p>
        <p>The authorities went out of their way to say that the case was about much more than a technical accounting issue.</p>
        <p>''This case boils down to greed, ego and arrogance,'' said Joseph R. Lewis, the special agent in charge of the F.B.I. investigation. ''Some people have referred to this as a case of earnings management. That is an attempt to sterilize the crime. It's about lying, deceit and fraud.''</p>
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno said in a statement that the case ''involves a grave betrayal of the public trust'' and added: ''Today's action sends a strong message that any executive who lies on company financial statements to manipulate earnings will be prosecuted to the fullest extent of the law.''</p>
        <p>Henry R. Silverman, the founder of HFS and now chairman and chief executive of Cendant, attended the court hearing and said he was happy. ''I'm satisfied for Phase 1, but I won't be fully satisfied until all the people responsible for this have been brought to justice,'' he said.</p>
        <p>People familiar with Cendant's legal plans said the company will take legal action on Thursday against Mr. Shelton and Stuart L. Bell, who was chief financial officer of CUC until he resigned in 1995 and was replaced by Mr. Corigliano. The company is already taking legal steps to recover a severance package paid to Mr. Forbes, and it has filed suit against Ernst &amp; Young.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell's lawyer said his client had no knowledge of or involvement in ''anything even remotely relating'' to the conspiracy described in court today.</p>
        <p>strong message that any executive who lies on company financial statements to manipulate earnings will be prosecuted to the fullest extent of the law.''</p>
        <p>Henry R. Silverman, the founder of HFS and now chairman and chief executive of Cendant, attended the court hearing and said he was happy. ''I'm satisfied for Phase 1, but I won't be fully satisfied until all the people responsible for this have been brought to justice,'' he said.</p>
        <p>People familiar with Cendant's legal plans said the company will take legal action on Thursday against Mr. Shelton and Stuart L. Bell, who was chief financial officer of CUC until he resigned in 1995 and was replaced by Mr. Corigliano. The company is already taking legal steps to recover a severance package paid to Mr. Forbefraud count each, face up to five years.</p>
        <p>All three could be fined billions of dollars under a law that allows fines to equal twice the losses suffered by victims. The fines are likely to be far smaller, however. Mr. Corigliano and Ms. Pember did not settle the charges by the S.E.C. today, evidently because they are still negotiating the penalties they will have to pay. The S.E.C. is seeking to force them to pay a combined $15 million, representing the losses they avoided by selling shares of CUC and Cendant before the fraud was uncovered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sabatino settled S.E.C. charges by agreeing not to become an officer of a public company, but was not required to pay any fine. Kevin T. Kearney, 33, of Reading, Conn., a former director of financial reporting, agreed to repay $40,677 in profits and interest from sales of stock, and to pay a $35,000 penalty, and was barred from practicing as an accountant before the S.E.C.</p>
        <p>Three other CUC employees settled administrative charges by the S.E.C. without admitting or denying wrongdoing. Steven Speaks, a former controller of CUC's largest division, and Mary Sattler Polverari, a former CUC supervisor of financial reporting, each agreed to pay civil penalties of $25,000. Paul Hiznay, a former divisional accounting manager, was not required to pay a fine but agreed not to violate securities laws in the future.</p>
        <p>Without admitting or denying guilt, Cendant itself settled an S.E.C. complaint that it had violated technical record-keeping rules and agreed not to violate those laws in the future. It was not penalized by the commission, which noted that Cendant's current managers had taken immediate action to uncover the fraud and had cooperated with the investigation.</p>
        <p>CUC, which sold memberships in buying groups that allowed credit card customers to save money on travel and other services, gained a large Wall Street following in the years that it appeared to be growing rapidly. The company went public in 1983 at $1.21 a share, adjusted for subsequent splits. After the merger that created Cendant, the stock rose to a high of $41.69 on April 6, 1998, shortly before the fraud was discovered. Its gain during that period was five times that of the Dow Jones industrial average. But the stock plunged to a low of $6.50 in 1998. Today, Cendant shares rose 18.75 cents, to $12.4375.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. report released today laid out details of how the CUC fraud began and expanded. At first, it was an attempt by the company to keep profits as high as Wall Street analysts expected. That involved a variety of false entries to inflate revenue and defer expenses.</p>
        <p>In later years, that was not enough, the S.E.C. said, and it became necessary for the company to grow through mergers. When a merger was accomplished, a reserve fund would be created to cover one-time costs related to the transaction. Wall Street analysts often ignored such reserves, which the S.E.C. said the company used to inflate revenue and hide real operating expenses.</p>
        <p>By the S.E.C. account, CUC management sought the merger with HFS primarily to create a reserve large enough to accommodate the improper accounting that would keep the fraud going. Instead, Mr. Silverman and former HFS employees reacted with fury after being told of the fraud by Mr. Sabatino, and the fraud was soon disclosed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
