<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Teenager With a (Very) Big Problem</title>
    <meta content="15GAME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">herold, charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2DA133EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Teenager With a (Very) Big Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">herold, charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Game Theory column on The Longest Journey, Norwegian adventure computer game; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APRIL RYAN is an 18-year-old art student living in the 23rd century. She has an art project due, the sleazy guy across the hall keeps pestering her for a date, and she holds the fate of two worlds in her hands. That's a lot of responsibility for a teenager, but April has yet one more feat to accomplish: she must get the attention of American game players without a missile launcher.</p>
        <p>April is the protagonist of The Longest Journey, an adventure game from Funcom of Norway. It has been translated into six languages and has received some of the most enthusiastic reviews of any adventure game ever produced. But you can't yet buy it in any store in the United States, where the adventure game has been declared dead. (DreamCatcher Interactive, a small, Toronto-based publisher, plans to announce this week that it will distribute the game in North America.) Adventure games have continued to be popular in Europe, leaving Americans to their main diet of flashy, immersive violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APRIL RYAN is an 18-year-old art student living in the 23rd century. She has an art project due, the sleazy guy across the hall keeps pestering her for a date, and she holds the fate of two worlds in her hands. That's a lot of responsibility for a teenager, but April has yet one more feat to accomplish: she must get the attention of American game players without a missile launcher.</p>
        <p>April is the protagonist of The Longest Journey, an adventure game from Funcom of Norway. It has been translated into six languages and has received some of the most enthusiastic reviews of any adventure game ever produced. But you can't yet buy it in any store in the United States, where the adventure game has been declared dead. (DreamCatcher Interactive, a small, Toronto-based publisher, plans to announce this week that it will distribute the game in North America.) Adventure games have continued to be popular in Europe, leaving Americans to their main diet of flashy, immersive violence.</p>
        <p>The Longest Journey has more than a smart protagonist with a tall order to fill. It is easily one of the best adventure games ever made, with beautiful graphics, a compelling story and interesting puzzles.</p>
        <p>You first meet April in her nightmare of a strange, supernatural world. It is the prettiest nightmare you are ever likely to see. The Longest Journey is an ostentatiously gorgeous game, the most stunning since Riven, with landscapes and animated sequences that will make you gasp.</p>
        <p>As in many fantasy stories, April discovers that she has a destiny. She doesn't want a destiny. She wants to get A's in art school and find a boyfriend, but the fate of two worlds and billions of people depends on her. April must somehow save the mystical Balance that keeps our earth, the world of science, in harmony with Arcadia, an alternate, magical earth.</p>
        <p>To that end, April goes everywhere from the bottom of the sea to outer space and talks to everyone from an ancient dragon to an unemployed actor. In breadth, depth and length, The Longest Journey qualifies as an epic adventure, at times seeming more like a novel than a computer game.</p>
        <p>The game environment is a fully realized universe. Arcadia is beautiful and enchanted, with a range of strange beings, many of whom would love to trade unpredictable magic for good old-fashioned science. Three hundred years into the future, our own world is surprisingly familiar, except for things like hovercars, holographic candles and corporate-sponsored police who arrest you and then try to sell you products.</p>
        <p>Story and character development have been given at least as much attention as the game's puzzles. The dialogue is terrific. Some of it is as funny as anything in the classic Lucas Arts adventure games, like Curse of Monkey Island and Grim Fandago. Characters like the cybergeek Flipper Burns or a prickly ship's captain will have you laughing out loud, although if you're offended by foul language, Flipper might make you cringe more than laugh.</p>
        <p>At other times the writing is thoughtful and original, as exemplified by conversations with Abnaxus, who belongs to a race that experiences the past, present and future as concurrent. When April asks him how he knows her name, he says: ''Have we not met then? I was sorry for confusing you. I will be Abnaxus.''</p>
        <p>While its puzzles lack the inspired ingenuity of a game like Day of the Tentacle, The Longest Journey is challenging without being unfairly difficult. Puzzles are logical, there are no dead ends, and even though April notes at one point that ''life should carry a big ol' caution sticker -- it's certain to kill you sooner or later,'' you can't die in this game. Some games seem designed to frustrate you as much as possible, but The Longest Journey wants you to win.</p>
        <p>While the tradition in adventure games is for puzzles to become more difficult as you proceed, the final puzzles in The Longest Journey are surprisingly easy. That's good because the story is so involving that it would be painful to be stuck for days on a puzzle so near the conclusion. Instead of hard puzzles, The Longest Journey's payoff is an emotional one, a satisfying and uplifting finale.</p>
        <p>The Longest Journey also raises the question, Can the adventure game genre be revived? In popular entertainment, one of the rules is that nothing ever dies -- some things just hibernate. (In 1976 the common wisdom was that no one wanted to watch science fiction movies, and in 1977 ''Star Wars'' came out.) If given the opportunity, The Longest Journey stands a better chance than any game in years of reawakening the adventure game in America. It also has the potential to pull in women without putting off men.</p>
        <p>The opportunity to play as a woman -- that is, a woman who is not simply a large-breasted male fantasy -- is rare. April Ryan, a heroine to Lara Croft's mannequin, could win the hearts and minds of disenfranchised female players.</p>
        <p>She is strong, clever and resourceful. And for the men, April is both prettier and more personable than Lara Croft. She makes a far better sex symbol than a girl with outsize breasts whose conversation rarely goes beyond ''aha.'' She may also be the best adventure computer game hero ever, one who creates the kind of emotional bond with the player that you expect from a good film or novel.</p>
        <p>Funcom has hired a model who looks like April to travel the German talk show circuit and is working on an MTV-style video of April covering the Depeche Mode song ''The Balance.'' With that determined media blitz, April Ryan is already doing more than fulfilling prophecies and saving two worlds. She is actually making the journey to a software store near you.</p>
        <p>The Longest Journey, published by Funcom; CD-ROM for Windows 95 and 98; about $35 at www  .softwarefirst.com; soon to be distributed in North America by DreamCatcher Interactive.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
