<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell &amp; Co., for Better or Worse, Get the Ball Rolling</title>
    <meta content="31KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/sports/31KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Philadelphia 76ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDC1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell &amp; Co., for Better or Worse, Get the Ball Rolling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers to play Philadelphia 76ers in season opening game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In today's National Basketball Association, where individualism rules, almost every club is associated with one player. The Philadelphia 76ers, who visit the Knicks at Madison Square Garden for Tuesday's season opener, belong to Allen Iverson. The Los Angeles Lakers, despite Kobe Bryant's brilliance, are led by Shaquille O'Neal. And for the last 15 years that were spent in heart-wrenching pursuit of a championship, the face of the Knicks has been Patrick Ewing.</p>
        <p>But a new era of pro basketball in New York is about to begin, and while the Knicks have three or four players of equal prominence, the public perception is that they are Latrell Sprewell's team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In today's National Basketball Association, where individualism rules, almost every club is associated with one player. The Philadelphia 76ers, who visit the Knicks at Madison Square Garden for Tuesday's season opener, belong to Allen Iverson. The Los Angeles Lakers, despite Kobe Bryant's brilliance, are led by Shaquille O'Neal. And for the last 15 years that were spent in heart-wrenching pursuit of a championship, the face of the Knicks has been Patrick Ewing.</p>
        <p>But a new era of pro basketball in New York is about to begin, and while the Knicks have three or four players of equal prominence, the public perception is that they are Latrell Sprewell's team.</p>
        <p>Sprewell does not agree with the sentiment that it is his team, but he understands.</p>
        <p>''It's probably the attitude that I bring and the passion that I play with,'' Sprewell said today after the team's final practice before the regular season. ''The way that I play fits New York. It's kind of grimy.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, with the thrilling tomahawk slams, is the one player the fans love most. The game of Allan Houston, who led the Knicks in scoring last season, is smooth but unspectacular. Larry Johnson, the key low-post scorer, does not play above the rim, and Glen Rice, who may be the team's best offensive player, is a newcomer.</p>
        <p>''I love it,'' Sprewell said of the reception he gets from the Garden crowd. ''That's probably the most important reason I love playing here, along with us having success.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell realizes, however, that this season will test that relationship far more than his previous two. Often, being the team's most celebrated player also means being the most blamed player. Part of the reason Ewing wanted to leave New York was the criticism he took for the Knicks' failure to win a championship. Sprewell knows that if the Knicks flounder this season, much of the condemnation once reserved for Ewing will land on him.</p>
        <p>''If that happens to me I couldn't care less about what other people think and say, as long as I felt in my heart that I was playing as hard as I could and I did what I had to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sprewell, however, has one thing going for him that Ewing did not. While Ewing's relationship with the news media was cold, Sprewell has become a favorite.</p>
        <p>''I think people are surprised by the way that I talk,'' said Sprewell, who is from Milwaukee. ''My being articulate and being able to communicate well kind of throws them off because when you think of somebody from the inner city you might not necessarily think they're going to sound articulate and be somewhat intelligent. There are other things about me, like my interest in computers, that people wouldn't necessarily associate with being from the inner city and being a tough guy, too.</p>
        <p>''I think my speaking ability came from when I was in junior college and college,'' added Sprewell, who attended Three Rivers Community College in Missouri and the University of Alabama.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't one of the guys that was given grades. I flunked English several times trying to get it right. I never let my tutors do my work or do my papers. I always did my own stuff and I think in the long run it paid off for me.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell's responsibility in the locker room will increase now that Ewing is gone. Sprewell is not a vocal leader and says he wants his work ethic, practice habits and play to speak for him. Some players, however, including his good friend Marcus Camby, have criticized Sprewell for arriving 10 to 20 minutes late for many home games.</p>
        <p>Publicly, Coach Jeff Van Gundy has not made a big issue out of Sprewell's habitual tardiness. And Sprewell, who typically arrives at about 6:15 for 7:30 games, does not seem prepared to leave home any earlier than usual.</p>
        <p>''If the game started at 6, I would be there at 6,'' Sprewell said. ''Guys shoot and do other things before the game. I just kind of sit in the training room and gather my thoughts, listen to music or watch the game tape. I don't know if I necessarily absolutely have to be there at 6. I just try to maximize my time. If I can get 20 extra minutes of sleep on a game day that's what I'm looking to do.''</p>
        <p>Besides not showing up on time, Sprewell seems willing to do whatever is in the best interest of the team. He has tried to sell the benefits of playing for the Knicks to his good friends Chris Webber and Joe Smith, and he will play out of position for the third consecutive season, starting at small forward instead of his natural shooting guard spot.</p>
        <p>Also, to get Rice added playing time, he will play point guard on occasion. Playing the point is a bit of a sacrifice because, while it may help the team, it could hurt Sprewell's individual production.</p>
        <p>''It's not my team,'' he said. ''I never thought it was Patrick's team. It takes 14 guys, the coaching staff, the trainers and everybody involved to make this thing work. No one person is going to make or break the team. Obviously, certain people carry a little more weight. I would say that among me, Allan, L. J. and Glen we have more responsibility than some of the other guys, but that doesn't make it just our team.</p>
        <p>''All of us are going to win together, and we're going to lose together.  We're not going to win or lose because of me.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone may see it that way.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
