<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barak Wins Support and Launches Strike Against Fatah</title>
    <meta content="Y31ISR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/world/31ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD71530F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barak Wins Support and Launches Strike Against Fatah</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak re-opens Parliament after three-month recess as violence again erupts in heart of contested East Jerusalem; tells legislators he left 'no stone unturned' in search for peace, but that Yasir Arafat proved not to be partner in effort; says Israeli people must unite in time of crisis; address is interrupted by persistent heckling; he reaches deal with ultra-Orthodox Shas party granting crumbling government one-month grace period to deal with Palestinian crisis without fear of being toppled; Barak orders missile attacks against offices of political faction and personal security forces of Arafat; move follows discovery of bound and mutilated body of Israeli man on edge of East Jerusalem; twin funerals are held for Palestinian brothers shot dead by Israeli soldiers; Palestinian gunman kills security guard and severely wounds another outside Israeli government office in East Jerusalem; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As violence again penetrated the heart of contested East Jerusalem, Prime Minister Ehud Barak stood at the helm of a crumbled government today and reopened Parliament after a three-month recess in which the Israeli-Palestinian reality underwent seismic change.</p>
        <p>Late tonight, in a graphic illustration of the shift, Mr. Barak, a former general turned peacemaker, ordered missile attacks on offices of the political faction and personal security forces of Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. No casualties were reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As violence again penetrated the heart of contested East Jerusalem, Prime Minister Ehud Barak stood at the helm of a crumbled government today and reopened Parliament after a three-month recess in which the Israeli-Palestinian reality underwent seismic change.</p>
        <p>Late tonight, in a graphic illustration of the shift, Mr. Barak, a former general turned peacemaker, ordered missile attacks on offices of the political faction and personal security forces of Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. No casualties were reported.</p>
        <p>The pounding aerial attacks closed a day that began with the discovery of an Israeli man's bound and mutilated body at the edge of East Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Twin funerals followed in a West Bank town for two Palestinian brothers shot dead by Israeli soldiers. And then, outside an Israeli government office in East Jerusalem, a Palestinian gunman killed one security guard and severely wounded another.</p>
        <p>''Israel will not stand by and accept attacks on its citizens and soldiers,'' Mr. Barak had warned earlier today before the rocket attacks.</p>
        <p>In a 35-minute speech to Parliament, Mr. Barak did not find any new words to address the radical deterioration of Israeli security, diplomacy and politics that has taken place since the lawmakers recessed in July. Instead, he drew from a familiar rhetorical repertory to assert that he had ''left no stone unturned'' in the pursuit of peace, that Mr. Arafat had not turned out be a ''partner for peace'' and that the Israeli people must unite in a time of crisis.</p>
        <p>Ending his speech with a tentative effort to lift the hopes of his unsettled population, Mr. Barak referred to the Bible. ''In the story of Noah, the second week brings a rainbow and the flood subsides,'' he said. ''I am sure here, too, the dove of peace will eventually appear, carrying a sprig from the olive tree.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Barak spoke, he was interrupted a dozen times by hecklers.</p>
        <p>Israeli-Arab lawmakers held up photographs of 13 Israeli Arabs shot dead by Israeli police officers in recent riots, shouting: ''You killed peace! You murdered it!''</p>
        <p>But by the standards of the Israeli Parliament, it was not a particularly stormy session, especially considering that brawls had been predicted and extra police posted. A political deal had been finalized before the meeting opened, defusing the pent-up antagonism of many lawmakers.</p>
        <p>Under the deal, the rigorously Orthodox Shas party agreed to grant the prime minister a one-month grace period during which he will be able to deal with the Palestinian conflict without fear of being toppled. Yossi Beilin, the dovish justice minister, hammered out the arrangement for Mr. Barak, promising Shas in exchange that the government would abandon its plans for a civic, or secular, ''revolution.''</p>
        <p>Shas's backing lessened Mr. Barak's urgent need to form an emergency unity government with Ariel Sharon, leader of the opposition Likud Party. The two men failed to forge a union that would have been a temporary political life raft for each of them. Both their parties, especially the Likud, which senses an opportunity to revive its standing if new elections are held, opposed the merger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak does not face a clear road ahead. But beyond the immediate emergency period, most experts expect new elections, probably late next spring.</p>
        <p>In an indication that Mr. Barak may be seeking to renew a dialogue with Mr. Arafat, television reports said that he was sending Shimon Peres, a former prime minister, to see the Palestinian leader. On Sunday, Leah Rabin, widow of assassinated Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin, had upbraided Mr. Barak publicly for not making use of Mr. Peres.</p>
        <p>A television reporter asked if the overture to Mr. Arafat meant that Mr. Barak's declared ''timeout'' from the peace effort -- which was perceived as a way to soften up the Likud leader for a political deal -- had ended.</p>
        <p>''Now he's in a timeout with Ariel Sharon,'' Emmanuel Rosen, a television political analyst, jokingly answered.</p>
        <p>Although both Mr. Barak and Mr. Sharon insisted today that they were still hoping to join forces, they expressed what seemed to be irreconcilable views about peacemaking -- differences that could only be overcome, some experts predicted, by a wave of terrorism that forced them into an emergency coalition.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Barak reaffirmed his commitment to peace talks without renouncing either the Oslo interim peace agreement or the understandings reached at Camp David in July, which his government still believes to be the basis for moving forward. He cautioned Mr. Arafat, however, that ''the window of opportunity was closing'' and that the Palestinian leader would ''achieve nothing through violence.''</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials dismissed the speech as ''more bombast'' from Mr. Barak, as one put it. They also denounced him for what they said were threats to use greater force in response to the killings today. That threat was made good later with the missile attacks.</p>
        <p>In a much more fiery, and more heckled, speech, Mr. Sharon blamed Mr. Barak for the conflict -- for ''putting us in this bind,'' he said, in which Israel appeared to be weak. He insisted that the government's aim to reach a permanent peace agreement with the Palestinians be abandoned in favor of the pursuit of a long-term interim arrangement, which would leave the thorniest issues unresolved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon spoke to the Israeli public's fears of insecurity while criticizing Mr. Barak's Camp David offers to divide Jerusalem. ''What's happening here?'' he said. ''People are running scared of being in public places'' for fear of terrorist attacks.</p>
        <p>''Just imagine how much worse our situation would be now if the Old City of Jerusalem were for the most part handed over to the Palestinians,'' Mr. Sharon added, referring to a proposal discussed at Camp David.</p>
        <p>An Israeli-Arab lawmaker, Taleb A-Sana, rose to his feet and shouted: ''You think you can get peace without that? You think peace comes for free?''</p>
        <p>Several rightist legislators attacked Mr. Barak for what they termed the Israeli Army's excessive restraint in the face of Palestinian provocation.</p>
        <p>''We're like King Kong saying, 'See, see our tanks,' '' said Uzi Landau, a Likud member of Parliament. ''Look at the message we're giving.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Landau spoke before the shelling, in which three missiles were fired on Fatah Party headquarters in Al-Bireh, near Ramallah, and two missiles demolished the party's Nablus headquarters. Fatah's militant cells have led the street rioting and gun battles with the Israelis. Helicopter gunships also targeted the Force 17 headquarters of Mr. Arafat's presidential security forces in Khan Yunis, Gaza.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians were warned in advance of the attacks, but said they did not understand what provoked them. ''What happened today to provide an excuse for this?'' asked Nabil Aburdeineh, a senior aide to Mr. Arafat. ''It's part of the war against us.''</p>
        <p>Clashes between Palestinians and Israeli soldiers continued in the West Bank and Gaza following several funerals.</p>
        <p>Palestinians found and turned over to Israeli police the stabbed body of Amos Mahlouf, a 30-year-old Israeli. They discovered him in a riverbed near the Palestinian town of Beit Jala at the edge of Jerusalem. A friend who identified Mr. Mahlouf said that the Arabic words for ''God is Great'' were carved into the man's body.</p>
        <p>In East Jerusalem, two security guards in front of a social welfare office were shot at close range in an apparent anti-Israeli attack. A group calling itself the Saladin Brigades, after the 12th century Muslim leader who captured Jerusalem, claimed responsibility for the incident in a fax to the Reuters news agency. The group is not known by Israeli or Palestinian security officials.</p>
        <p>''I have no doubt that this is an attempt to drag East Jerusalem into the violence,'' said Yair Yitzhaki, the Jerusalem police chief.</p>
        <p>The shooting may have been a revenge attack, Palestinian officials said. It followed an attack on a guard at a Palestinian hospital, Augusta Victoria, in East Jerusalem on Sunday. The guard said that a carload of Jewish youths wearing skullcaps drove by in the early morning, and one youth shot him in the shoulder.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
