<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets and Valentine Near Deal on New Contract</title>
    <meta content="31METS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/sports/31METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valentine, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DA1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets and Valentine Near Deal on New Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets reportedly near agreement on new three-year contract with manager Boby Valentine; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobby Valentine was hurt last winter when the Mets refused to discuss a new contract after he had managed the team to the playoffs. Now, after Valentine led the Mets to the World Series, the wait is about to pay off for him.</p>
        <p>The Mets have made multiple offers to Valentine, focusing on a three-year deal. According to a person familiar with the negotiations, the team is prepared to make Valentine one of the three highest-paid managers in baseball. The Yankees' Joe Torre is the highest-paid manager, at $3 million a year, and the Giants' Dusty Baker is second, earning about $2.75 million a year on his new deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bobby Valentine was hurt last winter when the Mets refused to discuss a new contract after he had managed the team to the playoffs. Now, after Valentine led the Mets to the World Series, the wait is about to pay off for him.</p>
        <p>The Mets have made multiple offers to Valentine, focusing on a three-year deal. According to a person familiar with the negotiations, the team is prepared to make Valentine one of the three highest-paid managers in baseball. The Yankees' Joe Torre is the highest-paid manager, at $3 million a year, and the Giants' Dusty Baker is second, earning about $2.75 million a year on his new deal.</p>
        <p>Mets General Manager Steve Phillips is hoping to sign Valentine to the contract by midnight tonight, when Valentine's contract expires. Valentine's deal is the most pressing off-season task for the Mets, but they are working on the rest of their to-do list. Phillips's first priority after the Valentine deal is to re-sign the Mets' No. 1 starter, Mike Hampton, who has not yet filed for free agency. The other potential ace on the free-agent market is the right-hander Mike Mussina from the Baltimore Orioles, and the Mets have initiated talks with his agent.</p>
        <p>The agent, Arn Tellem, said the sides had exchanged calls since Mussina filed last Friday. Mussina, who rejected the Orioles' six-year, $72 million offer in September, wants to play for a winning team, Tellem said, and proximity to his home in central Pennsylvania is a factor.</p>
        <p>''He's anxious to see what's out there, and I think he has a total open mind at this point,'' Tellem said.</p>
        <p>Valentine cannot test the market until tomorrow. Phillips -- whose own new deal has apparently been completed but not announced -- does not want Valentine talking with other teams.</p>
        <p>''The expectation was to try to get everything completed by midnight tomorrow, understanding that time is an element in it,'' Phillips said yesterday. ''If we're not able to, things change. It's a different environment in which we all live, and we have to make a decision.''</p>
        <p>Phillips needs time to focus on many other decisions. Teams cannot discuss money with free agents from other teams until Nov. 11, but besides Mussina, the Mets will probably look into other elite free agents like Alex Rodriguez and Manny Ramirez.</p>
        <p>The Mets have nine potential free agents of their own: Kurt Abbott, Derek Bell, Mike Bordick, John Franco, Hampton, Lenny Harris, Bobby J. Jones, Rick Reed and Turk Wendell.</p>
        <p>Phillips said yesterday that Reed and Jones would be considered independently of Hampton. Reed and Jones want to return, their agents said yesterday, though Reed's asking price has gone up from this summer, when he could have been signed for three years and $18 million.</p>
        <p>''The market has definitely gone north, and Rick's contributions certainly elicit a higher figure than that,'' said Reed's agent, Phil Tannenbaum, adding that Reed, 35, is seeking a three- or four-year deal.</p>
        <p>Jones's agent, Jeff Moorad, is waiting to hear from Phillips and is eager to begin negotiations if the Mets reciprocate that interest. ''Bobby would be very open to staying with the Mets, and we assume that when the dust settles after a long season, we'd hear from Steve,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Wendell has said he would like to return, but Franco has been coy about his status. ''I'm not even thinking about that,'' he said after the World Series. The 40-year-old Franco needs 59 saves to break Lee Smith's career record, 478, and he may have to decide between signing elsewhere as a closer or staying with his hometown Mets as a setup man.</p>
        <p>The Mets have not spoken to Bordick's agent, Joe Bick, since they acquired Bordick from Baltimore in late July. The shortstop filed for free agency the day after the World Series ended, and his tenure with the Mets is almost certainly over.</p>
        <p>Bordick batted .260 for the Mets and earned his first trip to the World Series in 10 years, but his season ended in disappointment. Hampered by a thumb injury, Bordick was removed for a pinch-hitter in the first four games of the World Series and was benched for Game 5.</p>
        <p>The Mets have options at shortstop: they owe Rey Ordonez $16 million over the next three years and are likely to make a strong push for Rodriguez, the Seattle shortstop who filed for free agency yesterday and should command $20 million a year.</p>
        <p>If they sign Rodriguez and thereby have a proven run producer at shortstop, the Mets could afford to start an unproven outfielder like Timo Perez or Bubba Trammell. If they do not sign Rodriguez, Ramirez is an outfield possibility, though the Mets have not called Moorad, his agent.</p>
        <p>It seems as if the Mets have no intention of retaining Bell, though the right fielder would like to come back. Bell hit .318 in the first half, .187 in the second. His agent, Eric Goldschmidt, said Bell was seeking a multiyear contract, but the sides have not talked and Goldschmidt did not sound optimistic.</p>
        <p>''You read stuff, and it sounds like the team has forgotten all that Derek did in the first half that kept them in the race,'' Goldschmidt said. ''He didn't have a great offensive second half, but his defense was still there and he was a great team player.''</p>
        <p>Another Goldschmidt client is Harris, the infielder who was not offered a free-agent contract after playing for the Mets in 1998. Harris is 37 and wants a multiyear deal, but his bat, speed and clubhouse presence might persuade the Mets to give it to him.</p>
        <p>Abbott, another reserve infielder, is unlikely to return. The Mets can pick up his option and pay him $700,000 next year or buy out his contract for $50,000.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
