<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goals Are Still Flowing for the Devils</title>
    <meta content="31DEVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/sports/31DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Panthers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goals Are Still Flowing for the Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils defeat Florida Panthers, 6-5; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seven goals on the first 10 shots of a hockey game is a nightmare for goaltenders and coaches but a delight for fans. The Devils trailed the Florida Panthers, 4-3, tonight before their game was 11 minutes old, but things settled down after that and the Devils  emerged with a 6-5 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur and Trevor Kidd had a miserable time of it in the early stages, but the Devils, after trailing by two goals, played better positional hockey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seven goals on the first 10 shots of a hockey game is a nightmare for goaltenders and coaches but a delight for fans. The Devils trailed the Florida Panthers, 4-3, tonight before their game was 11 minutes old, but things settled down after that and the Devils  emerged with a 6-5 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur and Trevor Kidd had a miserable time of it in the early stages, but the Devils, after trailing by two goals, played better positional hockey.</p>
        <p>''When you look up and the score is 4-3 and the shots are five-all, it's not pretty,'' Devils Coach Larry Robinson said. ''We ran around a little bit. Our defensive-zone coverage looked like we had never played in our zone before.''</p>
        <p>Bobby Holik, who scored the winning goal at 1 minute 55 seconds of overtime, said: ''There was a lot of helter-skelter play and a lot of moving around. I want to forget that period as quickly as possible. Teams won't let us come back from two goals down very often.''</p>
        <p>Holik scored the winner after he picked up a loose puck in his own zone and skated the other way to the right circle. Then he fired a blistering shot for his fourth goal of the season to the delight of the 13,168 fans at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The Devils (6-2-2-0) posted their second victory in six days over the Panthers (1-4-3-2), the team the Devils swept in the first round of the playoffs last spring en route to their Stanley Cup championship.</p>
        <p>Neither Randy McKay nor John Madden, who both scored four goals Saturday night in Pittsburgh to become the first twosome to do so in 78 years, scored tonight. But the Devils got two goals each from Scott Gomez and Patrik Elias and one from Sergei Brylin before Holik's winner.</p>
        <p>The goals by Gomez, last season's rookie of the year, were his first two of the season. Gomez said he had not worried about failing to score in the first nine games.</p>
        <p>''No one was down on me because I had not scored,'' he said. ''I knew it was going to happen. When you get so many opportunities like I did, it's due to come.''</p>
        <p>Olli Jokinen and Bret Hedican had two goals each, and Igor Larionov had the other goal for the Panthers against Brodeur, who faced 21 shots, including one in overtime. Brodeur allowed goals to Jokinen and Larionov on the first three shots as the Devils trailed, 2-0, before the game was three minutes old.</p>
        <p>He allowed two more goals, both to Hedican and both on the power play, before the first period reached the midway point.</p>
        <p>Gomez's goal at 10:48 of the first period completed the seven-goal frenzy.</p>
        <p>''We proved that we can play defense,'' Brodeur said, ''but when you allow goals like this, it's a concern.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>With JAY PANDOLFO's left shoulder healing very slowly, the Devils placed him on injured reserve Monday, retroactive to Oct. 14. . . . PETR SYKORA missed his third straight game with a groin problem. . . . WILLIE MITCHELL was scratched for the sixth consecutive game. . . . The game was the second of five in seven days for the Devils. They play host to Philadelphia on Wednesday night and play in Toronto on Thursday night before returning home for a Saturday afternoon game against Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
