<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Detection of Infant Deafness Is Vital</title>
    <meta content="31BROD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/science/31BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFDC1530F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Detection of Infant Deafness Is Vital</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody column says that unless newborns are tested for hearing loss, it is often not detected until child is 2 or 3, and fails to start talking; says such delays can permanently impair child's ability to learn to speak intelligibly and can result in long-lasting social, emotional and academic difficulties (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deafness is the most common disability present at birth. Every year, 12,000 American babies are born with moderate to severe hearing impairment and another 12,000 are born with lesser degrees of hearing loss.</p>
        <p>''A deaf newborn looks and acts like any other baby,'' said Dr. Andrew J. Schuman, adjunct professor of pediatrics at Dartmouth Medical School. There are rarely outward clues and, unless newborns are tested for hearing loss, it is often not detected until the child is 2 or 3 and fails to start talking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deafness is the most common disability present at birth. Every year, 12,000 American babies are born with moderate to severe hearing impairment and another 12,000 are born with lesser degrees of hearing loss.</p>
        <p>''A deaf newborn looks and acts like any other baby,'' said Dr. Andrew J. Schuman, adjunct professor of pediatrics at Dartmouth Medical School. There are rarely outward clues and, unless newborns are tested for hearing loss, it is often not detected until the child is 2 or 3 and fails to start talking.</p>
        <p>Such delays can permanently impair a child's ability to learn to speak intelligibly and can result in long-lasting social, emotional and academic difficulties.</p>
        <p>If a congenital hearing loss is not detected and corrected in the first months of life, the part of the brain that processes auditory signals fails to receive adequate stimulation and its development is likely to be permanently compromised. A delay of only six months can impede a child's language development, even with extensive rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Yet, despite the existence of a patchwork of legislation in 32 states mandating screening of newborns for hearing loss, fewer than half the newborns in this country have their hearing checked before they leave the hospital.</p>
        <p>Each day, 18 American newborns go home with a hearing impairment or profound deafness that neither their parents nor their doctors are aware of.</p>
        <p>Adding to the poignancy of the problem is that relatively inexpensive, easy-to-use and highly accurate devices for detecting hearing loss are available, as are treatments like hearing aids and cochlear implants that can restore hearing to near normal.</p>
        <p>Hearing Loss in Perspective</p>
        <p>In contrast to the 24,000 American babies born each year with significant hearing impairment, only 2,000 are born with cystic fibrosis, 800 are born with sickle cell disease, 800 are born with thyroid deficiency and 400 are born with phenylketonuria (PKU). Yet, standardized newborn screening programs exist throughout the country for all these disorders except hearing loss.</p>
        <p>Further, as noted by Dr. Schuman, who directs the screening at Elliot Hospital in Manchester, N.H., ''once the hospital buys the equipment, administering the test is not very costly -- about $30 a test, which is comparable to these other tests.''</p>
        <p>The estimated total cost involved in screening to detect each case of a hearing impaired newborn -- $9,600 -- is also well within the ballpark of these other disorders, he said. For example, it costs $6,000 to diagnose a single case of cystic fibrosis, $10,800 for thyroid deficiency, $23,000 for sickle cell anemia and $40,000 for PKU. And because it is much cheaper to rehabilitate a child whose hearing impairment is detected in infancy, screening programs for newborn hearing loss end up paying for themselves within a few years, according to advocates for universal screening.</p>
        <p>Seven years ago, a consensus panel convened by the National Institutes of Health concluded that the ''silent epidemic'' of severe hearing loss, warranted screening all newborns for hearing disorders, which affect one to three of every 1,000 babies born in this country. The panel also said that because as much as 30 percent of childhood hearing loss developed after the newborn period, periodic hearing screening should take place throughout childhood.</p>
        <p>Though professional groups were at first skeptical about these recommendations, in late 1994 universal newborn hearing screening was endorsed by the Joint Committee on Infant Hearing, made up of representatives of the American Academy of Pediatrics, the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association and the American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery.</p>
        <p>Since then, many states have passed laws establishing the circumstances and timetables for setting up screening programs, and at least 400 hospitals now have screening programs. But in many states, the laws exempt small hospitals and birthing centers or insist only that a majority of infants be tested. Those loopholes allow many hearing-impaired babies to fall through the cracks. The only way parents can know for sure if their babies have been tested is to ask.</p>
        <p>Although some experts insist that newborn testing be limited to children at high risk for hearing loss -- like those with family histories of the problem, low birth weight or those born with herpes infections -- this stipulation means that half of hearing-impaired babies will not be tested and will probably be missed.</p>
        <p>How Newborns Are Tested</p>
        <p>In recent years, several easy-to-use and painless screening tools have been marketed. With the most popular device, three electrodes placed on the baby's head automatically record brain wave activity in the auditory brain stem when a sound is played through earphones.</p>
        <p>It can be used on a sleeping newborn without disturbing the baby in any way. If an infant fails the test, it is repeated days or weeks later and, if the test is failed again, the baby is referred to an audiologist for more tests.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Dr. Schuman wrote in Contemporary Pediatrics, ''not all infants referred for evaluation after screening show up.'' He noted that in Colorado, ''as many as 50 percent may fail to do so.''</p>
        <p>Another screening device uses an ear probe to record ''evoked otoacoustic emissions'' -- tiny sounds made by cochlea hair cells when they are stimulated. One version costs about $5,000, uses earplugs that cost $1 and can be administered by a trained volunteer in a busy hospital nursery or doctor's office. Testing of both ears takes less than five minutes, Dr. Schuman said.</p>
        <p>Pediatricians with a testing device in the office can use it periodically to evaluate the hearing of patients who have repeated ear infections and fluid that remains lodged in the middle ear. If significant hearing impairment is detected, ear tubes may be recommended to unblock the ear canal until the child gets a little older.</p>
        <p>Parents, too, have a role to play. In addition to following through on recommended hearing checks, they should pay close attention to how the infant responds to sound. From birth to 3 months, a baby who can hear will react to loud sounds, be awakened by loud sounds, be soothed by a parent's voice, turn toward a parent when spoken to, smile when spoken to and seem to know the parents' voices.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Schuman cautioned that the usual clues used by parents and pediatricians to check a baby's hearing were unreliable. Even a baby with a severe hearing impairment may blink or act startled in response to a loud noise, like a loud clap. The baby reacts not to the noise itself but rather to vibrations set off by the noise. A hearing test is the only way to be sure an infant can hear normally.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
