<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blase About the Boom</title>
    <meta content="31DUNN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/opinion/31DUNN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunn, Robert M Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DD1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blase About the Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert M. Dunn Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunn, Robert M Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Robert M Dunn Jr says Vice Pres Al Gore is not getting bigger bounce from Clinton era's boom economy because many Americans only vaguely remember what it is like to be in serious recession, and young voters have never experienced one at all; says good times are increasingly being taken for granted, meaning incumbents are not getting credit for economic success these days; cites factors that could contribute to recession or two in next several years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some Democrats and pundits can't figure out why Al Gore isn't getting a bigger bounce from the Clinton era's boom economy. The implication is that the vice president isn't politically deft enough to capitalize on this huge advantage.</p>
        <p>But that's not the real reason why the economic conditions haven't favored Mr. Gore. The explanation is far simpler: many Americans only vaguely remember what it's like to be in a serious recession, and young voters have never experienced one at all. Good times are increasingly taken for granted, meaning that incumbents are not getting credit for economic success these days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some Democrats and pundits can't figure out why Al Gore isn't getting a bigger bounce from the Clinton era's boom economy. The implication is that the vice president isn't politically deft enough to capitalize on this huge advantage.</p>
        <p>But that's not the real reason why the economic conditions haven't favored Mr. Gore. The explanation is far simpler: many Americans only vaguely remember what it's like to be in a serious recession, and young voters have never experienced one at all. Good times are increasingly taken for granted, meaning that incumbents are not getting credit for economic success these days.</p>
        <p>From 1950 through 1982, the average business cycle was 4.2 years, with three years of growth often followed by one year of recession. The only sustained period of growth was from 1961 to 1969, but the accelerating inflation caused by the Vietnam War made those years far from painless. In every presidential election of the 30-year period, voters had a clear memory of bad times.</p>
        <p>These last 18 years have been very different. The United States has had almost two decades of strong economic growth, with only a shallow downturn in 1991. Voters now have to be almost 40 years old to have been adults during the recession of the early 1980's when unemployment was 9.6 percent. Many college students now think recessions are something that happened to their grandparents.</p>
        <p>Though of no solace to Mr. Gore, the perceived irrelevance of the business cycle to this year's presidential race is not permanent. Few if any economists believe the United States has repealed the business cycle. There is a recession out there waiting for us, whether the stock market's current problems augur one or not.</p>
        <p>We should be concerned, for example, that American families have been spending money beyond their incomes and that debt service costs are now at a record as a share of disposable income. If people decide to curtail their spending, or if banks find it prudent to stop lending them money, a recession will follow. Another source of concern is our high trade deficit, and our borrowing of hundreds of billions of dollars a year from the rest of the world to finance it. If foreign investors ever decided to stop lending here, the exchange rate for the dollar would plummet, and the higher costs for foreign goods could worsen inflation. The Federal Reserve would have to raise interest rates to control it.</p>
        <p>A recession or two in the next several years will mean the business cycle has returned to normal, and politicians' fortunes will once again be tied to economic ups and downs. The next president might actually benefit from recession in 2001 and 2002, if it were followed by a strong recovery in 2003 and 2004. Memories of recession would be fresh, and the recovery of the two years before the election greatly appreciated.</p>
        <p>Robert M. Dunn Jr. is a professor of economics at George Washington University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert M. Dunn Jr. is a professor of economics at George Washington University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
