<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Ask Nader to Back Gore in Swing States</title>
    <meta content="Y31NAD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/politics/31NADE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DD1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Ask Nader to Back Gore in Swing States</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Liberal Democrats begin aggressive campaign to urge Green Party candidate Ralph Nader to endorse Vice Pres Al Gore in important swing states; also ratchet up criticisms of Nader; warn him and advisers that his legacy among Democrats on Capitol Hill and elsewhere will be one of bitter resentment if Gore loses narrowly to Gov George W Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liberal Democrats have begun an aggressive campaign to urge Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate for president, to endorse Vice President Al Gore in important swing states. At the same time, many of those liberals have ratcheted up their criticism of Mr. Nader, saying he is not interested in abortion, gay or civil rights.</p>
        <p>The liberals say they have sharpened their once-polite attacks on Mr. Nader because they have given up any hope of persuading him to drop out of the race. Instead, they have begun warning Mr. Nader and his advisers that his legacy among Democrats on Capitol Hill and elsewhere will be one of bitter resentment if Mr. Gore loses narrowly to Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Liberal Democrats have begun an aggressive campaign to urge Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate for president, to endorse Vice President Al Gore in important swing states. At the same time, many of those liberals have ratcheted up their criticism of Mr. Nader, saying he is not interested in abortion, gay or civil rights.</p>
        <p>The liberals say they have sharpened their once-polite attacks on Mr. Nader because they have given up any hope of persuading him to drop out of the race. Instead, they have begun warning Mr. Nader and his advisers that his legacy among Democrats on Capitol Hill and elsewhere will be one of bitter resentment if Mr. Gore loses narrowly to Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''I've tried very carefully to convey to Nader supporters our highest regard for his career,'' said Ralph G. Neas, the president of People for the American Way. ''But I want him and his supporters to know how history will view him in the final analysis if he gives the Supreme Court to the right wing.''</p>
        <p>A number of Democrats who have worked with Mr. Nader over the years said today that they had been calling their friends in Mr. Nader's inner circle, urging them to persuade Mr. Nader to throw his support behind Mr. Gore in closely contested states like Oregon, Washington, Minnesota, Wisconsin and New Mexico.</p>
        <p>The idea would be to allow Mr. Nader to continue his push for 5 percent of the national vote -- which would entitle the Green Party to federal matching funds in 2004 -- while also helping Mr. Gore win enough electoral votes to defeat Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Much of the effort seemed focused on Joan Claybrook, who is the president of Public Citizen, a group Mr. Nader founded, and one of his oldest and closest friends.</p>
        <p>Former Representative Toby Moffett, who worked with Mr. Nader during the 1970's, said that he spoke with Ms. Claybrook last week and that she expressed interest in trying to get Mr. Nader to help Mr. Gore in strategic states.</p>
        <p>''She said she was worried about the possibility that Ralph could help elect Bush,'' Mr. Moffett said.</p>
        <p>But in an interview this evening, Ms. Claybrook said she had never seriously considered raising the idea with Mr. Nader.</p>
        <p>''It would be a waste of my time,'' Ms. Claybrook said. ''He's one of the most stubborn people in the United States.''</p>
        <p>Asked if she thought Mr. Nader's campaign might help elect Mr. Bush, she replied, ''I don't know.'' She added, ''I don't think anyone envisioned it would come down to this close of a race.''</p>
        <p>Theresa Amato, Mr. Nader's campaign manager, called the efforts to get Mr. Nader to work with Mr. Gore in certain states, ''frivolous and diversionary.''</p>
        <p>''People should vote their conscience and for who they believe in,'' Ms. Amato said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader has no plans to scale back his campaigning, with scheduled stops this week in three fiercely contested states, Michigan, Minnesota and Wisconsin, as well as in California, where he has cut into Mr. Gore's lead. His campaign also said it would unveil a new television commercial on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>On another front, Democrats in Congress who have worked closely with Mr. Nader, led by Representative Jan Schakowsky, Democrat of Illinois, have begun circulating a letter to Mr. Nader urging him to help Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''The prospect of waking up on November 8 to a Bush presidency is too dangerous for too many,'' the letter says. ''Ralph, do not let your candidacy be the reason for that to happen. Ask your supporters in swing states to vote for Al Gore.''</p>
        <p>Although the letter compliments Mr. Nader as an inspiration, some liberals in Congress and elsewhere have begun delivering a more threatening message.</p>
        <p>''If he succeeds and destroys the Gore candidacy, how many progressive congressmen will be prepared to take Joan Claybrook's telephone calls?'' asked Jack Blum, counsel to Americans for Democratic Action, a liberal lobbying group.</p>
        <p>The National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League and a group of female Democratic members of Congress also plan to hold a news conference on Wednesday in Washington to attack Mr. Nader for remarks he made Sunday on the ABC program ''This Week.''</p>
        <p>In response to a question about whether the election of Mr. Bush might lead to the overturning of the landmark case legalizing abortion, Mr. Nader said, ''Even if Roe vs. Wade is reversed, that doesn't end it. It just reverts it back to the states.''</p>
        <p>Representative Nita Lowey, Democrat of New York, called Mr. Nader's answer ''irresponsible and outrageous.''</p>
        <p>''Nader may be dismissive of the right to choose, but we are not,'' Ms. Lowey said. ''Many states would be poised to criminalize abortion immediately, if only given the chance.''</p>
        <p>Other liberal Democrats and organizations have argued that Mr. Nader has not been active in advocating gay rights.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Nader will come under attack from an old ally, Representative John Conyers Jr., Democrat of Michigan, in the next issue of The Nation. In a letter to the editor, Mr. Conyers contends that Mr. Nader has a weak record on women's rights, gun control and civil rights.</p>
        <p>''Gore is far more qualified to shepherd progressive causes than is Nader,'' Mr. Conyers asserts in the letter.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
