<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Nasdaq, Dow and New Principles of Physics for Wall Street</title>
    <meta content="Y31PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/business/31PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq 100-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5DE1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Nasdaq, Dow and New Principles of Physics for Wall Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on strong divergent moves in Dow Jones industrial average and Nasdaq composite index on Oct 30, the third such time this year that markets moved in such divergent direction; notes first two signaled that Nasdaq was in for very heavy selling in weeks that followed; says strength of Dow on Oct 30 was all the more impressive because it was so widespread; holds Nasdaq fall has not been monolithic one; Nasdaq 100 has done even worse than overall composite index, falling 3 percent on Oct 30 and 10.9 percent since Oct 20; Bloomberg Financial Markets says 47 of those 100 stocks rose Oct 30, and 40 of them are up since Oct 20; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stock market soared yesterday. It also plunged.</p>
        <p>So it is in the weird world of Wall Street, circa 2000. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 2.3 percent, while the Nasdaq composite index fell 2.7 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stock market soared yesterday. It also plunged.</p>
        <p>So it is in the weird world of Wall Street, circa 2000. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 2.3 percent, while the Nasdaq composite index fell 2.7 percent.</p>
        <p>Such strong divergent moves were virtually unheard of before this year, but this is the third such one in 2000. The first two signaled that the Nasdaq market was in for some very heavy selling in the weeks that followed.</p>
        <p>The first two days with opposite 2 percent moves this year came on March 15 and April 3. The first of those moves was  just days after the Nasdaq composite peaked and now appears to have presaged the change of leadership in the market, in which the once-hot technology stocks began to fall while other stocks, rooted in the old economy, began to attract investor attention. The second move came as the spring sell-off of Nasdaq stocks, with particular attention to dot-coms, began in earnest.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's contrary motion of the Dow and the Nasdaq continued a trend that began last week, though there had been no recent day with such stark contrasts as yesterday. Since Oct. 20, a period of six trading days, the Dow is up 6 percent, or more than 600 points. Over the same stretch, the Nasdaq composite is down 8.4 percent, a fall of nearly 300 points.</p>
        <p>The strength of the Dow yesterday was all the more impressive because it was so widespread. Of the 30 stocks in the index, 26 were up, with Intel, I.B.M., General Motors and Procter &amp; Gamble the only exceptions. Since Oct. 20, only five are down, with the worst performer being AT&amp;T, off 16 percent as investors reacted with scorn to its planned breakup. The three best Dow performers over the stretch were Alcoa, International Paper and Eastman Kodak, all firmly rooted in the so-called old economy.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq fall has not been a monolithic one. The Nasdaq 100, which consists of 100 very large stocks traded on Nasdaq, has done even worse than has the overall Nasdaq composite, falling 3 percent yesterday and 10.9 percent since Oct. 20. And yet 47 of those 100 stocks rose yesterday, and 40 of them are up since Oct. 20, according to calculations by Bloomberg Financial Markets.</p>
        <p>While the Nasdaq market has suffered this year, there have been some technology stocks that largely escaped the spring carnage and continued to rise as investors focused on Internet infrastructure plays, bidding some of those stocks to new heights on the theory that they were sure to prosper even if dot-coms did not.</p>
        <p>Now, some of the highest fliers are starting to fall. Within the Nasdaq 100, the three worst performers since Oct. 20 are Ciena, Applied Micro Circuits and SDL, with each of them having lost at least a third of their value. Yet even after those falls, each of them is trading more than twice as high as it was at the end of 1999. The stock price of Ciena, the worst performer of the lot since Oct. 20, is still three times what it was at the beginning of this year.</p>
        <p>The worst performer yesterday within the Nasdaq 100 was Network Appliance, down 13.7 percent. So far this year, it is up 155 percent.</p>
        <p>The optical equipment stocks -- a category that includes many of the worst Nasdaq performers the last week -- have been damaged by reports that growth in the business was not as fast as expected. While business is still good, it is not as good as investors had expected, and with weakened growth prospects there are questions as to whether huge multiples are deserved. Ciena, for example, is trading at 293 times estimated profits for this year.</p>
        <p>Network Appliance is in the business of producing data storage devices, a booming business as companies seek to store more and more data for Internet users. But it too has seen growth estimates decline, which can be dangerous for a high-multiple stock. It now trades at 266 times estimated earnings.</p>
        <p>When the Nasdaq was soaring earlier this year, there were days when it lifted off while the overall market was doing little -- if anything. In February, there were three days when the Nasdaq composite posted gains of more than 2.7 percent and the Dow fell, with the largest discrepancy on Feb. 23, when the Dow lost 0.8 percent while the Nasdaq rose 3.8 percent.</p>
        <p>Then on April 27 and 28, the Nasdaq climbed almost 4 percent and 2.3 percent, while the Dow was falling 0.5 percent and 1.4 percent. That set off hopes among Nasdaq investors that the decline was over, but the Nasdaq soon fell back.</p>
        <p>The only such day with very large divergent moves before this year was Oct. 20, 1987, the day after the 1987 crash, when the Dow rebounded 5.9 percent while the Nasdaq composite fell 9 percent. But that divergence was an indication not of varying investor perceptions but of the fact that the Nasdaq market had virtually shut down the day before, as market makers did not answer their telephones and the reported prices of many Nasdaq stocks, while down sharply, were well above where they would have traded in the panic of that day. For the two days combined, the Dow was down 18.1 percent, while the Nasdaq fell 19.3 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
