<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Week to Go: Franks and Corzine in a Hotter Race</title>
    <meta content="31JERS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/politics/31JERS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3DA1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Week to Go: Franks and Corzine in a Hotter Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY with MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert; Newman, Maria</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGETON, N.J., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon S Corzine opens last full week of campaigning with three-county swing through South Jersey in effort to attract independent and undecided voters; his Republican opponent, Repr Robert D Franks, embarks on bus tour through northern and central New Jersey; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jon S. Corzine opened his last full week of campaigning for the United States Senate today with a three-county swing through South Jersey that he described as part of a ''real chase'' for independent and undecided voters.</p>
        <p>And in northern and central New Jersey, his Republican opponent, Representative Bob Franks, continued the bus tour he began Friday, trading in his old bus for the one used in the year's most celebrated bid for independent votes, the Straight Talk Express formerly used by Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jon S. Corzine opened his last full week of campaigning for the United States Senate today with a three-county swing through South Jersey that he described as part of a ''real chase'' for independent and undecided voters.</p>
        <p>And in northern and central New Jersey, his Republican opponent, Representative Bob Franks, continued the bus tour he began Friday, trading in his old bus for the one used in the year's most celebrated bid for independent votes, the Straight Talk Express formerly used by Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>Both campaigns have become nearly round-the-clock affairs since last week, when a poll showed Mr. Corzine's lead narrowing. Over the last two days, Mr. Franks also received the endorsements of the editorial boards of three newspapers: The Asbury Park Press and The Record of Hackensack, on Sunday, and The New York Post today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's staff and local Democratic leaders planned 12 1/2 hours of campaigning today -- including a tour of a book-printing company and a visit to a 500-acre farm -- that provided him plenty of interaction with unionized workers, the elderly, shoppers and Democratic Party workers.</p>
        <p>Tom Shea, Mr. Corzine's spokesman, said the candidate came to South Jersey because the region was often neglected by candidates in statewide elections. ''We're fighting for votes in every part of the state,'' Mr. Shea said. ''We are not conceding anything.''</p>
        <p>The swing went smoothly, save for a few unplanned exchanges at an 11-story residence for the elderly here in this Cumberland County town.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Corzine took several questions from a dozen residents in the lobby, Joseph Spagnola, 67, asked him for his position on the desecration of the American flag. Moments later, Suzanne Reeves, 64, made Mr. Corzine blush with an abrupt question about his marital status.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spagnola, who said later that he served in the Army in Korea and in the Air Force in Vietnam, told Mr. Corzine that he supported candidates who favor a constitutional amendment banning the burning or other destruction of the flag. He asked Mr. Corzine where he stood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine seemed surprised by the question, but told Mr. Spagnola that though he believed in ''protecting the flag,'' he did not support an anti-desecration amendment. ''I believe the reason we protect the flag is to protect free speech and the rights that are embedded in our Constitution,'' said Mr. Corzine, who served in the Marine Corps Reserves from 1969 to 1975.</p>
        <p>''I disagree,'' Mr. Spagnola said.</p>
        <p>''I understand,'' Mr. Corzine answered calmly.</p>
        <p>As the candidate started to leave the lobby, Ms. Reeves approached with a question of her own.</p>
        <p>''Are you married?'' she asked, none too sweetly.</p>
        <p>The response came quickly from Mr. Corzine, 53. ''I've been married for 32 years to a woman I sat next to in kindergarten,'' he said, blushing. He also said he has three children, ages 30, 24 and 18.</p>
        <p>Then, with a glance toward Mr. Spagnola, he said, ''I do believe in loyalty.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Franks and his bus attracted newfound attention. In Union, he traded in his old campaign bus for the one used by Mr. McCain in his unsuccessful bid for the Republican presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>At the Tick-Tock Diner in Clifton, Denise Cleary, a seventh-grade teacher in Nutley, stopped at the diner when she saw Mr. Franks's bus, hoping to meet him, she said.  She went inside and wished him luck, saying she was turned off by Mr. Corzine's heavy campaign spending.</p>
        <p>''I think Jon Corzine is trying to buy the election,'' she said. ''It's kind of sickening. If he has so much money, pour it into the schools. Kids are in overcrowded classrooms.''</p>
        <p>Not that many days ago, Mr. Franks could barely draw a crowd to his events, and diner patrons looked at him almost blankly when he told them he was running for the Senate. Now, with his poll numbers up, with new money from the national Republican Party and with some major newspaper endorsements, the crowds at his appearances are bigger and more people come up to say they support him.</p>
        <p>''What we're going to test on Nov. 7 is a very simple proposition: whether or not one can actually buy a seat in the United States Senate,'' he told supporters at a rally in Belleville. ''I with every fiber in my body believe that New Jersey voters are not for sale.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks began his day just after dawn, greeting train commuters in Middletown, Monmouth County, and then moving on to several diners and a news conference in Bound Brook. Along the way, he ran into many party members, but also some voters who said they have recently been swayed to support him.</p>
        <p>At the Tick-Tock Diner, Ted Friedrich, a stockbroker from Clifton, told Mr. Franks that he was somewhat undecided, even though he usually votes for Democrats. He said he was definitely voting for Al Gore, and might vote for Mr. Franks.</p>
        <p>''I told him I would probably vote for him for the same reasons I will not vote for Bush,'' Mr. Friedrich said. ''Bush didn't go through the process. He didn't pay his dues and you have, I told him. And Jon Corzine didn't, either.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
