<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pepsico Buys a 90% Stake in South Beach Beverage</title>
    <meta content="Y31PEPS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/business/31PEPS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">South Beach Beverage Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pepsico Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Greg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD61530F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pepsico Buys a 90% Stake in South Beach Beverage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG WINTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winter, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pepsico acquires 90 percent stake in South Beach Beverage Co, small but fast-growing manufacturer that makes SoBe juice and tea drinks, for $370 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the end of September, as the Coca-Cola Company wavered over purchasing a stake in the South Beach Beverage Company, the small but fast-growing manufacturer that makes SoBe juice and tea drinks, Wall Street analysts started getting a bit impatient with the cola giant's prolonged indecision.</p>
        <p>''It's time to move on and act today,'' urged Bill Pecoriello, a Sanford Bernstein analyst. ''If Coke doesn't buy SoBe, Pepsi or Cadbury will.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the end of September, as the Coca-Cola Company wavered over purchasing a stake in the South Beach Beverage Company, the small but fast-growing manufacturer that makes SoBe juice and tea drinks, Wall Street analysts started getting a bit impatient with the cola giant's prolonged indecision.</p>
        <p>''It's time to move on and act today,'' urged Bill Pecoriello, a Sanford Bernstein analyst. ''If Coke doesn't buy SoBe, Pepsi or Cadbury will.''</p>
        <p>The warning went unheeded. And yesterday Pepsico said it bought a 90 percent stake in South Beach, based in Wallingford, Conn., for $370 million in cash, beating its rival again in one of the most dynamic segments of the beverage industry. Sales of SoBe's herb-laden ''elixirs,'' with names like Edge, Power and Tsunami, have jumped to $225 million this year from $1.2 million in 1996.</p>
        <p>Though the deal is small in numerical terms -- SoBe is expected to sell just 42 million cases this year, a mere trickle of the 3.1 billion cases of soda Pepsico sells in the United States each year -- analysts regard it as a symbol of how the dueling soft drink companies are adapting to sweeping changes in consumer tastes and buying habits.</p>
        <p>With sales growth flat in domestic soda, investors are pressuring soft drink companies to gain a foothold in the noncarbonated drink business, a category that has been posting double-digit gains for the last few years and represents the only significant source of growth in the nonalcoholic beverage industry.</p>
        <p>Cadbury Schweppes, traditionally the industry's distant third-place finisher, jumped ahead of the curve last month when it bought Snapple and Mistic from Triarc. And while Coke has been criticized for tarrying, hesitant to venture too far from the bubbly brews that have made it the king of the cola business, Pepsi has raced headlong into the noncarbonated market, recasting itself as a ''total refreshment'' company.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Pepsi introduced Aquafina, its bottled water brand, two years ahead of Dasani, Coke's answer in the field. Now Aquafina is the best-selling brand of ''single-serving'' bottled water, a market that grew 30 percent last year; Dasani sits in eighth place.</p>
        <p>Pepsico has also secured the lead in domestic iced tea sales with its Lipton Brisk commanding 32.5 percent of the market, compared with a 23.5 percent share for Coke's Nestea brand. In the coffee category the story is the same: Frappuccino, Pepsi's joint venture with Starbucks, outsells all others, while Coke has yet to roll out a national version.</p>
        <p>Many investors applauded Coke's interest in purchasing a minority stake in South Beach Beverage, and had eagerly anticipated a three-way deal with J. W. Childs, a private equity firm, since the companies began talks nearly six months ago. But the negotiations became mired in concerns that the Federal Trade Commission might object to the industry's biggest company owning another brand.</p>
        <p>''We're so small in the grand scheme of things I don't see why there should be any concern at all,'' said John Bello, co-founder and chief executive of South Beach. ''But it just kept dragging on and on.''</p>
        <p>Another sticking point in the talks were the health claims that helped build SoBe's image as a New Age drink distinct from Coke and other sodas. In February, the Food and Drug Administration warned Mr. Bello that several SoBe product labels carried exaggerated claims. The label on Lizard Blizzard, for example, said the drink was ''loaded with nature's most powerful cold and flu fighters,'' a statement the F.D.A. said it would allow only on a drug that had undergone extensive testing.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Bello said that South Beach Beverage revamped its packaging about four months ago to comply with the F.D.A. guidelines. And though some analysts criticized it for being overly cautious, Coke let its option to buy a stake in South Beach Beverage pass at the end of last month. With the door open, Pepsi officials almost immediately began talks with the company, which they had been looking at for more than a year.</p>
        <p>Pepsi officials said they felt confident that the F.D.A. issues were resolved, adding that SoBe's marketing might become even more daring to try to increase sales roughly 300 percent in the next three years.</p>
        <p>''That doesn't mean there couldn't be a bump in the road,'' said Gary Rodkin, Pepsi's North American president and chief executive. Mr. Rodkin added that South Beach would continue to operate as an independent company, ''but we're going to have a guard rails in place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
