<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DB1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Barak Reopens Parliament, And Orders New Strikes  Prime Minister Ehud Barak told returning legislators that he had ''left no stone unturned'' in pursuit of peace, but that Yasir Arafat had proved not to be a ''partner for peace'' and that Israelis must unite in a time of crisis. Hours later, he ordered missile attacks on Palestinian leadership offices after an Israeli man's bound and mutilated body was found at the edge of East Jerusalem, and a Palestinian gunman killed an Israeli security guard and wounded another in the city itself.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Barak Reopens Parliament, And Orders New Strikes  Prime Minister Ehud Barak told returning legislators that he had ''left no stone unturned'' in pursuit of peace, but that Yasir Arafat had proved not to be a ''partner for peace'' and that Israelis must unite in a time of crisis. Hours later, he ordered missile attacks on Palestinian leadership offices after an Israeli man's bound and mutilated body was found at the edge of East Jerusalem, and a Palestinian gunman killed an Israeli security guard and wounded another in the city itself.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Iraq to Resume Some Flights  Iraqi Airways, whose planes have been grounded much of the time since the Persian Gulf war in 1991, will resume domestic flights on Sunday, Iraqi news reports said.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Navy Orders Caution in Suez  Navy ships have been under orders to avoid the Suez Canal since Oct. 12, when 17 sailors were killed in the bombing of the destroyer Cole in Yemen, out of fear of another terrorist attack, senior officials said.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Madrid Car Bomb Kills 3  Gen. Jose Francisco Querol, a Spanish Supreme Court justice, was killed with his driver and bodyguard by a car bomb in Madrid. There was no claim of responsibility, but the attack followed the pattern of the Basque separatist group E.T.A.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Cuba-Venezuela Oil Alliance  Officials signed an agreement for Venezuela to supply one-third of Cuba's oil needs at cut-rate prices. The deal came at the end of Fidel Castro's five-day visit to Caracas.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Success for Kosovo Albanian  Ibrahim Rugova, who led his people on a 10-year campaign of peaceful protest for independence from Serbia, led his party to victory in 21 of 27 contested municipal elections on Saturday, results confirmed.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Protests After Zanzibar Vote  Police officers in Zanzibar, a part of Tanzania, opened fire on rock-throwing demonstrators protesting elections over incomplete or no ballot deliveries to numerous districts.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-25</p>
        <p>Bush Is Pushing Hard To Take California  Gov. George W. Bush campaigned in California instead of more closely contested Midwestern states, portraying Vice President Al Gore as someone who practices the ''politics of division'' and suggesting the Republicans would carry the state, a cornerstone of the last two Democratic Presidential victories.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and the Republican Party spent $5.5 million on television commercials in California since June 1. Mr. Gore and the Democrats spent no money on television there.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney said Vice President Gore was ''not up to the task'' of being commander in chief.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Liberal Pressure on Nader  Liberal Democrats want Ralph Nader to endorse Al Gore in swing states, even as many liberals assail Mr. Nader as uninterested in abortion or gay and civil rights.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore promised that as president he would hold an average of one open meeting a week with ordinary citizens and would not add a single extra job to the federal government.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman is in excellent health and has no condition that would bar his serving as vice president, he and his doctors said.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Succession in Missouri  Jean Carnahan, whose husband, Gov. Mel Carnahan, was killed in a plane crash this month, said she would accept gubernatorial appointment to the Senate in his place if voters chose his name over that of the Republican incumbent, Senator John Ashcroft, as polls suggest just may happen.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Vetoes Spending Bill  Intensifying the budget battle, President Clinton vetoed an $18.1 billion spending bill that finances the operations of the Treasury Department, the White House and Congress.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Weighs Secrecy Bill  Administration officials said there was sharp division over whether President Clinton should veto a bill that would tighten the lid of secrecy on government information.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Survey on Interfaith Marriage  Most American Jews accept marriages between Jews and non-Jews, in contrast with the positions held by many rabbis, a survey by the American Jewish Committee found.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-11</p>
        <p>Verdict Is Overturned In Death of Firefighter  A judge in Queens set aside the 1996 conviction of Edwin Smith, a homeless parolee convicted of arson and murder in an apparently accidental fire that killed a firefighter. The judge ruled a defense lawyer did not offer adequate advice on several plea offers from the prosecution.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Parade Honors Yankees  Hundreds of thousands of people jammed Lower Manhattan to throw confetti and cheer the Yankees for their World Series triumph.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Plan to Gain CUNY Prestige  Chancellor Matthew Goldstein is seeking to raise the status of select CUNY programs to levels of national prominence, but not to consolidate them on one star campus.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Nursing Home Violations  Congressional investigators found widespread violations of federal health and safety standards at nursing homes in California, Illinois, New Jersey, New York and Texas.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Work on New Hepatitis Vaccine  Researchers said they had moved a step closer to making an edible vaccine against hepatitis B, a potentially deadly virus that infects millions.</p>
        <p>F3</p>
        <p>Deadly Game  Some biologists say American hunters should be warned about a malady similar to mad cow disease that has infected wild deer and elk in parts of Colorado and Wyoming.</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-24</p>
        <p>Americans in Paris  The strong United States economy and dollar are leading about 12.4 million Americans to Europe this year, a 6 percent increase over 1999 and the eighth straight year of record traffic to Europe, according to the European Travel Commission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Automaker Signals Turnaround  Nissan Motor reported a solid half-year profit, the first evidence of a turnaround in the carmaker's fortunes since Renault rescued it from insolvency last year. Nissan also more than quadrupled projections for profits this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bailing Out of Globalstar  Investors fled the already beaten down stock and bonds of Globalstar Telecommunications, the Bermuda-based operating arm of the satellite phone company Globalstar. The exodus followed disappointing third-quarter earnings and remarks by Bernard L. Schwartz, the Loral chairman and chief executive, saying his company, a major investor, would make no further sacrifices to bail out the $4.3 billion venture.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Two-Way Street  The Dow gained 2.3 percent, or 245.15 points, to 10,835.77, while the Nasdaq fell 2.7 percent, or 86.96 points, to 3,191.40. The S.&amp; P. 500 rose 1.4 percent, or 19.08 points, to 1,398.66.</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1-8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: A report card on attack politics; Europe's last tyrant; for Congress from Connecticut.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
