<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Major Medical Mystery: Why People Avoid Doctors</title>
    <meta content="31FEAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/science/31FEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epstein, Randi Hutter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DD1530F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Major Medical Mystery: Why People Avoid Doctors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDI HUTTER EPSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Epstein, Randi Hutter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sociologists and medical clinicians seeking to bolster preventive medicine are trying to figure out why so many people are reluctant to see a doctor; public health experts agree that many people who have money, health insurance and access to good medical centers are choosing not to go for checkups; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Janet Grillo eats organic food, does not smoke or drink and keeps abreast of the latest health news. Yet Ms. Grillo, a 41-year-old independent film producer in Los Angeles, cannot remember the last time she had a complete physical exam, probably when her mother took her to a pediatrician.</p>
        <p>''If I'm feeling sick, it's echinacea and early to bed. I think part of the reason I never go is because I get a yearly gynecologic exam and mistake that for accounting for all of my key organs,'' Ms. Grillo said. ''I know it doesn't make sense, but who has time? My own health care lags far behind that of my son.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Janet Grillo eats organic food, does not smoke or drink and keeps abreast of the latest health news. Yet Ms. Grillo, a 41-year-old independent film producer in Los Angeles, cannot remember the last time she had a complete physical exam, probably when her mother took her to a pediatrician.</p>
        <p>''If I'm feeling sick, it's echinacea and early to bed. I think part of the reason I never go is because I get a yearly gynecologic exam and mistake that for accounting for all of my key organs,'' Ms. Grillo said. ''I know it doesn't make sense, but who has time? My own health care lags far behind that of my son.''</p>
        <p>Hank Norman's track record is not much better. Mr. Norman, 33, a television producer in New York City, avoided doctors for years until his new girlfriend insisted that he get a checkup for sexually transmitted diseases. ''I guess I grew up with the mentality that your body heals itself and it's a sign of weakness to go to a doctor,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wende Logan-Young, a breast cancer specialist, says her own mother-in-law hid a breast lump for five years, until cancer killed her. ''When she found the lump, she did not tell anyone and stopped going to her internist,'' said Dr. Logan-Young, director of the Elizabeth Wende Breast Clinic in Rochester. ''I would say to her, 'Why don't you come in for a mammogram?' But she would just change the subject. It wasn't until she had severe diarrhea and lost 15 pounds that her husband, an internist, forced her to see a doctor. By that time, she was diagnosed with metastatic breast cancer that had spread to her colon. She died six months later.''</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, at a time when consumers are bombarded with more health information than ever before -- much of it urging early detection and preventive care -- stories like these are increasingly common. Nobody knows how many people put off medical visits or whether it is harmful for most people. There are no national statistics tracking delays in care. But public health experts agree that scores of people who have money, health insurance and access to good medical centers are choosing not to go for checkups. To be sure, there are those who run to the doctor for every sniffle, but there is a whole other group that simply never goes.</p>
        <p>And now, a few sociologists and clinicians, aiming to bolster preventive services, are trying to figure out why so many people are reluctant to see a doctor. They are studying very different groups: those like Ms. Grillo who do not have the time or feel the necessity and those like Dr. Logan-Young's mother-in-law, who apparently cannot bear the possibility of grim news.</p>
        <p>So what is the barrier? Are people flooded with so much health information that they feel no need to go in person when they can easily click to a dot.com doctor? Are they frightened by the medical horror stories on the evening news? Or are they just too busy juggling work and children to make an appointment for every ache?</p>
        <p>All of the above, and more. Recent studies have shown that people who know they have health-endangering vices (like smoking or drinking) put off appointments because they do not want a healthy-living lecture. Others do not go because they feel doomed despite medical treatment. At the other extreme are the overly optimistic who are convinced they will get better no matter what. And then there are those who are embarrassed to discuss their symptoms, such as incontinence or impotence.</p>
        <p>The bottom line for many people is fear: fear of bad news, fear of an uncomfortable test, fear of discussing something intimate.</p>
        <p>And the reason for this dread of the doctor, experts say, has much to do with the breakdown of doctor-patient relationships. Few people nowadays have an old-fashioned family practitioner, the physician who is also friend and confidant.</p>
        <p>The American College of Physicians-American Society of Internal Medicine recommends annual medical visits for everyone beginning at the age of 40. Yearly visit for younger adults is probably not cost-effective, but checkups are helpful, said Dr. William J. Hall, president-elect of the physicians' association. ''It behooves everyone,'' said Dr. Hall, who is also chief of the general medicine unit at Strong Memorial Hospital in Rochester, ''to have a database of health information assembled. It's more like insurance than going because a doctor is likely to find something.''</p>
        <p>The biggest danger, he said, is to go with a new complaint to a new doctor, who may not put the symptoms in the right context.</p>
        <p>Many doctors interviewed blamed managed care for chasing patients away, pointing to overburdened physicians with no time to listen to patients and to patients uncomfortable talking to their assigned doctors.</p>
        <p>Though patients tend to show up for prepaid physicals, many health experts wonder whether they are revealing all of their symptoms or health concerns.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea of the fee used to be an  excuse; that was one of the reasons H.M.O.'s were set up, to remove the barrier so people wouldn't delay (medical visits), but it hasn't helped as much as it might,'' said Dr. Edward Krupat, a professor of psychology at the Massachusetts College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences in Boston. ''A lot of people are treated in a clinic model where you see a different person each time, and they may not feel comfortable with that practitioner.''</p>
        <p>Others say the problem has more to do with today's transient society. People change jobs, and insurance plans, forcing them to switch doctors.</p>
        <p>''The stability of the doctor-patient relationship, which is so much the core of trust, is not what it once was,'' said Dr. Robert J. Mayer, professor at Harvard Medical School and vice chairman for academic affairs at the Dana Farber Cancer Institute. ''That is a reflection not just on economics but on changing society. People move; doctors move; and all of these factors, that perhaps in an 'Ozzie and Harriet' day would have been less likely to have taken place, are commonplace now.''</p>
        <p>Hank Norman, the television producer, says he no longer has a doctor he can turn to.</p>
        <p>''I grew up in a small town in Maryland, and Dr. Roth was our family doctor,'' he said. ''I remember calling him in the middle of the night. We called him if we stubbed our toe. Now it's an assembly line; I don't know the doctor, and he doesn't know me.''</p>
        <p>About one in three men and one in five women have no regular doctor, a survey of 4,350 Americans projected. Money was a big concern, but beyond that, denial and embarrassment played a role, particularly for men, said Karen Davis, the president of the Commonwealth Fund, the social and health care research foundation in New York City that paid for the survey.</p>
        <p>Sonny Mehta, president and editor in chief of Random House's Knopf publishing group, had not seen a doctor for five years before having triple-bypass heart surgery in July. In an interview with a British newspaper, Mr. Mehta conceded that he avoided doctors because he knew they would discuss his years of ''bad living.''</p>
        <p>''I've always had a good time,'' Mr. Mehta said, ''maybe too good of a time.''</p>
        <p>Previous studies have shown that if patients are unable to express their concerns to a doctor they are not likely to follow the doctor's advice or return for further checkups, said Dr. Samuel Putnam, an internist in  Boston and co-author of ''The Medical Interview.'' He pointed to a study by Dr. Richard Frankel and colleagues that found most doctors interrupted patients 18 seconds into an interview. The findings were published in 1984 in The Annals of Internal Medicine.</p>
        <p>A study of 10,000 patients at the Kaiser Permanente Medical Care Program in Oakland, Calif., found that those who chose their physician were more satisfied with their care and made more outpatient appointments, said Dr. Joe Selby, the director of research at the Oakland branch of Kaiser. The results were published in the November 1991, issue of The Journal of the American Medical Association.</p>
        <p>Now Dr. Selby is tracking 1,400 patients to ''explore the best way to help people choose doctors so they  will come when they need help and be compliant with their treatment.''</p>
        <p>''At least in the long run, you would expect a better health outcome,'' he said.</p>
        <p>No one looks to be scolded about losing weight, smoking or drinking. One woman commented that her husband, a diabetic, had not been to a doctor in years because he had yet to lose 10 pounds that a doctor told him to shed.</p>
        <p>''It's a challenge, but we have to be able to have a positive supportive  relationship with patients without being judgmental or intimidating,'' said Dr. Leo Cooney, chief of general medicine at the Yale School of Medicine. ''We have to help patients deal with problems, whether it be smoking, drinking or substance abuse without having a holier-than-thou attitude and condemn them.''</p>
        <p>Focus groups by the What to Expect Foundation, an organization providing prenatal and early childhood support to low-income women, found that the greatest barrier keeping the women from seeking free prenatal care was their substance abuse or smoking.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lisa Cooper, an assistant professor at Johns Hopkins medical school, was prompted to investigate patient delays after a woman kept missing appointments and later admitted she was embarrassed to show up because she was an alcoholic.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cooper then surveyed 963 people with ailments, including hypertension, diabetes, heart disease and cancer. She found that alcoholics were three times as likely as others  to avoid regular care, and those with phobic disorders were about half as likely to return for treatment. She has yet to identify specific phobias involved or to explore why phobias prevent people from seeking treatment, but she speculates that they are more likely to fear bad news.</p>
        <p>Gael Morse, 57, a writer from Rochester, said media campaigns about cancer backfired with her. She delayed getting a mammogram for six years. ''I can't listen to that radio station anymore; there are so many cancer alerts,'' she said. ''And there's been so much about breast cancer, I guess it made its mark on me. I know it's irrational, after my mammogram. Everyone told me everything is fine, but fear of cancer was such a big thing for me.''</p>
        <p>And that, said Dr. Mayer of Harvard, gets back to doctor-patient relationship. People need someone to calm their fears, who will not scold them for being less than perfect in health care, and who is available to answer seemingly minor questions, he said.</p>
        <p>''There is so much a solid relationship can provide in terms of preventive health and the stresses we all face,'' said Dr. Mayer. ''Breaking down the formal barriers allows people to open up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
