<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks' Parade of Numbers: Dollar Signs Followed by 0's</title>
    <meta content="31SAND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/sports/31SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cablevision Systems Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDB1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks' Parade of Numbers: Dollar Signs Followed by 0's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV Sports column discusses status of negotiations between New York Yankees and Cablevision over television rights to Yankees games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that their 26th World Series title is secure and another parade is over, the Yankees can look ahead to next season, and wonder who will televise their games.</p>
        <p>MSG Network and Channel 5 deals have expired. And the Yankees are in a continuing clash with Cablevision, MSG's parent, over a fair price for the rights to carry the team's games for the next 10 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that their 26th World Series title is secure and another parade is over, the Yankees can look ahead to next season, and wonder who will televise their games.</p>
        <p>MSG Network and Channel 5 deals have expired. And the Yankees are in a continuing clash with Cablevision, MSG's parent, over a fair price for the rights to carry the team's games for the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>First, some background. During the summer, the team signed a deal with the International Management Group's Trans World International subsidiary to create a Yankee network that would eventually carry Nets and Devils games, too.</p>
        <p>But when the Yankees asked MSG to match the T.W.I. deal -- a right built into MSG's now expired deal -- State Supreme Court Justice Barry Cozier ordered the Yankees to present a fair and compliant bid and barred them from completing the contract with T.W.I.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 8, the Yankees presented MSG with a revised offer, which Kenneth Munoz, the Garden's general counsel, described in an affidavit as ''nothing more than made-up numbers with no connection to what any entity actually would be willing to pay.''</p>
        <p>Unable to negotiate a deal, the Yankees withdrew the offer two weeks ago, and Cablevision filed a new court action to declare the revised offer noncompliant with its rights. A Yankee official indicated that a more reasonable offer would be presented this week, but so far nothing has reached the desks at MSG or Cablevision.</p>
        <p>The longer this drags on, the more difficult it will be for the Yankees to set up a network, and the more likely the Yankees will need to negotiate a one-year extension with MSG. For now, it looks as if MSG can afford to wait for the team's demands to return to earth from the stratospheric level the Yankees are seeking for the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>The just-completed MSG deal paid the Yankees $493.5 million over 12 years, including $51 million last season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees contend that the network with T.W.I. would pay it $898 million over the next 10 years -- the same price MSG would have paid if it chose to match the T.W.I. deal and continue to carry Yankee games.</p>
        <p>When the Yankees made the new offer, they weren't forced by Cozier to comply with his order by setting a lower price, but were to offer MSG the option of buying all the TV rights, as it had in the past. So the second offer, tendered on Sept. 8, asked MSG to pay the Yankees $1.3 billion immediately; or if MSG wanted to spread payments over 10 years, the price was $2.4 billion. The payout would start next season with MSG paying $165 million (nearly 3.3 times last season's $51 million fee) and conclude with a $311 million payment in 2010.</p>
        <p>A lot of gumption went into demanding that kind of cash -- and steadfast confidence that subscriber and advertising fees would soar like Bob Beamon in the coming years -- which leads a skeptic to believe that the Yankees are puffing up the value of their TV rights to force MSG to walk away. When the Yankees talk about exploiting their TV rights -- which they do continuously in their correspondence with MSG -- you know they would really prefer to do it without MSG.</p>
        <p>Consider how the proposed Yankee rights fees compare with other deals: in 2004, when the Yankees would want MSG to pay $222.9 million, ESPN would pay Major League Baseball $200 million for national cable rights. The Fox Network's new six-year deal with baseball -- for all regular-season, playoff and World Series rights -- is worth $2.5 billion.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were valued at $600 million last year when they merged with the Nets. The valuation included the MSG deal. Is the TV deal now worth four times that of the team, less than a year later?</p>
        <p>MSG does not think so. In its court papers, the network insists that the financial assumptions backing the Sept. 8 offer are goofy and unrealistic. MSG said that Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, the Yankees' adviser, produced its financial valuation by using inflated, wrongheaded estimates for cable subscribers, subscriber rates and advertising rates.</p>
        <p>For example, the Yankees say they can get $1.35 monthly per cable subscriber, from the start, for a network that will reach 6.5 million homes, with only one seasonal product: Yankee games.</p>
        <p>MSG now gets $1.60 per subscriber from metropolitan area cable systems (and less than half of that for outer regions). According to Munoz, then, if the Yankees' value their games at $1.35 per subscriber, then the value of the Knicks, Rangers and Liberty games on MSG are worth 25 cents -- less than one-fifth of the value of Yankee games.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are valuable -- acquiring their games in 1989 provided the engine for MSG's immense growth into a regional sports network with 7.2 million subscribers -- but are they that valuable?</p>
        <p>Munoz also said the Yankees miscalculated the number of 30-second advertising spots per game (estimating that there would be 78, not the 48 that MSG has been selling) and placed an unrealistic value on how much they could charge for reselling 50 games a year on local broadcast television to an outlet like Channel 5, which was paying $17.5 million a year.</p>
        <p>Lonn Trost, the Yankees' chief operating officer, defended the terms of the proposed deal in a letter to Munoz, saying, ''The partnership is confident that, by exploiting its television exploitation rights itself, it can realize'' the $2.4 billion.</p>
        <p>But MSG's position remains completely different. The proposed price, Munoz said, is ''ludicrous, inflated, based on erroneous financial assumptions'' and contradicted by ''MSG's 12 years worth of experience.''</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
