<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North Korea Is All Smiles, And Bewildered by It All</title>
    <meta content="Y31KOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/world/31KORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6D71530F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North Korea Is All Smiles, And Bewildered by It All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on North Korea's campaign for conciliation with US and South Korea, old enemies, and its diplomatic blitz over past year to establish links with Britain, Canada, Australia, Italy and France; shift away from brinkmanship is most visible at top, but even more impressive at more mundane level of contacts with diplomats and middle-level bureaucrats; some possible reasons for new shift discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is impossible for any outsider to know exactly why North Korea has changed its tack so dramatically in recent months, inviting old enemies from South Korea and the United States to the capital, Pyongyang, and toasting them lavishly.</p>
        <p>But it was clear last week that the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il, had impressed his long-skeptical guests as someone Washington could work with when he made a quip to Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright about cooperation on missiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is impossible for any outsider to know exactly why North Korea has changed its tack so dramatically in recent months, inviting old enemies from South Korea and the United States to the capital, Pyongyang, and toasting them lavishly.</p>
        <p>But it was clear last week that the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il, had impressed his long-skeptical guests as someone Washington could work with when he made a quip to Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright about cooperation on missiles.</p>
        <p>Speculation over the reasons for North Korea's campaign ranges from sheer distress -- because of repeated famines and a collapsing economy -- to a push from the country's Chinese benefactors, who are eager to remove North Korea and its weapons programs from Washington's list of justifications for developing missile shields.</p>
        <p>But for all the attention to the reception given to Dr. Albright, the scenes of conciliation and good cheer were merely the latest in a gradually accelerating transformation that has been under way for at least a year.</p>
        <p>If the shift away from brinkmanship has been most visible at the top, diplomats and international aid workers who have had either long or recently intense exposure to the country say that the changes are even more impressive at the more mundane level of contacts with diplomats and middle-level bureaucrats.</p>
        <p>North Korea has been on a diplomatic blitz for a year now, establishing or planning links with Britain, Canada, Australia, Italy and France. ''Meeting with North Korean officials used to be like watching a man try to cross a river by feeling the rocks under his feet one by one,'' said a diplomat from one of those countries. ''The only thing is that whenever the North Koreans reached a rock, you could never be sure they wanted to proceed any further.''</p>
        <p>''Nowadays,'' the diplomat said, ''you walk into a meeting with them for the first time, and before you can even get acquainted, they are saying, 'Great, how quickly can we establish relations?' ''</p>
        <p>The cynical view is that this diplomatic offensive merely seeks as much aid as possible while diversifying the sources. Just as surely, though, these new engagements will expose people in the world's most reclusive nation to outside influences, a risky proposition, which perhaps explains why such an opening has not been tried before.</p>
        <p>In a system like North Korea's, with power highly concentrated and closely held, such changes reflect decisions at the summit of power. But it is clear that few of the changes have been explained to people down the bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>Now, suddenly, people in a nation that with China's help fought the United States to a standstill in the Korean War, and have been told all their lives that Americans are wolves, are seeing their leaders making merry with the enemy.</p>
        <p>''Why are people suddenly so cooperative?'' said a Western diplomat whose country is planning to open relations soon. ''Because they know the instructions have come from the chairman to smile and get as much help from the outside as possible, and they know they'd better not fail. But boy, are they confused.''</p>
        <p>The theme of confusion was repeated by almost every Westerner with experience in North Korea. ''Decisions in a pyramidal society like this are so centralized, so political and so personal, that it is hard for Americans to understand that kind of pressure,'' said Peter Hayes, co-executive director of the Nautilus Institute, a private aid group that has been active in the country for years.</p>
        <p>''Many people are confused,'' Mr. Hayes said. ''They don't know what the new edicts from the top mean. Those at the top might not even know. They are striking out in a completely new direction, and they are going to have to make it up as they go along.''</p>
        <p>But frequent visitors say that given the sheer weight of the country's totalitarian ideology and generations of mass indoctrination, changing course will be akin to turning a huge ship at sea.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Seoul Says No to Dalai Lama</p>
        <p>SEOUL, South Korea, Oct. 30 (Agence France-Presse) -- South Korea said today that it would not allow a visit in November by the Dalai Lama. The Foreign Ministry spokesman gave no reasons for the ban, but other officials cited China's strong protest against contacts with the Dalai Lama, whom it calls a Tibetan separatist.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the Dalai Lama's visit said they would work for Foreign Minister Lee Joung Binn's resignation. They have also asked why a government led by President Kim Dae Jung, who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize earlier this month, would not allow another Nobel peace laureate to visit.</p>
        <p>The Dalai Lama won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1989 for his nonviolent campaign on behalf of his homeland, which China occupied 50 years ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
