<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Radio Hosts Say Bush and Gore Pale Next to Clinton as a Talk Show Topic</title>
    <meta content="Y31COU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/31/politics/31COUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TALK IN AUSTIN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KLBJ-AM (Austin, Tex)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DF1230F932A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Radio Hosts Say Bush and Gore Pale Next to Clinton as a Talk Show Topic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Talk show hosts at KLBJ-AM in Austin, Tex, agree Vice Pres Al Gore or Gov George W Bush will make dull talk-show topics if either is elected president, and that life will not be same without polarizing presence of Pres Clinton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the candidate locally dubbed Dubya flew off from home base here today on his final sprint for the presidency, Mark and Ed, the talk-show team on KLBJ-AM's dawn patrol were already sensing fresh material in the air.</p>
        <p>''It won't have quite the sizzle of the Lewinsky scandal,'' conceded Mark Caesar, half of the broadcast team, anticipating the altered world of talk radio if Gov. George W. Bush won the White House. ''But Bush should be good for talk radio. There'll be outstanding material: the anticipation of his tax cut, for example, and how much he'll try to push his agenda through Congress.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the candidate locally dubbed Dubya flew off from home base here today on his final sprint for the presidency, Mark and Ed, the talk-show team on KLBJ-AM's dawn patrol were already sensing fresh material in the air.</p>
        <p>''It won't have quite the sizzle of the Lewinsky scandal,'' conceded Mark Caesar, half of the broadcast team, anticipating the altered world of talk radio if Gov. George W. Bush won the White House. ''But Bush should be good for talk radio. There'll be outstanding material: the anticipation of his tax cut, for example, and how much he'll try to push his agenda through Congress.''</p>
        <p>Tax cut? Congressional agenda? Mr. Caesar, the station's program director, sounded like a world-weary soul ready for the cloister after eight years of Chaucerian overdrive from the incumbency of Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>''Clinton's a likable rogue, no doubt about it,'' said Mr. Caesar's co-host, Ed Clements, wondering aloud how talk radio, not to mention the rest of the nation's institutions, will adjust to Clinton deprivation. ''He provided great fodder for us,'' said Mr. Clements, not ungrateful yet contending he could do with a dash less scandal in his civics.</p>
        <p>Maybe so, but as the two broadcasters chatted with microphones closed during a commercial break, they had to smile at a studio computer screen in appreciation of the latest offering on the Rush Limbaugh Web site, an innocent enough ground-level photograph of President Clinton that Mr. Limbaugh rudely termed ''Monica's view.''</p>
        <p>The Jedi master of radio's polemical universe, Mr. Limbaugh clearly is not letting Mr. Clinton go gentle into that good night beyond all talk, all the time.</p>
        <p>''There's one thing the liberals can't stop and it's a mandate!'' his voice boomed in the background in a taped promotion for his afternoon show happily predicting a Bush victory.</p>
        <p>The station professionals who groom if not tame the talk audiences agree that, whether Mr. Bush or Vice President Al Gore wins, life won't be the same without the polarizing, capering presence of Mr. Clinton crackling in the ether.</p>
        <p>''I know there's always stupid politicians doing stupid things somewhere,'' said Jeff Ward, who anchors the afternoon show. ''But we're going to have our work cut out for us to find them,'' he said, emphasizing that no politician could serve himself up on the half shell for the delectation of talk radio quite the way Mr. Clinton did.</p>
        <p>''We can make fun of Al Gore's goofiness if he's elected, and I'm not afraid of some Bush bashing if that's required,'' Mr. Ward said. ''But months from now I don't expect to have an easy talk show of Bush or Gore doing bizarre things.''</p>
        <p>Out beyond the studio, a heady mix of anticipation, fascination and begrudging pride is palpable in this urban liberal oasis of Texas. In the local excitement, 69,000 of the county's voters, 12 percent, have already cast sealed ballots before the official day, under a state procedure.</p>
        <p>This city that knows Mr. Bush better than other metropolises know him clearly loves political talk, from pending local proposals for a city ''living wage'' and a mass transit rail system, to the daily anguish and imponderables of the Middle East conflict.</p>
        <p>Austin liberals admit they have still not adjusted to the surprise of Mr. Bush's winning the governorship. How did his low-key brand of amiable determination sneak up on them so? And they fairly gape at how close the polls show Mr. Bush to be approaching the ultimate level, the presidency, with his same soft-edged wares.</p>
        <p>''We're wondering whether he can pull it off,'' observed Cactus Pryor, a fervid Democrat and legendary Texas broadcaster for five decades. He said he would be impressed if Mr. Bush could carry Austin, let alone the nation. ''This is the liberal dynasty of Texas,'' Mr. Pryor said of Austin's Travis County, noting that the only modern Republican to carry the city in a presidential vote was Ronald Reagan ''in a squeaker.''</p>
        <p>As Austin awoke this morning, the text to listeners boomed from Mr. Caesar: ''We're a week and a day away!'' He exulted in looking ahead. During a break, he offered not a scintilla of nostalgia as talk radio nears the end of the pungent Clinton incumbency. ''The impeachment was a very emotional time for our callers, and Ed and I had some very raucous debates on the Lewinsky saga,'' Mr. Caesar said, sounding aurally scarred.</p>
        <p>Soon the microphones were back on and the intricate morning routine took over and seemed a comfort in itself as words flew in and out of the studio. The two hosts handled dart-like cues as artfully as diner chefs working the breakfast griddle. With staccato bursts of a musical note as background, their baritones flashed from traffic report to commercial to weather to the overshadowing news of this day, Dubya's heading out of here on his last roundup for votes.</p>
        <p>And through it all came the callers, more or less wondering in behalf of all Austin: What's next?</p>
        <p>''Did you hear the latest?'' Mr. Caesar, leaning into the microphone, suddenly had to ask one caller. ''Clinton wants an apology from the Republicans for impeachment!'' the talk show host announced, not yet letting go as he smiled at this fresh audacity.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TALK IN AUSTIN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
