<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stray Bullet From Street Fight Kills a Neighborhood Fixture</title>
    <meta content="28BODE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/nyregion/28BODE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miravala, Enrique</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DA1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stray Bullet From Street Fight Kills a Neighborhood Fixture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Enrique Miravala is killed in street in Bushwick section of Brooklyn after being struck by stray bullet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Enrique Miravala, known to all as Flaco, was a fixture at the corner of Wilson Avenue and Palmetto Street in the Bushwick section of Brooklyn. A gentle, sometimes homeless alcoholic, 54 years old, he repaired cars expertly, swept storefronts and ran errands, earning beer money and the affection of his neighbors.</p>
        <p>But yesterday afternoon, the street where Mr. Miravala lived his life brought him his death. He was sitting on a blue swivel chair in front of a bodega eating onion rings from a paper container when a stray bullet from an argument hit him in the head, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Enrique Miravala, known to all as Flaco, was a fixture at the corner of Wilson Avenue and Palmetto Street in the Bushwick section of Brooklyn. A gentle, sometimes homeless alcoholic, 54 years old, he repaired cars expertly, swept storefronts and ran errands, earning beer money and the affection of his neighbors.</p>
        <p>But yesterday afternoon, the street where Mr. Miravala lived his life brought him his death. He was sitting on a blue swivel chair in front of a bodega eating onion rings from a paper container when a stray bullet from an argument hit him in the head, the police said.</p>
        <p>The gunman was arrested after being beaten by several onlookers, the police and witnesses said. And in front of the garage, the car service, and the grocery store, people mourned the loss of a neighbor. The police identified him as Steven Martinez, 24.</p>
        <p>Beatriz Ocasio, 28, said of Mr. Miravala: ''He was like the neighborhood grandfather around here. Everybody loved him, everybody got along with him.''</p>
        <p>The argument that killed Mr. Miravala started two blocks away, at Wilson and Madison Street, a corner well known as a place where heroin, crack and marijuana are openly traded, said Joe Vega, 30, who lives in the neighborhood. Mr. Martinez and another man began arguing over drugs around 2:30 p.m., several witnesses said. The other man chased Mr. Martinez down Wilson.</p>
        <p>At Palmetto and Wilson, Mr. Martinez pulled a gun and fired four shots, said a worker at an electronics repair store on the corner, who would not give his name.</p>
        <p>One bullet hit the front of a car parked in front of a mechanic's shop, startling a man who had his head under the hood. Two others struck elsewhere. The fourth hit Mr. Miravala, who stood up, staggered to the doorway of Los Primos Grocery, and collapsed, said Luisita Salgado, 33, who was watching from her mother's apartment window. Mr. Miravala died at Wyckoff Heights Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Several witnesses said a small crowd chased Mr. Martinez to a ramp in front of the Hope Gardens housing project two blocks down Palmetto and, when they caught him, beat him with fists, feet and a bicycle until the police arrived. One of those who caught and beat him was the man he fired at, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martinez, of Stanhope Street in Bushwick, was charged with second-degree murder, reckless endangerment and weapons possession, said Jerry Varson, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>For a long time, Mr. Miravala had stayed in an abandoned building next to Natasha's Car Service on Wilson Avenue, said Bochy Raffe, a dispatcher there. But when the building changed hands, he was evicted and moved into the basement of the car service and did odd jobs there.</p>
        <p>Armando Ortiz, a custodian at Intermediate School 291, across from Natasha's, said Mr. Miravala's neighbors looked out for him because he looked out for them.</p>
        <p>''Flaco'' -- it means skinny, which he was -- ''was typed homeless, but he wasn't, because everybody took care of him,'' Mr. Ortiz said. ''You'd ask him to go somewhere and he'd go for you. Go to McDonald's, go get Chinese, buy the paper. He'd walk three or four blocks to buy the Spanish newspaper.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Miravala's skill as an auto mechanic was a local legend.</p>
        <p>''Rain or snow, if you broke down, he'd find a way to get you on the road,'' Mr. Ortiz said.</p>
        <p>Last night, two candles, one purple and one white, burned in a milk crate outside Los Primos. Mr. Ortiz said Mr. Miravala would not be forgotten.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to let them put him in a potter's field,'' he said. ''We'll collect enough money for a decent funeral.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
