<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Democrat Who Doesn't Advertise It Leads in Hostile Territory</title>
    <meta content="Y28UTA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/politics/28UTAH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE UTAH RACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Utah</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Derek K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matheson, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D7113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Democrat Who Doesn't Advertise It Leads in Hostile Territory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on race for House seat from Utah between Derek Smith, Republican, and Jim Matheson, Democrat; Democrats package themselves carefully to achieve any measure of elective success in heavily Republican state; photos; map; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this overwhelmingly Republican state, Democrats have to tread carefully.</p>
        <p>Over in the First Congressional District, Kathleen McConkie-Collinwood is bringing in the president on Saturday to help her sagging efforts against the Republican incumbent, James V. Hansen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this overwhelmingly Republican state, Democrats have to tread carefully.</p>
        <p>Over in the First Congressional District, Kathleen McConkie-Collinwood is bringing in the president on Saturday to help her sagging efforts against the Republican incumbent, James V. Hansen.</p>
        <p>Oh, not the real president. Utah residents do not especially like President Clinton. Her guest is Martin Sheen, the actor who plays a president on ''The West Wing'' on NBC.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sheen's appearance is worth noting. As a cautionary tale about what it means to be a Democrat in Utah, it illustrates how carefully many Democrats package themselves to achieve any measure of elective success.</p>
        <p>Here in the Second District, which includes part of Salt Lake City and adjoining suburbs, Jim Matheson, the Democrat running for Congress,  has made no such overture to presidents of any kind. He has one advantage that Ms. McConkie-Collinwood lacks: widespread name recognition as the son of a former -- and immensely popular -- two-term Democratic governor, Scott M. Matheson.</p>
        <p>It is a major reason that polls show Mr. Matheson far ahead of the Republican candidate, Derek Smith, in a race to fill an open seat. Mr. Smith defeated the two-term incumbent, Merrill Cook, in a rowdy Republican primary this summer.</p>
        <p>But even here in the one region of Utah where Democrats can be found in significant numbers, Mr. Matheson has tailored his campaign to play down his party affiliation and loyalties to suit a district that has swung back and forth over the last two decades but never far from core centrist values that Utahans hold dear.</p>
        <p>The strategy appears to be working. The latest poll, conducted for Salt Lake's Deseret News and KSL-TV, the NBC affiliate, and released last Sunday showed Mr. Matheson leading Mr. Smith, a self-described conservative, by 46 percent to 32 percent, well outside the margin of sampling error of seven percentage points.</p>
        <p>That was encouraging news for the Democratic Party, which is counting on a Matheson victory as one of several turnovers that Democrats need to regain control of the House. The current breakdown is 222 Republicans, 210 Democrats, 2 independents and 1 vacancy.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Matheson is elected and  follows through on his campaign promises, House Democrats should not necessarily count on blind loyalty from him. For example, he says he does not support the registration and licensing of guns, a proposal Vice President Al Gore favors and most Republicans oppose, and he contends that Mr. Gore's plan to include prescription medicine as a Medicare benefit may be too expensive.</p>
        <p>Also, Mr. Matheson said he disagreed with the way the Clinton administration had used the Antiquities Act to create national monuments, a position held by legions of Republicans throughout the West.</p>
        <p>''I am a Democrat; I don't deny that,'' he said in an interview here this week. ''At the end of the day, everybody knows your party affiliation, and that's fine. But I would like to emphasize an approach that goes beyond singular partisan politics for how to address public policy. I would like to get away from the partisan approach.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Matheson's campaign literature underscores what he calls a ''common-sense approach'' to solving problems. One brochure says, ''I'll reach across party lines, work with everyone and do what is right.'' Nowhere does it identify him as a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Nor has Mr. Matheson, 40, a former energy company consultant, sought out high-profile Democrats to visit the district on his behalf. Only one of national stature has, Senator Russell D. Feingold of Wisconsin, a friend since their days at Harvard, and no one else is expected. At one campaign event this week, Mr. Matheson greeted voters at the home of his close friend Eric Leavitt, a Republican and the younger brother of Utah's Republican governor, Michael O. Leavitt, who is supporting Mr. Smith.</p>
        <p>By comparison, Mr. Smith, 35, who built a successful high-tech company, has shared a stage only with members of his own party, a steady stream of stalwarts that includes Speaker J. Dennis Hastert, Representative Dick Armey, the majority leader, and Representative Tom Delay, the majority whip. More are coming, Mr. Smith said, including Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Matheson, the accent on policy, not politics, is vital to win support from the fast-growing number of suburban voters in a district that President George Bush and Bob Dole carried in the last two presidential elections and Gov. George. W. Bush of Texas is expected to win this year.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, it has given Mr. Smith a convenient way to argue, in effect, that if voters support moderate or even Republican positions they should vote for a Republican, not a Democrat reaching for the political center. And besides, he emphasized, even Utah Democrats act like Washington Democrats after they win election.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, even though he supports traditional Republican issues in his fight for the middle, it won't matter much what he feels about them,'' Mr. Smith said of his opponent. ''The Democratic leadership is going to determine the issues that see the light of day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said he expected to overtake Mr. Matheson in the closing weeks of the campaign as voters became more familiar with him and his policy positions, like supporting tax cuts and education reform that provides more local control over spending federal money.</p>
        <p>The National Republican Congressional Committee is helping with nearly $1 million for television advertisements, about four times what the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee is spending for Mr. Matheson.</p>
        <p>''We're closing,'' Mr. Smith said, mindful of a Salt Lake Tribune poll three weeks ago that failed to mention party affiliation and showed Mr. Matheson leading by 27 points. ''He has a famous last name, but when Republican and independent voters become more familiar with me, I think they'll come over to my camp.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE UTAH RACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
