<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interpublic Group names a coordinator of its increasingly diversified units.</title>
    <meta content="Y28ADC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/business/28ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interpublic Group of Companies Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nelson, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D9113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interpublic Group names a coordinator of its increasingly diversified units.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce S Nelson is appointed executive vice president and chief marketing officer at Interpublic Group of Companies; will coordinate efforts to manage increasingly diversified Interpublic units specializing in interactive and direct marketing, public relations, media services, research, programming and consulting as well as traditional advertising (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SEASONED executive with experience in the account, creative and strategic realms of agency operations is being named to a new top post at the Interpublic Group of Companies in New York. The executive, Bruce S. Nelson, will coordinate efforts to manage the increasingly diversified Interpublic units specializing in interactive and direct marketing, public relations, media services, research, programming and consulting as well as traditional advertising.</p>
        <p>The appointment of Mr. Nelson, as executive vice president and chief marketing officer at Interpublic, is indicative of the growing importance of nonadvertising holdings to the Madison Avenue giants. About half of Interpublic's revenue for 2000 will be derived from fields outside the creation of television commercials and print advertisements, compared with about a third two years ago and less than a quarter four years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SEASONED executive with experience in the account, creative and strategic realms of agency operations is being named to a new top post at the Interpublic Group of Companies in New York. The executive, Bruce S. Nelson, will coordinate efforts to manage the increasingly diversified Interpublic units specializing in interactive and direct marketing, public relations, media services, research, programming and consulting as well as traditional advertising.</p>
        <p>The appointment of Mr. Nelson, as executive vice president and chief marketing officer at Interpublic, is indicative of the growing importance of nonadvertising holdings to the Madison Avenue giants. About half of Interpublic's revenue for 2000 will be derived from fields outside the creation of television commercials and print advertisements, compared with about a third two years ago and less than a quarter four years ago.</p>
        <p>For instance, just last week, Interpublic realigned its public relations agencies to form a shop, Weber Shandwick Worldwide, that will become the world's largest in revenue, at an estimated $320 million, overtaking the Burson-Marsteller unit of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc., which is being acquired by the WPP Group. Recent Interpublic acquisitions in nonadvertising fields include Adair-Greene, a health care communications agency; Brands Hatch, a sports marketing company; Capita Technologies, an e-business company; the Cassidy Companies, a public relations agency; NFO Worldwide, a research company; and the Waylon Company, a sales promotion agency.</p>
        <p>''Our industry has migrated from advertising solutions to integrated marketing solutions,'' said John J. Dooner Jr., president and chief operating officer at Interpublic. ''All the different marketing disciplines need to be rationalized so the impact clients are looking for will be there.''</p>
        <p>''One of Bruce's responsibilities will be to take a look at our portfolio of brands to be sure they are positioned properly,'' he added, ''examining how can and should they be put together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson, 48, will report to Mr. Dooner, who is to become chief executive at Interpublic on Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>''There has to be a sense the top guy's behind this,'' Mr. Nelson said, because his new job calls for him to roam across the Interpublic organizational chart, seeking ways to encourage the disparate units to cooperate with each other if so required by clients.</p>
        <p>The focus on nonadvertising operations ''represents a different business model that we think will be huge,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Interpublic will rank No. 2 among agency companies in billings, at $47.1 billion, and No. 3 in revenue, at $5.1 billion, after WPP completes its pending acquisition of Y.&amp; R. The principal Interpublic divisions are Draft Worldwide, Initiative Media Worldwide, the Lowe Group and the McCann-Erickson World Group.</p>
        <p>In joining Interpublic, Mr. Nelson is returning to advertising after taking a year off to spend more time with his family, he said. Mr. Nelson left Y.&amp; R. in September 1999 after 18 months there as vice chairman and chief knowledge officer.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad he saw the light not to do that for very long,'' Mr. Dooner said, laughing, referring to Mr. Nelson's stint at the rival agency company.</p>
        <p>During his time off Madison Avenue, Mr. Nelson said, he became involved with the dot-com world, becoming a director of three companies: the Official Payments Corporation, Pcsupport.com and Zeborg Inc. He will continue on those boards after joining Interpublic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dooner said he knew Mr. Nelson from the time they both spent at McCann-Erickson. Mr. Dooner worked there from 1984 until he left for Interpublic in April, and Mr. Nelson worked there from 1979 until he left for Y.&amp; R. in 1998, holding posts that included group creative director; co-leader of an agency within the agency named Ira Madris, Bruce Nelson &amp; Colleagues; director for worldwide accounts; and worldwide director for strategic creative development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson recalled that Mr. Dooner called him ''during the summer and said: 'It's a brand-new company, and we're looking forward to where we're going to go. And with half our interests outside advertising, they're of a size now that we need someone to look at our portfolio.' ''</p>
        <p>''A lot of people know me'' at Interpublic, Mr. Nelson added, ''and know I have sat in their seat or in the seat next to theirs, so this is not a theoretical sensibility.''</p>
        <p>While at McCann-Erickson, Mr. Nelson worked for and with marketers like American Express, Coca-Cola and Nestle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dooner said that in his new post, Mr. Nelson would ''also be available for some clients that need marketing strategy help -- and he's already getting calls.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
