<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protests Diminish at Conference in Prague on Worldwide Aid</title>
    <meta content="Y28FUN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/world/28FUND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D6113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protests Diminish at Conference in Prague on Worldwide Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE, Sept. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Protests in Prague diminish sharply as financial officials and many demonstrators condemn outbreak of violence and vandalism that turned conference on aid into street battle; officials end conference half-day early but say not because of protests; senior officials of World Bank and International Monetary Fund remain in city (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Protests diminished sharply today as financial officials and many demonstrators condemned an outbreak of violence and vandalism on Tuesday that turned a conference on aid into a street battle.</p>
        <p>The officials ended the conference a half-day early, saying the formal presentations on the agenda had been completed ahead of schedule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Protests diminished sharply today as financial officials and many demonstrators condemned an outbreak of violence and vandalism on Tuesday that turned a conference on aid into a street battle.</p>
        <p>The officials ended the conference a half-day early, saying the formal presentations on the agenda had been completed ahead of schedule.</p>
        <p>The officials said moving up the closing ceremony, originally planned for Thursday, had nothing to do with the protests.</p>
        <p>Some bilateral meetings and news conferences remain scheduled for Thursday.</p>
        <p>The delegates have been meeting here for a week. Although some began leaving today, the senior officials of the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund, which organize the annual event, stayed.</p>
        <p>But shattered glass covered the sidewalks along Wenceslas Square, where hundreds of protesters -- many masked anarchists with clubs -- smashed a Kentucky Fried Chicken, a Dunkin' Donuts and a Mercedes-Benz dealership on Tuesday. Earlier that day they had repeatedly clashed with the police near the hilltop Conference Center that was the site of the finance meeting.</p>
        <p>About 100 people were injured, including 63 police officials, a spokesman for the government said. The police arrested 420 people. But many of those taken into custody were quickly released.</p>
        <p>The police today sealed the protesters' center of operations in an old factory on the outskirts of Prague.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, two cordons of officers surrounded several hundred protesters in a downtown square, holding them in place until they agreed to disperse.</p>
        <p>The violence helped the demonstrators generate publicity, as well as highlighting a gulf between them and representatives of poor nations that they often say they represent.</p>
        <p>''Violence has no place in a civilized society,'' Finance Minister Yashwant Sinha of India told delegates this morning. ''I stand here on behalf of India, the land of Mahatma Gandhi, who espoused the cause of nonviolence, and I condemn the violence which was unleashed here.''</p>
        <p>Czech officials said the protesters had lied to them when they promised, at marathon negotiations before the meetings, to conduct peaceful sit-ins.</p>
        <p>Protest organizers distanced themselves from what they called hoodlums and extremists who had no ties to the main march. Even some anarchists criticized the violence.</p>
        <p>''We agreed to nonviolence, and it all turned out badly,'' said a 24-year-old Brazilian who gave his name as Ivan and wore a ''Punk Not Dead'' T-shirt caked with dust. He sat with other protesters on Peace Square today, hemmed in by the officers who would not let them march. ''But I should say that I respect the people who committed the violence. They are not my enemy. The enemy is the I.M.F.''</p>
        <p>Though protesters distracted the news media from the conference, just as they had helped to undermine a similar meeting last year in Seattle, some said the almost ritualistic violence common to several recent antiglobalization protests obscured their main message.</p>
        <p>Many protesters argue that the World Bank and the I.M.F. do more harm than good in poor countries and need to be radically overhauled or abolished.</p>
        <p>''The media only care about the violence, not about our arguments,'' said Katarina Bartovicova, 22, of Bratislava, Slovakia. ''They are making us pay for yesterday.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
