<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; For Ewing, A Last Shot At Changing</title>
    <meta content="28BERK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/sports/28BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDA113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; For Ewing, A Last Shot At Changing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times says that Patrick Ewing must change his style of play if he is to be successful with Seattle SuperSonics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AND so, as the late autumn, if not the hoary winter, of his career is upon him, Patrick Ewing, at age 38, with his 7-foot body battered but still willing after 15 bruising seasons with the Knicks, looked back on his professional basketball life. ''Athletically,'' he said, ''I'm not where I was back in my prime, but mentally I'm much better. When I think about what I knew back then and what I know now, I realize how great I could have been.''</p>
        <p>This candid, even surprising, observation from him occurred Monday at the news conference in Seattle that introduced Ewing, fresh from the recent trade, to the fans of his new team, the SuperSonics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AND so, as the late autumn, if not the hoary winter, of his career is upon him, Patrick Ewing, at age 38, with his 7-foot body battered but still willing after 15 bruising seasons with the Knicks, looked back on his professional basketball life. ''Athletically,'' he said, ''I'm not where I was back in my prime, but mentally I'm much better. When I think about what I knew back then and what I know now, I realize how great I could have been.''</p>
        <p>This candid, even surprising, observation from him occurred Monday at the news conference in Seattle that introduced Ewing, fresh from the recent trade, to the fans of his new team, the SuperSonics.</p>
        <p>The concept that youth is wasted on the young is less than original. Most of us have had it, but for many, what we missed we missed because of a combination of arrogance and ignorance: we didn't know, were never told, were certain we knew better, or let personal considerations outweigh anything else.</p>
        <p>Ewing seemed to have shared some of those characteristics. A wondrous talent, a superb scorer and one who often played hurt and invariably hard, he missed opportunities to become a champion, or to set himself into a better position to become a champion.</p>
        <p>He rarely seemed to trust his teammates, for example, or some of his coaches, believing that he was the one who knew how to win a championship, that he must carry the team on offense. But the goal of a title has thus far eluded him. Michael Jordan, who knew something about winning and is a friend of Ewing's, told him a few years ago, ''Patrick, you'll never win a championship until you learn how to pass out of the double team.'' It took Ewing until near the end of his Knick career to be willing to pass the ball -- and not just under duress -- to the open teammate.</p>
        <p>Jordan and the rest of the Bulls have generally agreed that Chicago would not have won its first three championships without Bill Cartwright, a limited player physically but a highly intelligent one. The Bulls needed a force at center, and Cartwright provided it. He was traded to the Bulls by the Knicks for Charles Oakley, a power forward. Early on, the Knicks had hoped to play Ewing at power forward and Cartwright at center, because Ewing, though a dominating center in college, had more versatility than Cartwright. Ewing balked at the suggestion. And management, for essentially and, it turns out, unfortunately, the whole of his career, submitted to Ewing's demands. And Ewing's best moves evolved into power forward drives and medium-range jump shots.</p>
        <p>Ewing liked to get the ball so much that when he took a defensive rebound, he rarely threw the outlet pass to start a fast break but had a guard circle around to take a hand-off, allowing him time to get downcourt and set up, frustrating a long line of up-tempo teammates.</p>
        <p>''I like Patrick, personally,'' said Dave DeBusschere, who, as general manager, drafted Ewing in 1985. ''But if I were playing, there were times I'd have said: 'Patrick, clear out of the center and go to the other side. Open things up!' I thought he cared too much for offense when he could have been an overwhelming force on defense.''</p>
        <p>When Don Nelson became coach of the Knicks, he told Ewing that he wanted him to be a better passer. Ewing was shocked. ''I am a good passer,'' he said. The Knicks opened the season on a winning streak. They were running and moving the ball. Ewing went to Nelson. ''I'm not getting enough touches,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''But Patrick,'' Nelson said, ''we're on a roll.''</p>
        <p>''I know,'' Ewing said. ''I'm not getting enough touches.''</p>
        <p>Watching Ewing for 15 years with the Knicks, one had occasion to wonder what he could be thinking. Coach after coach on the sideline hollered, on defense, ''Stay down, Patrick, stay down!'' But time after time, he went for the fake. Other actions were equally baffling, like his roaming off the bench when there was a scuffle against Miami in the playoffs in 1997, despite his knowing the rules. It earned him a game suspension and contributed mightily to the Heat's victory in the series.</p>
        <p>None of this has anything to do with Ewing's personality off the court -- his interaction, or lack of it, with the fans or the news media. That was purely his business. In the end, though, Ewing cheated not only himself of being, as he said, as great as he could have been, but he also, to a significant degree, deprived fans and his teams of a better, more satisfying kind of basketball that he was capable of providing.</p>
        <p>Now Patrick Ewing turns a new page in his career. It is never too late to learn. The genuine hope here is that, finally, he does.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
