<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Video Game With Cinematic Aspirations</title>
    <meta content="28GAME$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/technology/28GAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warp 10 Technologies</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sega Enterprises Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D8103AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Video Game With Cinematic Aspirations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold assesses D2, video game developed by Warp and published by Sega of America; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT could happen to any developer. You spend years working on a game, creating an elaborate story, detailed characters and beautiful snow scenes carefully lit to reflect the time of day. Then, just as you think you're finished, you realize that you have completely forgotten one thing: giving people something they can actually play. With no time left, you quickly toss in a little mindless action and release the game.</p>
        <p>That is not necessarily what happened with D2, Warp's action-adventure game, but it feels that way. D2 is a game that is good at all the extraneous elements of a video game but bad at the one central necessity -- that it be entertaining to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT could happen to any developer. You spend years working on a game, creating an elaborate story, detailed characters and beautiful snow scenes carefully lit to reflect the time of day. Then, just as you think you're finished, you realize that you have completely forgotten one thing: giving people something they can actually play. With no time left, you quickly toss in a little mindless action and release the game.</p>
        <p>That is not necessarily what happened with D2, Warp's action-adventure game, but it feels that way. D2 is a game that is good at all the extraneous elements of a video game but bad at the one central necessity -- that it be entertaining to play.</p>
        <p>The game begins with terrorists ranting about an entity called ''Shadow, the Final Destroyer'' as they cause a plane to crash over Canada. Laura, a passenger, awakes in a cabin she has been carried to by a fellow passenger, Kimberly, who found her eight days after the crash. How Laura survived for those eight days is one of the central mysteries of D2. Even more mysterious is why one of the terrorists arrives, pulls a gun on the two women and then turns into a savage plant.</p>
        <p>After Laura picks up a handy rifle and dispatches the plant, the game begins. D2 has an unusually lengthy introduction, 20 minutes long. Games often have ''cut scenes,'' which interrupt the game with short animations that move the story forward, but it soon becomes clear that D2 has enough footage for a full-length feature film. It's an excellent film -- the cut scenes are as good as you'll find in any game. The problem is what happens between them.</p>
        <p>The first indication of a problem comes when that terrorist ''blossoms,'' which is D2's poetic way of referring to the plant transformation. Until then, the look of the game is elegant and crisp, but the monster plant has the look of something out of a Roger Corman horror film: awkward, ugly and downright silly.</p>
        <p>Once Laura heads out into the snowy Canadian wilderness, she discovers that these plant monsters are everywhere. The game suggests that they may all be mutated passengers of the crashed plane, but if so, there must have been several thousand people aboard because you never run out of monsters.</p>
        <p>When attacked, you go into battle mode, which involves shooting at monsters until they're all dead. As you kill things, their green blood splatters on the screen as though you are inside a movie camera. At times you can barely see what you're shooting at. When everything is dead,  you start walking again.</p>
        <p>That will happen over and over again, with little variation. There are only a handful of different monster types, and there is not much strategy needed to kill any of them. Most action games position monsters for maximum effect, giving you a feeling of dread as you turn a corner because you know you're about to be inundated by zombies or aliens. But D2's monsters simply show up every time you have walked a dozen steps or so. All through the game it's the same thing: walk, kill, walk, kill, walk, kill.</p>
        <p>There is no terror, no surprise. Instead of feeling that you are trapped in a nightmare world where you are battling for your life, you feel as though you are being repeatedly asked to take out the garbage.</p>
        <p>You will also need to use your rifle to hunt for food, which can be used to replenish your health. That is rather tedious, but at least the bunnies don't look like horror movie rejects.</p>
        <p>The adventure component consists simply of going from place to place and picking up everything you find. D2 is an adventure game without puzzles, an action game without excitement.</p>
        <p>Failing miserably as a game, D2 succeeds remarkably well as a movie. The script would have made an excellent Japanese anime cartoon. A boy is forced to practice piano until he goes mad, a scientist puts his wife's mind into a computer, a mutating woman's eye falls out, and a butterfly emerges from the socket. The best thing Warp could do for D2 would be to string the cut scenes together and release it into theaters.</p>
        <p>One of the most notable oddities in D2 is that the character you lead through the snow to kill plant-people is less interesting than everyone she meets. Laura doesn't speak a word until the game is almost over. She generally expresses herself with thoughtful, empathic looks and a variety of sighs, grunts and screams, depending on the situation.</p>
        <p>The real star of D2 is Kimberly, a depressed drug-addicted poet who saves and befriends Laura and keeps telling her how wonderful she is. (That is almost a running joke of the game; Laura wins friendship, love and devotion while evincing absolutely no personality.)</p>
        <p>Kimberly is a fascinating character. In the real world a garrulous, self-involved poet would be annoying, but within the game her melancholic musings and sudden bursts of anger are fascinating. There is something truly remarkable about an action game in which a woman sits down and explains her poetry. At length.</p>
        <p>The imagination that informs the story contributes to the few successful action moments in the game, when you are required to battle the particularly strong ''boss'' monsters.</p>
        <p>These monsters are the least plantlike because they have retained vestiges of their humanity and talk to you while you are killing them. It is chilling to shoot a plant-man as he's reliving a conversation with his granddaughter or fire repeatedly at a plant-woman as she says, ''I thought we were friends.'' If D2 had fewer monsters with more personality, its humdrum pedestrian action would be more compelling.</p>
        <p>The last section of the game turns the tedious gameplay on full, as Laura runs a gantlet of monsters before facing the last boss. There is no secret to killing your final foe -- you just have to keep shooting and replenishing your health until the enemy dies. If you haven't stored up enough first-aid kits and killed enough bunnies to outlast the monster, you'll never make it to the end. It's the ignominious finish to the game's lackluster play.</p>
        <p>After the final lengthy cut scene, the game ends with a list of statistics involving pollution, starvation, AIDS and other modern horrors. The implication is that the story has something to do with the evils of war and disease, although it is impossible to see how that was meant to be conveyed.</p>
        <p>It is a puzzling finale for a puzzling game. The game's central mystery is not how Laura survived for eight days, or why people are turning into plants, but how D2's makers believed that they could get away with such anemic gameplay. As Laura would so eloquently put it, ''Hmmmm?''</p>
        <p>D2, developed by Warp and published by Sega of America for Dreamcast; $49.95; for 17 and older.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
