<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Priceline Shares Fall on Word Sales Won't Meet Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y28PRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/technology/28PRIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Priceline.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5D9113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Priceline Shares Fall on Word Sales Won't Meet Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares in online retailer Priceline.com fall more than 40 percent after company says its sales in third quarter will be as much as 11 percent below analysts' forecasts; company attributes shortfall to slow sales of airline tickets, it signature product, which still account for 87 percent of its sales (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares in the online retailer Priceline.com fell more than 40 percent yesterday after the company said its sales in the third quarter would be as much as 11 percent below analysts' forecasts.</p>
        <p>The company attributed the shortfall to slow sales of airline tickets -- its signature product, which still account for 87 percent of its sales. Priceline lets customers offer a set price for a ticket on the condition that the company can specify the time of the flight and the airline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares in the online retailer Priceline.com fell more than 40 percent yesterday after the company said its sales in the third quarter would be as much as 11 percent below analysts' forecasts.</p>
        <p>The company attributed the shortfall to slow sales of airline tickets -- its signature product, which still account for 87 percent of its sales. Priceline lets customers offer a set price for a ticket on the condition that the company can specify the time of the flight and the airline.</p>
        <p>In recent months, however, sales have been hurt because of the $20 surcharge the airlines imposed on each round trip to cover higher fuel costs and because of schedule disruptions at United Airlines. Moreover, rather than sell more tickets through Priceline, the airlines chose to have their own fare sales in September, the company said. To compensate, Priceline encouraged its customers to make lower bids for tickets.</p>
        <p>An e-mail message sent to customers last week, for example, sounded an increasingly desperate tone as it described Priceline's ''first ever airline ticket sale.'' It suggested that customers bid as little as $99 for tickets. ''No reasonable offer will be refused!'' the e-mail message said.</p>
        <p>The only effect of these promotions, the company said yesterday, was to reduce revenue even further. They did not increase overall sales volume, as hoped.</p>
        <p>Priceline said that ticket sales in the quarter ending this month would be $20 million to $25 million less than its sales in the quarter that ended in June. Even though the company has had as many customers bidding this quarter, the airlines made available fewer seats and the average ticket price declined.</p>
        <p>Over all, the company said it expected revenue in the third quarter to be $340 million to $345 million. Analysts had estimated revenue of $360 million to $380 million. In the second quarter, its revenue was $352 million.</p>
        <p>The company estimated that it would lose about 1 cent a share, the same as it lost in the second quarter, excluding various noncash charges. As a result, analysts no longer expect the company to post its first profitable quarter this year.</p>
        <p>Indeed, several analysts who had been bullish on Priceline -- including Henry Blodget of Merrill Lynch and Anthony Noto of Goldman, Sachs --  downgraded the stock yesterday.</p>
        <p>''While consumers may go to Priceline because of high airline prices or because of concerns about reliability, Priceline may not be in a position to fill that demand profitably when they are negatively affected by macroeconomic factors such as higher fuel costs and any competitive promotional pricing activity,'' Mr. Noto wrote to clients.</p>
        <p>Fay Landes, an analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein, who has been among Priceline's harshest critics, said the news emphasized the flaws in the company's business.</p>
        <p>''This is a wake-up call,'' she said. ''They have a business that targets cheapskates, and it's hard to make money off them.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, she said, the company is vulnerable to being able to get access to the airline tickets it needs, in the face of the airlines' own discounting and other competing Internet sites. ''They don't have control of their supply,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Priceline did say that its revenue from other categories -- including bidding for hotel rooms and long-distance telephone calls -- would grow by 20 percent in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Shares of Priceline fell $7.89, to $10.75, a record low, yesterday. As recently as March, the company's shares were at $104, giving it a value higher than any airline. Now the company is valued at $1.8 billion, a relatively modest multiple of 1.4 times the company's projected $1.3 billion in revenue for 2000.</p>
        <p>Shares of other Internet travel companies fell on the news. Travelocity, which has an extensive partnership with Priceline, fell $2.50, to $12. Expedia, which also runs a name-your-own-price service, fell by 25 cents, to $14.75.</p>
        <p>And stocks of other big Internet companies, which have nothing to do with airline tickets, also fell sharply on the news. Ebay's shares dropped $7.19, to $63.50. Amazon.com shares fell $1.88, to $37.88. And Yahoo fell $12.06, to $90.38.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
