<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Brooklyn, a Vision Of a Cultural Haven; Academy Plan Generates Buzz and Backlash</title>
    <meta content="28BAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/nyregion/28BAM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtenstein, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lutfy, Jeanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFD7113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Brooklyn, a Vision Of a Cultural Haven; Academy Plan Generates Buzz and Backlash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Harvey Lichtenstein, who led renaissance of Brooklyn Academy of Music and is now pushing to create cultural district in area surrounding academy; Jeanne Lutfy, president of Brooklyn Academy of Music's development corporation, comments; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three desolate lots that encircle the Brooklyn Academy of Music have gnawed at Harvey Lichtenstein for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichtenstein made his reputation rebuilding the academy of music by discovering how to turn Manhattan's attention to Brooklyn. Under Mr. Lichtenstein, the academy's stately Beaux-Arts opera house was filled with provocative and avant-garde productions. The strategy worked, bringing in the kind of Manhattanite who never before would have admitted to taking the No. 4 train past Bowling Green.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The three desolate lots that encircle the Brooklyn Academy of Music have gnawed at Harvey Lichtenstein for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichtenstein made his reputation rebuilding the academy of music by discovering how to turn Manhattan's attention to Brooklyn. Under Mr. Lichtenstein, the academy's stately Beaux-Arts opera house was filled with provocative and avant-garde productions. The strategy worked, bringing in the kind of Manhattanite who never before would have admitted to taking the No. 4 train past Bowling Green.</p>
        <p>But even as the academy thrived, the lots around it remained as scars on the street grid. When Mr. Lichtenstein stepped down in 1999, after 32 years as president and artistic director of the academy, the empty spaces continued to bother him. So he took charge of the academy's local development corporation to see if what clicked for an old opera house might work for vacant lots.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Lichtenstein has been trying to sell artists, community leaders and public officials on his idea of raising up a cultural district on those empty tracts and in the surrounding area. He envisions a visual and performing arts library, a charter school, a new-media center, a mixed-use arts complex, theaters, nonprofit offices, a museum, retail space, loft housing and a hotel.</p>
        <p>To match his ambitions, Mr. Lichtenstein dreams of unique buildings for the project and has hired Rem Koolhaas, a Dutch architect known for nontraditional designs. Mr. Lichtenstein says he hopes that Mr. Koolhaas will draft building plans that can lure established cultural institutions and create a great public architecture rarely seen in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''BAM had made a reputation as a performing arts center, but the context never grew up around it,'' Mr. Lichtenstein said. ''Now it is the right time to develop it as a cultural district.''</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Lichtenstein's game plan appears to be working. The city has pledged $25 million to the project and the academy's renovation of the Strand Theater, just north of the academy. Construction has begun on a new headquarters for the Mark Morris Dance Group. The development corporation is negotiating with other dance companies, theater groups, nonprofit organizations and a museum, all of which feel squeezed out of Manhattan. Mr. Lichtenstein has also piqued the interest of a charter school and the Brooklyn Public Library.</p>
        <p>In short, he has begun to generate buzz.</p>
        <p>But where there is buzz there is backlash. Some community leaders in Fort Greene, the neighborhood next to the academy, are worried that Mr. Koolhaas's ideas will clash with the neighborhood's brownstone architecture. Business owners who have helped usher in an African-American renaissance along Fulton Street worry about being left out of the project. Rents have already shot up in Fort Greene in recent months, and some black residents fear that the project will make the neighborhood whiter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichtenstein and Jeanne Lutfy, the president of the development corporation, argue vociferously that they are taking care to make sure their development only helps residents and merchants.</p>
        <p>But the district, Mr. Lichtenstein has made clear, is not supposed to be artistically safe. It is supposed to be exciting.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Lichtenstein has filled his office at the development corporation with the trappings of an urban planner (zoning rules, aerial photos, land-use maps), he still thinks like the creative director of a performing arts group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichtenstein's wild eyebrows, tightly packed teeth and wide smile give him an impish look that match his love of attention-getting actions.</p>
        <p>''The district will develop like a work of art,'' he said recently as he and Ms. Lutfy discussed their plans. ''It will be a creative process. It could be terrible; it could come out terribly.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Lichtenstein said ''terrible,'' Ms. Lutfy shifted uncomfortably in her seat and tried to cut him off. But Mr. Lichtenstein would not stop.</p>
        <p>''Anything creative starts out with that possibility, that it could be terrible,'' he continued. ''But we have the commitment, flexibility and nerve to go through with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichtenstein hopes his first show of nerve was hiring Mr. Koolhaas. Only the initial stages of research and study have begun, but Mr. Koolhaas has clearly begun to think about what he wants to create.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koolhaas argues that Manhattan has begun a process of super-gentrification, becoming an island of shiny buildings and unchecked consumerism.</p>
        <p>''In Brooklyn, I want to set up a polarity,'' Mr. Koolhaas said. ''I want something less shiny, less consumerist, more productive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Koolhaas first made his reputation not with a building but with a book on architecture, ''Delirious New York,'' first published in 1978. In the book, Mr. Koolhaas argues the city's position as a cultural capital is intertwined with its soaring, dense architecture. And that idea, he said, informs the Brooklyn Academy of Music's project. Packing many cultural institutions close together will produce creative results, for both the programs and the architecture, Mr. Koolhaas said.</p>
        <p>Those possibilities clearly excite some of the proposed tenants. The Brooklyn Public Library is studying a proposal to build a $50 million, 100,000-square-foot visual and performing arts branch in the district.</p>
        <p>''I look at the library as really being the center of knowledge for a neighborhood,'' said Martin Gomez, executive director of the library. ''Translate that to the BAM cultural district and you see that many of those groups are going to need a place to find information to enable  them to pursue their craft.''</p>
        <p>The initial ideas that have popped forth for the cultural district from Mr. Koolhaas's Office for Metropolitan Architecture bear his distinct stamp. Mr. Koolhaas is known for his preoccupation with horizontal layering, rendering buildings like off-kilter sandwiches. His team's early ideas for the museum and the library incorporate layers, each dedicated to different uses, and each set off from the floor below and above.</p>
        <p>Howard Pitsch, the president of the Fort Greene Association, said he was excited by the prospect of creating a district designed with ''good, clean, contemporary modern architecture.''</p>
        <p>''Why should it be bad?'' Mr. Pitsch said. ''There is nothing but parking lots there now.</p>
        <p>''If we can build Fort Greene as a cultural center, couldn't we all celebrate?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Others, though, are more reserved. Robert Evans, chairman of Community Board 2, said he liked the idea of the district. But he said architectural proposals that resulted in radical design, glass boxes or loft housing made him nervous.</p>
        <p>''Everyone in the area is very much interested in protecting quality,'' Mr. Evans said. ''We are not much interested in modernizing. You are going to create problems if the buildings are too outlandishly modern.''</p>
        <p>Business owners and residents worry that Mr. Lichtenstein will succeed too well, that he will change the character of the area. Some business owners in the Fort Greene shopping area known as the Bogolan District (named after the Mali word for ''mud cloth'') worry that the development could drive up commercial rents and provide new, subsidized retail space for Manhattan businesses, while shutting out existing merchants.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Adewumi, chairman of the Bogolan Merchants Association, said he worried that visitors to the academy of music district would never venture beyond its borders into Fort Greene proper.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to look across from your store and see a bright, shiny new retail space and you are not a part of it,'' Mr. Adewumi said. ''I think the current project just looks at luring people from Manhattan and does not look at the people who are already here.''</p>
        <p>Tracye Gardner, a black Fort Greene resident and founder of the Brooklyn Young Filmmakers Center, said that more white families had moved into the area recently, and that she worried that black families were being pushed out.</p>
        <p>''I am very happy about having a beautiful cultural district in my neighborhood, as long as I can stay in my neighborhood,'' Ms. Gardner said. ''Fort Greene is already an amazing community in terms of the black resources and black history, but that could change radically. It could become a culture district for a portion of Manhattan that is relocating.''</p>
        <p>Backers of the project contend that the cultural district is not the cause of gentrification. Rather, the project is the product of the same forces that are gentrifying Fort Greene.</p>
        <p>''Gentrification is happening in Fort Greene already, even though we haven't done anything yet,'' said Bruce C. Ratner, chairman of the academy of music and the president of Forest City Ratner Companies, a real estate development company. ''That proves that what causes gentrification are economic good times.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lutfy said that the development corporation had extended the borders of the cultural district into the Fort Greene shopping area, in an effort to integrate those businesses into the project. Both the development corporation officials and architects argue that they are taking pains to ensure that any plans they come up with enhance the brownstone neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to situate this so that it is not an alien mega-project dropped in the neighborhood,'' said Charles Renfro, the project manager for Diller &amp; Scofidio, the New York architecture firm working with Mr. Koolhaas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ratner said he thought that in the end, Brooklyn would accept a more avant-garde architectural proposal than parts of Manhattan might.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, we are at a stage in the city where we are more accepting of extraordinary architecture even if it doesn't mesh with what people are used to,'' Mr. Ratner said. ''It's even expected that we at BAM will do something that is cutting edge and contemporary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
