<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Artist the Web Was Made For</title>
    <meta content="28ESCH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/technology/28ESCH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SCREEN GRAB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Escher, Maurits Cornelis (1898-1972)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7D8103AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Artist the Web Was Made For</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maurits Cornelis Escher, Dutch graphic artist whose experiments in perspective, mathematically grounded lithographs and spatial illusions, provides a perfect subject for several Web sites; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU would think that art and the Internet were made for each other. But all artists are not equal on the Web. There are reproductions, to be sure, but what about ''appreciation''? Some renowned artists are represented by little more than a few capsule biographies and a lot of dealers, with precious little commentary or insight, even from museums.</p>
        <p>For an Internet art feast, try Maurits Cornelis Escher (1898-1972), the Dutch graphic artist. His experiments in perspective, his mathematically grounded lithographs and his spatial illusions have struck a chord with several Web audiences: art lovers, math and science students and fans of the fantastic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU would think that art and the Internet were made for each other. But all artists are not equal on the Web. There are reproductions, to be sure, but what about ''appreciation''? Some renowned artists are represented by little more than a few capsule biographies and a lot of dealers, with precious little commentary or insight, even from museums.</p>
        <p>For an Internet art feast, try Maurits Cornelis Escher (1898-1972), the Dutch graphic artist. His experiments in perspective, his mathematically grounded lithographs and his spatial illusions have struck a chord with several Web audiences: art lovers, math and science students and fans of the fantastic.</p>
        <p>Escher is known for drawings, woodcuts and lithographs of things like steps that go up and down at the same time, waterfalls that replenish themselves, hands that draw each other and repeating patterns, known mathematically as tessellations, of lizards, birds and other shapes.</p>
        <p>''Long before the first computer-generated 3-D images were thrilling the public, Escher was a master of the third dimension,'' notes a page from the World of Escher (www .worldofescher.com), a Texas company founded in 1993. Its five-year-old Web site includes an Escher gallery, a bibliography and a selection of Escher quotations and essays by and about him. It also offers posters, neckties, T-shirts, CD-ROM's, jigsaw puzzles and -- in a tie-in with its graphic-design merchandise -- a series of contests for students who would like to try their hand at creating their own Escher-style tessellations.</p>
        <p>The site draws 30,000 visitors a month, and it has received more than 1,700 entries from students around the world since June 1995, said Paul Schofield, the site's Webmaster, in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>In an online essay, a past editor of the site, Tom Litchfield, asks, ''Can you imagine his thoughts on computer programs that automatically generate tessellations; would he be excited or woefully disappointed?''</p>
        <p>He also wonders what Escher would think about all the merchandise. The site reprints a 1969 letter by Escher in which he complained to his son that ''the hippies of San Francisco continue to print my work illegally.'' He hated ''virulently colored posters,'' he added. But Mr. Litchfield surmises that Escher would have eventually accepted and approved of his work's popularization.</p>
        <p>Totally Tessellated (library .thinkquest.org/16661) won a 1998 ThinkQuest Internet Challenge contest sponsored by a company called Advanced Network and Services, which invites students and their academic coaches to form teams to design educational Web sites.</p>
        <p>It has an extensive discussion of tessellations, those repeating figures that fill two dimensions, as well as a series of hands-on activities. The site's many pages explore the history of tessellation as an artistic concept. It includes the Moorish motifs in the Alhambra in Spain, which Escher visited and which profoundly influenced him.</p>
        <p>The site has a large Escher section, with a lavishly illustrated biography that shows examples of Escher's explorations of infinity, knots, perspective and impossible architecture as well as tessellations. There are also sections on related art movements, like Cubism, and mathematical topics.</p>
        <p>Another teaching site, from IProject Online (www.iproject.com /escher/teaching/teaching.html), offers a number of lesson plans and classroom suggestions.</p>
        <p>On the official M. C. Escher Web site (www.mcescher.com), a biography of Escher points out that in addition to his famous impossible figures, he designed postage stamps and tapestries, illustrated books and sometimes worked in three dimensions, carving wooden spheres. Viewers can download a free interactive game. The site's news section warns about fake Escher prints being offered on eBay.</p>
        <p>The highlight of the site is a 3-D multimedia section that flies a viewer around and through three of Escher's most famous works. It was developed for a 1998 exhibition in Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where, the site says, visitors stood for two hours to watch what can now be seen online: a vivid unraveling of how Escher fooled the eye by compressing multiple viewpoints into one.</p>
        <p>Among the Escher quotations on the site is this one: ''I walk around in mysteries. Each time, youngsters say, You make Op Art, too. I don't know what that is, Op Art. This work I have been making for the past 30 years.''</p>
        <p>SCREEN GRAB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
