<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Museum-Class House That Post Toasties Built</title>
    <meta content="28HILL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/living/28HILL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Post, Marjorie Merriweather (1887-1973)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molotsky, Irvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6DA103AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Museum-Class House That Post Toasties Built</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRVIN MOLOTSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Molotsky, Irvin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillwood, museum-class house in Washington, DC, that belonged to late Marjorie Merriweather Post, reopens after $9 million renovation; houses greatest collection of Russian imperial art of 18th and 19th centuries outside of Russia and other imperial objects; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY, you live like a queen, don't you?'' was the comment of Queen Maude of Norway to Marjorie Merriweather Post. Mrs. Post did indeed, and she filled Hillwood, her home-museum at 4155 Linnean Avenue NW, which has just reopened, with a battalion of royal objects. Her collection of imperial Russian art from the 18th and 19th centuries is the greatest in the world outside Russia, and she had one of the leading United States collections of Sevres porcelain, much of it commissioned by Catherine the Great.</p>
        <p>Her 19th-century red Aubusson rug was a gift from Napoleon III to the ill-fated Emperor Maximilian of Mexico. Post lore has William Randolph Hearst (another American with a castle complex) as a onetime owner of the rug. But somehow it ''never got to San Simeon,'' said Ann Odom, the chief curator and deputy director of the collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY, you live like a queen, don't you?'' was the comment of Queen Maude of Norway to Marjorie Merriweather Post. Mrs. Post did indeed, and she filled Hillwood, her home-museum at 4155 Linnean Avenue NW, which has just reopened, with a battalion of royal objects. Her collection of imperial Russian art from the 18th and 19th centuries is the greatest in the world outside Russia, and she had one of the leading United States collections of Sevres porcelain, much of it commissioned by Catherine the Great.</p>
        <p>Her 19th-century red Aubusson rug was a gift from Napoleon III to the ill-fated Emperor Maximilian of Mexico. Post lore has William Randolph Hearst (another American with a castle complex) as a onetime owner of the rug. But somehow it ''never got to San Simeon,'' said Ann Odom, the chief curator and deputy director of the collection.</p>
        <p>Hillwood, which Mrs. Post bought in 1955, after her third divorce, sits on 25 acres at the edge of Rock Creek Park. Half the grounds are wooded and half are formal gardens. Besides the main house, which was shut for a three-year, $9 million renovation including some of the grounds, there are a dacha with Russian artifacts and an Adirondacks lodge with American Indian material.</p>
        <p>''It was a great party house,'' said Frederick J. Fisher, director of what is now the Hillwood Museum. ''She was a great entertainer in Washington, with one room designed for movies and dances.''</p>
        <p>Marjorie Merriweather Post was born into a family that became wealthy from Postum, Grape-Nuts and Post Toasties. She married and divorced, in succession, a New York lawyer named Edward Close; E. F. Hutton, the stockbroker (and father of her daughter Dina Merrill, the actress); Joseph E. Davies, a Washington lawyer; and Herbert A. May, a Pittsburgh industrialist. She took back her maiden name after the last divorce, but kept the ''Mrs.'' When she died in 1973, her fortune was estimated at $200 million, the equivalent of $769 million today.</p>
        <p>After husband No. 3, Mr. Davies, was appointed ambassador to the Soviet Union, Mrs. Post's collection of Russian furnishings and objets d'art grew. Hillwood's two-story entrance hall is lined with Russian portraits. ''They are almost all of the czars and czarinas, talking to each other, having nice conversations,'' Mr. Fisher said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Odum said, ''She had a fascination for porcelain and had collected Sevres.'' Bulk purchases were needed: Mrs. Post hauled out the Sevres for her frequent dinner parties for 30.</p>
        <p>The stars of the Post collection are its 90 works by Faberge, especially Easter eggs, but also boxes, clocks, a walking-stick handle made of gold, nephrite, diamonds and rubies and an ashtray of silver, enamel and quartz that does not seem ever to have felt the stub of a cigar.</p>
        <p>In the Icon Room is a large pink Faberge egg given by the last czar, Nicholas II, to his mother in 1914. It is made of gold, diamonds and pearls and decorated with enamel. Inside pearl-lined frames are allegorical paintings, after Francois Boucher, depicting the arts and the sciences. Mr. Fisher calls it ''the last of the really beautiful eggs.''</p>
        <p>In one corner of Hillwood, there is a present from Polina S. Zhemchuzhina, the wife of Prime Minister Vyacheslav M. Molotov and a Soviet official herself. As a parting gift, she allowed the couple to choose from the Kuskovo ceramics museum. What they liked were two vases made in 1836 at the Imperial Porcelain Factory in St. Petersburg. They are 27 inches high and gilded to imitate gilt bronze, with painted landscapes on their sides. Soviet officials were probably sorry to see the couple leave, since Mrs. Post bought much imperial procelain for her collection.</p>
        <p>Her divorce from Mr. Davies in 1955 forced her to split her Russian collection with him, so she began buying replacements. After Mr. Davies died in 1958, she bought pieces from his estate.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of her life, Mrs. Post decided that her collection should some day be made available to the public in a museum of the decorative arts, and Hillwood was renovated with that in mind. She consolidated pieces that had been at her 54-room triplex at 92nd Street and Fifth Avenue in Manhattan, which was described in the 1920's as the largest apartment ever built, and at her Mar-a-Lago estate in Palm Beach (now in Donald Trump's hands), and put them in Hillwood.</p>
        <p>The grounds around Hillwood are as carefully laid out as the public spaces inside the main house. A formal Japanese garden (as yet unrestored) was designed by Shogo Myaida, a Japanese-born landscape architect, who designed the gardens at the 1939-40 New York World's Fair, Jones Beach and the Brooklyn Botanic Garden. At Hillwood, he deployed stone lanterns, tiny wooden bridges and a stone pagoda. A parterre garden has also been rejuvenated with a new fountain.</p>
        <p>Another garden, in the formal French style, has a ring of rose bushes surrounding wax begonias and boxwood, which set off a 3-foot pink stone pedestal topped by a 10-foot column. It is Mrs. Post's memorial, and her ashes are there.</p>
        <p>Those ashes are near a putting green (she had one at each of her residences) and a planting of ivy. Even that has a claim to grandeur. A nearby sign states, ''This ivy is from Buckingham Palace, London, England.''</p>
        <p>Tours of the house and garden are by reservation only (refundable deposit required: $10; those over 65, $8; students and those under 18, $5). Only 250 people a day are allowed to visit the museum, which is in a residential neighborhood; (202) 686-5807.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
