<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Techno Fabrics Suffer Red Wine Stylishly</title>
    <meta content="28SHOP$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohrlich, Marianne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Personal Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7D9103AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Techno Fabrics Suffer Red Wine Stylishly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marianne Rohrlich</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohrlich, Marianne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Personal Shopper column on sources and prices of new techno-fabrics of man-made materials that are washable, scrubbable and water repellent; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THINK the withdrawal of Scotchgard from the market means being forever careful eating that bowl of cereal in the den? Don't worry. Spill whatever you want -- coffee, ice cream, mustard. We did it on these techno fabrics, all of man-made materials like polyester and plastic, and found that a cloth and hot soapy water removed everything. Techno fabrics are washable, scrubbable, even water-repellant. And they have a cachet borrowed from the world of fashion, where designers like Helmut Lang and Jil Sander have used them. ''It's all about cross-marketing,'' said Michael Maharam, an owner of Maharam, a textile company in the forefront of innovative materials. ''But plastic fabric is definitely fashionable.''</p>
        <p>Stylish plastic upholstery fabric? ''If the light is right you see rainbows in the plastic fabric on my new furniture,'' said Andree Putman. ''Plastic is not only fashionable now, it's also never tacky. In fact, it has a fantastic luster.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THINK the withdrawal of Scotchgard from the market means being forever careful eating that bowl of cereal in the den? Don't worry. Spill whatever you want -- coffee, ice cream, mustard. We did it on these techno fabrics, all of man-made materials like polyester and plastic, and found that a cloth and hot soapy water removed everything. Techno fabrics are washable, scrubbable, even water-repellant. And they have a cachet borrowed from the world of fashion, where designers like Helmut Lang and Jil Sander have used them. ''It's all about cross-marketing,'' said Michael Maharam, an owner of Maharam, a textile company in the forefront of innovative materials. ''But plastic fabric is definitely fashionable.''</p>
        <p>Stylish plastic upholstery fabric? ''If the light is right you see rainbows in the plastic fabric on my new furniture,'' said Andree Putman. ''Plastic is not only fashionable now, it's also never tacky. In fact, it has a fantastic luster.''</p>
        <p>Jhane Barnes, the men's clothing designer, has also developed her own line of upholstery fabric and furniture. Her newest computer-generated, brightly colored upholstery fabric, made in Japan, was originally created for cushioning the inside of running shoes. ''My fabric is so strong and durable that you are guaranteed to tire of your furniture before the fabric wears out,'' she said.  She acknowledges that she would want only natural fibers for bedding. ''But for upholstery that my dog is going to jump all over, then I love synthetics,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Certain new materials fall between vinyl and fabric, said Kathryn Gabriel, vice president of marketing at Design Tex, another company experimenting with durable high-tech materials. Some woven plastics feel and look like the elegant stiff horsehair on Victorian settees, but, she says, others have a very ''soft hand,'' meaning a sensuous drape and feel.</p>
        <p>1. Jhane Barnes's Spacer, originally used in automobile upholstery, is 100 percent polyester ($66 a yard). From (800) 922-0542 or www.jhanebarnestextiles.com.</p>
        <p>2. Ms. Putman's Sitting on a Cloud armchair, in Xorel, is $2,000 at Pucci International, 44 West 18th Street. Xorel, a woven polyethylene, comes in many textures: the two on the bottom are called Structures, by Anne Beetz, a Belgian designer ($27 a yard). The orange swatch comes in 11 other solids ($20 a yard). Speedbump (top) is $27 a yard. From Carnegie Fabrics, (800) 727-6770 or www.carnegiefabrics.com.</p>
        <p>3. Teflon-coated moleskin, a soft cotton and polyester chenille, repels everything; in 33 colors, $103 a yard at Donghia, 979 Third Avenue (59th Street) to the trade.</p>
        <p>4. Spectacle (cushion) is an iridescent 100-percent polyester fabric; $58 a yard. Tailored black and white stripes and gray herringbone, both plastic, are from Ms. Putman's Composites series; $30 a yard. Turquoise and chartreuse Action Fabric, used in running shoes, is polyester and comes in many bright combinations; $38 a yard. From Maharam, (800) 645-3943 or www.</p>
        <p>maharam.com.</p>
        <p>5. Sensuede, made of polyester and polyurethane, is available in a multitude of colors; $60 a yard at Joe's Fabric Warehouse, 108 Orchard Street (Delancey Street). It easily passed a lipstick and ink test.</p>
        <p>6. XenonToo (on the chair), and Indium, the black and white check, are woven vinyl-coated polyester; $56 a yard. All other swatches are Atomic, which feels soft and breathes like fabric but is as durable as</p>
        <p>vinyl; $60 a yard from Design Tex, (800) 221-1540 or www.dtex.com.</p>
        <p>7. Saarinen's 20th-century Womb Chair in a 21st-century nylon called Chroma (also the  green swatch); $28 a yard. Swatches from the bottom are Grate (polyester, rayon and cotton), $36 a yard; Synthesis (nylon and polyester), $29 a yard; and Una, (nylon and elastin), $69 a yard. All from Knoll, 105 Wooster Street (Spring Street), or (877) 615-6655 or www.knoll.com.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
