<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Open Will Be 4th L.P.G.A. Major</title>
    <meta content="28LPGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/sports/28LPGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weetabix Women's British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Du Maurier Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2D8113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Open Will Be 4th L.P.G.A. Major</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weetabix Women's British Open will become a major championship next year, allowing LPGA to continue having four majors on its schedule, after losing du Maurier Classic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Weetabix Women's British Open will become a major championship next year, allowing the L.P.G.A. to continue having four majors on its schedule, L.P.G.A. officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The L.P.G.A. lost the du Maurier Classic, a major championship that was played for the final time in August, because of sponsorship problems caused by anti-tobacco laws in Canada. That left the L.P.G.A. with two options for next year -- to have only three major championships or to designate another tournament as the fourth major.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Weetabix Women's British Open will become a major championship next year, allowing the L.P.G.A. to continue having four majors on its schedule, L.P.G.A. officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The L.P.G.A. lost the du Maurier Classic, a major championship that was played for the final time in August, because of sponsorship problems caused by anti-tobacco laws in Canada. That left the L.P.G.A. with two options for next year -- to have only three major championships or to designate another tournament as the fourth major.</p>
        <p>Selecting the women's British Open to become the fourth major became attractive to Ty Votaw, the L.P.G.A. commissioner, because the tournament has been on the L.P.G.A. schedule since 1994 and provided the criteria he was looking for: prestige, financial resources for a long-term commitment, a world-renowned site, television exposure and an attractive place on the L.P.G.A. schedule.</p>
        <p>Next year's women's British Open will be played Aug. 2 to Aug. 5 at Sunningdale Golf Club in Berkshire, England. In subsequent years, the tournament will be rotated among four of Europe's most prestigious courses -- Turnberry Golf Links in Scotland, Royal Lytham, St. Annes and Royal Birkdale in England, and Sunningdale.</p>
        <p>Votaw said the L.P.G.A. considered having just three majors next year, but adding the newest major quickly became the preferred option.</p>
        <p>''We wanted any major championship to have a sense of tradition and prestige in the world of golf, so that there would be public acceptance of the event as a major,'' Votaw said.</p>
        <p>The L.P.G.A. also released the bulk of next year's schedule, from January through Labor Day, including the dates of the other three majors: the Nabisco Championship (March 22 to 25), the United States Women's Open (May 31 to June 3) and the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship (June 21 to 24).</p>
        <p>The Women's Open next year in Pine Needles, N.C., should receive far more news media attention than this year's event, which was held the same week that Tiger Woods was winning the men's British Open at St. Andrews, Scotland. None of the women's majors next year will be held opposite a men's major. But next year's Nabisco Championship will still be held the same week as the Players Championship on the PGA Tour, a conflict that Votaw hopes will end within the next few years.</p>
        <p>''I know I'll get beaten up again by people saying we should not hold the Nabisco Championship opposite the Players Championship, but once again, television commitments prevented us from doing anything about it,'' Votaw said. ''At least for next year, and probably 2002, Nabisco will be opposite the Players, until the PGA Tour's new television contract possibly moves the Players.''</p>
        <p>Next year's ShopRite L.P.G.A. Classic will be held June 29 to July 1 at the Marriott Seaview Resort Bay Course in Atlantic City, N.J., while the Big Apple Classic will be held July 19 to 22 at Wykagyl Country Club in New Rochelle, N.Y.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
