<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; Back When A Water Scare Was a Crisis</title>
    <meta content="28MATT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/nyregion/28MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plutonium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plutonium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DB1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; Back When A Water Scare Was a Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column, noting recent scare over contamination of bottled water in New York City, recalls crisis 15 years ago over disclosure that city's water supply contained too much plutonium (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO the great water scare is over. There was no bad stuff in bottled water, just a guy pulling a scam, and maybe some wayward Palmolive.</p>
        <p>Yet for days, the city was all worked up about a few people getting purported stomachaches -- people gullible enough to buy water that is no more than gussied-up tap water anyway. A sad development indeed. The latest example of the wimpification of New York. Time was we could conduct a proper water crisis. Could we ever. In 1985, New York City lived through a water crisis worthy of a movie. Talk of drama. ''Spin City,'' move over. But the public was so nonchalant and the story such a blip that probably few remember the bizarre happenings of that bizarre day in late July. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO the great water scare is over. There was no bad stuff in bottled water, just a guy pulling a scam, and maybe some wayward Palmolive.</p>
        <p>Yet for days, the city was all worked up about a few people getting purported stomachaches -- people gullible enough to buy water that is no more than gussied-up tap water anyway. A sad development indeed. The latest example of the wimpification of New York. Time was we could conduct a proper water crisis. Could we ever. In 1985, New York City lived through a water crisis worthy of a movie. Talk of drama. ''Spin City,'' move over. But the public was so nonchalant and the story such a blip that probably few remember the bizarre happenings of that bizarre day in late July. . . .</p>
        <p>The story broke in City Hall. It was a hot and humid Friday, nice and slow -- always welcome with a summer weekend coming up. About 3 o'clock, a press secretary announced that Mayor Edward I. Koch would hold a news conference at 4:30 on ''a matter of scientific importance.'' That's all he would say, before beating a retreat behind the French doors separating the mayor's suite from the rest of City Hall -- closed for the first time anyone could remember.</p>
        <p>Even 15 years ago, before the advent of the perpetual news cycle, that tease was enough to send reporters into a dither. The ever-loquacious, accessible Mr. Koch was hiding out and planning a news conference on an ambiguous subject? And not for 90 minutes?</p>
        <p>Editors clamored. Rumors abounded. Frustration built. Tempers flared. Reporters being reporters, and mayoral aides being mayoral aides (in those premilitarized days at City Hall), the story leaked long before the official announcement, even before Mr. Koch called top editors at every newspaper, asking them to avoid sensationalism. Here's what was going on: They found plutonium in the water supply.</p>
        <p>Tests showed that our drinking water contained too much plutonium -- the stuff of nuclear power plants and bombs. The water was still judged safe to drink, though, even if it did betray a whiff of plutonium perfume. The full story came at the afternoon news conference in the Blue Room of City Hall, conducted not just by the mayor but by scientists from the federal Department of Energy, who had been huddling all day in the basement.</p>
        <p>Seems that nearly four months earlier, an anonymous letter addressed to the mayor had arrived in the mail room of City Hall. The writer threatened to contaminate the water supply with plutonium trichloride unless the government dropped all charges against Bernard Goetz -- charged with (and later acquitted of) attempted murder in the shooting of four teenagers on a subway train.</p>
        <p>The letter was referred to the Police Department's intelligence division, which notified the Federal Bureau of Investigation. Federal and city agences began coordinated tests. The mayor, top police officials and the regional director of the F.B.I. were not told about the letter until late June (nearly three months later), after a test of city water showed levels of plutonium-239 -- used in nuclear power plants, nuclear weapons and research laboratories -- nearly 200 times above the norm.</p>
        <p>THAT amount was still well below the level considered dangerous. But still, it was plutonium. Security was tightened at the reservoirs, and tests continued. One conducted nearly a month later still showed an elevated level of radiation, and two subsequent tests showed only trace levels of plutonium.</p>
        <p>Since the water was judged safe to drink, the authorities decided not to risk inducing panic by telling the public about those high radiation levels. But then a reporter for The Patriot of Harrisburg, Pa., began asking questions, as did one at WCBS-TV.</p>
        <p>So the mayor and friends held their news conference to a packed crowd, and quite the performance it was, complete with scientific testimony and a convincing show of mayoral mastery over ''femtocuries'' (a millionth of a billionth of a curie, the standard measure of radioactivity).</p>
        <p>Tests conducted later that summer showed only normal levels of plutonium in the city's water. To this day, it is not known, at least not officially, what happened or who wrote the letter. Could be the threat was carried out -- inadequately. Maybe it was a hoax (the threatening letter arrived on April Fools' Day); could be the test vials were somehow contaminated.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reality, the story was a one-  or two-day wonder. Sales of Evian water spiked, but only briefly, and most New Yorkers kept drinking tap water. Now that was a proper New York crisis. New Yorkers did what New Yorkers do. Or did. They ignored it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
