<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Man, 82, Is First Known West Nile Fatality in U.S. This Year</title>
    <meta content="28NILE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/nyregion/28NILE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Passaic County (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DB1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Man, 82, Is First Known West Nile Fatality in U.S. This Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey officials announce that 82-year-old Passaic County man died of West Nile virus two weeks ago, first person known to die of disease in United States this year; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey officials announced yesterday that an 82-year-old Passaic County man died of the West Nile virus two weeks ago, the first person known to die of the disease in the United States this year.</p>
        <p>Officials believe it is most likely that the man was bitten in August. He fell ill on Sept. 3, was admitted three days later to Mountainside Hospital in Montclair, and died there on Sept. 14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey officials announced yesterday that an 82-year-old Passaic County man died of the West Nile virus two weeks ago, the first person known to die of the disease in the United States this year.</p>
        <p>Officials believe it is most likely that the man was bitten in August. He fell ill on Sept. 3, was admitted three days later to Mountainside Hospital in Montclair, and died there on Sept. 14.</p>
        <p>The diagnosis of West Nile was delayed while blood and tissue studies were conducted. The man had chronic illnesses as well, officials said.</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman and other state officials did not name the man but said he had lived in Little Falls. He was identified as Anthony Opalka by the Herald News of West Paterson, The Associated Press reported last night.</p>
        <p>In all, there have been four cases of West Nile in New Jersey this year.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if I would call this an epidemic,'' Dr. Eddy A. Bresnitz, the deputy state commissioner of health, said yesterday at the news conference in Hackensack. ''I think what we do have is an outbreak.''</p>
        <p>A 72-year-old woman from Bayonne also contracted the disease in the last few months, but she is already home recovering, officials said. The other human cases previously confirmed in New Jersey involved a 43-year-old man from Jersey City and a 54-year-old man who had homes in both Cliffside Park and Brooklyn, N.Y. Both men were hospitalized for treatment and are recovering.</p>
        <p>Blood tests were performed on 18 other people in the state whose illnesses resembled West Nile, but the results are still pending.</p>
        <p>In New York City, West Nile has been diagnosed this year in 13 people, including a 73-year-old woman from Queens who the city announced yesterday was hospitalized but recovering. Among the other cases, eight were treated and released and four remain hospitalized.</p>
        <p>Scores of birds and other animals have contracted the disease this year, so many that many health care officials have been surprised that more human cases did not emerge. Explanations of why that could be range from crediting state prevention campaigns to musing about the weather: Did cold air keep people inside? Did the wet summer keep birds around so mosquitoes were drawn to them instead of to humans?</p>
        <p>While state officials never like to have any cases in their areas, the New York region has fared far better than Israel, where 14 people have died of West Nile this year.</p>
        <p>Last year, West Nile killed 7 people in the New York region and severely sickened 55 others.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman said yesterday that New Jersey would re-evaluate its West Nile control plan, which has included spraying insecticide to kill adult mosquitoes in every county. In Bergen County tomorrow, the state will spray between 3 and 6 a.m. in the Carlstadt, Wood-Ridge, Franklin Lakes and Mahwah areas.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, this is a disease that's going to be with us for some time,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''And I intend after this season is over to ask the relevant cabinet members, including the secretary of commerce and economic growth, the secretary of agriculture, the commissioner of health and senior services, to get together and to reassess everything that we have done.''</p>
        <p>Insecticides have been sprayed this year in all five New York City boroughs and in Westchester and Rockland Counties, on Long Island and in Connecticut and New Jersey, though not always to the satisfaction of New York City officials. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani had complained earlier this year that northern New Jersey and Nassau County were endangering public health by not spraying aggressively enough.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
