<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voila, and More: Black Readers</title>
    <meta content="28BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/arts/28BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000929T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DD113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voila, and More: Black Readers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's making Books column on large and growing citizenry of blacks who buy books and are greedy for reading material relevant to them; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the epiphanies that have smitten book publishing lately, the most interesting is not the future of the e-book or print-on-demand or online publishing. Rather it is that there is a large and growing citizenry of black people who buy books and are greedy for reading material relevant to them.</p>
        <p>Last week's column was about a small, new publishing house that next month will start selling a series of short, provocative pulp fiction paperbacks, violent and sexual, aimed at black urban youths, the literary equivalent of hip-hop videos. A captivating and roguish idea. But something far more extraordinary is happening in book publishing. Suddenly there are five imprints in major book publishing companies committed to publishing new lines of fiction (not romances) and nonfiction by black writers on black subjects, and three of them have started up this year. Of course, this is about money, not the sudden awakening of social consciousness in a business in which African-Americans as editors and writers haven't counted, with only the occasional exceptions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the epiphanies that have smitten book publishing lately, the most interesting is not the future of the e-book or print-on-demand or online publishing. Rather it is that there is a large and growing citizenry of black people who buy books and are greedy for reading material relevant to them.</p>
        <p>Last week's column was about a small, new publishing house that next month will start selling a series of short, provocative pulp fiction paperbacks, violent and sexual, aimed at black urban youths, the literary equivalent of hip-hop videos. A captivating and roguish idea. But something far more extraordinary is happening in book publishing. Suddenly there are five imprints in major book publishing companies committed to publishing new lines of fiction (not romances) and nonfiction by black writers on black subjects, and three of them have started up this year. Of course, this is about money, not the sudden awakening of social consciousness in a business in which African-Americans as editors and writers haven't counted, with only the occasional exceptions.</p>
        <p>Still, despite that touch of realism, Anita Diggs, the African-American director of One World Books, a Random House Inc. imprint, said, ''It's extraordinary, it's great, it's wonderful and it's book publishing history.'' One World was founded in 1992 to publish books by and about African-Americans, Hispanics and Asians,  though most of its books are about blacks. ''There's a lot of money in this area,'' Ms. Diggs said. ''We can't write them and publish them fast enough. Blacks are buying fiction at a rate we just can't keep up with. What we need now is more black sales reps, more blacks in marketing.'' One World publishes hardcover and trade and mass market paperbacks. It produces about 10 books a year but expects to go to 15 to 20 by 2003.</p>
        <p>I would posit that the idea that African-Americans, other than perhaps those who were college professors, would buy books in great numbers penetrated the thinking of book publishers only relatively recently. The voila came in 1992 with the publication of ''Waiting to Exhale'' (Viking), Terry McMillan's irreverent, rollicking novel about the friendship of four black women in Phoenix. The book became a huge best seller in hardcover and paperback, with more than three million copies sold worldwide, and then was a hit movie.</p>
        <p>Karen R. Thomas, executive editor of the new Dafina Books imprint at the Kensington Publishing Corporation, said, ''I think there was a lot of suspicion that 'Waiting to Exhale' was a fluke, maybe it was one book people wanted to read, but it was so successful that publishers began to realize that it wasn't a fluke; that there was a craving out there by blacks for quality books that speak to them.'' Dafina will publish books in all formats and most genres, although not romance. Its first two books, in trade paperback, came out this month. They are ''Souls of My Sisters: Black Women Break Their Silence, Tell Their Stories and Heal Their Spirits,'' written and edited by Dawn Marie Daniels and Candace Sandy, and a novel, ''Lookin' For Luv'' by Carol Weber.</p>
        <p>Of the five imprints, only Amistad Press was started before Ms. McMillan's novel. Its founder and publisher, Charles F. Harris, created a publishing program that included books by Arthur Ashe, the late tennis star who invested in the company, and Susan Taylor, the editor of Essence magazine. Mr. Harris also started the Amistad Literary Series, which did literary studies of Langston Hughes, Richard Wright, Alice Walker and Toni Morrison, among others, edited by Henry Louis Gates Jr.</p>
        <p>Last year HarperCollins acquired Amistad, and Mr. Harris remained as the imprint's editorial director. ''Book publishers lagged behind the rest of the entertainment industry in its interest in black Americans,'' Mr. Harris said. ''I think there's now a realization that to a great extent African-Americans are purchasing books, and are important consumers for publishing.''</p>
        <p>Is there a real increase in the purchasing or simply a new awareness that African-Americans buy books in greater numbers than was supposed? Although it's inferential, it's probably a real increase. If so, why? One reason is that even before the new imprints, in recent years there have been more books written and published for black Americans. Furthermore, Opra Winfrey's book club has noticeably increased the sales of books not only by and to whites, but by and to blacks also. Moreover, there is an ever growing black middle class, and it's the middle class that supports the book industry.</p>
        <p>Random House Inc. has three of the black imprints. Besides One World Books, it has two new black imprints:, Strivers Row, headed by Melody Guy, which will publish its first three novels in January, and Harlem Moon, headed by Janet Hill, which will continue to acquire and edit hardcover African-American books for Doubleday.</p>
        <p>Harlem Moon will specialize in black fiction and nonfiction trade paper originals, with the first ones scheduled for next fall. ''I also want to do a line of classics, with introductions, to get that work to larger audiences,'' Ms. Hill said. This year, too, Denise Stinson, a black literary agent, founded an imprint with Warner Books called Walk Worthy Press, which will specialize in hardcover Christian commercial fiction and nonfiction, starting with three novels to be published next year.</p>
        <p>Now if all this sounds promising, there are, within publishing, African-Americans who point out that many black authors in recent years started out in self-publishing and had to hawk their own novels not only in black bookstores but also in beauty parlors and other places where books are not usually sold. The fear is that because so many of the books that will be published by these five imprints will be paperbacks, the publishers are getting a good buy at bargain prices. That is because paperbacks traditionally mean smaller author advances and smaller marketing and advertising budgets and smaller book tours, if any. In essence, the critics say that the authors will be doing much of the same heavy hauling they did when they were self-published. One African-American in publishing said, ''This is boot camp for black writers.''</p>
        <p>The upside, of course, is the commitment of major mainstream publishers to black writers and to African-Americans who want to read books that connect to their lives. ''Black is beautiful'' was a slogan in full glory in the 1960's. It's taken book publishers about 40 years to catch on. Well, at least they've gotten as far as ''Black is pretty.''</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS  Correction:  September 29, 2000, Friday  The Making Books column yesterday, about the publishing industry's increasing attention to black readers, misspelled the given name of the television host whose book club has stimulated sales by and to blacks along with whites. She is Oprah Winfrey, not Opra.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 29, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>The Making Books column yesterday, about the publishing industry's increasing attention to black readers, misspelled the given name of the television host whose book club has stimulated sales by and to blacks along with whites. She is Oprah Winfrey, not Opra.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
