<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Engineers' Marvels, Solved in Pictures</title>
    <meta content="28DAVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/living/28DAVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001005T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCaulay, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Building Big (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DD113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Engineers' Marvels, Solved in Pictures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN LELAND</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David McCaulay's newest book, Building Big, explains dauntingly complex works of civil engineering in simple, comprehensible images and transforms physical principles into engaging narrative; photo; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN automobile piston, as anyone who has read David Macaulay's 1988 best seller, ''The Way Things Work,'' can tell you, is a simple reciprocating pump that operates on the principle of . . . well, it would be a lot easier to explain using one of the witty illustrations that fill Mr. Macaulay's books and television programs. You could blow a gasket trying to explain some of the principles that Mr. Macaulay, an author and illustrator, distills into simple, illuminating images.</p>
        <p>Under a heavy sky in Brooklyn earlier this week, Mr. Macaulay, 53, was at it again, pointing up at the maze of beams and cables supporting the Brooklyn Bridge and talking about force. The vertical cables, he explained, suspend the roadway from above, while the diagonal cables fight wind sheer by . . . frankly, here again it would help to call upon one of his eloquent sketches, which combine the technical insight of a draftsman's drawings with the chatty unpretentiousness of children's book illustrations. They make long stories short and sweet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN automobile piston, as anyone who has read David Macaulay's 1988 best seller, ''The Way Things Work,'' can tell you, is a simple reciprocating pump that operates on the principle of . . . well, it would be a lot easier to explain using one of the witty illustrations that fill Mr. Macaulay's books and television programs. You could blow a gasket trying to explain some of the principles that Mr. Macaulay, an author and illustrator, distills into simple, illuminating images.</p>
        <p>Under a heavy sky in Brooklyn earlier this week, Mr. Macaulay, 53, was at it again, pointing up at the maze of beams and cables supporting the Brooklyn Bridge and talking about force. The vertical cables, he explained, suspend the roadway from above, while the diagonal cables fight wind sheer by . . . frankly, here again it would help to call upon one of his eloquent sketches, which combine the technical insight of a draftsman's drawings with the chatty unpretentiousness of children's book illustrations. They make long stories short and sweet.</p>
        <p>The bridge is one of the massive engineering projects Mr. Macaulay seeks to demystify in his new book, ''Building Big'' (Houghton Mifflin, $30), and in a five-part public television series of the same name that begins on Tuesday. ''Building Big,'' whether book or television program, comes stuffed with his illustrations, explaining civil works of daunting complexity in simple, comprehensible images and transforming physical principles into engaging narratives. Along the way, the project examines the confluence of ambition, risk and vision that has shaped the growth of modern cities and the lives of the people who inhabit them.</p>
        <p>An architect by training, Mr. Macaulay has made a career of explaining the mechanics of the commonplace fixtures of modern life: the toasters, cathedrals, mills, ships and other engineering feats whose inner lives often pass unexamined. The most popular of his books, ''The Way Things Work,'' has sold 2.5 million copies, plus another 500,000 for a later version, updated as ''The New Way Things Work,'' which adds explanations of things like CD players and the computer mouse. In all his works, he focuses on the bones of design, treating the visible surfaces as the obligatory neat endings to more interesting backstories.</p>
        <p>At the Brooklyn waterfront, raising his voice to compete with the wind and the traffic noise, Mr. Macaulay found he had a lot of explaining to do. Imposing, homely edifices towered all around, monumental constructions of steel and concrete encrusted with layers of soot. Mr. Macaulay could not have been happier.</p>
        <p>''I love process,'' he said, ''and these structures are all about process. They're autobiographical. If you look closely at them, they describe their origins.''</p>
        <p>''Building Big'' is Mr. Macaulay's way of letting those autobiographies speak. Divided into five segments -- tunnels, dams, skyscrapers, bridges and domes -- the project took him from the Aswan High Dam in Egypt to the bowels of the Holland Tunnel. Combining social history with engineering basics, the book and series examine the forces of ego as well as those of tension and compression, and the ways those forces conspire to create the alternatively inspiring and oppressive cityscapes in which modern urbanites live and work.</p>
        <p>Though ''Building Big'' marvels at the scale and daring of its huge edifices, Mr. Macaulay and his producers are careful to note the consequences of the underlying ambitions. Some dams, particularly in the Pacific Northwest, have prevented salmon from swimming upstream to their spawning grounds, contributing to the extinction of as many as 100 salmon species; 500 workers died building the Aswan Dam. Big structures have big impacts on the environments around them.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Macaulay reserves his harshest criticisms for skyscrapers, whose rise he traces from the stone towers erected by feuding clans in San Gimignano, in Tuscany, to the ugly glass boxes of the International style that lurch upward with little regard for the other buildings around them or the people slumped inside. The modern city, he says, is dehumanized by architecture that fails its narrative function.</p>
        <p>''If a skyscraper says something about how it works, it engages you,'' he said. ''If it's just a box, you're held back,'' reducing a building to ''a storage system for the people inside.''</p>
        <p>In his own home life, Mr. Macaulay has sought a smaller scale. With his wife and two young children, he lives in an 1848 Gothic revival house in the coastal town of Bristol, R.I., and makes his studio above a nearby shipbuilding museum. The house has required extensive renovation over the years, and Mr. Macaulay, following the pull of his curiosity, has busied himself with plaster and molding.</p>
        <p>''I'm bigger on the destruction end, tearing down a bathroom,'' he said, than putting it all together again. ''I leave that to the contractor.'' But for an illustrator who specializes in pulling things apart, such demolition provides another way to tell the story of a building.</p>
        <p>The most harrowing story in ''Building Big,'' a segment that appears in the television series but not in the book, raises the prospect of destruction on a much larger scale. During the construction of the Citicorp Center in Manhattan, contractors cut costs by bolting together a series of joints, rather than welding them. A small change, but as engineers realized during construction, it left the building unable to withstand punishing winds. As Hurricane Ella approached in 1962, city officials met secretly with the Red Cross to discuss plans for evacuating Midtown.</p>
        <p>Ella, fortunately, turned out to sea, and welders secured the construction. But the lesson remains at the core of ''Building Big'': every desire for bigness comes with human costs, often reducible to formulas. Mr. Macaulay makes these formulas easy to understand, and all the more brutal in their clarity.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 5, 2000, Thursday  An article last Thursday about ''Building Big,'' a new book and television series that explains large-scale engineering projects, incorrectly dated the hurricane that led Red Cross officials to plan an evacuation of Midtown and, by implication, misstated the year an engineering flaw was discovered in the construction of the Citicorp Building. The hurricane was Ella in 1978, not the one in 1962.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 5, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last Thursday about ''Building Big,'' a new book and television series that explains large-scale engineering projects, incorrectly dated the hurricane that led Red Cross officials to plan an evacuation of Midtown and, by implication, misstated the year an engineering flaw was discovered in the construction of the Citicorp Building. The hurricane was Ella in 1978, not the one in 1962.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
