<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Actors' Strike Dragging On As Talks Break Down</title>
    <meta content="28STRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/business/28STRI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Screen Actors Guild</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Television and Radio Artists</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EEDC1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Actors' Strike Dragging On As Talks Break Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thirteen days of negotiations between representatives of advertisers and actors on strike break down as strike approaches end of its fifth month; negotiators for Screen Actors Guild and American Federation of Television and Radio Artists reject 90-day cooling off period in which actors could return to work under their 1997 contract (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thirteen days of negotiations between representatives of advertisers and actors on strike broke down yesterday as the strike approached the end of its fifth month.</p>
        <p>The day ended with negotiators for the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists rejecting a 90-day cooling off period in which actors could return to work under their 1997 contract, said Greg Krizman, a spokesman for S.A.G.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thirteen days of negotiations between representatives of advertisers and actors on strike broke down yesterday as the strike approached the end of its fifth month.</p>
        <p>The day ended with negotiators for the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists rejecting a 90-day cooling off period in which actors could return to work under their 1997 contract, said Greg Krizman, a spokesman for S.A.G.</p>
        <p>John A. McGuinn, a lawyer representing advertisers, said industry negotiators initially opposed the cooling-off period but then accepted it, going so far as to offer to pay actors retroactively under the new scale for work during the period once a contract was reached. ''I'm really, really disappointed,'' Mr. McGuinn said. ''I thought a deal was within range.''</p>
        <p>Negotiators, who were meeting in New York, said talks broke down over two main issues: whether the new contract would cover work on the Internet and how much actors would be paid for commercials shown on cable television.</p>
        <p>The sides have been at odds over how actors will be paid for advertisements shown on television. Actors have been pushing to expand a system used for network commercials known as pay-for-play, in which they are paid each time a commercial is broadcast. Advertisers had been seeking a flat-fee arrangement like the one used on cable networks.</p>
        <p>The two sides have bridged that gap, agreeing to continue pay-for-play on networks and extending the system of a flat fee for cable. But the two sides are still trying to agree on pay scales for actors' work on cable. Advertisers have proposed a tiered payment system over three years starting at $1,250 for a 13-week cycle the first year of the contract and increasing to $1,850 by the third year. That is well below the $2,500 being sought by the unions for the third year.</p>
        <p>The negotiating committee for the unions was meeting into the evening to determine the next step, Mr. Krizman said. He said actors remained steadfast in their resolve.</p>
        <p>''Our members have known since day one what is at stake here, and it's basically the survival of middle-class actors,'' Mr. Krizman said. ''Middle-class actors won't be able to survive under the terms that they have offered.''</p>
        <p>The talks broke down late in the day after a rally at the Crowne Plaza Hotel in Manhattan featuring several celebrities, including Tim Robbins, Susan Sarandon, Julia Roberts and Richard Dreyfus.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
