<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congressional Leaders Approve a Deal to Allow Food Sales to Cuba</title>
    <meta content="Y28CUB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/national/28CUBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuba-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congressional Leaders Approve a Deal to Allow Food Sales to Cuba</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House and Senate leadership approve deal to allow sale of American food products to Cuba, clearing way for most significant rollback of United States sanctions against Cuba in four decades; sales agreement is brokered between farm-state and anti-Castro lawmakers; it would allow cash sales to Cuba and financing through third countries but bar United States financing; it would also add new category to designated groups of Americans allowed to travel to Cuba (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The House and Senate leadership today approved a deal to allow the sale of American food products to Cuba, clearing the way for the most significant rollback of United States sanctions against the island in four decades.</p>
        <p>The agreement on sales, which was brokered between farm-state and anti-Castro lawmakers, was eagerly sought by American farm groups and first proposed this spring by Representative George Nethercutt, Republican of Washington. It would allow cash sales to Cuba and financing through third countries but bar United States financing, lawmakers said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The House and Senate leadership today approved a deal to allow the sale of American food products to Cuba, clearing the way for the most significant rollback of United States sanctions against the island in four decades.</p>
        <p>The agreement on sales, which was brokered between farm-state and anti-Castro lawmakers, was eagerly sought by American farm groups and first proposed this spring by Representative George Nethercutt, Republican of Washington. It would allow cash sales to Cuba and financing through third countries but bar United States financing, lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>It would also add a new category to the designated groups of Americans who are allowed to travel to Cuba, despite restrictions on spending money there. United States exporters of grains and other food products would be authorized to visit the island to promote sales, just as scholars and journalists are currently allowed, the lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>The arrangement does not, however, allow for the sale of Cuban products in the United States.</p>
        <p>Washington first imposed a ban on trade with Cuba in 1962, after the revolutionary government of President Fidel Castro appropriated more than 6,000 American-owned properties without paying compensation.</p>
        <p>Representative Roy Blunt, Republican of Missouri, brokered the deal  between Mr. Nethercutt and Representative Jo Ann Emerson, Republican of Missouri, on one hand, and Congress's two Cuban-American lawmakers from Florida, Representatives Ileana Ros-Lehtinen and Lincoln Diaz-Balart, both Republicans, on the other. Until now, the two Cuban-Americans have opposed any easing of sanctions against Cuba.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blunt, who said Republican leaders in Congress had approved the deal, said in a telephone interview that it would open Cuban markets to American exporters of rice, pork and other staples. Cuba has long sought to resume trade with the United States, arguing that the trade embargo had forced it to pay a premium in shipping costs.</p>
        <p>''It provides a significant opening of that market to U.S. agricultural products,'' Mr. Blunt said.</p>
        <p>Negotiations in recent weeks between the farm-state and the anti-Castro lawmakers bogged down over the question of financing. The Cuban- American lawmakers prevailed by ruling out American credits for the sales, but those favoring sales scored a victory by winning an allowance for third-country financing.</p>
        <p>Cuba, which has been under an austerity program for a decade since the breakup of the Soviet Union, its former patron, relies on foreign banks for most of its imports.</p>
        <p>Once the new deal becomes law, it would in theory allow the Havana government to turn to a Mexican bank, for example, to finance a purchase. That bank would then notify an American bank that a transaction had been approved, and the American bank would notify the American exporter to proceed with the sale, Mr. Blunt said.</p>
        <p>Congressional sources close to the negotiations warned tonight that it could still fall apart, especially if pro-trade Republican lawmakers, such as Senator John Ashcroft, Republican of Missouri, object to the restrictions against American financing.</p>
        <p>But the drive toward greater openness with Cuba has been evident in recent months, as lawmakers have steadily approved measures to ease restrictions on trade and travel. The Clinton administration has facilitated that effort, by approving visits throughout the Midwest by Cuban diplomats and agricultural officials.</p>
        <p>A White House spokesman did not immediately return a call for comment.</p>
        <p>The deal does not affect the sale of American medicines to Cuba, which is already authorized, provided that purchasers there can demonstrate that the items are not misused or packaged for resale.</p>
        <p>The full House is expected to vote on the Cuba food bill as part of a $75 billion agriculture funding bill next week, Mr. Blunt said, with the Senate expected to follow later in the week.</p>
        <p>The compromise was reached on Capitol Hill as eight prominent Republicans released a joint statement calling for an end to the embargo on food and medical sales to Cuba and a lifting of all travel restrictions imposed on Americans.</p>
        <p>The group -- including Gov. George Ryan of Illinois, William P. Clark, the national security adviser under President Reagan, and Frank Carlucci, defense secretary in the Reagan administration -- said, ''Humanitarian trade should not be used for political leverage.'' A lifting of sanctions would allow ''a flow of people, commerce and ideas that would increase American influence,'' they said.</p>
        <p>In the statement released through the Lexington Institute, a conservative research group, the Republicans said the 1996 Helms-Burton Act, which tightened sanctions on Cuba had proved ineffective. ''It has not brought political change,'' they said. ''It has not resolved property claims; it creates costly disputes with major trading partners.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
