<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SYDNEY 2000: Sports of The Times; Drug Alibi: Dog Ate My Homework</title>
    <meta content="28VECS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hunter, C J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1DD113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SYDNEY 2000: Sports of The Times; Drug Alibi: Dog Ate My Homework</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goerge Vecsey Sports of The Times column says Marion Jones, track star, is in midst of personal drama--her husband, C J Hunter, tested positive for drugs before Games--as she tries to qualify for various events at Olyumpoc Games; says truth is that athletes only mirror rest of world, world full of chemical junkies; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REGARDING that form of drug known as ''performance enhancing,'' there is only one claim I would definitely believe from any athlete:</p>
        <p>''Personally, Chief, I slurp 'em up like corn flakes. I can't wait to finish talking to you so I can go get me some more.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REGARDING that form of drug known as ''performance enhancing,'' there is only one claim I would definitely believe from any athlete:</p>
        <p>''Personally, Chief, I slurp 'em up like corn flakes. I can't wait to finish talking to you so I can go get me some more.''</p>
        <p>That person I would believe.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, it's better to not say anything. If you haven't touched off the alarms, like some hapless tourist trying to enter Olympic Park with a manhole-sized 50-cent coin in your pocket, just keep quiet.</p>
        <p>If they haven't busted you, don't make rash statements. Don't hold news conferences. Don't release your latest urinalysis printouts. I don't want to know. Just keep running or jumping or flinging heavy weights into the atmosphere, whatever your redeeming social value may be.</p>
        <p>Or, if this is your thing, keep jogging around the premises with your burly significant other strapped onto your back. This brand-new Olympic event is currently being performed by Marion Jones, the latest ''Perils of Pauline'' heroine to capture the imagination, the sympathy, of the world during these Final Days (how biblical) of these Summer Games.</p>
        <p>First, Cathy Freeman survived her frigid dousing from the artificial Olympic rain forest during the opening ceremony, and won a gold medal. Then Marie-Jose Perec did not survive the goblins, external or internal, that pursued her, and she got outta town. Now it is Marion Jones's soap opera, and welcome to it.</p>
        <p>Jones became a candidate for Oprah, or maybe even Springer, on Monday when it became known that her husband, C. J. Hunter, had tested positive before the Games. He's a very large person who throws the shot. He says the stuff probably got into his system through some nutritional supplement he was taking. I say, yeah-yeah-yeah.</p>
        <p>Nothing personal about Hunter, but because I suspect many athletes are ingesting or inoculating all kinds of stuff.</p>
        <p>Just yesterday we witnessed the weird spectacle of a former world-record holder, Mihaela Melinte of Romania, being escorted off the infield moments before she was to commence throwing the hammer. Melinte has been suspended for testing positive for nandrolone, the very same substance that was found in Hunter.</p>
        <p>No doubt she has her explanation, but Hunter surely did not get much sympathy from the members of the International Olympic Committee, who are becoming world-class skeptics. There is plenty to be skeptical about.</p>
        <p>There was a story in the paper the other day that workers in the Athletes' Village were concerned after finding syringes in the bedsheets and towels and general detritus of the residents. At least one worker was pricked, a scary prospect in this day and age. It is doubtful there are that many diabetics in the village, and besides, people with real medical needs tend to be responsible.</p>
        <p>The truth is, the athletes only mirror the rest of us, a world full of chemical junkies, gobbling one thing or another for the sniffles or the pips or the blues or the skinny biceps or whatever it is we think ails us.</p>
        <p>Athletes can only hope their chemists are on top of their game, unlike the blithering idiot of a doctor who apparently or allegedly gave cold medicine to the 16-year-old gymnastics gold medalist from Romania, Andreea Raducan.</p>
        <p>The kid was told to cough up her gold medal because we're all on the lookout for drug cheats. It's all so sad, but what are you going to do? When they wake us up in the middle of the night in Seoul or Sydney and say, hey, they just busted Ben Johnson, or Marion Jones's husband, the whole world goes on drug alert. What a bore.</p>
        <p>Jones, who has no known history of dabbling with forbidden fruit, had to pursue her dream of five gold medals while dealing with the busting of her husband. Goodness only knows whether she was aware of it. Husbands don't necessarily tell their wives everything they do.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Jones stood by her man at a news conference. Yesterday she had to qualify in two more events, a long day at the Olympic Stadium.</p>
        <p>Shortly after 11 a.m., she ran the first heat of the women's 200-meter qualifier, finishing in 22.75 seconds, not exactly gold-medal-final pace.</p>
        <p>''I said all along this would be my hardest day at the Olympics,'' Jones said. ''The heats and the long jump. I took it easy in my race, and now I'll try to stay off my feet for a few hours.''</p>
        <p>She came back in the evening and qualified for the finals. Then she qualified for the long-jump final round in her first qualifying jump and got off her feet again. She's carrying a lot of weight around these days.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
