<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4-Star Kitchens Delivered on a Takeout Budget</title>
    <meta content="28KITC$19" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/living/28KITC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRADE SECRETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kitchens</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Louie, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Trade Secrets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kitchens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E3DC113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4-Star Kitchens Delivered on a Takeout Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE LOUIE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Louie, Elaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manhattan apartment kitchen can be remodeled on restricted budget of $20,000; projects undertaken by four designers run from modest $5,000 redo to makeover that slightly topped budget because wall was demolished; photos; diagram; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN New York City, remodeling an entire kitchen for less than $20,000 -- with new appliances in better locations, new countertops, cabinets, floor and labor -- is the equivalent of finding a two-bedroom apartment for $1,000 a month. It's possible, but not very likely.</p>
        <p>To Michael McDonough, a New York architect, the $20,000 remodeled kitchen is an urban fairy tale. ''It's 'the brother-in-law kitchen,' '' he said, meaning that it can be achieved only if your brother-in-law is a licensed plumber, electrician and general contractor, and utterly devoted to you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN New York City, remodeling an entire kitchen for less than $20,000 -- with new appliances in better locations, new countertops, cabinets, floor and labor -- is the equivalent of finding a two-bedroom apartment for $1,000 a month. It's possible, but not very likely.</p>
        <p>To Michael McDonough, a New York architect, the $20,000 remodeled kitchen is an urban fairy tale. ''It's 'the brother-in-law kitchen,' '' he said, meaning that it can be achieved only if your brother-in-law is a licensed plumber, electrician and general contractor, and utterly devoted to you.</p>
        <p>The kitchen and bath are the most expensive rooms to redo because they require appliances, cabinetry, countertops, electricity, water and gas lines, plus the labor to install them. Remodeling magazine pegs a minor American kitchen makeover (new paint, new cabinet fronts, perhaps a new floor) for this year at $8,655, and a major remodeling (the works) at an average of $31,090. The appliances and materials are one-third of the cost; the rest is labor. And in New York, labor runs high. ''All the trades have to be involved,'' said Paul Deffenbaugh, Remodeling's editor in chief. ''You'll do it once or twice in your lifetime, kind of like getting married, and you'll want to do it right.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the $20,000 makeover is possible, especially if no walls or fixtures have to be moved. Here are four kitchens to prove it, from a modest $5,000 redo to a makeover that slightly topped the budget because a wall was demolished. In addition, House &amp; Home asked three Manhattan design firms for budget ''concept'' kitchens. Ikea cabinets, those affordable chameleons, turned up in kitchens traditional and modern (with finishes from aluminum to laminate to cherry). In realizing her vision, Helene Verin sacrificed custom cabinetry -- but not style -- for Ikea's frosted-glass cabinets, lighted from within to glow softly. The savings let her splurge on walnut counters. Each kitchen, real or theoretical, offers uncluttered counter space and invites a person to get busy and cook.</p>
        <p>Whimsical Feminism</p>
        <p>Ms. Verin is a designer of interiors, furniture and wallpaper who lives in the Flatiron district, and her kitchen is a tongue-in-cheek statement of feminism (she just got divorced and she's happy). The pass-through from the kitchen to the dining room is cut in the shape of an egg. And the thick walnut counter for the pass-through? ''It's the shadow of the egg,'' Ms. Verin said. Three ceiling lamps in the shape of milk bottles, designed by Droog, complete the feminist symbolism.</p>
        <p>Ms. Verin knew how to prioritize artfully. She loved the voluptuousness of custom-cut solid walnut, made for the pass-through and around the sink. She then economized by using walnut veneer for below-the-counter cabinetry and the front of the refrigerator. For a backsplash, she had glass cut to fit, but she frosted it herself using a $4 tube of spray frost, called Krylon Glass Interior Frosting Spray. The Magic Chef stove, Bosch dishwasher and Franke sink are new; their chrome or stainless steel finishes resemble those of higher-end appliances. But she kept the old refrigerator.</p>
        <p>The kitchen is 10 feet by 7 feet 3 inches, but ''the advantage of this place is that the ceiling is 12 feet high,'' she said. So she raised the height of the cut-out entrance to the kitchen from 7 1/2 feet to its full 12 feet, and suddenly a small kitchen soared. Total cost: $12,000.</p>
        <p>The Endless Counter</p>
        <p>Suzie Jackson wanted a kitchen with more than enough counter space. Ms. Jackson is a food stylist who until last month lived with her husband, James, and daughter, Edwina, in a TriBeCa loft. (They have since moved to Australia.) Brad Zizmor, who designed the loft with Dag Folger, his partner at A&amp;I Design in Manhattan, obliged. The kitchen is 18 feet long by 12 feet 9 inches wide; the counters run the entire length on both sides.</p>
        <p>The efficient room is an austere homage to the loft's industrial heritage, warmed with wood. The countertops are Fireslate, a synthetic heat-resistant, laboratory countertop material (800-523-5902), so Ms. Jackson could put hot pots directly on it. Although Fireslate is only half an inch thick, the architects attached it to the sides, so the counters appear to be ''big and bulky and permanent,'' Mr. Folger said. They designed a storage system of birch plywood shelves, drawers and cabinetry, framed with Speed-Rail, a cast aluminum tubing system intended for scaffolding or industrial handrails. The floor is trompe l'oeil: What appears to be concrete is 4-by-4-foot squares of Ply-cem, half-inch thick panels of concrete impregnated with wood fibers. ''It's used for industrial roofing,'' Mr. Zizmor said, ''but it's lighter and more stable than plain concrete, which can also crack.'' Total cost: $17,450.</p>
        <p>Midcentury Modern for Less</p>
        <p>David Colman's clutter-free, cozy (that's another word for ''small'')  midcentury-modern kitchen cost only $5,000. ''I wanted a nice, clean, white and green kitchen,'' said Mr. Colman, a freelance writer who lives in the Wall Street district. ''The kitchen had an awful ivory and wood laminate-accented cabinet with a hideous tile floor and fluorescent light.'' Out went everything except the refrigerator and stove.</p>
        <p>He installed an antique porcelain sink, a new pine floor, butcher-block counters and those glass-fronted cabinets from Ikea (to hold his red and white 1950's Paul McCobb dishes, found on eBay). To economize, he gave up on the idea of $50 crystal knobs and bought chrome ones at P. Guerin, a custom hardware house in Greenwich Village, for $5 each, and painted the walls himself. ''My knobs have pedigree,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Minimalist, Barrier-Free, Zen</p>
        <p>At age 89, Will Machado, an interior designer who lives on the Upper West Side, gave himself an inspiring present: a minimalist Zen kitchen that is warm, serene and efficient. He wanted a kitchen that was easy to walk around, and he demolished a wall separating the kitchen from the living room. ''I wanted to simplify my life,'' he said, but even with a $30,000 budget (including demolition) he had to make trade-offs. He loves wood for its warmth and tactility, and he hired Stephen Iino, a cabinetmaker, to execute his design in ash and maple. (The old appliances stayed -- Mr. Machado cooks some meals at home, or goes out to Nick &amp; Toni's Cafe a block away.) Mr. Machado eliminated the thing that annoyed him most: overhead doors that swung out.</p>
        <p>''Why open doors and bang your head?'' Mr. Machado asked. ''All the doors slide, the pulls are holes and drawers slide out.'' He pulled out a drawer, and shut it with a bump of his hip. The cabinetry was $20,000. The demolition, rubber floor, and other work cost an additional $10,000.</p>
        <p>THREE KITCHEN SCHEMES</p>
        <p>House &amp; Home asked three design firms to take an 8-by-10 foot Manhattan galley kitchen and create a replacement kitchen for $20,000, labor included. Their recipes included a mix of things expensive (Antonio Citterio's $800 plastic rolling carts for Kartell) and modest (those Ikea glass-fronted cabinets).</p>
        <p>Plan I: Pret-a-Porter</p>
        <p>''We used off-the-shelf pieces that would require a minimum amount of craft,'' said Robert Young, who did the design with his partner, Shea Murdock, of Murdock Young Architects. They were inspired by industrial kitchens to use two under-the-counter refrigerators and a freezer.</p>
        <p>''We made it open to seem larger, and banished any big vertical space hog, like a full-size refrigerator,'' he said. ''You reach down and grab what you need,'' just as chefs do, he said. They used only one closed cabinet. ''You have to be able to deal with putting things in nice containers. But it's not for everyone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The custom stainless steel counter has a built-in sink and backsplash; stainless steel shelves are bolted onto painted plywood panels. The planned appliances, like the Jenn-Air gas range and dishwasher, Braun hood, Marvel refrigerators and freezer, are also stainless steel.</p>
        <p>Closed storage includes, yes, one Ikea glass-fronted cabinet ($148), but also Antonio Citterio's cobalt blue plastic rolling carts from Kartell ($800 each), custom-fitted with butcher block tops.</p>
        <p>The rubber tile floor is from Flexco. ''It's easier on your feet than a ceramic tile floor,'' Mr. Young said. Total cost: $19,586.</p>
        <p>Plan II: See Through</p>
        <p>Deborah Gans and Matt Jelacic, of Gans &amp; Jelacic Architecture, designed a glowing kitchen with sliding glass cabinet doors and glass shelves. ''We wanted the transparency,'' Ms. Gans said, ''because part of making the shoe box kitchen a great space is the quality of the light, and the cleanliness of the line.''</p>
        <p>The architects proposed industrial-grade steel brackets and standards, and laminated glass doors made of two pieces of glass with plastic film in between. ''You can go from opaque white to clear just by choosing a different kind of film,'' Ms. Gans said. The sliding doors are hung on a heavy-duty track. Cereal boxes can go behind opaque doors, and Champagne flutes behind clear.</p>
        <p>An open shelf holds the computer, perhaps the kitchen tool of the 21st century. They also proposed a poetic sheet of glass along one wall, etched with measurement equivalents.</p>
        <p>The stainless steel counters have two holes cut into the top, for nonrecyclable and recyclable garbage. Elsewhere, inexpensive ($146 each) wire cabinet-carts will roll out on wheels; they have plywood fronts  sprayed with durable auto body paint. ''You can get a slick, personalized, color-coordinated finish,'' said Ms. Gans, who likes the brilliant color palette of the Volkswagen Bug available from Heavenly Bodyworks in Chelsea (212-691-1092). The walls and floor are equally slick, and are made of Pergo, a washable composite laminate that resembles wood. Total cost: $17,000.</p>
        <p>Plan III: Optical Tricks</p>
        <p>Like Gans and Jelacic, Ronald Bricke, an interior designer, created a kitchen with glass-fronted cabinets (Ikea again) and an open shelf for appliances. His design differs, however, in his use of tiles for texture and scale. For the counters and floor, he used dusty green glass ceramic tiles 12 inches square, from Trans Ceramica Ltd. in Pennsauken, N.J. They're ''the color of a dried bay leaf,'' said Mr. Bricke, a great amateur cook. Total cost: $18,031.</p>
        <p>The tiles for the backsplash and the back half of the counters are polished, and the ones in front of the counter are unpolished to keep water from flowing over the edge. On the floor, he alternated double rows of polished tile with double rows of unpolished ones, for both aesthetics and function. ''The stripes give an impression of widening the room,'' Mr. Bricke said, ''and although it would be safest if you kept the whole floor unpolished, the staggered pattern of polished and unpolished is fairly safe.'' He has tried it on a client, who in three years has never slipped, ''and still has all her teeth,'' he said.</p>
        <p>TRADE SECRETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
