<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="28TRAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1DA1E3AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>MLB--Named Rafael O. Perez administrator of league's Dominican office.</p>
        <p>American League  MINNESOTA TWINS--Signed RHP Jason Simontacchi to a minor league contract.</p>
        <p>Northern League  SCHAUMBERG FLYERS--Re-signed Ron Kittle, manager, and Greg Hibbard, pitching coach, to one-year contracts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>MLB--Named Rafael O. Perez administrator of league's Dominican office.</p>
        <p>American League  MINNESOTA TWINS--Signed RHP Jason Simontacchi to a minor league contract.</p>
        <p>Northern League  SCHAUMBERG FLYERS--Re-signed Ron Kittle, manager, and Greg Hibbard, pitching coach, to one-year contracts.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  BOSTON CELTICS--Signed F Jerome Moiso.  CLEVELAND CAVALIERS--Agreed to terms with F Lari Ketner and then placed him on waivers.  INDIANA PACERS--Announced the retirement of C Rik Smits.  SACRAMENTO KINGS--Announced the contract extension of coach Rick Adelman through 2002.</p>
        <p>International Basketball Association  FARGO-MOORHEAD BEEZ--Signed G Peter Munro and F Daymond Forney.  SOUTH DAKOTA GOLD--Signed F Derrick Price and G Rasheed Brokenborough.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  GREEN BAY PACKERS--Signed DT Chuck Osborne. Waived OT Barry Stokes. Signed TE Adam Newman to the practice squad. Released G Tom Schau from the practice squad.  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Placed C John Wade on injured reserve. Waived DE David Richie. Signed G Aaron Koch and S Craig Miller. Waived OT Gannon Shepherd from the practice squad. Signed OT Reggie Nelson to the practice squad.  KANSAS CITY CHIEFS--Placed DT Ty Parten on injured reserve. Signed DE Tyrone Williams to two-year contract.  MINNESOTA VIKINGS--Signed Dennis Green, coach, to a three-year contract extension, through 2004.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Signed LB Josh Gentry to the practice squad.  Canadian Football League  MONTREAL ALOUETTES--Traded OT Dwayne Morgan to Toronto for future considerations.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  NHL--Named Kenneth Martin, Jr., director, community and diversity programs.  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Recalled Dan Snyder from Orlando of the IHL.  CAROLINA HURRICANES--Assigned F Jaroslav Svoboda and F Ian MacNeil to Cincinnati of the IHL.  DALLAS STARS--Assigned LW Ryan Christie, LW Jamie Wright, D John Erskine, D Mark Wotton and C Chris Wells to Utah of the IHL.  NASHVILLE PREDATORS--Assigned D Alexandre Boikov, RW David Gosselin, LW Sean Haggerty and LW Ryan Tobler to Milwaukee of the IHL.  TAMPA BAY LIGHTNING--Reassigned RW Sheldon Keefe to Detroit of the IHL. Waived D Mel Angelstad.</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League  CHARLOTTE CHECKERS--Announced Hartford of the AHL has assigned RW Mike Hurley to the team. Re-signed D Kevin Pozzo.  PENSACOLA ICE PILOTS--Named Eric Hoffberg assistant coach.</p>
        <p>United Hockey League  ADIRONDACK ICEHAWKS--Acquired G Sergei Zvyagin from Quad City for future considerations.  MISSOURI RIVER OTTERS--Signed F Darin Kimble to a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>West Coast Hockey League  ANCHORAGE ACES--Waived D Dallas Ferguson.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BROWN--Named Michael Fraioli and Jim Finlay men's assistant lacrosse coaches.  CINCINNATI--Named Chris Moore women's assistant basketball coach and Christina Jansen women's basketball program coordinator.  JAMES MADISON--Signed Sherman Dillard, men's basketball coach, to a contract extension through the 2004-05 season.  FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON--Named Dana Lynn Jeannetti assistant softball coach.  HOFSTRA--Named David Duke men's assistant basketball coach, Veta Williams men's basketball administrative assistant and Lawrence Thomas men's basketball strength and conditioning coach.  MASSACHUSETTS-BOSTON--Named Joe Mallen men's ice hockey coach.  PRINCETON UNIVERSITY--Named Rob Burke men's assistant basketball coach and Terri Dadio Campbell women's assistant basketball coach.  RHODE ISLAND--Named Julia Chilicki women's crew coach.  SACRED HEART--Named Andrew DeCicco men's assistant lacrosse coach and Jade Kersey men's assistant ice hockey coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
