<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Air France Sues Continental Over Crash of the Concorde</title>
    <meta content="Y28CON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/28/world/28CONC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concorde Airplane</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gonesse (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Air France</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Continental Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DB113AF93BA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Air France Sues Continental Over Crash of the Concorde</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Sept 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Air France says it has filed lawsuit against Continental Airlines because it believes metal strip from Continental DC-10 led to crash of its Concorde jet in July; Air France statement says that under civil aviation legal code, airline is responsible for damage caused by any pieces that fall off its aircraft; industry experts say it is rare for airlines to sue each other, but somewhat logical in this case; Continental issues brief statement saying there is no proof that it is linked to crash, which killed 109 people on board and 5 on ground (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Air France said today that it had filed a lawsuit against Continental Airlines because it believed a metal strip from a Continental DC-10 led to the crash of its Concorde jet in July.</p>
        <p>French investigators have said they believe that a thin strip of metal fell off the Continental plane, which had taken off on the same runway as the Concorde, and set off the events that caused the Air France jet to burst into flames and crash within minutes after its own takeoff. All 109 people aboard were killed as well as 5 on the ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Air France said today that it had filed a lawsuit against Continental Airlines because it believed a metal strip from a Continental DC-10 led to the crash of its Concorde jet in July.</p>
        <p>French investigators have said they believe that a thin strip of metal fell off the Continental plane, which had taken off on the same runway as the Concorde, and set off the events that caused the Air France jet to burst into flames and crash within minutes after its own takeoff. All 109 people aboard were killed as well as 5 on the ground.</p>
        <p>Air France issued only a one-paragraph statement on its lawsuit, saying it had been filed in the Pontoise commercial court, which covers the town of Gonesse, where the plane dropped onto a small wooden hotel.</p>
        <p>The statement said that under the civil aviation legal code, an airline is  responsible for damage caused by any pieces that fall off its aircraft.</p>
        <p>Three weeks ago, Continental acknowledged that a strip of metal found on the runway among debris from the Concorde was similar in shape to a piece missing from its DC-10, which had been heading for New Jersey just minutes before the doomed plane took off.</p>
        <p>French investigators believe the strip shredded one of the Concorde's tires, sending huge chunks of rubber through the jet's fuel tanks.</p>
        <p>Today, Continental issued a brief statement, saying there was no proof that it was linked to the crash. ''At this stage in the investigation there is no conclusive evidence that Continental is involved in the Concorde crash,'' the statement said. ''Continental will continue to cooperate fully with all the French authorities investigating the accident.''</p>
        <p>The legal case was lodged by Air France and the airline insurance consortium Reunion Aerienne. Industry experts said it was rare for airlines to sue each other, but somewhat logical in this particular case.</p>
        <p>''These are very unusual circumstances,'' said Shephard Melzer, who recently stepped down as the chairman of the Aeronautic Committee of the Association of the Bar of New York City. ''Usually it's a manufacturer who gets sued for a defective part. But here that is not the issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Melzer said it was really the insurance companies who called the shots in such lawsuits. ''Which insurance company is going to pay? That's what this is about,'' he said. ''And from Air France's point of view, you can see the advantages. They are saying there was nothing wrong with their plane. It was really a freak accident.''</p>
        <p>French and British aviation authorities withdrew Concorde's airworthiness certificate last month, saying a burst tire should not be able to bring a plane down. Air France and British Airways, the only two airlines to operate the supersonic jets, have been studying whether corrective actions can be taken to ensure that such an accident could not occur again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
