<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crestfallen, Devils Try to Regroup</title>
    <meta content="10DEVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STANLEY CUP FINALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D91F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crestfallen, Devils Try to Regroup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils, exhausted and disappointed about missing chance to clinch second Stanley Cup on home ice, discuss losing to Dallas Stars in Game 5 of championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils' day began early this morning on the ice, playing sudden-death Stanley Cup hockey. After more than 106 minutes, including 46:21 of overtime, they lost Game 5 in stunning fashion, 1-0, to the Dallas Stars in a stirring match that ended at 1:11 a.m.</p>
        <p>Exhausted and bitterly disappointed from blowing a chance to clinch their second Stanley Cup in five years, the Devils trudged home for a few hours of sleep. They awoke and drowsily boarded a charter flight to Dallas for Game 6 Saturday night, but even that journey was problematic. Their plane had to be diverted to Tulsa, Okla., because of weather conditions in the Dallas area and did not arrive here until 8 p.m. local time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils' day began early this morning on the ice, playing sudden-death Stanley Cup hockey. After more than 106 minutes, including 46:21 of overtime, they lost Game 5 in stunning fashion, 1-0, to the Dallas Stars in a stirring match that ended at 1:11 a.m.</p>
        <p>Exhausted and bitterly disappointed from blowing a chance to clinch their second Stanley Cup in five years, the Devils trudged home for a few hours of sleep. They awoke and drowsily boarded a charter flight to Dallas for Game 6 Saturday night, but even that journey was problematic. Their plane had to be diverted to Tulsa, Okla., because of weather conditions in the Dallas area and did not arrive here until 8 p.m. local time.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Devils Coach Larry Robinson remained upbeat. ''You don't want the guys to hang their heads,'' he said. ''Sports is a mind game. The guys are down a little, but we do have a cushion here a little bit, and I think we're the fresher team.''</p>
        <p>The Devils had numerous chances to win the cup in front of their fans at Continental Arena, but Dallas goaltender Ed Belfour was brilliant. Bobby Holik, more than any of the other Devils, had the best chances to shatter the scoreless tie. He was credited with a game-high eight shots and two missed shots, but he had just as many opportunities to score on breakaways, one-timers and two-on-ones. In the second period he had four shots.</p>
        <p>''Bobby Holik could have had six goals himself,'' Robinson lamented after the Game 5 loss.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather not talk about it because there's nothing I can do about it now,'' Holik said. ''You have all these opportunities and nothing to show for it. It hits the post. Belfour made a couple of great saves. It could have been the end of the game, but it's not. It's certainly not fun.''</p>
        <p>The Devils' top line of Jason Arnott, Patrik Elias and Petr Sykora had numerous chances but could not solve Belfour, who made 48 saves.  Neither did Alexander Mogilny, Sergei Brylin and Jay Pandolfo.</p>
        <p>''We knew that if we had a goal, we'd win the game,'' Martin Brodeur, who made 40 saves, said without hesitation.</p>
        <p>Mike Modano's tip-in off Brett Hull's shot from the right point 6:21 into the third overtime ended the longest scoreless game in Stanley Cup finals history and the fourth-longest game in finals history.</p>
        <p>Brodeur's teammate Ken Daneyko was stunned when the puck went in. ''You could hear a pin drop at the end because you don't expect it,'' he said. ''We were very confident and every time we came in here we were very positive deep down that maybe things would go our way.''</p>
        <p>They did not. But Daneyko wondered how long things would go Belfour's way. ''That's going to be tough to repeat,'' the Devils defenseman said. ''But Marty made some spectacular saves as well. It was a classic game, but unfortunately we lost. It always seems to end like that.''</p>
        <p>''We were emotionally and physically drained,'' Arnott said. ''It was a tough one to play because of all the emotion. But we've got a lot of character in the room and we want to stay positive.''</p>
        <p>The Devils are a confident team on the road, where they have won nine playoff games this postseason. In 1995 they clinched the Stanley Cup with 10 road victories and have won the previous two games in Dallas.</p>
        <p>Scott Stevens, the Devils' captain, dismissed a question on whether the Stars could rally from a 3-1 deficit the way the Devils did in the semifinals against Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>''I'm not thinking about that,'' Stevens snapped. ''I'm thinking about the fact that we're up, three games to two. That is the bottom line right now. I mean, that is not a bad position to be in.''</p>
        <p>STANLEY CUP FINALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
