<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tsakane Journal; Apartheid Still Burdens A Girl Who Didn't Fit</title>
    <meta content="Y10AFR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laing, Sandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDF1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tsakane Journal; Apartheid Still Burdens A Girl Who Didn't Fit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>TSAKANE, South Africa, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South Africans are reminded of the pain that apartheid caused ordinary people by a television documentary on Sandra Laing, now 44, who grew up a black child in a white family; she was expelled from her white school and classified as black in 1966; her parents had her reclassified as white, but then disowned her when they caught her dating a black man; Laing recently visted her mother for the first time since then in her nursing home; her brothers refuse to see her; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, the country girl wished she could wiggle out of her skin and shed her color like the molting snakes that rustled through the green fields. It was the 1960's,  and she was the daughter of white Afrikaners who proudly supported the government's brutal system of apartheid and racial segregation.</p>
        <p>But for Sandra Laing, it was hard to swallow the message of hate. Her birth certificate said she was white, but when she looked in the mirror, she saw a honey brown face framed by a halo of kinky-curly hair. ''They loved me,'' she said of her parents. ''But I knew I was different.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, the country girl wished she could wiggle out of her skin and shed her color like the molting snakes that rustled through the green fields. It was the 1960's,  and she was the daughter of white Afrikaners who proudly supported the government's brutal system of apartheid and racial segregation.</p>
        <p>But for Sandra Laing, it was hard to swallow the message of hate. Her birth certificate said she was white, but when she looked in the mirror, she saw a honey brown face framed by a halo of kinky-curly hair. ''They loved me,'' she said of her parents. ''But I knew I was different.''</p>
        <p>For a time, the Laings tried to ignore the trick of genetics and ignored the whispers about the African blood many suspected flowed through their veins. But by age 15, Sandra Laing had been expelled from her all-white school and disowned by her humiliated parents and her story had become one of the country's the most publicized examples of a family destroyed by the crushing weight of apartheid.</p>
        <p>The saga should have faded into the yellowing pages of forgotten newspapers. But about eight months ago, Ms. Laing drove home for the first time in nearly 30 years, accompanied by a documentary film maker, and what she saw became prime-time news. In the once segregated town of Piet Retief in Mpumalanga Province, she found a black farmer living in her parents' old house. At the school that had once rejected her, she met students black and white. One told her, ''God has changed this world.''</p>
        <p>And in January, she saw her mother for the first time since 1973, in a tearful reunion that was splashed across the nation's newspapers.</p>
        <p>But if Ms. Laing's story reflects the triumphs of a fledgling democracy that has managed to overcome decades of racial animosity, it also mirrors the halting and painful journeys of ordinary people who sometimes stumble along the road of racial reconciliation. Her two brothers, who have prospered in the white world, are so ashamed of their sister that they refuse to see her or speak to her.</p>
        <p>And so go race relations in this country, with tentative steps forward and tentative steps back, as whites and blacks, Indians and coloreds wrestle with the past. Six years after South Africa elected its first black president, the apartheid laws and racial classifications are long gone. Blacks are moving into white neighborhoods. Lovers exchange wedding rings across the color line in a country that once outlawed mixed marriages.</p>
        <p>But here in this poor black township where she now lives, Ms. Laing has discovered that while much has changed, much has not. The legacy of apartheid still divides her family. In March, her brothers sent a letter to Ms. Laing, 44, who was facing eviction here, and promised to help her buy food. But the money would come at an almost unspeakable cost.</p>
        <p>She would receive their help, the letter said, only if she vowed never to see her 79-year-old mother again and only if she promised to keep quiet about her family history. At the time she heard from her brothers, she had managed to visit her mother twice.</p>
        <p>She never answered the heartbreaking letter, but it is a measure of her isolation that she now treasures it, keeping it safe in a plain envelope tucked in her wardrobe. These days, she believes it may be one of the only tangible connections she will ever have to her family.</p>
        <p>''I always thought after apartheid it would be all right,'' Ms. Laing said, her hands twisting nervously in her lap, her fingernails bitten to the quick. ''Maybe we would have lived well together. Maybe we would have been all right. I always thought, if only I had a bigger place, then my mother could live with me until the end.</p>
        <p>''I hoped my brothers would come looking for me,'' she said wistfully. ''I still hope they will come.''</p>
        <p>She falls silent, maybe because she knows they will never come looking. Maybe because, as horrible as it may sound, she can almost understand how they feel. Even as she kissed her mother's wrinkled cheek six months ago, she could still feel the unbearable distance between them.</p>
        <p>''When I saw my real mother again, I was happy to see her, but it didn't feel right,'' Ms. Laing admitted quietly. ''She's white and I'm dark. It just doesn't feel right.''</p>
        <p>Her older brother, Leon Laing, says he is sorry for the pain of the past, but he insists that history cannot be undone.</p>
        <p>The siblings will probably never know whether their family had a black ancestor somewhere, as some suspect, or whether their mother had an affair with a black man, as others believe.</p>
        <p>But even in the new South Africa, Mr. Laing says, his children would be humiliated if their white friends and neighbors suspected they had African ancestry. So he pretends his little sister was never born and begs reporters to help him keep the secret.</p>
        <p>''This story is 35 years old,'' Mr. Laing said, his voice growing ragged as he explained why he would not discuss his sister. ''I've got my wife and kids to think of. You understand? I have to keep them safe.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to imagine now, but there was a brief time in Sandra Laing's life when color did not seem to matter.</p>
        <p>The South African Broadcasting Corporation, which aired the documentary on her life on its ''Special Assignment'' program in December, recovered an old black-and-white video which was shot before she was expelled from school and before her brothers learned to view her with shame.</p>
        <p>In the flickering, silent footage, Ms. Laing is a laughing little girl who races into her mother's arms, nestles close to her smiling father and cuddles her brother on her knee. But she was a brown child living in a white world and she inevitably tripped up against the country's apartheid laws.</p>
        <p>Under the Population Registration Act, which was enacted in 1950 and repealed in 1991, every newborn baby was classified by race. Those classified as black or mixed-race -- known as coloreds -- could not live or study in white communities. It was under that law that Ms. Laing was expelled from her white school in 1966, when her schoolmates complained and the government reclassified her as black.</p>
        <p>Her parents managed to reclassify her as white, taking blood tests to prove she was their child. But they disowned her when they caught her dating a black man. To live legally with the man she loved, Ms. Laing had to reclassify herself as colored and leave the white community. And the family slowly learned to live in two separate worlds, one white, one black.</p>
        <p>Her father, Abraham, still not speaking to her, died in 1989. And her mother, Sannie, sits in a suburban nursing home just outside Pretoria, finding safety from history in silence and forgetfulness.</p>
        <p>''I never see her, I never see her,'' Sannie Lang said recently, when a reporter asked about her only daughter.</p>
        <p>When she was gently reminded that her daughter had visited twice, the silver-haired woman nodded slowly. ''Oh, yes, yes,'' she said. ''I can remember.''</p>
        <p>But she refuses to say more. The memories are too painful or too elusive, flickering in and out of her mind like fireflies on a warm summer night. And after so many years, Ms. Laing no longer has the courage to ask, How could you have ignored all my letters and phone calls? How could you have abandoned me for so many years?</p>
        <p>Instead, Ms. Laing finds comfort in black townships, where she has lived since she left her white family, where people do not view her as an oddity.</p>
        <p>Here, she is simply the friendly neighbor who tends the pink roses in her tiny garden and hangs fraying towels on the clothesline like other black women here. ''At home, I wished I was lighter like my family,'' she said. ''Here, it's O.K. who I am.''</p>
        <p>But it is not an easy life. Ms. Laing is unemployed and her second husband, a machine operator, works only part time. The family struggles to pay the rent on their four-room house and often goes without bread or meat. Most weeks, she does not even have the 72 cents to make a 10-minute phone call to her mother.</p>
        <p>She places her hopes for the future in her 12-year-old son, Steve, who plans to become a doctor in a country that no longer denies opportunities to blacks. He studies hard and mixes easily with the whites he meets in town. But when asked whether he will move into a white neighborhood or practice medicine in a white community someday, Ms. Laing shakes her head.</p>
        <p>Her children will be safe, she says. They will not cross the line.</p>
        <p>''They know how I grew up,'' she said. ''They will remain with black people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
