<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DB1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Pakistan Outlines Plans To Curb Militant Networks  Pakistan outlined a plan to slowly curb militant Islamic networks that have taken root there and in Afghanistan. Although Washington has criticized Pakistan for months over its handling of terrorism, senior officials said the military government had decided to act not because of the American pressure but because the networks threatened Pakistan.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Pakistan Outlines Plans To Curb Militant Networks  Pakistan outlined a plan to slowly curb militant Islamic networks that have taken root there and in Afghanistan. Although Washington has criticized Pakistan for months over its handling of terrorism, senior officials said the military government had decided to act not because of the American pressure but because the networks threatened Pakistan.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Greek Plan Against Terrorism  The government said it would enact new antiterrorism measures after the killing of a British military attache on Thursday. The announcement came as the victim's widow delivered an emotional appeal for the killers to be brought to justice.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Iraq Oil Program Extended  The Security Council has extended the ''oil-for-food'' program for another six months to allow the imports of food, medicine and other civilian necessities. During this period, a new arms inspection system will be prepared, the chief inspector said, challenging Iraq to take advantage of a more lenient set of requirements for suspending economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>National Strike in Argentina  Several million workers joined or were forced to acquiesce to a one-day strike to protest economic austerity policies and a 14 percent unemployment rate.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Brazil Advances Gay Rights  The government, in an action that gay groups describe as the first of its sort in Latin America, has extended de facto legal recognition to same-sex relationships by granting couples the right to inherit each other's pension and social security benefits.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Mexican Leader in Washington  President Clinton warmly received President Ernesto Zedillo in Washington, and White House officials expressed confidence in Mexico's electoral process, three weeks before that country's most tightly contested presidential election ever.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-12, 16</p>
        <p>House Ignores Veto Threat In Vote to End Estate Tax  The House voted, 279 to 136, to repeal the federal estate tax, drawing a veto threat from President Clinton even as Democrats joined Republicans in recognizing the issue's political potency; 65 Democrats voted in favor of the bill. Republican leaders have made repeal of what they call the ''death tax'' a priority, saying they seek in part to help owners of small businesses and family farms.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Donor Disclosure Bill Fails  The House, voting 216 to 202 mostly along party lines, rejected a measure to require secretive groups that raise and spend unlimited sums on political activities to reveal their donors and spending.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Inquiry Finds No Conspiracy  The Justice Department said an 18-month investigation had found no evidence to support assertions that the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. was killed by conspirators who aided or framed James Earl Ray.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Move to Expand DNA Testing  Efforts are growing in state legislatures and in Congress to help inmates overcome the obstacles they face in obtaining DNA evidence that might exonerate them. But those efforts are facing continued reluctance by some prosecutors and victims' rights groups.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Protection for a Salmon Run  Vice President Al Gore announced President Clinton's designation of the Hanford Reach section of the Columbia River in Washington, one of the most important salmon-spawning beds in the world, as a national monument. The designation provides protection from dams, dredging and development for 195,000 acres of public land along the river.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Gore Faulted on Bureaucracy  Gov. George W. Bush assailed Vice President Al Gore's signature effort to streamline government, saying the Clinton administration had not reinvented the bureaucracy but ''simply reshuffled it.''</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Emissions Test Flaws Were Known, Inquiry Finds  A panel appointed by Governor Whitman reported that the lengthy delays New Jersey motorists experienced getting new auto emissions tests last winter had been caused by a faulty system that senior officials had been warned about before its installation. Three state officials resigned or were disciplined as a result.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Rabbi's Relatives Die in Fire  The granddaughter and 5-month-old great-granddaughter of Grand Rabbi Moses Teitelbaum, the spiritual leader of a sect of ultra-Orthodox Jews in Brooklyn, died in a predawn fire that officials said had been touched off by religious candles lit for Shavuot.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Signs of West Nile Virus  Three dead crows -- two in New York and one in New Jersey -- were confirmed as the year's first known victims of West Nile virus, the mosquito-borne disease that killed seven people in New York City last year.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Lakers Take 2-0 Lead  Los Angeles beat the Indiana Pacers, 111-104, in the second game of the N.B.A. finals. Game 3 of the series will be tomorrow in Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A12-13</p>
        <p>Jacob Lawrence  A leading modern figurative painter and, since the beginning of his career in the 1930's, among the most prominent and impassioned visual chroniclers of the African-American experience, he was 82.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>George Segal  A sculptor whose often eerie, rough-surfaced casts of actual people made him one of the most influential artists of the second half of the century, he was 75.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Online Music Settlement  The Internet music service MP3.com will pay roughly $20 million each to BMG Entertainment, a unit of Bertelsmann, and Warner Music Group, a subsidiary of Time Warner, to settle a copyright lawsuit. MP3.com was also said to have agreed to pay licensing fees for use of the labels' music on its service.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ruling in Drug Patent Dispute  Transkaryotic Therapies won a round in its patent fight with Amgen when a federal judge in Boston ruled that Transkaryotic had not infringed on one of Amgen's patents covering its best-selling drug, erythropoietin, an anemia treatment.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>No Inflation at Producer Level  Prices paid to manufacturers, farmers and other producers showed no change in May, as lower costs for energy and food offset higher prices for cars and a big rise in book costs, according to the Producer Price Index, which measures inflation pressures before they reach consumers.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Toward cleaner campaigns -- a setback on Section 527 groups, fattening Albany's cats; ensuring access to RU-486; budget follies in New York.  Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B15  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
