<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greece Vows Antiterror Action as British Victim's Widow Issues Plea</title>
    <meta content="Y10DIP$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greece</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">November 17 (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saunders, Heather</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saunders, Stephen (Brig)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDB1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greece Vows Antiterror Action as British Victim's Widow Issues Plea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>ATHENS, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Greek government pledges to introduce new antiterrorism measures in response to June 8 killing of the British military attache, Brig Stephen Saunders; his widow, Heather Saunders, pleads with government to bring assassins to justice; group called Novembver 17 says it killed Saunders because of Britain's role in the NATO bombing of Yugoslavia in 1999 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Greek government pledged today to introduce new antiterrorism measures after the killing a British military attache on Thursday, the victim's widow delivered an emotional appeal to the Greek nation.</p>
        <p>''I stand before you half the person I was yesterday,'' Heather Saunders told reporters outside her house in Athens this morning, her two teenage daughters standing at her side. ''The Greek people, I know, are not responsible for what happened yesterday. But for the sake and future of Greece within a European community, I feel that these wicked men must be  brought to justice.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Greek government pledged today to introduce new antiterrorism measures after the killing a British military attache on Thursday, the victim's widow delivered an emotional appeal to the Greek nation.</p>
        <p>''I stand before you half the person I was yesterday,'' Heather Saunders told reporters outside her house in Athens this morning, her two teenage daughters standing at her side. ''The Greek people, I know, are not responsible for what happened yesterday. But for the sake and future of Greece within a European community, I feel that these wicked men must be  brought to justice.''</p>
        <p>In a letter delivered to a Greek newspaper early this morning, a group called November 17 claimed responsibility for the death of Brig. Stephen Saunders, 53, saying he had been killed because of Britain's role in the ''barbaric'' NATO bombing of Yugoslavia last year.</p>
        <p>It was believed to be the 23rd killing in 25 years linked to November 17, a left-wing guerrilla organization that first emerged in 1975 with the killing of Richard Welch, the Central Intelligence Agency station chief in Athens. In all, the deaths of four American officials have been linked to the group.</p>
        <p>The United States and Britain renewed pressure on Greek officials to take serious antiterrorist steps, noting that no member of November 17 has ever been arrested or even identified. Washington has long faulted Athens for lacking the political will to root out the  organization. Four days before the attack, a special bipartisan commission set up by Congress recommended sanctions against Greece for ''failing to fully cooperate'' with Western antiterrorist activity.</p>
        <p>Today, a spokesman for the Greek government said Prime Minister Costas Simitis had held a cabinet meeting to discuss new counterterrorism steps.</p>
        <p>''The prime minister is determined to undertake all the necessary and additional measures that are required to combat and eradicate terrorism,'' the spokesman, Dimitris Reppas, said after the meeting. ''Efforts in the future will be more intense.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reppas said Mr. Simitis ''also stressed the importance of taking all the necessary measures to ensure a framework of total safety for the 2004 Athens Olympic Games.'' Greece has presented some security plans to the International Olympic Committee but has not yet developed a full security strategy for the Games.</p>
        <p>''The Games have always been a favored forum for terrorists striving to internationalize their campaign, and this risk does exist also in the case of Athens,'' said Dennis Oswald, a Swiss official on the International Olympic Committee. ''Greece has ample time to put a security plan in force. That's the good thing about hosting the Games -- governments are forced to do things they normally wouldn't or neglect to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reppas said the government did not foresee fundamental changes to the legal system, but added that it was considering some extraordinary measures, citing the possibility of using a one-judge trial in terrorist cases instead of a jury, a step used by Italy in  the 1970's to try Red Brigade  terrorists.</p>
        <p>Italy and other nations also resorted to other extraordinary measures, including secret hearings, anonymous prosecutors and witness protection programs, to reduce the possibility of jury intimidation and terrorist reprisals against judges and magistrates.</p>
        <p>It was not clear today whether the Greek government planned to consider further measures, but some Western diplomats took heart.</p>
        <p>''That is exactly the right path for Greece to take,'' a Western official said today. ''These are measures that Greece's European allies took to defend themselves against their indigenous terrorist movements in the 1970's and 1980's.''</p>
        <p>A Greek official told Reuters that an unprecedented search for the killers had been started. As yet, the police have not even found the motorbike that was used.</p>
        <p>Security was visibly tighter  in downtown Athens today, and nerves were edgy. When an explosion was reported near the city of Rhodes, some Greek news services immediately speculated that it was another terrorist attack. Turkish officials later explained that the noise came from submarine torpedo practice during a naval exercise in the Aegean.</p>
        <p>The intense international scrutiny of Greece's antiterrorism record also hit a raw nerve.  Some newspapers today blamed the United States and Europe for darkening Greece's image. But there were also signs that the killing of Brigadier Saunders had profoundly shocked the nation.</p>
        <p>Even in To Vima, a newspaper that traditionally supports Prime Minister Simitis's Socialist Party, editorials spoke of a national disgrace. For the first time, the paper acknowledged Washington's concerns about counterterrorism in Greece.</p>
        <p>''We are incompetent to provide protection to the families we host in our country,'' the paper's senior editorial writer, Ioannis Pretenderis, wrote. ''For 25 years, this same group of terrorists have been moving around freely, killing anyone they desire, and then sending their proclamations to the press. This is the sign of a bankrupt society.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The Americans are absolutely right to complain. Twenty-five years and we have done nothing about terrorism. It is the bitter reality. Yet instead we  prefer to flaunt an anti-American bravado.''</p>
        <p>Some in Greece worried today that such sentiments might not last.</p>
        <p>''Obviously I really, really hope that this time will be different, that something will happen,'' said Nikos Peratikis, whose brother Costas, an Athens shipowner who was a British citizen, was killed by November 17 in 1997. ''But people have been saying that after every murder for the past 25 years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
