<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rent Protesters Want to Sleep On Street by Gracie Mansion</title>
    <meta content="10GRAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gracie Mansion (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sidewalks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wood, Kimba M (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDE1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rent Protesters Want to Sleep On Street by Gracie Mansion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tenant advocacy group Metropolitan Council asks US District Court Judge Kimba Wood to order New York City officials to allow demonstrators to spend night sleeping on sidwalk across street from Gracie Mansion in protest against planned rent increase on rent-controlled and rent-stabilized apartments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tenants' rights advocates asked a federal judge yesterday afternoon to order city officials to allow demonstrators to spend a night sleeping on the sidewalk across the street from Gracie Mansion in protest of the mayor's housing policy.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the New York Civil Liberties Union, which is representing the protesters, said they believed the police would arrest anyone sleeping or lying on the sidewalk during a 12-hour vigil planned for Tuesday. City lawyers have said that sleeping on the sidewalk is considered disorderly conduct in New York and will make the protesters subject to arrest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tenants' rights advocates asked a federal judge yesterday afternoon to order city officials to allow demonstrators to spend a night sleeping on the sidewalk across the street from Gracie Mansion in protest of the mayor's housing policy.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the New York Civil Liberties Union, which is representing the protesters, said they believed the police would arrest anyone sleeping or lying on the sidewalk during a 12-hour vigil planned for Tuesday. City lawyers have said that sleeping on the sidewalk is considered disorderly conduct in New York and will make the protesters subject to arrest.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's hearing was the latest in a series of free speech battles between the administration of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and protesters. The Metropolitan Council, the tenants' group planning the protest, called for the demonstration against a proposed rent increase for rent-controlled and rent-stabilized apartments.</p>
        <p>The council plans to hold a news conference and a demonstration in Carl Shurz Park, near Gracie Mansion, on Tuesday night. Because the park closes at 1 a.m., the group planned to move to the sidewalk. Organizers estimate that 25 people plan to sleep on the sidewalk from 1 a.m. to 8 a.m.</p>
        <p>Christopher Dunn, the lawyer representing the group, told Judge Kimba M. Wood of United States District Court that the sleeping protest was a valid expression of free speech and a reflection of the group's beliefs about the city housing policy. Mr. Dunn said there was no specific city or state law against sleeping on the city sidewalk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunn said that in a similar demonstration in December, the police arrested protesters for lying on the ground. He asked Judge Wood to prohibit officers from making those kinds of arrests again.</p>
        <p>But Daniel S. Connolly, the lawyer representing the city, said that the state courts had recognized that lying or sleeping on a public sidewalk  was disorderly conduct and that the police were acting properly to arrest people who did so. He said the proper legal question was not whether the demonstrators had a right to free speech but ''can the city regulate the use of its sidewalks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Connolly said the city had no objection to the news conference or to the demonstration in the park and would not object to a normal demonstration on the sidewalk across the street from Gracie Mansion. But he said the city could not allow people to sleep on the sidewalk and claim it was an exercise of free expression. He said that if the city opened the door to considering that constitutionally protected speech rather than illegal behavior, it would severely limit the city's duty to maintain free and clear walkways.</p>
        <p>''The sidewalks are first and foremost to allow people to walk in safety from one place to another,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In her questioning yesterday afternoon, Judge Wood concentrated on the specifics of the planned protests, asking whether the demonstrators would entirely block the sidewalk and whether organizers planned to provide security to prevent injury to sleeping protesters. Mr. Dunn said that the sleepers would use only part of the sidewalk and that people would be present to watch over the demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Because the protest has been scheduled for next week, Judge Wood is expected to issue a ruling soon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
