<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off the Train, Onto the Block; Auction House to Put Vintage Graffiti on Sale</title>
    <meta content="10GRAF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Guernsey's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Eddie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haring, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D81F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off the Train, Onto the Block; Auction House to Put Vintage Graffiti on Sale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Guernsey's auction house will hold two-day sale of vintage New York City graffiti, including works by such artists as Eddie Rodriguez and Keith Haring; photos; chart compares asking prices for graffiti with those for masterworks recently sold by Christies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a memento from Eddie Rodriguez's past and, in a way, the city's -- a 30-foot-wide canvas that he and some friends painted when they were teenagers in the 1970's. It was a wall-filler in his apartment in the 1980's and a garage-filler after he rolled it up and moved to New Jersey in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Now he hopes it will be a bid-getter in an auction organized by Guernsey's, an Upper East Side auction house that has sold everything from Rembrandts and Renoirs to a $3 million baseball. Mr. Rodriguez's work -- Lot No. 71 in a two-day sale that begins on Wednesday -- is pictured in Guernsey's glossy catalog, which described his loopy lettering as ''elegant'' and ''highly influential.'' And pricey: the presale estimate on Lot No. 71 is $100,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a memento from Eddie Rodriguez's past and, in a way, the city's -- a 30-foot-wide canvas that he and some friends painted when they were teenagers in the 1970's. It was a wall-filler in his apartment in the 1980's and a garage-filler after he rolled it up and moved to New Jersey in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Now he hopes it will be a bid-getter in an auction organized by Guernsey's, an Upper East Side auction house that has sold everything from Rembrandts and Renoirs to a $3 million baseball. Mr. Rodriguez's work -- Lot No. 71 in a two-day sale that begins on Wednesday -- is pictured in Guernsey's glossy catalog, which described his loopy lettering as ''elegant'' and ''highly influential.'' And pricey: the presale estimate on Lot No. 71 is $100,000.</p>
        <p>The auction is of vintage graffiti, or, as one of Mr. Rodriguez's fellow practitioners prefers to call it, ''aerosol art.''</p>
        <p>As Snake-I in the 1970's, Mr. Rodriguez was a pioneer in an eye-popping genre that angered mayors and editorial writers and was romanticized by the likes of Norman Mailer. Mr. Rodriguez sprayed Snake-I in big, fat letters on dozens of subway cars, tunnels, even the 34th Precinct station house in Washington Heights.</p>
        <p>But graffiti artists who gave any thought to preserving their works could not simply slice off the side of a subway car and put it in a frame. So Mr. Rodriguez worked on canvases -- bus-sized, if not subway-sized -- that were never seen by paying passengers who cursed or cheered the graffiti artists' more public creations.</p>
        <p>The canvases, of course, survived the city's multimillion-dollar war on graffiti. And the auction could turn his and others' surviving creations into annuities for middle-age guys who now have business cards, W-2's, mortgages and memories.</p>
        <p>''They have to eat like anyone else,'' said Arlan Ettinger, the owner of Guernsey's. ''You don't get paid for work in a tunnel.''</p>
        <p>And so the auction has joined men who still go by 30-year-old alphanumeric ''tags'' like Coco 144, Crash, Stitch and MICO (all capital letters, please, he says) with the coolly curatorial Mr. Ettinger, who categorizes his new clients as only an art dealer could. Some belong to ''the old school'' of the early 1970's, he says. Others fall into ''the middle group,'' from 1978 to 1982 (''It was good to be a graffiti artist then,'' Mr. Ettinger says). And then there are ''the new guys'' (''I say guys because there are only one or two women that we've encountered'').</p>
        <p>Some of them hope for a bidding frenzy. Some hope that deep-pocketed buyers will fight to outspend each other the way bidders did at auctions of the belongings of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis and Marilyn Monroe. And there are those in the art world who say that graffiti has finally become salable in this country.</p>
        <p>''It was embraced more internationally than it was locally because it wasn't defacing their buildings abroad,'' said Jenny Dixon, the director of the Bronx Museum of the Arts. ''It reflected the texture of the city before we became so Disneyed. I think people want to get back to something that has some real teeth, instead of everything being so pasteurized, so I think its time may have come.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ettinger faces a problem that Sotheby's and Christie's, which organized the Onassis and Monroe sales, did not have to deal with. ''These artists didn't have the wherewithal or the money for stretchers'' to hold their canvases at full size, he said, ''so this is the world's most difficult show to hang.'' (His own quarters uptown, a few steps from Park Avenue, are too small for the auction, so he is heading downtown. He has rented the Puck Building, at 295 Lafayette Street, and has scheduled previews from noon to 6 p.m. on Tuesday and from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. on Wednesday and Thursday. The sales are scheduled for Wednesday and Thursday evenings.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Ettinger -- who has sold movie posters, turn-of-the-century race cars and Elvis Presley memorabilia -- has assembled about 400 lots. The largest item is at least 30 feet wide,  he said, and several are 20 feet wide. ''When you're accustomed to painting on a tunnel wall,'' he said, ''it's hard to confine yourself.''</p>
        <p>But some items in the auction are not large at all. Lot No. 363 -- the words ''blood,'' ''sweat'' and ''tears'' spray-painted on what was once a scroll-like direction sign in a subway car window -- is only 33 by 22 inches. Its presale estimate is $2,000 to $3,000. Mr. Ettinger estimates that 10 photographs of graffiti-covered subway cars by Henry Chalfant would go for $800 to $1,000 apiece. There is even a case of 12 cans of Krylon spray paint (estimate: $400 to $600).</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, the art world flirted with graffiti; Mr. Ettinger is selling the doors from 51X, a Manhattan gallery on St. Mark's Place that catered to the aerosol-art crowd. The doors' tags include examples from Keith Haring and Jean-Michel Basquiat (who used the tag ''Samo'' when he was young).</p>
        <p>''To some people, this door is like the Holy Grail,'' Mr. Ettinger said. (Actually, he explained a moment later, the door was the entrance to the apartment above the gallery. ''Part of the deal is we had to get the guy another door,'' he said.)</p>
        <p>The two Basquiats in Mr. Ettinger's sale are modest pencil drawings with estimates in the $15,000-to-$30,000 range, a small fraction of the $3.3 million that a Basquiat sold for at a Christie's sale in 1998. Just last month, Mr. Basquiat's 1985 graffiti painting ''Peter and the Wolf'' sold for $662,500 at Phillips Auctioneers.</p>
        <p>The oldest piece in the sale is a ''downtown'' sign that Mr. Ettinger expects will sell for $10,000 to $15,000. It was tagged by Joe 182, Ernie 189, Kelly 196 and Kiely 104 (at least twice), as well as by Taki 183, whom Mr. Ettinger calls ''the grandfather of graffiti artists.''</p>
        <p>''In 1969, as a young illustrator at Esquire, they asked me to incorporate the name of this guy who was everywhere: Taki 183,'' Mr. Ettinger said. ''One could argue that somewhere there was someone who was first, but in my search for him, the paint was still wet when I'd get to a scene, and I never did catch him.''</p>
        <p>He said the other day that he still hasn't. But Taki 183 turned out to be only a phone call away -- and he made the call to a reporter. The name-signer who launched a thousand felt-tipped pens would say only that his real first name is Demetrius, that he lives in ''lower Westchester'' and that he works with cars -- again, no details.</p>
        <p>''I'm a family man; I'm a mainstream guy,'' he said. ''Sometimes I see a wall and say, it would be nice there. I guess I'm a dangerous guy to carry around a marker, still. But that's something you do when you're 16. It's not something you make a career out of.''</p>
        <p>Which may be why Robert Gualtieri, a k a Coco 144, is an electrician at Rockefeller University in Manhattan. Or why J. J. Ramirez, a k a MICO, works as a Spanish-language interpreter and translator in State Supreme Court in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''The system that used to persecute me when I was a full-time vandal in the 1970's, I am now a part of,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He is the one who resists ''the 'g' word'' and prefers the term ''aerosol art.''</p>
        <p>''Graffiti is a denigrating term,'' Mr. Ramirez said. ''If you look it up in the dictionary, it means to scrawl. I have never done any scrawling. I have written my name and developed masterpieces from my name.''</p>
        <p>And Michael Tracy, who goes by Tracy 168, said he had made money from his masterpieces: he said he copyrighted his graffiti and had challenged companies that used the phrase ''wild style,'' which appears in most of his works. ''Coca-Cola already settled,'' he said. ''I don't think I'm allowed to say any more.'' He said, though, that he has filed other copyright claims.</p>
        <p>''It's my turn to get paid,'' Mr. Tracy said. ''I'm going after the ones  who robbed my stuff over the years. I'm like the Rolling Stones. I always come up with a new hit every year. Life is good. I earned this.''</p>
        <p>The contrasts to the big-arrest days of the early 1970's are inevitable. ''I was hitting the trains parked in the underground yard at City Hall, which at that time was the RR's and the N trains,'' when he was caught, Mr. Ramirez said.</p>
        <p>Other graffiti artists reminisced about the detectives assigned to chase them down. Crash, a k a John Matos, said that, like Mr. Rodriguez, he had tagged a police station (the 40th Precinct), as well as Murry Bergtraum High School, across from police headquarters in Lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''We were just so fixated with doing and doing and doing it, you don't see anything else but that,'' said Mr. Matos, who now works as an artist and whose recent projects include a subway station -- not in New York but in Hanover, Germany, on a commission from the municipal authorities there. ''You're basically doing everything for your peers. All the guys that paint, that's who you're aiming at, show these guys what I'm doing. It was a very simple thing. You're not trying to hurt anybody, you just want to paint.''</p>
        <p>Andy Witten, a k a Zephyr, who at 39 is a few years younger than some of the ''old school'' graffiti artists in the Guernsey's sale, sounded wistful that some of his works were included in the sale. ''It makes me feel a little old,'' he said. ''I'm a little old to be associated with graffiti subculture.''</p>
        <p>But not if there is money to be had.</p>
        <p>''You've got to remember that if opening your wallet and plopping down greenbacks is a final commitment,'' he said, ''then it's the last word in giving something like graffiti a resounding thumbs up.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2000, Monday  An article on June 10 about an auction of graffiti art referred incorrectly in some editions to the name used by Jean-Michel Basquiat when he created graffiti in his youth. It was Samo, not Sarno.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on June 10 about an auction of graffiti art referred incorrectly in some editions to the name used by Jean-Michel Basquiat when he created graffiti in his youth. It was Samo, not Sarno.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
