<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="10TRN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2D81F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Agreed to terms with OF Bo Ivy, OF Eddie Young, LHP James Sweeney, RHP Brian Graham, RHP Curtis Young, LHP Brad Murray, RHP Kyle Bohannan and OF Anthony Monegan.  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with LHP Chad Petty, SS Ronald Merrill, RHP Thomas Rodney and RHP Michael Steele.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Agreed to terms with OF Bo Ivy, OF Eddie Young, LHP James Sweeney, RHP Brian Graham, RHP Curtis Young, LHP Brad Murray, RHP Kyle Bohannan and OF Anthony Monegan.  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with LHP Chad Petty, SS Ronald Merrill, RHP Thomas Rodney and RHP Michael Steele.</p>
        <p>National League  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Transferred LHP Sterling Hitchcock from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of RHP Carlos Reyes from Las Vegas of the PCL. Optioned RHP Domingo Guzman to Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Northern League  ALBANY-COLONIE DIAMOND DOGS--Sold the contract of OF Angel Ramirez to Duluth-Superior. Signed OF Drew Zachry.  NEW JERSEY JACKALS--Placed LHP Mark Lemke on the seven-day disabled list. Released OF Kenny Craddox. Signed RHP Clay Eason and P Heath Altman.  SIOUX FALLS CANARIES--Signed RHP Jason Mathys. Waived LHP Jaime Adames.  WATERBURY SPIRIT--Signed INF Ron Maurer and P Brian Schwalm. Traded INF Juan Penalver to Allentown for future considerations. Placed RHP Jarod Juelsgaard on the disabled list, retroactive to June 4.</p>
        <p>Frontier League</p>
        <p>CANTON CROCODILES--Signed RHP Brian Zima. Released RHP Jerry Zaffis.  CHILLICOTHE PAINTS--Signed LHP Bart Lindsey. Released LHP Rip Fleming.  DUBOIS COUNTY DRAGONS--Activated C Matt Freeman from the suspended list. Released INF Steve Coleman.  RICHMOND ROOSTERS--Signed LHP Steve Carver. Released RHP Takanori Mizuno.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  Women's National Basketball Association</p>
        <p>MIAMI SOL--Activated G Kisha Ford from the injured list. Placed Sharon Manning on the injured list.</p>
        <p>United States Basketball League</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN KINGS--Released G Scott Harmatuck and F Angel Santana. Signed G Treoyan Ridgas and F Donald Harrison.  FLORIDA SEA DRAGONS--Placed G Keeweemada King and F Cypheus Bunton on the inactive list. Signed C-F Mohamed Woni and G Wayne Copeland.  NEW JERSEY SHORECATS--Activated G Terrell Baker and G John Giraldo. Placed G Aubrey Reese and G-F Ray Tutt on the inactive list.  PENNSYLVANIA VALLEYDAWGS--Released F Kevin Freeman.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND BROWNS--Cut DE Mike Gantous, LB Marcus Gunn, FB Mike Jones, LB Caspor Stiles and LB Lamont Turner.</p>
        <p>Arena Football League</p>
        <p>GRAND RAPIDS RAMPAGE--Signed Michael Trigg, coach and director of football operations, to a two-year contract extension.  LOS ANGELES AVENGERS--Activated DS Ken Haslip from the injured reserve list. Waived DS Carlos Brooks.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>MINEESOTA WILD--Signed G Derek Gustafson and LW Randy Fitzgerald.  NEW YORK ISLANDERS--Re-signed D Eric Cairns to a two-year contract.  Central Hockey League  OKLAHOMA CITY BLAZERS--Signed D Paul Johnson and D Tyler Fleck for the 2000-01 season.</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League</p>
        <p>WHEELING NAILERS--Acquired D Jon Sorg from Dayton.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
        <p>OLYMPIC REGIONAL DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY--Promoted acting director Liz DeFazio to director of the 1932 and 1980 Winter Olympic Museum in Lake Placid, N.Y.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>AUBURN--Named Rusty Cooper assistant volleyball coach.  BINGHAMTON--Named David O'Brian assistant sports information director.  BOWDOIN--Named Bradford M. Burnham men's and women's swimming coach.  MINNESOTA-CROOKSTON--Named Dave Simon women's volleyball coach.  NORTH CAROLINA-ASHEVILLE--Named Jon Comstock athletic director.  NORTHWESTERN STATE--Named Steve Roberts football coach.  TENNESSEE--Named Craig Pinkerton assistant sports information director for men's basketball.  TROY STATE--Signed Don Maestri, men's basketball coach, to a three-year contract extension.  TULSA--Announced the resignation of Bill Self, men's basketball coach, to take the same position at Illinois.  UNION--Named Val Belmonte athletic director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
