<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Invited the Bears?</title>
    <meta content="10BUDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Budiansky, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DC1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Invited the Bears?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Budiansky</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Budiansky, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>LEESBURG, Va.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Budiansky Op-Ed article says bears living near populated streets in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut are exploiting a habitat that has been unwittingly created for them by human actions; notes that forested area of Northeast is double what it was 150 years ago; says animal populations whose size, location and feeding habits have been shaped by human interference will have to be subject to human control, including scientifically managed hunting; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As black bears have begun showing up at surprising places in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut -- including backyard barbecues and even living rooms -- animal rights and environmental groups have predictably argued that the bears shouldn't be hunted, that people just need to learn to coexist with nature.</p>
        <p>But there is nothing ''natural'' about where bears are found these days or the things they do. Human activity has created a new ecological niche that bears and other adaptable species, like coyotes, foxes, raccoons and deer, adeptly exploit. And as bears are drawn ever more to this artificial niche, it is inevitable that incidents like the one in which a bear ripped out an air conditioner to gain entry to a family's home will become more frequent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As black bears have begun showing up at surprising places in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut -- including backyard barbecues and even living rooms -- animal rights and environmental groups have predictably argued that the bears shouldn't be hunted, that people just need to learn to coexist with nature.</p>
        <p>But there is nothing ''natural'' about where bears are found these days or the things they do. Human activity has created a new ecological niche that bears and other adaptable species, like coyotes, foxes, raccoons and deer, adeptly exploit. And as bears are drawn ever more to this artificial niche, it is inevitable that incidents like the one in which a bear ripped out an air conditioner to gain entry to a family's home will become more frequent.</p>
        <p>The idea that bears and other wild animals just want to be left alone may be appealing, but it offers a false sense of security. Livestock, garbage, backyard bird feeders and even well-stored food in locked houses pose an irresistible attraction to bears. Some that  come to associate people with food are actually drawn to humans, with results that are not always peaceful.</p>
        <p>Bears who live near populated streets are not simply doing what they were doing before some recent onset of suburban sprawl. The surge in bear numbers is a reflection of human actions. In many parts of the Northeast, the forested area is double what it was 150 years ago, when as much as 60 or 70 percent of Connecticut, for example, was farmland. Modern suburban development, in other words, has actually created a new and attractive bear habitat.</p>
        <p>The return of woodland in the Northeast may look like a return to nature, but it is a far different landscape from any that has existed since the glaciers retreated 10,000 years ago. For one thing, the vast influence that Indians had on the land through hunting and deliberate burning of forest tracts is gone today.</p>
        <p>In addition to attracting and supporting a large bear population, the suburbs and outlying populated areas have become home to booming numbers of highly adaptable species that cause trouble not only for people but for biodiversity as well. Exploding deer populations throughout the East, for example, are destroying the habitats for many rare songbirds.</p>
        <p>In the largest sense, animal protection groups are right to point out that we must find ways to coexist with other species on the planet. But coexistence must mean more than simply standing by as bears, deer and other species do as they please.</p>
        <p>Rather, we must face up to our responsibility to manage the animal populations whose size, location and feeding habits have often been shaped, consciously or not, by our actions. The only lasting solution will be scientifically managed hunting, combined with habitat protection and management in the interests of all species.</p>
        <p>A laissez-faire approach to nature is not merely an inconvenience to people; it is ultimately bad for nature, too. When animal populations artificially explode as a result of human influence, the consequences for the ecosystem are often devastating. And for a large, adaptable and potentially destructive species like the black bear, the best long-term chances for survival lie in establishing sustainable populations in places where the animals are less likely to become dependent on humans. Today, preserving nature requires us to manage nature.</p>
        <p>Stephen Budiansky is a correspondent for The Atlantic Monthly and the author of ''If a Lion Could Talk: Animal Intelligence and the Evolution of Consciousness.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stephen Budiansky is a correspondent for The Atlantic Monthly and the author of ''If a Lion Could Talk: Animal Intelligence and the Evolution of Consciousness.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
