<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Penicheiro Dominates The Liberty</title>
    <meta content="10LIBE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sacramento Monarchs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6D81F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Penicheiro Dominates The Liberty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sacramento Monarchs defeat New York Liberty, 77-56 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Liberty players missed their shots, and that was with stunning frequency last night at Madison Square Garden, Sacramento sent the rebounds directly to point guard Ticha Penicheiro. From there, Penicheiro only accelerated, starting the fast break every time down court with such urgency, it was as if she were entering the autobahn.</p>
        <p>Her Monarch teammates filled the lanes seamlessly and she flipped them no-look passes, leaving the Liberty looking dazed and breathing hard through their open mouths as the ball landed neatly in the net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Liberty players missed their shots, and that was with stunning frequency last night at Madison Square Garden, Sacramento sent the rebounds directly to point guard Ticha Penicheiro. From there, Penicheiro only accelerated, starting the fast break every time down court with such urgency, it was as if she were entering the autobahn.</p>
        <p>Her Monarch teammates filled the lanes seamlessly and she flipped them no-look passes, leaving the Liberty looking dazed and breathing hard through their open mouths as the ball landed neatly in the net.</p>
        <p>When Penicheiro was not igniting the fastest break in the Women's National Basketball Association, Yolanda Griffith, the 6-foot-3-inch Olympian, was proving why she was named the league's most valuable player last season. New York's Tari Phillips succeeded in matching her, even getting a game-high 25 points and 9 rebounds to Griffith's 24 points and 8 rebounds, but no one else on the Liberty could keep up with the rest of the Monarchs.</p>
        <p>With a small bench, whittled down by injuries, and ice in its fingertips, New York (2-4) lost its fourth and worst game of the season last night, 77-56. The Monarchs, considered one of the top teams in the preseason, overwhelmed the Liberty early, using a 46-27 halftime lead to win for the first time in four games.</p>
        <p>Including Phillips, who converted 9 of 16 shots from the field, the Liberty shot 28.6 percent. ''It was almost like there was a lid on the basket,'' Liberty Coach Richie Adubato said. ''When you shoot 28 percent, you're not going to win. We just played the worst game that we've ever played since I've been here, in regard to giving them a head start and not being able to shoot the basketball.''</p>
        <p>Penicheiro and her teammates orchestrated the head start. With 13 minutes 46 seconds remaining in the first half, Liberty forward Vickie Johnson's 3-pointer put New York ahead, 10-7, but Griffith scored 5 straight points, and suddenly, the Monarchs were in the middle of their minirun, a warm-up for their 14-0 run two minutes later.</p>
        <p>By the time they were done, the Monarchs held a 31-15 lead. Griffith went into halftime having scored 14 points. ''Tonight,'' Griffith said, ''we ran the floor like the old Sacramento Monarchs used to do last year.''</p>
        <p>Phillips noticed. ''One way to kill the morale of a team is on fast-break points because sometimes you look up and you don't know the ball is going the other way,'' Phillips said. ''It kills you offensively, defensively. It kills your legs and your stamina.''</p>
        <p>The Liberty was without the sure-shooter Crystal Robinson, her sprained left ankle only about 75 percent healthy, as well as the reserve guard Jessica Bibby. The Monarchs took advantage by running the break again and again, pushing the game out of the reach of the gasping Liberty, which now must turn around and play at Indiana tonight.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
