<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stars Say Winning Gives Them Momentum</title>
    <meta content="10STAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STANLEY CUP FINALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DA1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stars Say Winning Gives Them Momentum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Dallas Stars staving off elimination in Stanley Cup Finals by defeating New Jersey Devils in Game 3 in triple overtime; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Stars looked the part of the late-night revelers on the day after, their hangovers firmly entrenched. The three team leaders who spoke to the news media today -- Mike Modano, Joe Nieuwendyk and the team captain, Derian Hatcher -- all looked haggard. All three were unshaven. Each was puffy under and around his eyes.</p>
        <p>For good reason.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Stars looked the part of the late-night revelers on the day after, their hangovers firmly entrenched. The three team leaders who spoke to the news media today -- Mike Modano, Joe Nieuwendyk and the team captain, Derian Hatcher -- all looked haggard. All three were unshaven. Each was puffy under and around his eyes.</p>
        <p>For good reason.</p>
        <p>''We haven't had a chance to go over the tapes,'' Coach Ken Hitchcock said. ''It's like 'War and Peace.' ''</p>
        <p>Less than 24 hours earlier, the Stars had staved off elimination in New Jersey with a stirring 1-0 triple-overtime victory over the Devils in Game 5.</p>
        <p>The first puck was dropped at 8:10 p.m. Eastern time and the game lasted until Modano redirected a Brett Hull pass past Martin Brodeur at 1:11 a.m. The 5-hour-1-minute victory enabled them to bring the Stanley Cup finals back to Dallas, with the Devils leading the four-of-seven-game series, three games to two.</p>
        <p>Hitchcock had decided that his team would stay overnight in New Jersey if the game went longer than one overtime. By the time the Stars had showered, dressed, done their interviews and taken a 45-minute bus ride to a hotel in Piscataway, N.J., it was about 3 a.m.</p>
        <p>A few hours later, it was back on a bus to Newark International Airport for an 11 a.m. flight to the Dallas-Fort Worth airport. The flight was fittingly delayed by inclement weather. The pilot made two passes at the runway before finally landing at the farthest possible point from the Stars' usual terminal, necessitating another 20 minutes of taxiing in the plane.</p>
        <p>Modano, who was the best skater for either team in the game, said: ''Last night was a long night. Today's been a long day.''</p>
        <p>Hitchcock can therefore be excused for bristling today when he was told of the postgame comments by Devils Coach Larry Robinson.</p>
        <p>Robinson had been asked how tough it would be for the Devils to lose a six-period game, travel to Dallas, then try to motivate themselves to close out the series Saturday night on the road.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' said Robinson, making a late-night attempt at levity, ''I think we are the fresher team anyway. With Modano playing about 75 minutes tonight, he probably played more than half our team put together.</p>
        <p>''Every second shift he was out there,'' Robinson said about Modano, who turned 30 on Wednesday and played a team-high 43 minutes 37 seconds. ''And he's not a young man anymore. And they have a lot of guys that played a lot of hockey. So I think with the way our guys play and the fact that we use more players than they do, it should be an advantage to us going back there.''</p>
        <p>Hitchcock raised up on his haunches like an angry cat when he heard the paraphrased version of Robinson's comments.</p>
        <p>''Larry should mind his own business and worry about his own team,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Even though the Stars are still a game away from elimination and need two more victories to repeat as champions, Hitchcock and his players think that the momentum has shifted back to them.</p>
        <p>''Mentally, I think we may have an edge,'' Nieuwendyk said, ''because they had their party ready and we took it away from them.''</p>
        <p>Modano added: ''We all felt if we won last night, we're going back there to play Monday. And that's still our mind-set. We can't lose three in a row at home.''</p>
        <p>So the Stars are back home and still standing, however unsteadily.</p>
        <p>''I do think the momentum has shifted,'' Nieuwendyk said. ''I think it hurt them real bad. To go that long, to be that close to winning the cup. And you come up short.''</p>
        <p>If the Stars can hold serve at home, they will force the series back to New Jersey for a deciding seventh game. The finals have not gone the limit since the Rangers defeated the Vancouver Canucks in Game 7 to win the cup in 1994.</p>
        <p>But if the Devils can win here on Saturday night, they will repeat their success from 1995. And the Stars' effort in Game 5 will have gone for naught. ''To win Game 5 and then to allow that to happen in our building, that would be a horrible feeling,'' Hatcher said.</p>
        <p>About the way the Devils probably felt early this morning.</p>
        <p>STANLEY CUP FINALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
