<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Lesson Of Lebanon</title>
    <meta content="10LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DB1E3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Lesson Of Lebanon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column says moral of Israeli occupation of southern Lebanon is that when Israel holds the territory of another nation, it damages its own security and well-being; says this moral applies to West Bank, Gaza and East Jerusalem as well (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The story of Israel's military presence in Lebanon, which ended just now in sudden withdrawal, has a moral that we are in danger of missing. The moral is simple but crucial. When Israel holds the territory of another nation, it damages its own security and well-being.</p>
        <p>Israeli forces were in southern Lebanon for 22 years. They, and the local militia they created, were supposed to assure security for northern Israel. But that end was never achieved, and in the fruitless effort more than 900 Israeli soldiers were killed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The story of Israel's military presence in Lebanon, which ended just now in sudden withdrawal, has a moral that we are in danger of missing. The moral is simple but crucial. When Israel holds the territory of another nation, it damages its own security and well-being.</p>
        <p>Israeli forces were in southern Lebanon for 22 years. They, and the local militia they created, were supposed to assure security for northern Israel. But that end was never achieved, and in the fruitless effort more than 900 Israeli soldiers were killed.</p>
        <p>In political terms the adventure was drastically counterproductive. The Lebanese, who had been rather mild in their attitude toward Israel, were embittered by the long occupation and by civilian deaths and suffering. Hezbollah, the militant Muslim movement, flourished.</p>
        <p>The withdrawal, accomplished as it was without casualties, was cheered by most Israelis. They understood, as Prime Minister Ehud Barak did, that trying to control Lebanese territory was an exercise in painful futility.</p>
        <p>What some Israelis, and their American supporters, have not understood is that the moral of the Lebanese experience applies also to Israel's hold on areas of the West Bank, Gaza and East Jerusalem. In culture and national identification they are alien territories, and Israel only harms itself by trying to maintain a grip on them.</p>
        <p>Take the easy case first: Gaza. Israel still holds onto significant pieces of that overcrowded strip. It is incongruous to find, amid desperate Palestinian refugee camps, an Israeli resort or well-watered agricultural settlement. They are a recipe for resentment, and they exist only because Israel devotes expensive military and economic resources to them.</p>
        <p>In the West Bank vast Jewish settlements -- really towns -- are home to Israelis who are there not for ideological reasons but because they got subsidized housing at commuting distance from jobs in Israel. In the Israeli-Palestinian negotiations, Prime Minister Barak proposes to incorporate the suburban settlements near the border into Israel. That may well happen as part of a final agreement.</p>
        <p>The more remote Jewish settlements staked out in the hills of the West Bank are another story. They are ideological in character: planted there as part of a religious-nationalist effort to keep control of all the historical ''Land of Israel.'' In any serious tension or, worse, an armed conflict, they would be a security nightmare for the Israel Defense Force.</p>
        <p>Any realist coming upon those ideological settlements sees them for what they are: outposts in an alien land. They are utterly inconsistent with peace and stability for Israel.</p>
        <p>A majority of Israelis have for some time favored letting the Palestinians have their own country. Consistent with that view, they are prepared to abandon many settlements. But extremists in the settler movement put their vision ahead of a negotiated peace. Some are going so far as to suggest that violence should be used against Mr. Barak to prevent a peace agreement that requires abandonment of settlements -- as any agreement must.</p>
        <p>The hard case is Jerusalem. That is because the majority of Israelis, who have come to see the danger of holding onto alien land elsewhere, find it hard to apply that logic to Jerusalem, with all its historic resonance for Jews.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials always say they will not agree to divide ''united Jerusalem.'' But that phrase is rhetoric, not reality.</p>
        <p>A tourist driving eastward from the modern center of West Jerusalem suddenly feels, as he passes the Old City on his right, a complete change in the character of the scene before him. It is a souk, a bazaar. Salah a-Din Street, the shopping center of East Jerusalem, is entirely Arab in its flavor. The chance that Israeli officials who talk about ''united Jerusalem'' actually go to East Jerusalem is approximately zero.</p>
        <p>To accommodate the realities of Jerusalem into an Israeli-Palestinian peace will be difficult, given the emotions; but it is not impossible. One thing is sure. Locating the government of a new Palestine in a bit of East Jerusalem is the best way to avoid Palestinian irredentism and relieve Israel of the burden of policing another people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
