<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>East Harlem Shopping Center Snagged Over Financing of Garage</title>
    <meta content="10HARL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">East River Plaza (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD81E3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>East Harlem Shopping Center Snagged Over Financing of Garage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plans to build East River Plaza shopping center in East Harlem run into snag because no financing has been found for $30 million parking garage; additional public financing is being sought for $160 million project, which is expected to provide more than 1,000 jobs; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was supposed to bring Manhattan its first Costco and Home Depot superstores and add more than a thousand jobs in East Harlem. But now, plans to build a shopping center along Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive have run into a serious snag because no financing has been found for the $30 million garage that is needed to make the project work, officials said this week.</p>
        <p>But they say they remain hopeful that the $160 million complex, known as East River Plaza, will eventually get off the ground. ''I don't think it's in anybody's interest for this project to be abandoned,'' said Councilman Philip Reed, who represents East Harlem. ''We worked very hard to sell this project, and the community was ultimately receptive to it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was supposed to bring Manhattan its first Costco and Home Depot superstores and add more than a thousand jobs in East Harlem. But now, plans to build a shopping center along Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive have run into a serious snag because no financing has been found for the $30 million garage that is needed to make the project work, officials said this week.</p>
        <p>But they say they remain hopeful that the $160 million complex, known as East River Plaza, will eventually get off the ground. ''I don't think it's in anybody's interest for this project to be abandoned,'' said Councilman Philip Reed, who represents East Harlem. ''We worked very hard to sell this project, and the community was ultimately receptive to it.''</p>
        <p>Approved last fall by the City Council, the shopping center, one of the largest projects planned for Manhattan in recent years, is intended to replace the long-dormant Washburn Wire Factory along the highway between 116th and 119th Streets. In addition to the superstores, leases have been signed with Old Navy, Gap and Best Buy. Other tenants are expected to include Staples, T. J. Maxx and Modell's Sporting Goods, said David Blumenfeld, a vice president of the Blumenfeld Development Corporation, which is developing the shopping center with Canyon Capital Management.</p>
        <p>Blumenfeld is also building a smaller retail center on 125th Street, near Lexington Avenue and opposite a Pathmark supermarket that opened last year. The complex was originally expected to house a 10-screen United Artists movie theater, but United Artists has backed out of the deal and no replacement was found, said Jesse Masyr, the lawyer representing the developers.</p>
        <p>As for East River Plaza, Mr. Blumenfeld said his tenants were unwilling to foot the construction cost of a seven-level garage containing 1,248 spaces and had insisted on free parking for the first two hours. But state officials, who would discuss the project only privately, say that the developer should not expect the public to absorb the entire cost of a private parking garage.</p>
        <p>The garage is needed because the developers estimate that the complex will draw 5,000 cars a day -- a figure that the project's critics say is much too low. Many people in the neighborhood are concerned about the added noise and pollution from the influx of cars to East Harlem, which has one of the highest asthma rates in the country.</p>
        <p>But opponents, including William Minic, a cabinetmaker who would have to give up the shop he has owned for more than two decades, were never able to muster a serious challenge to the project. And on Tuesday, a Supreme Court Appellate Division dismissed a lawsuit seeking to block the state from condemning property for the shopping center, saying it had not been filed in time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Masyr said he expected the decision to stand, but Jack R. Lester, the lawyer for the project's opponents, said the ruling did not bar further legal challenges.</p>
        <p>Pointing out that the cost of the project had nearly doubled since it was unveiled three years ago, state officials said they were working with the city's Economic Development Corporation to try to get additional financing from the Upper Manhattan Empowerment Zone, a federal, state and city program.</p>
        <p>One stumbling block, state officials say, is that developers would not guarantee how many jobs the project would generate, although they expect the number to be 1,200 to 1,500. Mr. Masyr said that it was impossible to get tenants to promise to hire a specific number of employees. But he said the developers were willing to pay a penalty if certain goals were not met.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumenfeld said he was disappointed that the state was not pushing harder to get the project going. ''It's disheartening for the people of Harlem and for myself,'' he said. ''It's rare that you have a project that has tenants, financing and approvals and still hasn't started.''</p>
        <p>C. Virginia Fields, the Manhattan borough president, said she would urge Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani to find a way to rescue the project. And she said she was still optimistic. ''This is just a fork in the road,'' she said. ''So much has already been invested that ultimately the resources will be found.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
