<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paris Final Is Set as Kuerten Rallies and Norman Breezes</title>
    <meta content="10TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuerten, Gustavo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norman, Magnus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D91E3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paris Final Is Set as Kuerten Rallies and Norman Breezes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Magnus Norman and Gustavo Kuerten advance to final of French Open tennis tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It will be Magnus Norman versus Gustavo Kuerten in the French Open final Sunday, but anyone who had the good fortune to spend 3 hours 38 minutes watching the second semifinal today knows that it could very easily have been Magnus Norman versus Juan Carlos Ferrero instead.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Kuerten came to Roland Garros as a 20-year-old and won hearts, minds and eventually the tournament by beating up on his elders. For much of today's match, Kuerten must have felt as if he were seeing his own reflection across the net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It will be Magnus Norman versus Gustavo Kuerten in the French Open final Sunday, but anyone who had the good fortune to spend 3 hours 38 minutes watching the second semifinal today knows that it could very easily have been Magnus Norman versus Juan Carlos Ferrero instead.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Kuerten came to Roland Garros as a 20-year-old and won hearts, minds and eventually the tournament by beating up on his elders. For much of today's match, Kuerten must have felt as if he were seeing his own reflection across the net.</p>
        <p>Ferrero is the one who is 20 this year, the one who lashed his ground strokes with insouciance and precision, the one chasing down and trumping the best efforts of more experienced men. And when the Spaniard took a two-set-to-one lead and then broke Kuerten's serve early in the fourth set to take a 3-1 lead, it appeared that his very first French Open would be a debut for tennis historians to remember.</p>
        <p>''It felt so close,'' said Ferrero, whose rise has been so swift that he was seeded 16th here.</p>
        <p>But Kuerten, the fifth-seeded Brazilian who wears a wide bandanna, was not ready to congratulate Ferrero just yet. Despite a sore back and sore legs, Kuerten somehow summoned the energy to start finding the lines again and won in five sets, 7-5, 4-6, 2-6, 6-4, 6-3.</p>
        <p>Norman, who is seeded No. 3 and has lost only one set this tournament, expended a great deal less energy and emotion in his victory today in defeating Franco Squillari, the unseeded Argentine left-hander, 6-1, 6-4, 6-3, to reach his first Grand Slam final.</p>
        <p>''I was expecting maybe a tougher match, but that was his first semifinal, so maybe his nerves were a little bit like mine down in Australia,'' said Norman, who had great difficulty keeping the ball in the court when he lost his first Grand Slam semifinal at the Australian Open this year.</p>
        <p>This time, the Swede had no such difficulty, picking on Squillari's weaker backhand swing. Norman is a powerful athlete and a complete tennis player who, with his white cap, sturdy build and Calvinist work ethic, is reminiscent of Jim Courier at his peak, but with a much more penetrating serve and two-handed backhand and better technique at the net.</p>
        <p>Norman's lopsided victory was merely a prelude to the best match of the men's tournament thus far, and what made it good was the percussive brilliance of both men from the backcourt and Kuerten's ability to ignore the signals his skinny body was sending him.</p>
        <p>''He won that match with his shots, but he really won it with his heart,'' said Patrice Hagelauer, a former French Davis Cup coach who, like many people, left the stands feeling a bit weak in the knees.</p>
        <p>This was Kuerten's second consecutive five-set match. In the quarterfinals, he survived despite trailing by two sets to one against Yevgeny Kafelnikov, with Kafelnikov up by 4-2 in the fourth set and serving at 40-15. Kuerten prevailed largely because Kafelnikov's play dropped off dramatically.</p>
        <p>This time, Kuerten lifted his game in a hurry and Ferrero's game dropped off only slightly. The change came with Ferrero up a break and leading by 3-2. On the changeover, Kuerten received treatment on his chronically tight lower back, which has been bothering him since February.</p>
        <p>Kuerten then broke Ferrero in the next game with a backhand volley winner to get back to 3-3 and then broke him again in a terrific and hard-fought 10th game to even the match. Down the stretch, the difference was in the details: Kuerten's better serve, his willingness to push forward and his experience.</p>
        <p>''I think we played one of the best matches here, great performance,'' Kuerten said. ''The crowd was so into it. It was great to be there. In the fifth set, I was so pumped up. That's the feeling we always try to experience on court. Today was that kind of day. Even if I went off court losing in five sets, I was going to be satisfied.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he got the chance to be ecstatic, raising both arms triumphantly and turning his handshake with Ferrero into a hug.</p>
        <p>''He pushed me close to my limit; I really had to do everything right to beat him,'' Kuerten said.</p>
        <p>Kuerten also said that he still had some energy left for his encounter Sunday with Norman.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm very strong now,'' Kuerten said, ''and I think I'm going to be even stronger in the final.''</p>
        <p>The question is, should Norman believe him?</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
