<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Studies Thaw The Exploits Of Undercover Cold Warriors</title>
    <meta content="10GOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Ted</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lovestone, Jay (1897-1990)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grose, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saunders, Frances Stonor</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Covert Life, A (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Operation Rollback (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cultural Cold War, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DD1E3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Studies Thaw The Exploits Of Undercover Cold Warriors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several books provide new insights into American anti-Communism and anti-Soviet espionage during Cold War, particularly activities of Central Intelligence Agency; article discusses Ted Morgan book A Covert Life: Jay Lovestone, Communist, Anti-Communist and Spymaster, Preter Gross book Operation Rollback: America's Secret War Behind the Iron Curtain, and Frances Stonor Saunders book The Cultural Cold War: The CIA and the World of Arts and Letters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the years since the breakup of the Soviet Union and the opening of its secret files, much has been learned about the accomplishments of Soviet spies in the United States, particularly in the 1930's and 40's. The still-accumulating evidence has silenced some of the truest believers in the innocence of the likes of Alger Hiss and Julius Rosenberg.</p>
        <p>But lest Americans are left with the uncomfortable notion that their country remained passively at the mercy of traitors, new studies are drawing attention to huggermugger by the Western allies after World War II. In some ways these books are reassuring; in some ways they raise or reinforce doubts about the means and ends of Washington's undercover wars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the years since the breakup of the Soviet Union and the opening of its secret files, much has been learned about the accomplishments of Soviet spies in the United States, particularly in the 1930's and 40's. The still-accumulating evidence has silenced some of the truest believers in the innocence of the likes of Alger Hiss and Julius Rosenberg.</p>
        <p>But lest Americans are left with the uncomfortable notion that their country remained passively at the mercy of traitors, new studies are drawing attention to huggermugger by the Western allies after World War II. In some ways these books are reassuring; in some ways they raise or reinforce doubts about the means and ends of Washington's undercover wars.</p>
        <p>At the close of World War II, with much of Europe in economic and political disarray, Washington was troubled by what it saw as a surge of Communist influence promoted from Moscow. The Truman administration being new to the geopolitical game and the Central Intelligence Agency not yet invented, a few leaders of the American Federation of Labor undertook their own anti-Communist effort.</p>
        <p>To direct it, George Meany, who was in effect running the A.F.L., and David Dubinsky, president of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, picked Jay Lovestone to be their commander in chief for the labor wars. The result is engagingly chronicled by Ted Morgan in ''A Covert Life: Jay Lovestone, Communist, Anti-Communist and Spymaster'' (Random House).</p>
        <p>Lovestone had the credentials for the job. As a young Communist in the 1920's he was deeply enmeshed in the party's incessant factional conflicts; for a couple of years he headed the American Communist Party, until he was ousted on Stalin's orders. Like other radicals of the time he wound up as an anti-Communist crusader.</p>
        <p>Lovestone masterminded an energetic assault on European unions and parties with communist leanings. In West Germany he supported the Social Democrats under Kurt Schumacher and fostered free trade unions. In France, abetted by Irving Brown, another tough Communist hater, he helped beat back a Communist-inspired effort to derail the Marshall Plan, and in Italy Lovestone and Brown bolstered democratic parties in parliamentary elections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morgan credits the A.F.L. with standing alone from November 1945 to the spring of 1948 ''in acting against Soviet expansion via the trade unions.'' Well, not altogether alone. In an audience with Pope Pius XII Lovestone announced, ''We are anti-Communists without any reservations or hesitations.'' The startled pope replied, ''But Mr. Lovestone, I, too, am anti-Communist.''</p>
        <p>Although the just-formed C.I.A. slipped $10 million to Italy's Christian Democrats when the Communist Party mounted a serious parliamentary challenge in the 1948 elections, the agency's relations with the contentious Lovestone were always testy. The F.B.I. kept close watch on an operator with so flagrant a set of Communist credentials, and he also had run-ins with Congress, the State Department and the White House, all of which he felt were insufficiently aggressive toward Stalin.</p>
        <p>Lovestone's great years came early, but he lasted for decades, supplying worldwide intelligence to the C.I.A.'s fabled and perhaps paranoiac James Jesus Angleton. At Lovestone's death in 1990, a year before the dissolution of the Soviet Union, he was still fighting his good fight, leaving behind the anomalous legacy of ostensibly free trade unions' consorting secretly with a spy agency. The consolation was that unlike some other cold war adventurers, they proved good at it.</p>
        <p>How bad these others could be is chronicled by Peter Grose in ''Operation Rollback: America's Secret War Behind the Iron Curtain'' (Houghton Mifflin). His account of American forays into espionage in the late 40's and early 50's might be humorous, were the stakes not so serious. In a plan hatched by George F. Kennan, known for inventing the policy of containment, and backed by the C.I.A. director Allen Dulles, the supersecret Office of Policy Coordination financed a multimillion-dollar campaign of sabotage in Soviet-bloc countries. Or such was the concept, which failed wherever it was tried. Front groups with words like liberation in their titles were cobbled together. Bickering bands of emigres, including sometime fascists and Nazi hangers-on, were recruited in displaced-person camps and sent on impossible missions.</p>
        <p>In Albania, Romania, Poland and within the Soviet Union itself the results were the same: Eric Ambler as adapted by the Three Stooges. The Soviets, abetted in some cases by information supplied by Kim Philby, the British double agent, captured and executed most of the infiltrators, and Washington was put to the trouble of denying all knowledge of its inept provocations.</p>
        <p>In sum ''Rollback'' was not the estimable Mr. Kennan's most successful project. If it had served as a cautionary lesson, it might have spared the nation even more dubious adventures from Southeast Asia to Latin America in decades to come.</p>
        <p>In a more successful and less lethal cold war assay, the C.I.A. was waging a cultural-political battle that roiled the intelligentsia of several countries and continues to stir controversy.</p>
        <p>The revelation in the late 60's that the agency was secretly financing seemingly independent intellectuals and organizations caused a sensation, but it awaited Frances Stoner Saunders, in ''The Cultural Cold War: The C.I.A. and the World of Arts and Letters'' (New Press), to provide a detailed picture of who did what and how it was done.</p>
        <p>To combat Comintern propaganda, beginning around 1950 Washington mounted a counteroffensive aimed at challenging a prevailing image of the United States as a land whose matchless wealth was matched by a paucity of culture. With C.I.A. support, known fully only to a few, a stellar collection of generally liberal and assuredly anti-Communist intellectuals were recruited for battle.</p>
        <p>Magazines in several countries, most notably Encounter in Britain, were created and edited with distinction, and others, like the influential Partisan Review, were subsidized. Big-name forums, art exhibits and celebratory festivals were organized, and the Metropolitan Opera and the Boston Symphony were sent on European tour. The message was that the United States was a fount of cultural ferment.</p>
        <p>It worked. The few stars of the fellow-traveling circuit like Paul Robeson, Lillian Hellman and Howard Fast were easily outgunned by an imposing array of writers, scholars and artists gathered in the Congress for Cultural Freedom. A few names: Arthur Koestler, Andre Malraux, Isaiah Berlin, Raymond Aron, Mary McCarthy, Reinhold Neibuhr, George Orwell, Robert Lowell, Bertrand Russell, Stephen Spender, Arthur Schlesinger Jr., Ignazio Silone, Andre Gide. While the Stalinists tended to be middlebrow, this group was weighted decidedly toward the highbrow. Ms. Saunders gives much of the credit, or blame, for the popularity of abstract art to its promotion by the C.I.A.</p>
        <p>She leaves little doubt that some of the players were in on the C.I.A. connection, but even this highly critical chronicler does not charge that most of the stars knew that the Congress for Cultural Freedom was an arm of the agency. (Many thought, if they thought about it at all, that the money was coming from foundations.) Nor, despite examples of C.I.A. efforts to exert pressure, does she make much of a case that the luminaries were tailoring their ideas to suit agency specifications: they were, after all, non-Communist men and women of the left to whom championing Western values against Stalin's despotism came naturally.</p>
        <p>In the fashion of the intellectual set, there was plenty of disagreement within ranks, notably a fierce fight over how to deal or fail to deal with the rampages of Senator Joseph R. McCarthy. Hard-line anti-Communists in the American Committee for Cultural Freedom, led by Sidney Hook and abetted by the C.I.A. handlers, succeeded in blocking a public statement attacking McCarthyism, lest it get in the way of their primary mission to attack Communism, while less doctrinaire liberals were distressed by the failure to act against what they saw as the McCarthyite attack on freedom. The split led to the American group's demise.</p>
        <p>The exposure of the C.I.A. largess of course embarrassed the pro-American cause as intellectuals famed for being know-it-alls scurried to proclaim their ignorance. The sticking point was not so much the substance as the secrecy: for a group like the congress, dedicated to free and open discussion, to be revealed as a C.I.A. client, with all that implied by way of influence or control, did not go down easily. Ms. Saunders holds that there was certainly influence and possibly control.</p>
        <p>Depending on their predilections, readers can find cause in these histories for cheering or deploring America's cold war excursions. The one sure constant is that the central issue they raise -- what principled actions a free country may take in a battle with a pronounced enemy of freedom -- will not soon, if ever, be resolved.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
