<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Vote as a Political Excuse</title>
    <meta content="10ASSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D91F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Vote as a Political Excuse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard L Berke analysis says substantial campaign finance reform may have been set back by Senate vote on June 8 to require tax-exempt groups that are amassing and spending huge sums on political activities to disclose their donors and spending; says senators who voted yes on June 8 can now assure constituents that they backed reform and resist more comprehensive prescriptions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It looked like a huge breakthrough for the forces of campaign finance reform. For the first time in seven years, the Senate approved major legislation to tighten campaign finance laws. Supporters of Senator John McCain called it a testament to his political potency and his crusading on the issue.</p>
        <p>And many Republicans, fearful that they might be tagged as anti-reform by voters in November, went along with it, many for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It looked like a huge breakthrough for the forces of campaign finance reform. For the first time in seven years, the Senate approved major legislation to tighten campaign finance laws. Supporters of Senator John McCain called it a testament to his political potency and his crusading on the issue.</p>
        <p>And many Republicans, fearful that they might be tagged as anti-reform by voters in November, went along with it, many for the first time.</p>
        <p>''The political fear of God -- that's what did it,'' said Senator John B. Breaux, Democrat of Louisiana.</p>
        <p>Both parties did manage to join forces on a new battle front: the proliferation of tax-exempt groups that are secretly amassing and spending huge sums on political activities. The Senate bill would require those groups to disclose their donors and spending.</p>
        <p>Yet, for all the supporters' glee about the vote on Thursday, there was no reason to believe that Congress had moved closer to substantially changing the system or addressing what critics argue is the biggest problem. That is the vast sums of unregulated soft money that Democrats and Republicans are pouring into politics.</p>
        <p>By today, it was clear that the disclosure effort would not go far. Some Republicans, saying it was not sweeping enough, voted against a similar measure in the House, which was defeated today. It was viewed as a thinly disguised way to kill the legislation.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the Senate seemed eager to carry the reform banner. Even many lawmakers who are not usually reform-minded backed the measure. Who could condone secretive, even sinister-sounding, organizations? Eight Republican senators who are up for re-election voted for the legislation. Most are not known as passionate advocates of reform.</p>
        <p>Still, many who voted with the majority said it did not mean they would budge from their past positions and sign off on banning soft money. In fact, voting for the bill on Thursday gave many lawmakers an excuse not to endorse more far-reaching restrictions.</p>
        <p>Walter F. Mondale, the former vice president who, as a senator, pressed for campaign reform after the Watergate scandal, said that while the vote created an opening, larger matters such as restricting soft money may not go anywhere because some senators can now assure constituents that they had backed changes to the system.</p>
        <p>''People can say, 'O.K., you've had your reform, now be a good boy,' '' Mr. Mondale said in an interview today. ''Or will they say, 'This shows that the public wants us to go on to the real evil, soft money?' ''</p>
        <p>Expressing skepticism about the interest of Republican leadership, he added that they ''will draw the line as hard as they can'' and resist more comprehensive prescriptions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breaux agreed that, politically, the vote gives senators an excuse for not acting more boldly.</p>
        <p>''If we do resolve this, at least we've done something that was significant,'' he said. ''It does take some of the pressure off of the big goal.''</p>
        <p>There are notable similarities, of all things, to the abortion issue. Many Democrats who favored abortion rights backed efforts to curtail late-term abortion because the procedure was seen as so egregious. It also gave them cover not to go all the way and oppose abortion outright. As with campaign finance, politicians who felt one way on the issue found a reason to break the pattern.</p>
        <p>Senator Spencer Abraham, a Michigan Republican who is seeking re-election, has opposed Mr. McCain's bill to prohibit soft money. Mr. Abraham, like many Republicans, derided it as an unconstitutional infringement on free speech.</p>
        <p>But he said he did not hesitate to back the measure on Thursday because he favors tightening disclosure of political giving.</p>
        <p>Asked if the vote would pave the way for the parties to find common ground on broader reform, Mr. Abraham said: ''It might. But I don't think that you're going to get a consensus for any bill that comes along.'' He has no fresh interest, he said, in backing the McCain measure.</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the minority leader, sounded more discouraged than encouraged.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call it cynical,'' Mr. Daschle said when asked whether some Republicans were hoping to show they had done something on the issue. ''In some cases, it's well intended.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Daschle said expectations were as low as ever. ''It's a commentary, though, on how far we've come from those days when we really thought we could see real, comprehensive reform,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the very least, reformers could claim credit for taking on the secret sources of financing. But advocates, like Mr. McCain, seemed to have surprised even themselves with the outcome on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The reality is that despite the attention Mr. McCain attracted in raising campaign finance during the Republican primaries, it is not a priority among voters.</p>
        <p>''They'd like to see campaign reform,'' said Gov. Gray Davis of California, a Democrat. ''But it's not like voters are saying, 'My whole life will change if you pass campaign reform.' ''</p>
        <p>For the reform advocates, there was a glimmer of hope.</p>
        <p>''The battle still has to be won,'' said Fred Wertheimer, president of Democracy 21, a Washington group that advocates campaign finance reform. ''But this is an opening.''</p>
        <p>At the very least, he can take heart that some lawmakers felt fresh pressure to be seen as doing something on campaign finance and that the issue is on the radar screen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
