<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Near-Unanimous Vote Elects O'Neal M.V.P.</title>
    <meta content="10SHAQ$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neal, Shaquille</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Near-Unanimous Vote Elects O'Neal M.V.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles Lakers center Shaquille O'Neal is elected National Basketball Association's Most Valuable Player for 1999-2000 season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of his first seven seasons, Shaquille O'Neal's pulverization of his 7-foot peers brought almost as much admiration as criticism. Observers wondered if O'Neal's skill and desire could match his bullish play near the rim.</p>
        <p>This season, he began to add range to his jump hook. A spin to the right, a spin to the left and 12-foot shots would drop. On defense, the Lakers' indomitable 7-foot-1-inch, 330-pound center moved his feet as never before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most of his first seven seasons, Shaquille O'Neal's pulverization of his 7-foot peers brought almost as much admiration as criticism. Observers wondered if O'Neal's skill and desire could match his bullish play near the rim.</p>
        <p>This season, he began to add range to his jump hook. A spin to the right, a spin to the left and 12-foot shots would drop. On defense, the Lakers' indomitable 7-foot-1-inch, 330-pound center moved his feet as never before.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in Los Angeles, O'Neal added another facet to his evolving game: best basketball player in the world. Finishing one vote shy of becoming the first unanimous choice in National Basketball Association history, O'Neal ran away with the league's most valuable player award.</p>
        <p>The voting was so lopsided that Karl Malone, Grant Hill, Kevin Garnett and Alonzo Mourning did not receive a single first-place vote among the 121 cast from sportswriters and broadcasters. O'Neal received 120 first-place votes, and Allen Iverson of the Philadelphia 76ers received one. O'Neal received 1,207 points in the voting. Minnesota's Kevin Garnett was second with 407 and Miami's Alonzo Mourning was third with 367. Iverson was seventh with 132. The New York Times does not participate in the voting.</p>
        <p>''That was kind of hard to believe,'' O'Neal said. ''I've always thought that Michael Jordan, Magic and Kareem and Wilt were the greatest players in the N.B.A.''</p>
        <p>Leading the league in scoring and field goal percentage, O'Neal amassed the highest vote percentage (99.1) for a winner since the award was first given out after the 1955-56 season.</p>
        <p>Since the All-Star Game break, there was little doubt who would win the award. Anchored by O'Neal and Kobe Bryant, the Lakers became the league's most dominant team and finished with a 67-15 record during the regular season. O'Neal's quest to show everyone he was the league's top performer was only overshadowed by his goal to bring the Lakers their first championship since 1988.</p>
        <p>''This is a very special day for a very special player,'' said Jerry West, the Lakers' vice president of basketball operations. ''I think we're all very excited he was able to win this award in such unprecedented fashion.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal, 28, is the first Lakers player to win the award since Magic Johnson won for second consecutive time in 1990. Utah's Karl Malone won the award last season and for the 1996-97 season. O'Neal won his second scoring title this season, averaging a career-high 29.7 points. He also led the N.B.A. in field-goal percentage (.574), was second in rebounding with a 13.6 average and averaged 3.03 blocks and a career-high 3.8 assists.</p>
        <p>''He's expanded his game,'' said Jack Ramsay, a former coach and now an N.B.A. analyst. ''Phil Jackson challenged him before the season began to play more of a Wilt Chamberlain-type game, which was big minutes, rebounding, assists, shot-blocking, intimidating and scoring. He's become the best passing center in the game.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal attributed his superb season to being healthy. In addition to seeing an acupuncturist regularly and eating well, he has not been limited by injuries. He missed only two games this season because of injury, both last month after the Lakers had clinched the best record and the home-court advantage throughout the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''The ultimate goal is to win the championship,'' O'Neal said. ''This is the best team I've ever played on. If we can get it done this year, my plate will be full as a player.''</p>
        <p>O'Neal has also averaged 30.7 points and 16.8 rebounds in six playoff games. The Lakers lead the Phoenix Suns, 1-0, in the Western Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>''It's terrific for the team and for Shaq,'' Lakers Coach Phil Jackson. ''He certainly deserved it this year. His leadership has been the most important thing for us.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The rookie of the year award will be announced tomorrow. A league official, speaking on the condition of anonymity, said STEVE FRANCIS of the Houston Rockets and ELTON BRAND of the Chicago Bulls tied for the award. This would be the third time there were co-winners following JASON KIDD and GRANT HILL in 1994-95 and DAVE COWENS and GEOFF PETRIE in 1970-71.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
