<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cisco's $662 Million Profit Tops Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="Y10CISC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cisco Systems Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DF1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cisco's $662 Million Profit Tops Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cisco Systems Inc says its third-quarter profit ended April 29 beat expectations; reports earnings of $662 million, compared with $636 million a year earlier; sales rose 55 percent, to $4.92 billion from $3.17 billion; president-chief executive John Chambers comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cisco Systems Inc., the leading supplier of hardware for the Internet, said today that its third-quarter profit beat expectations while it posted a 55 percent gain in sales.</p>
        <p>For the quarter, which ended April 29, Cisco reported earnings of $662 million, or 9 cents a diluted share. That compared with $636 million, or 9 cents a share, a year earlier. Per-share figures reflect a stock split that was effective March 22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cisco Systems Inc., the leading supplier of hardware for the Internet, said today that its third-quarter profit beat expectations while it posted a 55 percent gain in sales.</p>
        <p>For the quarter, which ended April 29, Cisco reported earnings of $662 million, or 9 cents a diluted share. That compared with $636 million, or 9 cents a share, a year earlier. Per-share figures reflect a stock split that was effective March 22.</p>
        <p>Sales rose 55 percent, to $4.92 billion from $3.17 billion. It was the company's ninth consecutive quarter of higher revenue growth.</p>
        <p>The quarter included acquisition-related charges of $488 million, or about 6 cents a share, after taxes. Pro forma net income, which excludes the acquisition charges, payroll tax on the exercise of stock options and gains realized on certain investments, was $1.03 billion, or 14 cents a share, up 58 percent from $649 million, or 9 cents a share, in the comparable period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected Cisco to earn 13 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks such estimates.</p>
        <p>Before Cisco reported its results, the company's shares closed unchanged at $62.75. Cisco's shares had dropped earlier in the week after an article in Barron's questioned the company's high valuation and acquisition strategy.</p>
        <p>''It was another amazing quarter from Cisco,'' said Paul Johnson, an analyst with Robertson Stephens &amp; Company. He said he did not think the company's valuation or ability to continue acquiring other companies was an issue, at least not this quarter. ''Most of the growth came from home-grown products,'' he said. ''The growth has continued despite the acquisitions.''</p>
        <p>In a conference call with analysts, John Chambers, Cisco's president and chief executive, said: ''Globally, business and government leaders are beginning to dramatically transform their traditional business models into Internet economy business models. Business leaders are beginning to get it, and as they get it they begin to bring the applications up and spend at an accelerated rate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chambers said the greatest competitive threat to Cisco came not from the established players in networking but from new smaller companies. ''Our toughest pinpoint competition continues to come from the existing start-ups and the virtually unlimited venture capital available to fund new ones,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Johnson of Robertson Stephens said that some of these smaller companies were growing much more rapidly than Cisco, noting that three of them -- Juniper Networks, Redback and Copper Mountain -- had combined revenue of $1 billion in the quarter. ''When you look at Cisco, it's hard to believe there are any threats, but the non-Cisco next generation companies are now a $4 billion business growing in excess of 150 percent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>During the quarter, Cisco, which is based in San Jose, Calif., completed the acquisitions of Aironet Wireless Communications and Pirelli Optical Systems for a combined total, including assumed liabilities, of about $2.85 billion. During the quarter, Cisco also announced it planned to acquire Pentacom Ltd., Growth Networks, Atlantech Technologies and a unit of Seagull Semiconductor Ltd. Last week, Cisco said that it had agreed to acquire ArrowPoint Communications, Inc. in a stock swap valued at $5.7 billion.</p>
        <p>''Companies that lead in this decade will not only have the ability to develop products internally and acquire effectively, but they'll also have the ability to form an ecosystem of partners,'' Mr. Chambers said. ''For this reason, Cisco is better positioned than ever to lead the Internet revolution through a combination of internal development, acquisitions, and partnerships.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
