<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Online Seller of Abstract Work Adds a Money-Back Guarantee</title>
    <meta content="10EBAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dobrzynski, Judith H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walton, Kenneth A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keereweer, Rob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diebenkorn, Richard (1922-93)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFD91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Online Seller of Abstract Work Adds a Money-Back Guarantee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH H. DOBRZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dobrzynski, Judith H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenneth A Walton, who put painting up for auction on eBay Internet site for 25 cents and ended up making $135,805 deal, admits he concocted part of story he used to describe work and is willing to let buyer, Rob Keereweer, out of deal if work is not by Richard Diebenkorn; speculation that work might be by Diebenkorn sparked bidding frenzy, even though description did not name painter; Walton is currently listing four other paintings on eBay (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The man who put a painting up for auction on the Internet for 25 cents and ended up making a $135,805 deal acknowledged yesterday that he concocted part of the story he used to describe the work and said he would be willing to let the buyer out of the sale.</p>
        <p>Before the bidding closed on Monday, speculation that the vivid abstract work -- which bore the initials ''R.D.'' -- was by the California artist Richard Diebenkorn set off a frenzy, though the description never said who had painted the work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The man who put a painting up for auction on the Internet for 25 cents and ended up making a $135,805 deal acknowledged yesterday that he concocted part of the story he used to describe the work and said he would be willing to let the buyer out of the sale.</p>
        <p>Before the bidding closed on Monday, speculation that the vivid abstract work -- which bore the initials ''R.D.'' -- was by the California artist Richard Diebenkorn set off a frenzy, though the description never said who had painted the work.</p>
        <p>Kenneth A. Walton, a lawyer in Sacramento who used the Internet name ''golfpoorly'' in offering the painting on eBay, said that he would cancel the sale, which is legally binding, if experts determine that the canvas is not by Diebenkorn and the buyer wants out. The buyer is Rob Keereweer of Nieuwkoop, the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton, far from being a married homeowner who removed the painting from his garage to please his wife, is single and has sold a number of paintings on eBay, where he also uses the Internet name ''advice.''</p>
        <p>''It's been a heck of a ride,'' he said. Since The New York Times reported the sale, he added, ''I've had people ringing my doorbell, calling me late at night and calling my family.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Walton said that he had not faked the painting or added the signature. He said he was only trying to raise cash to finance his new law practice by reselling works he bought cheaply at estate sales.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton and Mr. Keereweer spoke by phone yesterday and, after Mr. Walton acknowledged that he had ''made up a little story to go with the painting,'' the two decided to put off the transaction temporarily.</p>
        <p>''We will bring in an expert opinion from the outside before finalizing the deal,'' Mr. Keereweer said from his home in the Netherlands. ''Both he and I want to be sure. If it is authentic, then we will proceed -- that's a fair deal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton, using the name ''advice,'' is currently listing four other paintings in eBay auctions that close on Friday.</p>
        <p>He has run into trouble selling art over the Internet. Last summer, he offered an unattributed California impressionist work that bore a signature ''P. Gray,'' but again made no claims for its authorship. Thinking the artist was Henry Percy Gray, an early 20th-century painter known for his oak-laden landscapes, Michael Luther, a Nebraska businessman, agreed to pay $7,600 for it, sent a check and received the painting.</p>
        <p>''It was an amateur painting; it was garbage,'' Mr. Luther said yesterday. ''We put a black light on it, and the signature swam on the paint,'' using a term that indicates a signature was added long after the painting itself was completed.</p>
        <p>''I wrote a letter saying I'd sue,'' Mr. Luther added, ''and he e-mailed me back saying that he was an attorney and that he would fight back.'' Mr. Luther has not filed suit.</p>
        <p>Such tales -- especially those involving sums like $135,805 -- certainly illustrate the perils of buying art online, but some lawyers say Mr. Walton probably stands on solid ground if Mr. Luther sues. ''The definition of fraud on the Internet is no different than in the offline world,'' said Susan Crawford, an expert in e-commerce law at Wilmer, Cutler &amp; Pickering in Washington. A party who feels wronged in an auction on a site like eBay, which does not vouch for the authenticity of sellers' merchandise, can prevail legally only if the seller makes materially false statements in the item's description, several lawyers said.</p>
        <p>When he offered the painting signed ''P. Gray,'' Mr. Walton said he did not make up a story. He bought the work at an estate sale, he said, and made no changes to it.</p>
        <p>''I absolutely never added a signature to a painting,'' he said. ''That's totally untrue.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether, in the case of the $135,805 painting, the fact that Mr. Walton is not married and does not have a child who put a hole in the painting -- things he said in his offer -- is material information that affected the decisions of potential buyers.</p>
        <p>''It looks like he was intending to confuse people,'' Ms. Crawford said, ''but it would be up to a judge.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton, who is 32, insisted that he did, as he said online, buy the work at a garage sale in Berkeley, Calif. At the time, in the mid-1990's, he was a law student at the University of California Hastings School of Law in San Francisco. ''I can't remember what I paid,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton also said that he had  never sold anything as potentially valuable as the painting bid on by Mr. Keereweer, which ''golfpoorly'' had described as a ''great big wild abstract painting'' that he kept in his garage because his wife would not allow it in the house.</p>
        <p>The 33 paintings he has sold on eBay since March 30 as ''advice'' fetched a total of $5,766.62, with the biggest price being $697 for what he described as a ''FINE Impressionist Oil -- Nude Bathing Woman.''</p>
        <p>In the bidding on the four items currently on the site, a painting he described as an ''OUTSTANDING ESTATE OIL -- ARABS ON HORSEBACK,'' has gone highest, $1,100 yesterday evening.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton said he had made something of a hobby of going to estate and garage sales on weekends to search for paintings because he is trying to raise money to start a private law practice. Until about six months ago, he worked at Kronick, Moskovitz, Tiedemann &amp; Girard in Sacramento, but he said he left because he wanted to work in copyright, intellectual property and trademark law, an area related to his brothers' employment in the software industry.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to start a law practice,  and it's tough,'' he said. ''I don't come from a family with money, and I spend my time on weekends going around to estate sales and buying paintings. I can find these paintings for $20 to $30 a pop and put them up on eBay and get $300.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walton declined to say how much he had made this way. He has used the name ''advice'' on eBay since November 1998 and ''golfpoorly'' since last August. Because records for eBay sellers are accessible for only 30 days, it is impossible to determine a total for Mr. Walton during that entire period.</p>
        <p>''I made not that much last year, and this year it's more,'' Mr. Walton said. He said no one other than Mr. Luther had tried to return a painting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keereweer, a managing director of a software company who turns 43 next week, said that he had discovered eBay about seven weeks ago. Since he began collecting art about 15 years ago, he has focused on American and European art from 1900 to 1960 and owns works by Arshile Gorky and Franz Kline, among others. But since he and his wife had the first of their two sons four years ago, he said, ''it's hard to find the time to go to auctions and galleries.''</p>
        <p>A friend told him about eBay. ''I started to look for things,'' he said, ''and I have bought seven or eight things,'' including works by Leger and Mondrian.</p>
        <p>''I haven't received them all yet, but what I bought was O.K.,'' Mr. Keereweer said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
