<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plants That Redeem Water With Murky Pasts</title>
    <meta content="10SEWA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rickey, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3D91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plants That Redeem Water With Murky Pasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes tour of New York City's waste water treatment plant in Red Hook section of Brooklyn in honor of National Water Week, time designated by Congress for contemplation of water's vast and varied uses; tour director Robert Rickey comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe you missed the invitation to tour one of New York City's waste water treatment plants yesterday, in honor of National Water Week, a time designated by Congress for contemplation of water's vast and varied uses, from diluting single-malt Scotch to filling hot tubs and flushing toilets.</p>
        <p>Still, Robert Rickey, who has worked for 25 years for the city's water system, was standing by yesterday at the city's Red Hook plant on the East River in Brooklyn, ready for any and all comers seeking instruction on the waste water cycle. He was ready to describe how the plants, with their pumps, pools and pathways, turn raw sewage into the relatively clean water that is released each day into the East River, the Hudson and the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe you missed the invitation to tour one of New York City's waste water treatment plants yesterday, in honor of National Water Week, a time designated by Congress for contemplation of water's vast and varied uses, from diluting single-malt Scotch to filling hot tubs and flushing toilets.</p>
        <p>Still, Robert Rickey, who has worked for 25 years for the city's water system, was standing by yesterday at the city's Red Hook plant on the East River in Brooklyn, ready for any and all comers seeking instruction on the waste water cycle. He was ready to describe how the plants, with their pumps, pools and pathways, turn raw sewage into the relatively clean water that is released each day into the East River, the Hudson and the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>By the end of the day, he had had only two visitors. But Mr. Rickey did not seem downcast. He is often called on to give tours to engineers and municipal politicians from as far away as Thailand, Korea and Japan, as well as ''all the mayors of Israel,'' students from elementary schools to colleges, and Frank Perdue, the chicken man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rickey, a corpulent, ebullient engineer who resembles James Beard, the chef and cooking writer, said he always began his tours with the same question: ''What happens when you flush your toilet?'' Yesterday, as usual, he answered it himself: ''It's a very complex treatment. It's not just a matter of taking out the solids and dumping it into the ocean.''</p>
        <p>Well, it was about that simple once, and not so long ago. Until the Red Hook plant, one of the newest and smallest of New York's 14 water treatment plants, was completed in 1988 at the Brooklyn Navy Yard at a cost of $444 million, the nearby neighborhoods' 60 million gallons of waste water a day were merely filtered through a screen and discharged. (The city as a whole produces about 1.6 billion gallons of waste water a day.)</p>
        <p>Now, though, when a toilet nearby flushes, the sewage flows through pipes into a chamber at the plant 40 feet below the surface, where it is pumped through screens and then into a series of outdoor pools to be cleaned by oxygen and microorganisms. That process of aerating sewage water is one of the cheapest and most effective ways of cleaning it, Mr. Rickey said. The other main method used by the city to remove pollutants is the addition of pathogen-consuming bacteria. ''Good bacteria,'' he said, ''eat the bad bacteria. The good bacteria are the unsung heroes of the show.''</p>
        <p>Standing on a concrete walkway between eight open pools of turgid, odorous sewage water, he said: ''This is food. It needs to be eaten.'' Then he stood by another group of pools a few feet away, where several thin streams of bacteria-rich water were carrying in the bacteria that eat the bad microbes.</p>
        <p>''This is where the diners are,'' he said of the cloudy, medium-brown fluid with a topping of thick brown scum. ''Too white means too much oxygen,'' he said. ''Too black means too high a sludge density level.'' The brown is just right.</p>
        <p>Switching from culinary to medical metaphors, Mr. Rickey continued: ''We're like doctors. We ask ourselves: 'What is the state, the condition, of the bacteria? We watch the bacteria's ingestion, digestion, flow, respiration -- a lot of terms you think of as medical terms. Waste water treatment is a biological process, a living thing just like your body.''</p>
        <p>In the first pools, the heavier sludge settles to the bottom. In the secondary pools, the bacteria that are introduced latch onto the suspended sludge particles, pulling them down to the bottom like weights on a swimmer. The sludge is removed from the pool bottoms, dried for a month or longer in storage containers, and sent to farms in the Midwest for use as fertilizer. Last year, the city produced 1,200 tons of fertilizer sludge a day.</p>
        <p>The water in the final pools is noticeably paler and clearer. Green algae adhere to the pool's edges, a signal that higher organisms can also survive in the water. No algae can grow in the poisonous, oxygen-empty raw sewage that is piped into the plant. Before the water is released into the East River, chlorine is added to kill any disease-causing bacteria. The entire treatment process lasts 12 hours.</p>
        <p>The tour at its end, Mr. Rickey tosses out a few of the waste water trivia questions he has collected in more than two decades in the field.</p>
        <p>When did New York City stop using well water? In the late 1800's. Around 1890, the city provided its exploding population with a continuous supply of fresh rainwater when it bought watershed property upstate. Where was New York City's first waste water treatment plant? In Coney Island, in the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>And finally, a question from the audience: After 25 years, is Mr. Rickey still bothered by the smell from the open pools?</p>
        <p>''Smell?'' he said. ''What smell? It doesn't smell bad. It just smells different.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
