<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nelson Gains 6th Victory In Relief for the Yankees</title>
    <meta content="10YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1D91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nelson Gains 6th Victory In Relief for the Yankees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeff Nelson kept pace with James Baldwin and David Wells last night. Even more impressively, he moved ahead of Pedro Martinez. Let the Cy Young award voting begin.</p>
        <p>Nelson, the Yankees' ubiquitous relief pitcher, gained his sixth victory of the season as the Yankees scored a run in the 10th inning and edged the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 4-3, at Yankee Stadium. Not much earlier in the evening, Baldwin had gained his sixth victory for the Chicago White Sox and Wells his sixth for the Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeff Nelson kept pace with James Baldwin and David Wells last night. Even more impressively, he moved ahead of Pedro Martinez. Let the Cy Young award voting begin.</p>
        <p>Nelson, the Yankees' ubiquitous relief pitcher, gained his sixth victory of the season as the Yankees scored a run in the 10th inning and edged the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 4-3, at Yankee Stadium. Not much earlier in the evening, Baldwin had gained his sixth victory for the Chicago White Sox and Wells his sixth for the Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>Martinez can't secure his sixth victory until Friday because he is serving a five-game suspension. By then Nelson could have No. 7 because the Yankees play the Devil Rays again tonight.</p>
        <p>Actually Nelson could already have had seven victories. He was in line to be the winning pitcher last Sunday against the Baltimore Orioles after Scott Brosius hit a grand slam for a 6-4 lead. But in a rare breakdown, Mariano Rivera failed to hold the lead, and Nelson emerged from the game with no victory to show for his effort.</p>
        <p>The difference between Nelson and Martinez, Baldwin and Wells is that the others are starters. They are expected to pile up victories. Relievers are not expected to have a 6-0 record in the second week of May.</p>
        <p>''That's something that probably will never happen again,'' Nelson said after the game. ''I just try to shrug it off and enjoy the moment. People tell me you're going to win 20. I'll take 10, or 7.''</p>
        <p>In his previous eight seasons, seven was Nelson's personal high in victories. He attained that number with the Seattle Mariners in 1995, a few months before he was traded to the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Relieving last night for the 17th time in the team's 31 games, the 33-year-old right-hander pitched a perfect pair of innings, retiring all six batters he faced in the ninth and 10th. Four ground balls, one fly ball and one strikeout, and Nelson had done his job. All he needed was for the Yankees to score in their half of the 10th, and he would pick up yet another victory. His teammates cooperated.</p>
        <p>With one out in the Yankees' 10th, Rick White walked Brosius. Chuck Knoblauch, who had missed the previous six games because of a sprained right wrist, followed with a bloop that fell near the right-field line and bounced into the stands for a ground-rule double. The Devil Rays then walked Derek Jeter intentionally, loading the bases.</p>
        <p>Manager Larry Rothschild called for a new pitcher, Jim Morris, a 36-year-old rookie left-hander, to face the left-handed Paul O'Neill. Morris, who had walked six batters in 10 1/3 innings over 15 relief appearances, reached the mound, took his warmup tosses, then proceeded to throw four pitches to O'Neill, all balls. The walk forced home Brosius with the winning run and No. 6 for Nelson, against no defeats, of course.</p>
        <p>''He's on pace to win 30,'' a smiling David Cone said.</p>
        <p>Do the other pitchers needle Nelson about his record? ''Oh yeah,'' Cone said. ''He's officially the Vulture. No doubt about it.''</p>
        <p>The Vulture was Phil Regan, a relief pitcher for the Los Angeles Dodgers, who earned the name when he won 14 games in 1966, often giving up the tying run, then hanging around long enough for the Dodgers to score and make him the winning pitcher. Roy Face fit that role to an even greater degree with the Pittsburgh Pirates in 1959. He was the winning pitcher 18 times.</p>
        <p>''He earned that win tonight,'' Cone said of Nelson. ''He's been outstanding from Day 1. He takes a lot of pressure off the entire pitching staff. You don't have to worry about Mendoza being in the bullpen. Keep him as a starter. The bullpen is the reason we have the record we have right now.''</p>
        <p>Mike Stanton has relieved 19 times and has no victories to show for it. Is he envious of his bullpen mate?</p>
        <p>''No, not at all,'' the left-hander said. ''He's pitched great. But if you get wins out of the bullpen, it's basically you're just in the right place at the right time. I think it's a tribute to a lot of things. We're scoring some runs late in the game. Our starters are doing a great job keeping us close and giving us a chance to win in the late innings.''</p>
        <p>Cone performed that role last night. He gave up three runs early, two on Greg Vaughn's 10th home run in the third inning, but shut down the Devil Rays for his final four and two-thirds innings, leaving with two out in the eighth and a 3-3 tie.</p>
        <p>Just as they battered the Devil Rays with home runs in the first game of the series Monday night, the Yankees used home runs to get even last night. Shane Spencer drove the first pitch he saw from Esteban Yan into the Yankees' bullpen in left-center field in the fifth inning and Jorge Posada opened the seventh with a drive over the center field fence.</p>
        <p>Spencer's seventh home run of the season followed Ricky Ledee's leadoff single, ended a 0-for-12 stretch for Spencer and slashed the Yankees' deficit from 3-0 to 3-2. Posada's eighth home run tied the score and set the stage for No. 6 for Nelson.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
