<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Pollution Officer Fired After He Promotes an Aide</title>
    <meta content="10WATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gatto, Ronald A (Capt)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5D91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Pollution Officer Fired After He Promotes an Aide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Department of Environmental Protection dismisses Deputy Chief Lee Siegel, its second-highest-ranking police officer, after he promoted Captain Ronald A Gatto, who had accused city officials of impeding investigations of suspected polluters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Department of Environmental Protection has dismissed its second-highest-ranking police officer, after he promoted an officer who had accused city officials of impeding investigations of suspected polluters.</p>
        <p>The officer, Deputy Chief Lee Siegel, was fired Monday, a few days after he was ordered to revoke the promotion of Capt. Ronald A. Gatto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Department of Environmental Protection has dismissed its second-highest-ranking police officer, after he promoted an officer who had accused city officials of impeding investigations of suspected polluters.</p>
        <p>The officer, Deputy Chief Lee Siegel, was fired Monday, a few days after he was ordered to revoke the promotion of Capt. Ronald A. Gatto.</p>
        <p>Captain Gatto has long clashed with city officials, and he sued the city last year, saying that his superiors retaliated after he complained about inaction on investigations.</p>
        <p>But he has won praise from environmentalists for his aggressive pursuit of people and companies found polluting the 19 upstate reservoirs that supply drinking water to nine million people in New York City and its suburbs. Last month, a special Earth Day issue of Time magazine profiled Captain Gatto as one of nine ''Heroes for the Planet.''</p>
        <p>Chief Siegel oversaw a special unit of 12 officers, including Captain Gatto, who started the unit in 1992 when he was a lieutenant to investigate illegal dumping and other pollution in the department's 2,000-square-mile jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>Chief Siegel said a superior told him to revoke Captain Gatto's promotion to deputy inspector and to turn over the unit's investigations to local police departments, a move environmentalists say would jeopardize the water supply because local agencies lack the expertise to handle such cases.</p>
        <p>''I believe they just want to dismantle the unit and leave Captain Gatto hanging,'' Chief Siegel said.</p>
        <p>Chief Siegel said he demoted Captain Gatto under protest but refused to comply with the order regarding investigations until he received a written notice to make the change, which had not come by the time he was dismissed.</p>
        <p>But Charles G. Sturcken, the chief of staff of the Environmental Protection Department, said that there was no such directive on investigations and that the department's police force, which he said grew in the last year to 142 officers from 52, would continue to fight environmental crimes.</p>
        <p>He said he believed that Chief Siegel had misconstrued a message that the agency's commissioner, Joel A. Miele Sr., sent out to clarify the role of environmental police when an incident arises on department property -- like a recent suicide at a Westchester County reservoir -- requiring the involvement of local police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturcken said Chief Siegel's dismissal came after what he called the unauthorized promotion of Captain Gatto, but he would not elaborate, citing a policy against commenting on personnel matters.</p>
        <p>Captain Gatto filed a lawsuit in June in State Supreme Court in Manhattan under the state's whistle-blower law over what his lawyer, Jill Greenwald, called a pattern of retaliation and harassment by superiors that included providing him with shoddy equipment and repeatedly denying him raises and promotions.</p>
        <p>Ms. Greenwald said Captain Gatto fell out of favor after he testified at a City Council hearing in 1991 that superiors at the department had ordered him not to ticket a state prison and county hospital that he charged had dumped raw sewage into reservoirs. He has continued to run afoul of city officials, she said, in part because he cooperates with environmental groups critical of city policies regarding the watershed.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Kennedy Jr., a lawyer with the environmental group Hudson Riverkeeper and a frequent critic of the department, said the personnel moves were another example of  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's politically motivated interference with the department. He said Mr. Giuliani, as he contemplated a run for the United States Senate, had made it clear that the department should not aggressively pursue real estate developers and corporations, who are often the targets of pollution complaints but may also contribute to his campaign.</p>
        <p>''The message has gone out to lay off the big shots upstate,'' Mr. Kennedy said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Giuliani declined to comment.</p>
        <p>As Chief Siegel tells it, he decided in April to promote Captain Gatto, who has worked for the police force for nearly 18 years and whom he credited with more than 150 arrests and a conviction rate of 100 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
