<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Place Where Cuban Is a Cuisine, Not Just a Trend</title>
    <meta content="10UNDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Havana NY (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DF1138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Place Where Cuban Is a Cuisine, Not Just a Trend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov, in $25 and Under column, reviews Havana NY, Cuban restaurant on West 38th Street (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORKERS have developed quite the taste for tropical cocktails, as you can tell from the fashionable pan-Latin restaurants, where patrons down mojitos, pisco sours and caipirinhas as if it were perpetually Carnival. But you won't find a mojito -- sort of a mint julep made with rum -- at Havana NY, a bustling Cuban restaurant that is a lunchtime hot spot in its Midtown neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Nobody orders them, and the fresh mint just goes bad,'' a bartender growled after I tried. No mint, no trendy drinks or anything particularly stylish, but this largely commercial area will settle for tasty, inexpensive food in pleasant surroundings. And that is the specialty here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORKERS have developed quite the taste for tropical cocktails, as you can tell from the fashionable pan-Latin restaurants, where patrons down mojitos, pisco sours and caipirinhas as if it were perpetually Carnival. But you won't find a mojito -- sort of a mint julep made with rum -- at Havana NY, a bustling Cuban restaurant that is a lunchtime hot spot in its Midtown neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Nobody orders them, and the fresh mint just goes bad,'' a bartender growled after I tried. No mint, no trendy drinks or anything particularly stylish, but this largely commercial area will settle for tasty, inexpensive food in pleasant surroundings. And that is the specialty here.</p>
        <p>You can barely spot the entrance from the street, and peering through a window merely reveals a scattering of tables and a long bar in a narrow room. But if you walk past the bar, past the elderly cigar smokers eating their lunches and watching the television, you will see that Havana NY opens into a trim brick-walled dining room, attractive enough that a line of people waited 20 minutes on a recent Friday.</p>
        <p>The food is typically robust, flavored with lusty doses of garlic and lime, yet it can be delicate, too, as in an octopus salad ($9.95), which is marinated in citrus until tender like a ceviche and served with lettuce, rice, beans and plantains. Another dish, Chilean sea bass ($13.95), is moist and subtly flavored, not the sort of dish that would succeed in an assembly-line kitchen.</p>
        <p>These are a far cry from the restaurant's stock in trade, though, dishes like the excellent grilled skirt steak ($10.95), beefy and charred crisp around the edges, served with a pungent chimichurri sauce, essentially garlic and parsley, that is delicious spread over the steak. I loved the vaca frita ($8.95), thin strips of sauteed beef in a tangy sauce of lime and bitter orange juice, with plenty of onions cooked until soft, translucent and almost sweet.</p>
        <p>Pork dishes don't quite match the beef dishes, but roast pork ($8.95), falling-apart tender, is especially good when livened up with mojo, a garlic-and-citrus sauce. The same is true with masitas de cerdo ($8.95), chunks of pork that are marinated then fried: they are a little dry on their own but improve with mojo. Stewed chicken in creole sauce ($6.95) and shrimp in creole sauce ($10.95) are both too bland.</p>
        <p>All the main courses are enormous, served with rice, beans and sweet plantains -- so appetizers are usually unnecessary. Still, the beef empanadas ($3.75), tangy ground beef encased in thin half-moons of flaky dough, are very good, and the fried yuca fingers ($3.75) are like Latin French fries, but denser. They come with mojo, which I'll take over ketchup anytime. You may not manage dessert, either, which may not be a bad thing. I tried a bread pudding ($2.25) and a coconut flan ($2.50) and had trouble telling them apart.</p>
        <p>Service is swift and likable. In fact, there's little not to like about Havana NY, except that little mint problem.  But if it started serving mojitos, the next thing you know people would be buying lofts across the street and, all of a sudden, there goes the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Havana NY  27 West 38th Street, (212) 944-0990.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Octopus salad, Chilean sea bass, grilled skirt steak, vaca frita, roast pork, masitas de cerdo, beef empanadas, fried yuca fingers.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $2.50 to $6.95; main courses, $8.95 to $12.95.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Monday through Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 8:30 p.m. Closed Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Step at entrance; steps to dining room and restrooms.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
