<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Temple of Modern Art and Spectacle</title>
    <meta content="10TATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tate Modern (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herzog, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">de Meuron, Pierre</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DB1138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Temple of Modern Art and Spectacle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman appraises new Tate Modern in London, which occupies former Bankside power plant; architects are Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What are people going to say in 100 years about all these new museums for modern art that we're building, which seem to be getting almost as big as the Met?</p>
        <p>The latest behemoth is the new Tate Modern, across the Thames from St. Paul's Cathedral in the former Bankside power plant. The fashionable Swiss architects Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron have done the renovation -- lovingly preserving the brick exterior with the big chimney in the middle -- at a cost of $200 million, half in government grants, half private money. Queen Elizabeth II inaugurates the place on May 11. The next day the public arrives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What are people going to say in 100 years about all these new museums for modern art that we're building, which seem to be getting almost as big as the Met?</p>
        <p>The latest behemoth is the new Tate Modern, across the Thames from St. Paul's Cathedral in the former Bankside power plant. The fashionable Swiss architects Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron have done the renovation -- lovingly preserving the brick exterior with the big chimney in the middle -- at a cost of $200 million, half in government grants, half private money. Queen Elizabeth II inaugurates the place on May 11. The next day the public arrives.</p>
        <p>First things first: the museum is of course a contribution to contemporary art not just here but throughout Europe; a boon to Southwark, the run-down borough of London that it is in; and a major achievement by Sir Nicholas Serota, the quietly subversive Tate director who miraculously overcame decades of reluctance among stodgy British officials to finally establish a proper modern art museum.</p>
        <p>Proper but problematic. The Tate is in part a temple to vanity, the vanity of a culture that equates spectacle with substance, with half the building devoted to a vast entranceway, the museum's deeply gloomy signature space -- and with an installation that is occasionally eccentric to the point of distraction.</p>
        <p>To Britons who for decades got admirable but tepid Ben Nicholson and Barbara Hepworth when they went to the old Tate for modern art, the new Tate must seem like a revolution. Dozens of living artists of different generations and nationalities (Bruce Nauman, Matthew Barney, Juan Munoz, James Coleman, Ilya Kabakov, Tatsuo Miyajima, Rebecca Horn -- the list goes on) are mixed in among the British. No doubt the choices will cause grumbling because such choices do, but they seem fine.  All this comes when London is suddenly vying with New York as the mecca for contemporary art. British art's rising fortunes in the 1990's helped the Tate come about. Now the Tate will surely raise those fortunes more. Whether there will be enough money to run the museum is an open question, which is partly why the Tate has just begun a for-profit on line collaboration with the Museum of Modern Art in New York. But that is another matter.</p>
        <p>You may recall that the old Tate upriver mixed British and modern art. The arrangement made no sense. Renamed Tate Britain, the old building, a handsome gallery, has become a museum just for British art. Gainsborough has been liberated from Duchamp.</p>
        <p>This solves one problem, but museums of national art are suffering identity crises in the new global culture. Contemporary art, a global phenomenon, exists uneasily in a traditional nationalist context.</p>
        <p>So Tate officials, evidently trying not to prejudice the public against one museum or the other and wanting to make living artists and their audiences feel at home in both places, have settled on strategies to mix new art and old art. Mona Hatoum, a young British star, has enormous sculptures (a giant vegetable grater the size of a truck, among them) in the main hall at Tate Britain -- ridiculous work but new and conspicuous, which is the point.</p>
        <p>At the same time, both Tate Britain and Tate Modern are showing works not chronologically but according to themes, as the Museum of Modern Art in New York has been doing lately but with art from much more limited periods of time. Contemporary work is cheek by jowl with early 20th century art here.</p>
        <p>''Landscape, matter, environment'' is the title of one section at Tate Modern, ''nude, action, body'' another. The pretentiousness of the titles should tell you something. The museum says the goal is to avoid the old ''isms,'' but it's also, no doubt, to disguise gaps. At this, the strategy is a failure. Compared with the holdings of the Modern or Pompidou in Paris, the Tate collection is spotty before 1975, the legacy of previous British unease about modernism. Much of the best of what's on view comes from the last 25 years.</p>
        <p>There are some clever conjunctions that do result from the thematic installation: a room called ''Subversive Objects'' mixes Salvador Dali and Hans Bellmer, early Surrealists, with living artists like Sarah Lucas and Rosemarie Trockel; another room, ''Structures for Survival,'' puts together Andrea Zittel, Mario Merz and Franz West, unusually.</p>
        <p>But it's a parlor game trying to figure out why a Monet hangs next to a Richard Long, art being forced to play second fiddle to curatorial concept. A Cezanne is orphaned beside Minimalist sculptures. Kandinsky is demeaned in a room titled ''Manifestoes.''</p>
        <p>And a room of nudes by Picasso, Lucian Freud, Bonnard and others is upstaged by Sam Taylor-Wood's video of a naked man dancing to Samuel Barber's Adagio for Strings in the next gallery, the collision of media inevitably skewing the relative impact of the works.</p>
        <p>Suffice it to say that the collisions are even more startling at Tate Britain, where the 16th century and the 20th century meet. Museums should make it easier for people to stand in front of a work of art unencumbered. The Tate's installation makes a case for a return to the old chronological approach, or for a blend of old approach and new, time being a cruel master but at least a reliable way to get a handle on the past.</p>
        <p>And the building itself? A London journalist joked that the new Tate is the Millennium Dome for the educated class -- a nasty remark considering that the dome has become a $1.3 billion joke, but looked at a certain way, not wrong. Both are celebrations of national pride, colossal and populist, the Tate being more upscale but still based on the economy of tourism and on a cocktail of boosterism, urban renewal, youth culture and unexceptionable programs of cultural uplift. Art is part but only part of what the new Tate is about.</p>
        <p>There is sheer theatricality, for example. Modern art museums serving among other things as highbrow amusement parks these days, Tate officials working with Mr. Herzog and Mr. de Meuron have made sure to provide the expected thrill. The lobby, the former plant's turbine hall, entered from the west down a 75-foot-wide ramp, is nearly two football fields long and 12 stories high, an industrial St. Peter's with the original cherry-picker cranes left overhead.</p>
        <p>Awesome. Memorable.</p>
        <p>And dour. The natural point of comparison, the Orsay in Paris, also an industrial conversion and a museum with its own problems, is airy, not austere. But this is England and that is France. No frills here.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the impression that the place is grim is exaggerated by the presence of several giant new sculptures by Louise Bourgeois: a spider and three 30-foot steel spiral staircases, like prison guard towers with enormous mirrors on top, plunked at the east end of the hall. The sculptures are awful. Previously a neglected artist, Ms. Bourgeois is now vastly overrated.</p>
        <p>The quality of art improves episodically in the galleries. Tate officials (who can blame them?) have generally avoided art that would be too controversial. No decapitated cows. Nothing really risque. Nothing that might overshadow the experience of wandering fresh galleries for the first time.</p>
        <p>Occupying three floors on one side of the building, these galleries wrap halfway around escalator landings, a layout akin to the Modern in New York. Wending from one end of a floor to the other can feel like going through a rat's maze. Time will tell whether the choice of unfinished wood floors (they will become increasingly marked up by footprints) will seem smart or lunatic.</p>
        <p>The rooms otherwise are minimal boxes, varied in size. Plain, clean and useful, they won't please acolytes of Frank Gehry, but artists should like them. They are not temporary and partitioned, as at the Pompidou, or precious, as at the Getty.</p>
        <p>It's only too bad more of them don't have natural light, although a few have great views of St. Paul's and the river, the views breaking up the monotony of consecutive white spaces. Towering galleries suit enormous sculptures. Others do for drawings, photographs and documentary material. (There's an excellent Fluxus room, for example.) Much of the inaugural display consists of recent installations and videos, big works that had been difficult to show off in the old building.</p>
        <p>Two of the three floors of galleries will be for the permanent collection, sandwiching a floor for temporary exhibitions; this is less space for temporary shows than at the old Tate, apparently, gallery space having been sacrificed to the lobby. The exhibition rooms are nonetheless much better. At the moment they have sculptures and videos from the permanent collection: works by two dozen artists getting a room apiece, more or less. A few rooms on the permanent collection floors, interludes in the thematic display, are monographic, too.</p>
        <p>This is where the value of the new Tate becomes clearest. British artists, including Bridget Riley, Anthony Caro and Anish Kapoor, are stressed, but there's plenty of room for foreign artists like Mr. Nauman, Mr. Kabakov and Mr. Coleman to be prominent. Mr. Kabakov's Soviet hallway is a miracle of nostalgic re-creation, deeply ironic, and Mr. Coleman's video about a photographer is alarming, vivid and very funny. They stay in the mind.</p>
        <p>The new Tate's capacity to accommodate different art flexibly is its asset at a time when contemporary art seems to be moving in divergent, unpredictable directions.</p>
        <p>But the question lingers: Must a museum of modern art be quite this gigantic? Is the tradition that begins with Cezanne so important historically that it demands a building as big as the National Gallery?</p>
        <p>Maybe this seems odd to ask. The more room the better, especially for previously underprivileged new art. But the question might be asked differently: Will the tradition of art post-Cezanne still seem coherent in a century? The kind of person who became an artist 100 years ago is not the same person who becomes an artist today. What is defined as art and the people who make it are changing all the time.</p>
        <p>Maybe video and installation will come to belong to different stories, disconnected from Cezanne. Maybe Cezanne will no longer seem like a beginning of anything but a middle, or an end. Maybe, God forbid, no one will want to show Richard Long or Louise Bourgeois in 100 years.</p>
        <p>One thing is certain. This moment, the turn of the 21st century, will be remembered as a time when a rich and egocentric culture saw fit to memorialize itself on an incredible scale.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
