<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Louisiana Governor Guilty of Extortion on Casinos</title>
    <meta content="10EDWA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conspiracy, Criminal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Edwin W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1DC1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Louisiana Governor Guilty of Extortion on Casinos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal court jury convicts former Louisiana Gov Edwin W Edwards of racketeering, conspiracy and extortion charges related to awarding of state riverboat casino licenses; convicts his son, Stephen, and three other co-conspirators charged with being middlemen between Edwardses and several businessmen seeking casino license; acquits two others of relatively minor charges; Edwards vows appeal; chronology of events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a picaresque career lived at the edge of the law, the hayride ended for Edwin W. Edwards today as a federal court jury in Baton Rouge, La., convicted the former Louisiana governor of racketeering, conspiracy and extortion charges related to the awarding of state riverboat casino licenses.</p>
        <p>The 72-year-old Mr. Edwards, who served four terms in office and survived two previous criminal trials without being convicted, was found guilty today on 17 of the 26 counts against him, including the most serious racketeering and conspiracy charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a picaresque career lived at the edge of the law, the hayride ended for Edwin W. Edwards today as a federal court jury in Baton Rouge, La., convicted the former Louisiana governor of racketeering, conspiracy and extortion charges related to the awarding of state riverboat casino licenses.</p>
        <p>The 72-year-old Mr. Edwards, who served four terms in office and survived two previous criminal trials without being convicted, was found guilty today on 17 of the 26 counts against him, including the most serious racketeering and conspiracy charges.</p>
        <p>His son Stephen was also convicted of multiple counts, as were three other co-conspirators who were charged with being middlemen between the Edwardses and several businessmen seeking casino licenses. Two defendants, a prominent state senator and a member of the state's gaming board, were acquitted of the relatively minor charges against them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, who is rarely at a loss for words, was prohibited by a judge's silencing rule from discussing the verdicts in detail today. But in brief comments to reporters outside the federal courthouse in Baton Rouge, he thanked family members who supported him during the more than four-month trial, and he vowed to appeal. A high-stakes gambler known for being host to $10,000-ante poker games in the governor's mansion, Mr. Edwards then acknowledged that his luck might finally have run dry.</p>
        <p>''The Chinese have a saying that if you sit by the river long enough, the dead body of your enemy will come floating down the river,'' he said, his voice calm and measured. ''I suppose the feds sat by the river long enough, and here comes my body.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, who will remain out of jail pending a bond hearing, could receive sentences totaling more than 200 years in prison and be fined millions of dollars. A forfeiture hearing to be held on Wednesday could cost Mr. Edwards, a Democrat, a substantial amount of cash and property as well.</p>
        <p>After being indicted in November 1998, Mr. Edwards joked that if he was sentenced to the maximum possible term, he did not expect to serve it all. Today, he was less cavalier as he faced the prospect of what he called ''a very large, long prison term.''</p>
        <p>''I regret that it has ended this way,'' Mr. Edwards said, shaded by a canopy of oaks, ''but there is the system. I've lived 72 years of my life within the system. I will spend the rest of my life within the system. Whatever consequences flow from this I'm prepared to face.'' He added: ''I will try to maintain the same demeanor of confidence and support that I've had in the past three years as all of this began to unfold. And in due course, whatever comes, comes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, who was the only defendant to testify during the trial, showed little emotion as he listened to the verdicts. His 35-year-old wife, Candy, who kept a front-row seat throughout the trial, broke down in tears as the first guilty verdict was read.</p>
        <p>The team of federal prosecutors, who succeeded where their predecessors had not, suppressed their glee in public today. Most walked sternly from the courthouse without speaking to reporters. But some allowed themselves a wee smile. ''Look at my face,'' said Eddie J. Jordan Jr., the United States attorney in New Orleans, who oversaw the prosecution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards still faces a June trial on federal fraud charges that he had helped a failed insurance company evade millions of dollars in state payments.</p>
        <p>The jury received the casino case on April 24 after a long and captivating trial highlighted by the playing of wiretap-generated audiotapes and the testimony of former friends of Mr. Edwards who turned state's evidence against him.</p>
        <p>Among the star witnesses was Edward J. DeBartolo Jr., the former owner of the San Francisco 49ers, who secured a reduced sentence by agreeing to testify that he had paid Mr. Edwards $400,000 in exchange for his help in winning a casino license for a DeBartolo partnership. Under pressure from the National Football League, Mr. DeBartolo turned over control of the football team to his sister because of the scandal.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors outlined a series of five distinct schemes in which Mr. Edwards and his son demanded substantial payments -- nearly $3 million in all -- in exchange for his assistance in procuring the coveted casino licenses. Some of the extortion schemes took place during Mr. Edwards's final term in office, which ended in 1996, while others occurred after he stepped down but still held influence over legislators and gaming regulators.</p>
        <p>He was found guilty of the broadest racketeering and conspiracy charges, and of involvement in four of the five schemes. Stephen Edwards was convicted on 18 of 23 counts. Andrew Martin, a former top aide to Edwin Edwards, was convicted of all six counts against him; Cecil Brown, a longtime Edwards friend and business partner, of four counts; and Bobby Johnson, another Edwards friend, of nine counts. State Senator Greg Tarver and Ecotry Fuller, the gaming board member, were acquitted of charges that they had helped Mr. Edwards illegally obtain a confidential report for Mr. DeBartolo.</p>
        <p>The case against Mr. Edwards was circumstantial, because even the hundreds of hours of audiotape never captured him making an explicit demand. But the testimony of his former friends and several suggestive conversations caught on the tapes were apparently enough to convince the jury. The tapes revealed him talking about splitting up proceeds that he maintained he had never received and brainstorming schemes to launder money.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people were surprised that Edwin, who has always been so smart, let them get so much information on him,'' said Bernie R. Pinsonat, a Baton Rouge pollster. ''They had tapes in his office, tapes in his house, and they obviously nailed him. Regardless of what happens from here on out, it is the end of an era.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, who by his own count has been investigated by 22 grand juries, first escaped conviction in 1985 when a federal jury in New Orleans deadlocked while considering charges that he had taken payoffs to help his patrons win state hospital licenses. He was retried and acquitted the next year.</p>
        <p>The prosecution clearly had stronger evidence in this year's case, including the tapes and the witness testimony. It also benefited by trying the case in Baton Rouge, where jurors are considered more conservative than in New Orleans. All but one of the jurors were white; Mr. Edwards's strongest support always came from black Louisianians.</p>
        <p>Even before today's verdicts were rendered, the defense team had been handed at least one significant cause for appeal. Last Thursday, after two days of investigation and legal hand-wringing, Judge Frank Polozola of United States District Court dismissed one of the 12 jurors, a white man known only as Juror 68. The verdicts, thus, were returned by a jury of 11, and defense lawyers have assumed that the dismissed juror was resisting the majority's arguments for conviction.</p>
        <p>The judge did not explain the dismissal, but Louisiana newspapers have reported that the juror asked to be dismissed. The newspapers, including The Advocate in Baton Rouge and The Times-Picayune in New Orleans, reported that the juror had sent Judge Polozola a note saying: ''I am being very intimidated because of how I may feel. There is such an awesome responsibility with the lives of people in our and my hands that I am trying to erase some doubts but can't seem to forget them in my mind.''</p>
        <p>After the juror was dismissed, defense lawyers asked for a mistrial and were rebuffed by the judge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
