<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From News Conference With Bush and McCain</title>
    <meta content="Y10BTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5D61138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From News Conference With Bush and McCain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from news conference by Gov George W Bush and Sen John McCain announcing McCain's endorsement of Bush for president</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference yesterday by Gov. George W. Bush and Senator John McCain, announcing Mr. McCain's endorsement of Mr. Bush for president, as recorded by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Q. -- Senator, why do you have difficulty using the word ''endorsement'' in your support for Governor Bush?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference yesterday by Gov. George W. Bush and Senator John McCain, announcing Mr. McCain's endorsement of Mr. Bush for president, as recorded by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Q. -- Senator, why do you have difficulty using the word ''endorsement'' in your support for Governor Bush?</p>
        <p>MR. McCAIN. -- I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse -- I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse Governor Bush. I endorse Governor ----</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH. -- By the way, I enthusiastically accept.</p>
        <p>Q. -- Does that have to do with the feelings you still have about the primary that you ran and the bitterness you had at the time about some of the tactics that Governor Bush used?</p>
        <p>MR. McCAIN. -- Look, the only way you can approach American politics and seeking elective office is to move forward. For me to look back in anger or with any rancor would be a mistake. It would harm me; it would harm Governor Bush, and it would harm those who supported me in this campaign. I look forward and not back. I hold no rancor. Others will be the judge of this campaign, not me.</p>
        <p>And my job is to further our efforts to bring about institutions -- reforming the institutions of government. I can't do that effectively if I look back rather than forward. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. -- How important is that endorsement to you, A? And B, what do you say to that block out there, 23 percent, according to a recent poll, on this day that he's endorsing you?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH. -- Well, I think this endorsement's important because of that reason.</p>
        <p>There's a lot of people who think John is not only a great American, but a person who's got a good solid agenda for the future. And as we just said, there's a lot of areas where we agree. And I intend to continue talking about reform and I'm -- and it's very helpful to have John embrace reform.</p>
        <p>Now, I'll tell you a good area where we both agree and there was going to be a stark difference of opinion, and that's on Social Security.</p>
        <p>There's a lot of Americans who understand it's time to have a different attitude when it comes to making sure there's pension plans available for younger workers. John and I both agree we must trust younger workers with some of their money in the private sector. We both agree. . . .</p>
        <p>And it's going to be a big difference of opinion between what he and I believe and what Vice President Gore believes. Vice President Gore's willing to accept the status quo. He's willing to think the current system is going to work. And we don't. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. -- Senator, can you tell us what, in your view, is the single most important reason why Al Gore should not be president?</p>
        <p>MR. McCAIN. -- I think the single most important reason is that Governor Bush is the most qualified person to be president of the United States. He has the vision; he has the knowledge and the expertise to carry out the mission of maintaining United States supremacy, both militarily and economically in the world.</p>
        <p>I think that it's clear that Governor Bush's philosophy, his ideals and his ability to articulate a vision for the future is the major reason why he should be president of the United States and not Al Gore.</p>
        <p>And I want to emphasize one more time, and I made it very clear to Governor Bush, I will continue to pursue the issues of reform. That is the agenda that drove me in my campaign and will drive me as long as I am in public service. I believe we will have disagreements, but I also believe we will have a lot more agreements than disagreements. And I think our discussions and our debate will be healthy, and in the long run helpful to the party and the country.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
