<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Play the Vengeance Game</title>
    <meta content="10BEGA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Begala, Paul E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delay, Tom (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD71138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Play the Vengeance Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul E. Begala</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Begala, Paul E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul E Begala Op-Ed article scores Democrats' suit charging Rep Tom DeLay with extortion, racketeering and money laundering in his aggressive fund-raising for Republicans; Begala, former counsel to Pres Clinton, holds those who decried abuse of legal system for partisan ends against Clinton must now condemn legal pursuit of DeLay; holds DeLay's conduct raises serious ethical questions, but is not criminal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Congressional Democrats' racketeering lawsuit against Tom DeLay, the House majority whip, is wrong, ethically, legally and politically.</p>
        <p>The suit, which charges Mr. DeLay with extortion, racketeering and money laundering in his aggressive fund-raising for Republicans, represents everything I hated about the politics of personal destruction as it was waged against President Clinton. Those of us who decried the abuse of the legal system for partisan ends now have a moral obligation to condemn the legal pursuit of Mr. DeLay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Congressional Democrats' racketeering lawsuit against Tom DeLay, the House majority whip, is wrong, ethically, legally and politically.</p>
        <p>The suit, which charges Mr. DeLay with extortion, racketeering and money laundering in his aggressive fund-raising for Republicans, represents everything I hated about the politics of personal destruction as it was waged against President Clinton. Those of us who decried the abuse of the legal system for partisan ends now have a moral obligation to condemn the legal pursuit of Mr. DeLay.</p>
        <p>It is wrong to treat the legal system as nothing more than politics by other means. In a free society, political differences are most legitimately resolved by voters, not courts.</p>
        <p>By going after Mr. DeLay using the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act, the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee is doing Republicans an enormous favor: shifting attention from the G.O.P.'s pathetic record on gun control, Social Security, the patients' bill of rights and other issues that matter.</p>
        <p>Outrageously, Mr. DeLay has reportedly allowed lobbyists who contribute to write their own special interest legislation (''because,'' he said, ''they have the expertise''). He is proud of his nickname, ''the Hammer,'' for his strong-arm tactics.</p>
        <p>His conduct raises serious ethical questions, but it isn't criminal. Maybe it should be, but until Congress toughens campaign finance laws, politicians will seize every advantage they can. And if there is a question about criminal conduct we have a perfectly competent Justice Department to decide if there's a case to be made.</p>
        <p>If I were still running Democratic campaigns, I would undoubtedly be troubled by news reports that Mr. DeLay has a scheme to swamp my candidates with unlimited, undisclosed money. But the answer is: Run to the press and call on reporters to investigate. Run to the voters and tell them about any secret schemes. But don't run to the courthouse to file a suit that equates Tom (the Hammer) DeLay with Sammy (the Bull) Gravano.</p>
        <p>At about the same time the Congressional Democrats were pursuing their nasty business against Mr. DeLay, House Republicans were busy using hearings to torment current and former White House aides. The former deputy White House counsel Cheryl Mills, now a private citizen, spoke for many of us when she addressed the G.O.P. members harassing her. ''You could spend your time making the lives of the individuals you serve better,'' she said, ''as opposed to tearing down the staff of a president with whose vision and policies you disagree.''</p>
        <p>Democrats sue Republicans. Republicans investigate Democrats. As I watched the president, the first lady, innumerable staffers and too many honest cabinet officers drained by right-wing attempts to carry their partisan warfare into the courtroom and the committee room, I wondered how the cycle would ever be broken. Payback is a natural human emotion.</p>
        <p>Well, here is how it ends: I'm going to say what too few Republicans of conscience were willing to say. The G.O.P. wrongfully harassed the president and those around him. My party should drop the suit against Tom DeLay and return to talking about issues. If we do that, we're more likely to win. And I know we'll be more deserving of victory.</p>
        <p>Paul E. Begala, who served as counselor to President Clinton from 1997 to 1999, teaches government at Georgetown and is co-host of ''Equal Time'' on MSNBC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul E. Begala, who served as counselor to President Clinton from 1997 to 1999, teaches government at Georgetown and is co-host of ''Equal Time'' on MSNBC.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
