<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Backs Former Rival, Uniting G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="10BUSH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDA1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Backs Former Rival, Uniting G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain, citing common goals and shared values that transcend any bitterness between them, endorses Gov George W Bush for president and pledges to campaign for him, news conference with Bush, Pittsburgh; it remains unclear how much McCain will do for Bush; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citing common goals and shared values that transcended any of the bitterness between them, Senator John McCain at last endorsed Gov. George W. Bush today and pledged to help him achieve what Mr. McCain had wanted so badly for himself: a seat behind the desk in the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to enthusiastically campaigning for Governor Bush for the next six months,'' Mr. McCain said at a news conference here that was attended by more than 100 members of the news media, a reflection of just how unpredictable and closely watched the interactions between the Arizona senator and the Texas governor had become.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citing common goals and shared values that transcended any of the bitterness between them, Senator John McCain at last endorsed Gov. George W. Bush today and pledged to help him achieve what Mr. McCain had wanted so badly for himself: a seat behind the desk in the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to enthusiastically campaigning for Governor Bush for the next six months,'' Mr. McCain said at a news conference here that was attended by more than 100 members of the news media, a reflection of just how unpredictable and closely watched the interactions between the Arizona senator and the Texas governor had become.</p>
        <p>''I believe that it's very important that we restore integrity and honor to the White House,'' Mr. McCain said. ''I'm convinced that Governor Bush can do that more than adequately.'' [Excerpts, Page A28.]</p>
        <p>The announcement by Mr. McCain, which followed his private 90-minute meeting with Mr. Bush, heralded a new phase in a rocky political relationship that went from remarkable amity in December to extraordinary animosity in March and a tense, delicate dance of reconciliation over the last two months.</p>
        <p>Even more important, Mr. McCain's formal endorsement allowed Mr. Bush to lay claim to a unified party, to put an important piece of unfinished business behind him and to reach out to independent and swing voters with the blessing of Mr. McCain, who had proved to be alluring to that group in the primaries.</p>
        <p>But aides to Mr. Bush and Mr. McCain and political analysts said it remained unclear just how much work Mr. McCain would do on Mr. Bush's behalf -- and just how thoroughly the wounds of a lacerating primary season had healed. Mr. McCain's often tepid demeanor and restrained language today only heightened those questions.</p>
        <p>He repeated several times that his support for Governor Bush did not alter or diminish his commitment to an overhaul of campaign funding laws that was more sweeping than the plan favored by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>He did not actually use the words ''endorse'' or ''endorsement'' until reporters pressed him to make sure they understood correctly what was going on. At that point, Mr. McCain made something of a comedy routine, saying, ''I endorse Governor Bush,'' six times in a row. And when one journalist asked Mr. McCain if his actions today -- an almost inevitable obligation for any politician wishing to remain loyal to his party -- were like swallowing a dose of necessary medicine sooner rather than later, Mr. McCain answered, ''I think 'take the medicine now' probably is a good description.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides chose to interpret the ambiguous remark as an example of the senator's sometimes deadpan humor, and it did not diminish their conviction, shared by many Republican operatives, that the Texas governor had accomplished something important today.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain also made clear today that he had told Mr. Bush what he had been saying publicly for some time: that he had no interest in the vice presidency. He and Mr. Bush said they had discussed other strong candidates, including Governors Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania, Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin and John Engler of Michigan.</p>
        <p>In accepting Mr. McCain's endorsement, Mr. Bush heaped praise on him, providing a stark contrast to some of the dismissive remarks that he and his aides had made about Mr. McCain after Mr. Bush effectively secured the Republican presidential nomination in mid-March.</p>
        <p>And he cast their acrimonious exchanges during the primaries as a beneficial experience that prepared him for the general election.</p>
        <p>''I told him point blank he made me a better candidate,'' Mr. Bush said, referring to their meeting in a room of the Westin William Penn hotel here. ''He waged a really good campaign and put me through my paces. And as a result of the campaign, I stand better prepared to become the president, which is exactly what I intend to do.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. McCain said it made no sense to revisit the past.</p>
        <p>''For me to look back in anger or with any rancor would be a mistake,'' he said. ''It would harm me. It would harm Governor Bush. And it would harm those who supported me in this campaign.''</p>
        <p>But the tone of his remarks suggested that his ire and that of his aides over the negative tactics used by Mr. Bush and his supporters in the primaries had not dissipated.</p>
        <p>That anger was rekindled today when Mr. Bush dodged a question about whether he would repudiate a  statement by the evangelist Pat Robertson two days ago that choosing Mr. McCain as a vice president would be dangerous.</p>
        <p>Rick Davis, who had managed Mr. McCain's campaign, said of the Bush response: ''I'm very disappointed. I don't think there's a Republican around who doesn't think Pat Robertson's comments Sunday were outside the mainstream of our party. What's the harm of saying that?''</p>
        <p>Political analysts said Mr. McCain's eventual endorsement of Mr. Bush was never really in much doubt, in part because the senator, seen as something of a maverick in his own party, needed to show his  peers that he could follow the loyal, polite course. That would be critical if Mr. Bush loses and Mr. McCain seeks to become the party's nominee four years from now.</p>
        <p>But the road leading to this point was bumpy, and it was not clear until Monday that this morning's meeting, scheduled a month ago, would bring the waiting to an end. Mr. McCain's previous statements that he would support the party's nominee fell short of a formal seal of approval and fueled speculation, which Mr. Bush's aides were eager to quell, about what was taking so long.</p>
        <p>The two men's aides said Mr. Bush did not offer Mr. McCain anything concrete in exchange for his support. And one McCain supporter said efforts by the aides to hammer out a document detailing joint policy goals had failed.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McCain's aides have let Bush campaign officials know that the Arizona senator would like a prominent speaking role at the Republican National Convention, and the Bush campaign has indicated interest in making that happen.</p>
        <p>Coming out of the meeting, both Mr. McCain and Mr. Bush acknowledged that they still had policy disagreements, although they declined to linger on them. During the primaries, for example, Mr. McCain repeatedly asserted that the size of Mr. Bush's proposed tax cut might jeopardize the health of Social Security.</p>
        <p>And Mr. McCain's vision of campaign finance reform, for example, includes bans on unlimited donations to political parties from both corporations and individuals; Mr. Bush does not think individual contributions should be limited.</p>
        <p>Aides to both politicians said there had not yet been any discussion about specific ways in which Mr. McCain could or would bolster Mr. Bush's campaign.</p>
        <p>But several Republican strategists in Washington said that Mr. McCain would probably wind up doing a great deal and that his tone today simply reflected the difficulty of accepting that it was finally time to cede the stage to someone else.</p>
        <p>''He went from huge media star and man-of-the-moment to having to fall back in line,'' said William Dal Col, who managed Steve Forbes's campaign for the Republican nomination. ''But it'll get better and better as time goes by, and if he wants to run in 2004, the smart thing for him to do is be as energetic and pro-Bush as possible.''</p>
        <p>Nelson Warfield, who was the press secretary for the 1996 presidential campaign of Bob Dole, acknowledged that Mr. McCain was ''flippant and unconventional'' in delivering his endorsement but that his manner did not change ''how important it really is.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, in the immediate aftermath of McCain's defeat, there was furious speculation that he might run as a third-party candidate,'' Mr. Warfield said. ''As recently as last week, there was a poll that showed McCain, in a hypothetical three-way race, with more than 20 percent. Any time you get endorsed by someone with that kind of star quality is a very good day.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
