<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="10PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baldoria (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beard, James, Foundation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chase Wildlife Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jagger, Mick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morad, Luciana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Rosie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED91138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Glenn Collins</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James; Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; status of child custody trial between Mick Jagger and Luciana Morad noted; scene at new Baldoria restaurant in midtown Manhattan following James Beard Foundation awards described; scene at Chase Wildlife Foundation's dinner dance described; Rosie O'Donnell discusses her 20th reunion at Commack High School on Long Island (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Money Talks, Jagger Balks</p>
        <p>Once again in the MICK JAGGER child support case, the subject is money -- how little he wants to pay, and how much LUCIANA MORAD, the 29-year-old lingerie model who gave birth to LUCAS MAURICE MORAD JAGGER a year ago next week, is demanding. Her number: $35,000 a month. His number: $5,600 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Money Talks, Jagger Balks</p>
        <p>Once again in the MICK JAGGER child support case, the subject is money -- how little he wants to pay, and how much LUCIANA MORAD, the 29-year-old lingerie model who gave birth to LUCAS MAURICE MORAD JAGGER a year ago next week, is demanding. Her number: $35,000 a month. His number: $5,600 a month.</p>
        <p>Through his lawyer, JOHN VASSALLO, Mr. Jagger also asked that his financial records remain secret and that he not have to testify about how much he is worth.</p>
        <p>''Obviously he's trying to avoid show-and-tell,'' Ms. Morad's lawyer, RAOUL FELDER, said outside Family Court in Manhattan, ''but he's going to have to.''</p>
        <p>DAVID KIRSHBLUM, a Family Court hearing examiner, scheduled another session for June 19.</p>
        <p>Just There to Eat, Not to Cook</p>
        <p>With a little help from friends: How else to introduce Baldoria, the Midtown offspring of the famously exclusive Rao's restaurant in East Harlem? How else to explain the throng that headed to Baldoria, at 249 West 49th Street, after the James Beard Foundation's awards on Monday night at the Mariott Marquis Hotel?</p>
        <p>But it was hard to find anyone who would go near the kitchen. ''Look,'' said BOBBY FLAY, an owner of Mesa Grill. ''These people own the hardest-to-get-into restaurant in America. They don't need any help from me.''</p>
        <p>Culinary assistance ''isn't my job tonight,'' said DREW NIEPORENT, the Beard House Humanitarian Award medal that he had just won dangling from his neck.</p>
        <p>''I'm a happy partygoer tonight, and that's it,'' RITA JAMMET, an owner of La Caravelle, said as she chatted with ALEX VON BIDDER, an owner of the Four Seasons.</p>
        <p>Even MARTHA STEWART said that she had ''no helpful hints tonight.'' Instead, she had a kissy fit with FRANK PELLEGRINO SR., the patriarch of Rao's, and FRANK PELLEGRINO JR., the patriarch of Baldoria.</p>
        <p>Like Elmer Fudd At a Bunny Hop</p>
        <p>The Chase Wildlife Foundation's dinner dance (the Chase is LYNN CHASE, an artist, not the Rockefellers' Chase Bank) turned out to be one of the more unintentionally funny evenings of the season. The crowd was the big-game-world equivalent of former addicts: most of the men and many of the women admitted to having hunted. Some said they still do.</p>
        <p>''That's all right,'' Ms. Chase said. ''Hunters have done more for wildlife than anyone.''</p>
        <p>The black-tie dress code was loosely interpreted. One man's tie matched his wife's dress. Another man wore red sailor pants with his dinner jacket. MICHAEL WINSTON, a documentary filmmaker, ripped his pants and went looking for duct tape after murmuring something about ''pricey cheap material.''</p>
        <p>The singer PEGGY CONE, who announced the door-prize winners, had pronunciation problems. ''The next prize is for a cachet pot,'' she said at one point. Somehow, two men thought she had called their names and stood up to claim the cachepot: PAUL CABOT and CARL LANDEGGER. The people at Mr. Cabot's table cheered, but he returned empty-handed. The prize went to the man whose name she had called in the first place, Mr. Landegger.</p>
        <p>The Best Moment Went Unrecorded</p>
        <p>ROSIE O'DONNELL'S advice to people who go to high school reunions: Don't do what she did. Don't take along a camera crew.</p>
        <p>''It was distracting, truthfully,'' she said after her 20th at Commack High School on Long Island over the weekend. ''I didn't know how people would react to my being on TV. I just assume if you grew up with me, it's no big whoop. But celebrity is a strange animal. You never know how people are going to react to it. So I think it throws a wrench. My really good friends weren't coming over to me. My best friend was a woman named Mary Rose. I saw her when I was going to the bathroom. She said, 'Everybody's around you; I didn't want to stand in line.' I had security open a special room so we could talk. That was the best part for me.''</p>
        <p>Don't expect to see the encounter on Ms. O'Donnell's talk show this morning. When she was editing the videotape, ''I was like, find the thing of Mary Rose, and they went, 'We don't have anything of her.' ''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Glenn Collins</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
