<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One More Africa Mediating Effort for U.N. Traveling Mission</title>
    <meta content="Y10ETH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Famine</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Eritrea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Congo (Formerly Zaire)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Security Council (Un)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Organization of American States</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zenawi, Meles (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Afwerki, Isaias (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holbrooke, Richard C (Amb)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Eritrea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Eritrea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Famine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One More Africa Mediating Effort for U.N. Traveling Mission</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>ASMARA, Eritrea, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations Security Council delegation visiting Africa has abruptly shifted its attention from Congo crisis to Ethiopian-Eritrean border, where hundreds of thousands of troops on both sides reportedly prepare for war; council members, shuttling back and forth between two capitals, are urging Ethiopian Prime Min Meles Zenawi and Eritrean Pres Isaias Afwerki to avoid renewed fighting; Amb Richard C Holbrooke says they seek to restart Organization of African Unity peace talks; scores threat of war over disputed border territory in midst of famine; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A United Nations Security Council delegation visiting Africa has abruptly shifted its attention from the crisis in Congo to the Ethiopian-Eritrean border, where, Western intelligence reports say, hundreds of thousands of troops on each side are preparing for imminent war.</p>
        <p>With the horror of Sierra Leone haunting both regional problems, the Security Council decided in the past 24 hours to intervene in the Horn of Africa conflict, hoping to prevent an outbreak of fighting along the border. As the three crises have come together in the past week, the Security Council's unusual field trip to Africa has become more eventful, complicated and immediately purposeful than any members had imagined, officials agreed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A United Nations Security Council delegation visiting Africa has abruptly shifted its attention from the crisis in Congo to the Ethiopian-Eritrean border, where, Western intelligence reports say, hundreds of thousands of troops on each side are preparing for imminent war.</p>
        <p>With the horror of Sierra Leone haunting both regional problems, the Security Council decided in the past 24 hours to intervene in the Horn of Africa conflict, hoping to prevent an outbreak of fighting along the border. As the three crises have come together in the past week, the Security Council's unusual field trip to Africa has become more eventful, complicated and immediately purposeful than any members had imagined, officials agreed.</p>
        <p>''When the trip was planned,'' said Richard C. Holbrooke, American ambassador to the United Nations and the leader of the council delegation, ''Congo was the No. 1 crisis in Africa. By the time we got here, it had dropped to No. 3.''</p>
        <p>Shuttling back and forth today between Ethiopia's capital, Addis Ababa, and the Eritrean capital, Asmara, the council members were urging Prime Minister Meles Zenawi of Ethiopia and President Isaias Afwerki of Eritrea to consider seriously the consequences of reigniting what one diplomat called ''the stupidest war in Africa.''</p>
        <p>Talks began on Monday night and are expected to continue through Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Since 1998, Ethiopia and Eritrea have battled sporadically over inland border territory at a cost of tens of thousands of lives. With a peace agreement brokered by the Organization of African Unity almost within reach, negotiations broke down last week in Algiers. After reports that more troops were being moved to the border, the British and French ambassadors on the Security Council delegation proposed visiting.</p>
        <p>''The chances of us succeeding are very small,'' Mr. Holbrooke said. ''Our sole objective is to get the O.A.U. talks restarted.</p>
        <p>''It is unacceptable that two of the poorest countries on earth -- one with 16 million people facing famine -- should bring their troops to the border to prepare for war.''</p>
        <p>And he said after today's talks, ''I was sitting there listening to these two highly articulate, intelligent men on the edge of a war over trivial differences in the midst of a famine'' in Ethiopia, ''and I thought: This is one of the saddest things I ever saw in international affairs.''</p>
        <p>The crux of the problem between Ethiopia and Eritrea -- led by two men who were once allies, until Eritrea effectively won independence from Ethiopia -- has been the last of three pacts in a peace package. It covers the technicalities of pulling back troops and restoring property along the disputed border.</p>
        <p>The French ambassador, Jean-David Levitte, said in an interview today that remaining problems could be solved by arbitration. He said he emerged from a session with Prime Minister Meles of Ethiopia taken aback by the casual way in which the countries seem to be gearing up for war. ''I said to Meles, 'When you start a war you think you will achieve results fast,' '' Mr. Levitte said. ''But that could be a miscalculation. That's exactly what happened when the war started in 1914 in Europe. On both sides, the French and the Germans and their allies, were convinced that after a few weeks, there would be a victory -- and a victory on their side.''</p>
        <p>Looking at reports on preparations for war on the border, Mr. Levitte said he is reminded frequently of World War I, and he said he pointed that out to Mr. Meles.</p>
        <p>''The answer of Meles was absolutely incredible,'' Mr. Levitte said. ''He said: 'No, there is a difference. We poor countries cannot afford long wars. We have not enough money to buy arms in quantities to maintain the war effort for a long period.' He implied that having made the effort to equip an army, he wanted a fast return on the investment.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>New Congo Fighting</p>
        <p>(By The New York Times), NAIROBI, Kenya, May 9 -- Rwanda and Uganda accused each other of continued attacks in Kisangani today, only a day after they agreed to a cease-fire and to evacuate the city to make way for United Nations peacekeepers. Each nation supports rebels fighting Congo's government, but twice now they have clashed in Kisangani, an important strategic city. Rwanda says Uganda fired 70 mortar shells at Rwandan positions overnight. The Ugandan military said Rwandans fired first. No one was killed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
