<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Serving Sizes: Confusion in Fat City</title>
    <meta content="10WELL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING WELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Eating Well</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DB1138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Serving Sizes: Confusion in Fat City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros Eating Well column says new 'single-serving' packages being marketed by food manufacturers are often twice as big as they used to be, making it extremely difficult for small percentage of shoppers who rely on nutrition labeling to sort out calories and portion sizes; notes companies have FDA permission; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Oscar Mayer's first Lunchables came to market in 1988, the package contained a small piece of cheese, a small piece of ham and a few crackers -- 340 calories in all. Over the years Lunchables have morphed, first into a meal with 410 to 510 calories and just last month into Lunchables Mega Pack with 640 calories for the pizza stick version and 780 calories for the nachos version. A company  spokeswoman said the smaller version was not a large enough meal for many customers. Lunchables Mega Packs also contain soft drinks and candy.</p>
        <p>Now that the nutrition police of the 1980's and 90's have been silenced, Americans are going hog wild, eating more food than ever and eating it in larger quantities. Food manufacturers are happily encouraging the  eating binge by providing single-serving packages that are often twice as big as they used to be. It's an easy way to sell more food and make more money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Oscar Mayer's first Lunchables came to market in 1988, the package contained a small piece of cheese, a small piece of ham and a few crackers -- 340 calories in all. Over the years Lunchables have morphed, first into a meal with 410 to 510 calories and just last month into Lunchables Mega Pack with 640 calories for the pizza stick version and 780 calories for the nachos version. A company  spokeswoman said the smaller version was not a large enough meal for many customers. Lunchables Mega Packs also contain soft drinks and candy.</p>
        <p>Now that the nutrition police of the 1980's and 90's have been silenced, Americans are going hog wild, eating more food than ever and eating it in larger quantities. Food manufacturers are happily encouraging the  eating binge by providing single-serving packages that are often twice as big as they used to be. It's an easy way to sell more food and make more money.</p>
        <p>This has made it extremely difficult for that small percentage of shoppers who rely on nutrition labeling to sort out calories and portion sizes. The companies are doing nothing illegal. The Food and Drug Administration has given them permission.</p>
        <p>Planters Honey Roasted Peanuts illustrates the point. The Nutrition Labeling and Education Act, which sets serving sizes for all food, says that a single serving of peanuts is 28 grams, about an ounce. But it also says that a single serving can be up to 60 grams, or two ounces. So if you buy a package of peanuts that contains 56 grams,  or about two ounces, the label says it is a single serving; that serving contains 310 calories. But if the package weighs more than 60 grams, under the law a single serving has to be considered one ounce. On a three-ounce package, or 84 grams, the nutrition label says it contains three servings, and each serving contains 140 calories.</p>
        <p>According to Ann Smith, a spokeswoman for Nabisco, which owns Planters, the different sizes ''fill consumer needs and demands for a lunchbox or single serving, and the three-ounce package is one you put in your purse or gym bag to share with someone else.'' But do you?</p>
        <p>Many companies have different serving sizes depending on the packaging. Take Fritos. A serving from a large bag is an ounce and contains 160 calories, but an individual bag (also a single serving) weighs 1.25 ounces and has 200 calories.</p>
        <p>Those 1.25-ounce packages are actually small compared with other snacks. Utz potato chips now come in a ''super snack'' package with one serving that weighs 1.75 ounces and contains 260 calories. (A serving from a large bag remains one ounce and 150 calories.) Even more confusing is the difference between a single serving from a full-size package of fat-free Fig Newtons and the new packets containing two bars of Fig Newtons. The full-size package says a serving is two cookies and 90 calories. The individual packages contain two bars, each weighing slightly more than two cookies. The package says a single bar is a serving and contains 100 calories, but who is going to eat just one bar? A two-cookie snack has become a 200-calorie indulgence.</p>
        <p>A large pepperoni pizza from Celeste claims that a serving is one-sixth of the pie and has 380 calories. But an individual pepperoni pizza from Celeste has 470 calories.</p>
        <p>Who is going to take the time to figure out the difference in calories among the various Reese's Peanut Butter Cups? One supermarket carried six different packages and four different calorie counts. In packages of Reese's snack size, two pieces equal a serving and contain 190 calories. In Reese's Miniatures, a serving equals five pieces and contains 210 calories. In ReeseSticks, a serving is a whole package and contains 230 calories. In Reese's six-pack, one serving is one package and contains 250 calories.</p>
        <p>Size creep and confusion are rampant. But most Americans apparently don't think twice about eating everything that is put in front of them, whether it's junk food or a full salad-to-pie meal.</p>
        <p>A survey conducted last November for the American Institute of Cancer Research among 1,003 Americans 18 and older found that respondents do not pay attention to portion size, whether in restaurants, shopping for groceries or preparing meals at home. Fifty-six percent said the amount they eat is determined by how hungry they are; 26 percent belong to the ''clean plate'' club in which what is served determines what is consumed. Only 12 percent said they used the nutrition information on a food label to determine portion size.</p>
        <p>In the same survey, 8 out of 10 respondents said the portions they ate at home were the same or smaller than 10 years ago. Many (62 percent) were apparently unaware that restaurant portions have also increased and that food eaten away from home is generally filled with more calories than a home-cooked meal. Combine that with the tremendous increase in eating out,  and it is pretty easy to understand why there is an epidemic of obesity.</p>
        <p>The most recent plan the government fostered to reduce fat in the diet didn't help the situation either, because many people reduced their fat intake by replacing it with simple carbohydrates, like sugar. The result was a net gain in caloric consumption, from 1,774 a day on average from 1989 through 1991 to 2,002 from 1994 through 1996, the most recent date for which such information is available. That is 228 calories a day, which could turn into a weight gain of more than 21 pounds a year. (Theoretically 3,500 extra calories cause a gain of one pound.) Stores specializing in large-size clothes are a growth industry. Subway seats are not wide enough to contain the girth of many passengers.</p>
        <p>Since the 1950's, the level of obesity in the United States has risen to 22.5 percent from nearly 13 percent, most of the increase occurring in the 1990's. The problem will be the focus of the National Nutrition Summit in Washington sponsored by the Agriculture and Health and Human Services Departments on May 30 and 31 (http://summit .iqsolutions.com).</p>
        <p>But public indifference, easy availability of food, constant advertising and that insidious trend, size creep, provide tough competition.</p>
        <p>EATING WELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
