<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judging People by the Pictures They Keep</title>
    <meta content="10PHOT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vanguard Group of Investment Cos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olsen, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brennan, John J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DC1138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judging People by the Pictures They Keep</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA R. OLSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olsen, Patricia</byline>
      <dateline>MALVERN, Pa.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on photographs employees choose to display on their desks and image they try to present; tour of workspaces and photos displayed by employees at Vanguard Group in Malvern, Pa, including Vanguard's chief executive John J Brennan, discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If one picture is worth a thousand words, what is the meaning of the dozens of photos of spouse and children on display in your manager's office? Or what is the significance of all those nature photographs tacked to the receptionist's cubicle partition?</p>
        <p>Executives and office workers everywhere, of course, put up photos that say, ''This is what I am all about.'' Psychologists and sociologists see great import in their choices. As Dr. Ira Cohen, associate professor of sociology at Rutgers University, put it, ''Employees choose what photos to display by calculated design, presenting an image that may or may not be true.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If one picture is worth a thousand words, what is the meaning of the dozens of photos of spouse and children on display in your manager's office? Or what is the significance of all those nature photographs tacked to the receptionist's cubicle partition?</p>
        <p>Executives and office workers everywhere, of course, put up photos that say, ''This is what I am all about.'' Psychologists and sociologists see great import in their choices. As Dr. Ira Cohen, associate professor of sociology at Rutgers University, put it, ''Employees choose what photos to display by calculated design, presenting an image that may or may not be true.''</p>
        <p>And so it was that the Vanguard Group agreed recently to open many of its office suites for a prying look at the photographs therein. Then, the evidence was described to various professionals for their comment.</p>
        <p>Vanguard, the big mutual fund company with more than $550 billion under management, goes about its business with great seriousness of purpose. Its campus here exudes the gravitas of its mission. The earth-toned buildings have lush lobbies and quiet halls that lead to neat rows of cubicles.</p>
        <p>A tour of two buildings at Vanguard reflected a multitude of self-portraits. Nothing quite tugs at the heartstrings like family, of course, and pictures of wives, husbands and children predominate. ''There is a feeling of wholeness and well-being when we keep their image near,'' said Dr. Joyce Warshow, a Manhattan psychologist.</p>
        <p>Enter the office of John J. Brennan, the chief executive, for example, and you can't miss the gold triple frame that holds photos of his daughter and two sons in the large bookcase directly in front of you.</p>
        <p>But the same bookcase holds at least a dozen other photos, giving Mr. Brennan rein to reveal a range of character traits. In one he is riding a Zamboni ice resurfacer at a company skating-rink party, and in another he is sitting astride an elephant at a circus that came to the Vanguard campus. Others show him standing with a children's lacrosse team that he coached to a state championship and posing with Walter L. Morgan, who created the Wellington Fund, which became a Vanguard mainstay.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robin Leidner, associate professor of sociology at the University of Pennsylvania, notes that except for the lacrosse team picture, Mr. Brennan's photos reflect his executive status. They indicate his dedication to Vanguard and his starring roles in company events, she said, and send out the message that he is a good sport and a well-rounded person.</p>
        <p>Outside the top officer, employees are even freer to expose their idiosyncrasies. In the Client Services department, where service representatives are kept busy answering callers' questions, Monique Hauser's cubicle is a kaleidoscope of visual imagery.</p>
        <p>''Jason Sehorn is the love of my life,'' Ms. Hauser said, gazing at a huge color poster of the Giants safety, who smiles back at her. Then she turns to the 10 identical likenesses of the soap opera actor Scott Reeves on her screen saver and announces: ''He's my motivation.'' But not her only one: tacked to her cubicle walls are two dozen posters of various sizes depicting other celebrities and a Mercedes C280. Almost lost in the riot of color, five small photos in Mickey Mouse frames on her desk and shelves show family members and fellow stylists at a hair salon where she moonlights.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hauser is ''making a point of her specialness as an individual,'' Dr. Leidner said.</p>
        <p>Some employees are reticent about making such strong personal statements. Diana Scheffler, an administrative assistant, goes for soothing pictures like a bike path in West Virginia and a nondescript tree-lined street. ''It doesn't really capture the essence I wanted,'' she mused. ''But it's peaceful. When I look at it, I have good thoughts.''</p>
        <p>While most parents are proud of their children, a select few turn their office space into virtual art galleries of family life. A visitor walking past John Woerth's office might think he has 34 children. That's how many photos of children are neatly arranged in groups and taped on sheets of copier paper along one wall. It's actually a growth chain that follows his children -- just the two of them -- through the years. Mr. Woerth, associate director of public relations, ''is really inviting people into his office,'' Dr. Cohen said.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Jeff Molitor, who directs the team that evaluates Vanguard's funds, has dutifully placed four pictures of his daughters, and one of his wife and a daughter, on his credenza, but they are small and, he acknowledges mostly out of date.</p>
        <p>He plans to update his photos soon. But first he will bring in a treasured 2-by-3-foot photo of a pensive pig that his wife has ordered him to remove from the den of their home. It will serve as a constant reminder, he says, of the Wall Street axiom that bulls make money, and bears make money, but pigs get slaughtered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Molitor's playful nature is already on view. An award called ''The Curse of the Bambino,'' which he won for a pithy market forecast, hangs above his credenza. But none of this means that he cares more about having fun than he cares about his family. Rather, ''he wants to give his colleagues a business lesson,'' Dr. Leidner said, even though he is doing it in a whimsical way.</p>
        <p>With so many employees using photos to paint so many different portraits of themselves, what does Vanguard itself have to say to them about its culture? If a five-foot-long photo hanging in one hallway is any guide, it may be telling them to lighten up. The photo shows a small herd of cows on a hilltop, some standing, some sitting, and all looking directly at the photographer.</p>
        <p>''Everyone stops and looks at this,'' said John Demming, Vanguard's communications manager.</p>
        <p>Added John Haines, who oversees the company's Individual Investment Services department: ''You walk by, you get happy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
