<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MANAGEMENT: Breaking Out of the Back Room; Chief Information Officers Get New Respect and Power</title>
    <meta content="Y10INF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Egon Zehnder International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tech Data Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Compaq Computer Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zyan Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prudential Property and Casualty Insurance</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siwolop, Sana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lockow, H John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capellas, Michael D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garrett, Sharon D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rafter, Edward M 3d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, William W 3d</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DF1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MANAGEMENT: Breaking Out of the Back Room; Chief Information Officers Get New Respect and Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANA SIWOLOP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siwolop, Sana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on growing number of chief information officers known as 'techies,' who are getting new respect and power; recent survey by Egon Zehnder International, executive search firm, found that companies are increasingly looking to new generation of chief information officers to be business strategists, and that these 'new' CIO's spend at least half their time outside information-technology department on efforts like developing and incubating new prospects for electronic commerce; found that 15 percent of new chief information officers now serve on boards of their companies and 70 percent are on their companies' high-level management teams; careers of H John Lockow of Tech Data Corp, Michael D Capellas of Compaq Computer, Sharon D Garrett of Zyan Communications, Edward M Rafter 3d of Prudential Property and Casualty Insurance and William W Wilson 3d of ClientSoft, discussed; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, H. John Lochow felt as though the word ''techie'' were practically branded on his forehead. As a computer systems manager at the AT&amp;T Capital Corporation and at the CNA Insurance Companies, and later as the chief information officer for a succession of corporations, he says he was never allowed to run other departments, let alone serve on high-level management teams at these firms.</p>
        <p>For him, things have turned out well. But Mr. Lochow's lurch up the corporate ladder is not an isolated case. In corporate America, an increasing number of chief information officers -- basically, they are the folks in charge of the computers -- are amassing greater power as top bosses and company boards realize how crucial technical expertise is in staying ahead of the competition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, H. John Lochow felt as though the word ''techie'' were practically branded on his forehead. As a computer systems manager at the AT&amp;T Capital Corporation and at the CNA Insurance Companies, and later as the chief information officer for a succession of corporations, he says he was never allowed to run other departments, let alone serve on high-level management teams at these firms.</p>
        <p>For him, things have turned out well. But Mr. Lochow's lurch up the corporate ladder is not an isolated case. In corporate America, an increasing number of chief information officers -- basically, they are the folks in charge of the computers -- are amassing greater power as top bosses and company boards realize how crucial technical expertise is in staying ahead of the competition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lochow (pronounced LUCK-oh) got his chance to break loose from the techie label last year. Opportunity called in the form of a mini-crisis at his current employer, the Tech Data Corporation in Clearwater, Fla., a giant computer distributor that was growing so fast it could not hire enough people to keep up with orders. Its warehouses were bulging with products that could not be shipped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lochow, whose main responsibility as C.I.O. until then had been to maintain the smooth functioning of the company's computers in 35 countries, believed he was the man to break the logjam. So he asked Tech Data's chief executive, Steven A. Raymund, to put him in charge of the company's supply division. After all, he told Mr. Raymund, he had already turned around the information technology operations to make them more efficient, and at no additional cost to the company.</p>
        <p>He got the assignment and threw himself into it with tasks like picking apart and mapping every process that Tech Data used in its warehouses to receive and ship its products.</p>
        <p>He emerged a hero: within three months, Tech Data had almost doubled its shipments and had trimmed inventory. Now Mr. Lockow reports directly to Mr. Raymund, and earlier this year he was given responsibility for managing yet another department, the one that assembles the company's products.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lochow clearly savors his new role at Tech Data. ''Now my responsibilities cross many lines of business,'' he said. ''Before, I felt like I was up against a glass ceiling.''</p>
        <p>A recent survey by Egon Zehnder International, an executive search firm, found that companies are increasingly looking to a new generation of chief information officers to be business strategists, and that these ''new'' C.I.O.'s spend at least half their time outside the information-technology department on efforts like developing and incubating new prospects for electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>The survey found that 15 percent of new chief information officers now serve on the boards of their companies and 70 percent are on their companies' high-level management teams. Those numbers are up sharply from a decade ago, industry specialists say, when 0 percent and 10 percent would have been more likely figures.</p>
        <p>The information officers are reveling in their elevation from back-room tinkerers with fancy titles to strategic thinkers on an equal footing with corporate presidents, chief operating officers and chief financial officers.</p>
        <p>''We're in the third generation of C.I.O. now,'' Mr. Lochow said. ''The first generation was made up of techies, like data center directors. And although the second generation was more vocal in terms of becoming part of corporate planning, its members were still one level below directly reporting to their chief executives. Now, however, thanks to the Internet, C.I.O.'s are moving directly into corporate decision-making.''</p>
        <p>Executive recruiters say the trend is the inevitable fallout of the Internet revolution, which has recast the dynamics of the marketplace of almost every industry overnight and forced companies to react with equal speed or face extinction.</p>
        <p>''It used to be that companies would say, 'Find us a C.I.O. who will take care of our computer systems,' '' said S. Ross Brown, the director of the high-technology and telecommunications recruiting practice at Egon Zehnder. ''But now they're calling to say, 'We need a C.I.O. who can help us define our whole way of doing business.' ''</p>
        <p>Those new responsibilities require new duties, of course, including spending more time with both the corporate brass and customers.</p>
        <p>Cecilia Claudio, the chief information officer at the Farmers Group, the Zurich Financial Services subsidiary based in Los Angeles, says her new travel schedule takes some getting used to. In March, Ms. Claudio spent three days crisscrossing Indiana to meet with more than 60 sales agents, something that chief information officers like her would never have done five years ago.</p>
        <p>''People don't look to me as just being a C.I.O.,'' she said. ''I'm expected to bring wisdom, to understand all aspects of our business, as well as not work in isolation.''</p>
        <p>Before Ms. Claudio joined Farmers two years ago, she said, her job at a former employer was focused entirely on the information systems. But now she is asked almost daily for her views on questions like whether to increase the company's sales staff and how to sell multiple products to existing customers.</p>
        <p>Because technology now touches every corner of almost every company's business, Ms. Claudio said, chief information officers are probably better prepared than other top managers to assume new responsibilities -- including the mantle of chief executive. ''I know of quite a few situations where this has already happened,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Patrick J. Zilvitis, the chief information officer of the Gillette Company, says his expertise is sought out because technology touches every aspect of Gillette's operations, even product design. ''I tend to be involved in change management in everything I do,'' Mr. Zilvitis said.</p>
        <p>It is not as though C.I.O.'s are on an unstoppable march to the top at every corporation in America, of course. One school of thought is of the opinion, in fact, that as a group they retain a detail-oriented mentality that can miss the big picture.</p>
        <p>Paul Bernard, who founded his own consulting firm in Manhattan, for example, says that for all the changes wrought by the Internet, too many chief information officers continue to ''worship'' technology, while all but ignoring both the strategic and the customer-service aspects of their jobs.</p>
        <p>''The issue for C.I.O.'s and their staffers is that no one has articulated to them how much their jobs have changed,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some do grasp those changes, of course, and are leveraging their new stature to shop themselves around.</p>
        <p>Chris Hjelm left his job as chief information officer at Federal Express in January to become chief operating officer at the Zoho Corporation, an Internet vendor in Sunnyvale, Calif., that caters to hotels and casinos.</p>
        <p>After 14 years at Federal Express, Mr. Hjelm said, he had become tired of endlessly reinventing the giant company's computer systems and yearned for a more expansive role.</p>
        <p>''I was ready to try something different, as well as be a part of the Internet economy,'' he said. ''Now, I'm creating something new, as well as an entire business model in an industry that's ripe for it. That's why a lot of chief information officers like me are leaving.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
