<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Persevering In Spite of The Pain</title>
    <meta content="10ARAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1D91E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Persevering In Spite of The Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column on several basketball players playing with painful injuries in playoffs; cites New York Knickerbockers center Patrick Ewing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIRTY years and two days after Willis Reed hobbled out of the Madison Square Garden tunnel and set a New York standard for big-game heroism, there are examples everywhere that the contemporary professional basketball player has been living up to the legend quite well.</p>
        <p>Here at the American Airlines Arena last night, Patrick Ewing discarded his ice packs again and continued his mission to become a limping champion in his own right, while Tim Hardaway taped up his badly sprained left foot and returned to his pursuit of local Willis-hood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIRTY years and two days after Willis Reed hobbled out of the Madison Square Garden tunnel and set a New York standard for big-game heroism, there are examples everywhere that the contemporary professional basketball player has been living up to the legend quite well.</p>
        <p>Here at the American Airlines Arena last night, Patrick Ewing discarded his ice packs again and continued his mission to become a limping champion in his own right, while Tim Hardaway taped up his badly sprained left foot and returned to his pursuit of local Willis-hood.</p>
        <p>''Who in this league doesn't play with any pains or nicks?'' Ewing said before the Knicks evened their war of halfcourt attrition with a wildly uneven 82-76 victory over the Heat in Game 2 of the Eastern Conference semifinal, a game so unsightly you wondered if everyone, including the refs, was in need of medical attention.</p>
        <p>This has been the postseason of playing with pain, for muscular forwards and frail guards, aging warriors and young bucks, franchise players and scrappy vets. They didn't put up with 82 regular-season games and all those insufferable practices to let their bodies deprive them of rich post-season desserts.</p>
        <p>So Grant Hill tried to play on a broken ankle against Miami in the first round. Karl Malone shook off a recent sprain after scrambling off the bench when a teammate dove into it. Jason Kidd rushed back from what was supposed to be a season-ending broken ankle. Allen Iverson has played on with a medical chart that is longer than him. His Philadelphia backcourt partner, Eric Snow, pushed himself Monday night until the dam broke.</p>
        <p>''He was bawling, right?'' Chris Childs said, posing as a question what he already knew because he would have preferred for the camera to have lied.</p>
        <p>Childs had only seen Snow on the bench during Indiana's victory, then tuned out before the Turner Network cameras later found Snow still in tears, and out for the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry, really sorry, to hear that,'' Childs said. ''I know him, just from being cordial around the league. Allen's the best player on that team but he would be the first to tell you that Eric's their leader. It's a shame. He played. He tried.''</p>
        <p>Reggie Miller ran Snow until his injured foot gave out. Last night, the Knicks had Charlie Ward attack Hardaway and Ward, of all people, was their leading scorer for much of the game. On the court, there is no sympathy, only matchups to be exploited.</p>
        <p>The players are paid handsomely, but their money is guaranteed and they don't have to play when they are hurting and they all know exactly what Hardaway is feeling when Ward or Childs turns him on defense and lights what Hardaway said feels like a fire inside his foot.</p>
        <p>''People don't understand what a high threshold of pain we have to have to just get to this level,'' said Childs.</p>
        <p>Jeff Van Gundy said, ''Some players don't like to be out there when they can't play their best.'' Not Hardaway or Ewing. Between visits to the acupuncturist for back spasms, Ewing has often looked glacial in this series but there he was, hitting the biggest basket of the game, lofting a sweet jumper over Alonzo Mourning in the third quarter after Miami had surged to within 51-50. And there he was again, putting back Latrell Sprewell's missed drive with a 1 minute 34 seconds left to snuff out one final Heat charge.</p>
        <p>As Ewing learned last spring, no doctor can guarantee that an injury can't be made worse by playing. Hardaway, in a contract year, said his father has told him, ''Do what you have to do but don't be foolish and go out there and hurt yourself.''</p>
        <p>He's vowed to ''fight through the pain'' and he gave Pat Riley another valiant 30 minutes and 13 points last night. Hardaway just doesn't have the mobility for dribble penetration, and Miami's offense has no margin for error when Mourning is contained, as he was last night. Conversely, the Knicks won despite Sprewell and Allan Houston shooting a combined 5 for 27. It's a long shot that Miami can survive. Hardaway will probably have to settle for an opponent's respect.</p>
        <p>''Big men go up and back,'' Childs said. ''He's a guard, cutting this way and that way. He wants to be out there.''</p>
        <p>This time of year, most of the players do, but they are vulnerable, human. At a time when more and more fans have grown tired of the corporate hype, and when premier games are as tough to watch as last night's, that's not a bad marketing thought for a sport under television-ratings siege.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
