<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jurors May Not Use Professional Expertise to Sway Others, Court Says</title>
    <meta content="10JURY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Professions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Orange County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Professions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DD1E38F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jurors May Not Use Professional Expertise to Sway Others, Court Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses impact of new rules in New York State that professionals have to serve jury duty; New York State Court of Appeals, in ordering new trial for man convicted of causing death of his girlfriend in Orange County, held that opinions of two nurses on jury concerning conflicting testimony of witnesses led to jury's guilty verdict; concludes that such circumstances has grown far more likely since professions lost long-standing ability to avoid jury service (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last few years, New York's court system has changed its rules to force professionals to do jury duty, and a growing number of lawyers, doctors and engineers have trudged, grumbling, into jury rooms alongside the retirees, waiters and laborers.</p>
        <p>The new crop of jurors arrives armed with expert knowledge that could be relevant to the cases they hear. That may seem like an advantage, but the state's highest court today called it a serious problem, ruling that jurors must keep their professional expertise to themselves, or they risk unfairly swaying their fellow jurors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last few years, New York's court system has changed its rules to force professionals to do jury duty, and a growing number of lawyers, doctors and engineers have trudged, grumbling, into jury rooms alongside the retirees, waiters and laborers.</p>
        <p>The new crop of jurors arrives armed with expert knowledge that could be relevant to the cases they hear. That may seem like an advantage, but the state's highest court today called it a serious problem, ruling that jurors must keep their professional expertise to themselves, or they risk unfairly swaying their fellow jurors.</p>
        <p>That is what happened, the Court of Appeals found, in a case in Orange County, where a man was convicted of causing the death of his girlfriend, and the court ordered that he be given a new trial. The case turned on conflicting expert testimony, and two nurses on the jury voiced their professional opinions that the prosecution's version of how the victim died was credible, a view that helped produce a guilty verdict.</p>
        <p>In a unanimous decision, the seven-member court concluded that such circumstances had grown far more likely since the professions lost the long-standing ability to avoid jury service. The risk is now so common, Judge Joseph W. Bellacosa wrote for the court, that trial judges should alter their standard instructions to juries, ''differentiating between ordinary and professional opinions of jurors, and directing that jurors may not use their professional expertise to insert facts and evidence outside the record with respect to material issues into the deliberative process.''</p>
        <p>Judge Bellacosa noted that ''an application of everyday experience'' is not only acceptable in deliberations, but desirable. Jurors may still use their professional judgment in their own, internal reasoning, he said, but added that they could not share it with others on a panel.</p>
        <p>''That would violate the rights of the litigants to have their cases decided only on the evidence'' introduced, he wrote. He said that the jurors would, in effect, become witnesses for one side in a case, without the other side having the chance to cross-examine them.</p>
        <p>The decision is striking because, as Judge Bellacosa wrote, ''Generally, a jury vedict may not be impeached by probes into the jury's deliberative process.''</p>
        <p>The opinion, and the prescription for a new jury instruction, caught lawyers on both sides of the case off guard. They noted that Judge Bellacosa has a reputation as the most prosecution-friendly member of the court. ''I would think this kind of thing would come up a lot, and it's problematic,'' said Frank Phillips, the Orange County district attorney. ''It may very well be an unrealistic standard for jurors to comply with. If you're in the room and you're the one holdout and they say you're being unreasonable, and you're not because you have this select knowledge that you know might change their minds, you're not supposed to share that? I'm having quite a hard time understanding that.''</p>
        <p>He argued that the ruling could add new, time-consuming elements to many cases, prompting lawyers to inquire, after trial, into a jury's reasoning, and leading to a rash of appeals.</p>
        <p>But this is not the first example of the courts asking jurors to leave aside what they know. When a witness testifies in a foreign language through an interpreter, judges often instruct that jurors who speak the witness' language must go not by the witness' testimony, but by the interpreter's English version of it -- even if they know that interpretation to be inaccurate. And judges routinely tell juries to disregard testimony they have heard that is deemed inappropriate, a difficult exercise, at best.</p>
        <p>In a way, the Court of Appeals was recognizing what every trial lawyer knows: that professional people are often undesirable as jurors because of their ability to persuade others, particularly if their professions are relevant to the case.</p>
        <p>''This is a growing problem,'' said the defense lawyer in the case, Benjamin Ostrer. ''We weren't looking for a new jury instruction, but I think it's entirely justified.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips, the district attorney, said he was not sure whether he would seek a new trial for the defendant, Michael Maragh.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maragh, a high school dropout who did odd jobs for a living, lived in Middletown with his girlfriend, May DeGroat. They had two sons together, one born just nine days before she died in March 1997, Mr. Ostrer said.</p>
        <p>On the day she died, Mr. Maragh told police, they were having sex when Ms. DeGroat, 26, collapsed in pain. He called 911, and paramedics tried, unsuccessfully, to resuscitate her. An autopsy showed that she had internal bleeding and a lacerated liver.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors charged Mr. Maragh, then 24, with manslaughter, contending that he had struck her in the abdomen, causing the internal bleeding, which, in turn, caused an abnormal heart rhythm, which killed her.</p>
        <p>The defense contended that the abnormal rhythm resulted from an embolism, a blockage of a blood vessel, possibly related to her obesity. The defense's medical expert testified that the internal bleeding was not sufficient to cause the abnormal rhythm, and that the bleeding and liver damage could have been caused by improperly administered  cardiopulmonary resuscitation.</p>
        <p>During jury deliberations in November 1997, one nurse on the jury told the others that the blood loss could have caused the heart malfunction and death. The second nurse-juror supported the view of the first one, giving her estimate of how much blood Ms. DeGroat had lost.</p>
        <p>The jury acquitted Mr. Maragh on the manslaughter charge, but found him guilty of criminally negligent homicide. He was sentenced to up to 4 years in prison, and has served 16 months.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
