<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Dogs Can Survive Family Life</title>
    <meta content="10RUNT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Runt (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DB1138F933A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Dogs Can Survive Family Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews play Runt, based on Cabot Caboche, tale by Daniel Pennac, presented at New Victory Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dogs galore are peopling the stage of the New Victory Theater, and before anyone yells ''mixed metaphor,'' that happens to be true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dogs galore are peopling the stage of the New Victory Theater, and before anyone yells ''mixed metaphor,'' that happens to be true.</p>
        <p>Mutts, pink poodles, boxers, dachshunds, chihuahuas and other canines, as well as humans of many personalities, are capering across the stage in ''Runt,'' the thoroughly enjoyable show that is bringing to an end a consistently fine New Victory season with performances on a Friday-through-Sunday schedule through May 21.</p>
        <p>Part soap opera, part musical, part comedy, part satire, part puppet show, part children's tale, ''Runt'' is intended for audiences from 7 up; adults who gag on the treacle that so often is served under the banner of children's entertainment may find the less-than-sunny family at the center of the story a refreshing breath of dysfunctional home.</p>
        <p>But the mischievous survivor that gives the show its title fills ''Runt'' with charm, both as a raggedy little red puppet with one black eye and in human guise as the winsome, pink-haired Rogier in 't Hout, the visible puppeteer (like the others in this show) who gives this frisky dog voice and personality.</p>
        <p>Along the way, which includes a French dog pound whose inhabitants have a three-day life expectancy, there are brave calls for dignity, freedom and independence as well as lessons in survival.</p>
        <p>''Runt,'' a co-production of the Ro Theater Company and Firma Rieks Swarte, arrives by way of Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where, under the title ''Hondje,'' it was the 1999 family show that Ro Theater presents each Christmas. Firma Rieks Swarte is Mr. Swarte's theater company, known for blending actors, puppets, props, music and visual arts.</p>
        <p>In ''Runt,'' written by Daniel Pennac, whose name adorns the majestic little ocean liner that cruises past the beach at St. Tropez in one of the show's many inventive scenes, these companies and artists have concocted a richly rewarding show that embraces life from its buoyant heights to its psychological depths.</p>
        <p>By the time the tale even begins, poor Runt has survived a murder attempt. A native of St. Tropez, part of a litter of five whose brothers and sisters were sold, little Runt, tiny and ugly, was plunged into a bucket of water to drown, thrown into a box and left for dead.</p>
        <p>But Runt is rescued by a pack of scruffy dogs in a dump and suckled by a motherly dachshund who is promptly killed when a garbage truck drops a refrigerator on her. But the dachshund has already imparted a valuable lesson: Go to the city and find a mistress to take care of you.</p>
        <p>And so the grief-stricken Runt does. In St. Tropez, where he makes the acquaintance of whizzing cars, gendarmes, butchers and the opposite sex (''Runt,'' like real children, finds humor in flatulence, urinating and the bare human behind), this dog is going to find despair and hope.</p>
        <p>Taken prisoner by a dog catcher, he is held in a pound where a chihuahua manipulates an obnoxious television reporter to win freedom, his best friend is hauled off to die and he, at last, is adopted by a rather nasty little girl over her parents' objections.</p>
        <p>The girl, who uses the threat of hunger strikes to get her way, is known simply as Girlie (Feike Looyen), and some idea of her parents' personalities may be gleaned from the kind of direct names that characterize tales created by children: Armpitman (Hans Thissen) and Ammonia (Marian Luif).</p>
        <p>After vacationing on the beach with the newly named Doggy, all return to Paris, where Doggy is soon neglected and runs off, leading to life in the Paris animal underworld with the scruffy but wise Prairiewolf (Siem van Leeuwen); Prairiewolf's  friend, the artist Wild Boar (Ferdi Jansen), and a few high-living cats.</p>
        <p>In time, Doggy will be reunited with a contrite Girlie, betrayed by Armpitman en route to another vacation in St. Tropez and eventually reunited with the family after he has exacted vengeance and they have become sadder but wiser.</p>
        <p>Through all the highs and lows of Doggy's life, guitar, violin, banjo, accordion and other musical accompaniment, most of it by Cornell van Vuuren and Joost Belinfante, evoke the sort of Gallic heartbreak and joy one associates with Edith Piaf, and Mr. Swarte's stage design sweeps swiftly from the streets and beaches of St. Tropez to the high rises and canine haunts of Paris.</p>
        <p>''Runt'' may be all about a little dog, but with a cast of 14 creating more than 60 human and animal characters, it is the big-hearted product of big talent.</p>
        <p>RUNT</p>
        <p>Ro Theater Company, co-produced with Firma Rieks Swarte. Based on ''Cabot Caboche,'' a tale by Daniel Pennac. Text editor, Jules Noyons; translation by Adrienne Altenhaus; co-director, Mark Rietman; co-director and stage design by Rieks Swarte. Costumes by Carly Everaert; lighting by Henk Van Der Geest; music and compostion by Fay Lovsky; puppets, Beatrijs Persijn; artistic coordinator, Ina Veen; English language coach, Joe Weston. Presented by the New 42nd Street Inc. At the New Victory Theater, 209 West 42nd Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Rogier in 't Hout (Doggy), Feike Looyen (Girlie), Siem van Leeuwen (Prairiewolf), Marian Luif (Ammonia), Hans Thissen (Armpitman) Ferdi Jansen (Wild Boar), Cornell van Vuuren (Dog Pound Manager) and Joost Belinfante (Editor in Chief).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
